<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr2830288_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>The Pi Beta Phi Settlement School</title>
                        <author><name>Stone, Edna L.</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>April 1912</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr2830288_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">April 1912</date>, The Pi Beta Phi Settlement School</title>
                        <author><name>Stone, Edna L.</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 288-292</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">35</note>
                        <note type="Folder">9</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 28, Number 3 (April 1912), Pages 288-292.</note>
			<note type="document">arr2830288_0000</note>

                        <note type="Additional Information">includes unpaginated plate of Miss Martha Hill</note>
	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Founding of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1909-1927</item>
                                <item>Planning</item>
                                <item>Living conditions</item>
                                <item>Curriculum</item>
                                <item>Health care</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr2830288_0001" seq="01" n="288  "/>
       <p>THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI FIE PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL BY EDNA L. STONE-MARYLAND ALPHA circular letter from the chairman of the National Settlement of Committee, sent to all subscribers with this issue of the ARROW to all alumnae clubs and chapters, has given an account of the ress of the work of founding the school during the past year of the beginning of the work itself at Gatlinburg, Tennessee. that our long hoped-for school has a local habitaton it seems h while to recall the nature of the work which we desire to do 1g the mountain people and to learn a little more about the 11 plans that are now being carried out. ost of us have read, especially during the last year or two, of iature and character of the three millions of people, mostly of Lish and Scotch-Irish stock, who live among the hills and valleys Le southern Appalachian mountain region. We have read of the tion, poverty and ignorance of many of them, but no one not )uch with the work among them can realize how deep is the rance or how lonely and bleak are the lives shut off from the ants of life and thought in the great world outside. Nor can minitiated realize how great is the need of more light and how tothe desire for it. Of course there are schools scattered here there through this great region and the states are extending and .oving the public school system very rapidly but, as yet are unable ape adequately with conditions in the sparsely settled mountain icts. The teachers have often had, but two or three years of oling, and the school term, where school exist, often lasts for only months. There are, in addition, schools and colleges supported lenominations or by private subscription, many of which are g splendid work, but they are very few among so many. As mas Nelson Page remarked in a recent address, "They are but :s on the mountain to show the wanderer that human sympathy exists and to encourage the lost not to despair." When we hear he hundreds of children who are eagerly waiting for a chance rater these schools; of the seven hundred, for instance, on the ing list of the school at Hindman, Kentucky, some of whom must .reed away from its doors almost daily, we can not help feeling here is a work that must appeal to us especially, as college Len. MISS MARTHA HILL Teacher in the Pi 'Beta Phi Settlement School </p>
      <pb ref="arr2830288_0002" seq="02" n="289  "/>
       <p>THE P1 BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL 289 It is not by the old education, not by establishing a "college," that we wish to help these children, these farmers and hunters and these lonely, drudging mothers. The old education, by which is meant knowledge acquired altogether from books, is too apt to make the young people dissatisfied with life in the mountains and to lead them away from home, leaving the life there impoverished rather than improved. What we wish to do is to join in the effort to show them how to use their own resources, to develop industries suitable to their environment, and to lead more happy, healthful lives. We want to help, as far as we can, to educate the mountain boys and girls back to their homes instead of away from them. In the community which we have selected we are beginning with lesons in sewing and cooking for the girls, and with primary classes for the younger children. The usual "literary" branches will be taught as local conditions seem to call for them and there seems limit for these youngsters at first. Miss Martha Hill, our teacher, believes that she will be able to accomplish much good through her mothers' clubs and classes, with an occasional tea or coffee drinking in the little school-home. She also plans some extensive visiting among the surrounding mountains during the spring. The following is an extract from her letter telling something about Gatlinburg and its people, written before her return to that place in March: "Gatlinburg, the proposed place of your educational beneficence, is a settlement in Sevier County, Tennessee, about sixty miles from Knoxville, as the crow flies. The one railroad in the county covers thirty miles on the route from Knoxville to Sevierville. The telephone facilities are limited, there being only one near Gatlin-burg, but this is owned by a man friendly to your school who has four children to whom he is anxious to give the opportunities he was denied. "When I arrived at Sevierville, two men from Gatlinburg called on me and said they had received my message and had arranged my transportation to their village, and if I could brave a snow storm and rough roads I should be ready at two-thirty P. M. I was ready! The `rig' came, no-top buggy, wraps, mule, boy, snow storm! The journey of fifteen miles was very enjoyable, the scenery grand, </p>
      <pb ref="arr2830288_0003" seq="03" n="290-291  "/>
       <p>290 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI and the boy bright and entertaining. The air was delightful, the mule a fine traveler and the novel trip was over in four hours and I was sitting by a great woodfire with savory odors coming from the kitchen. "The women and girls of this neighborhood need your best efforts. I am informed that not many years have passed since whiskey drinking was common even among women; and indeed I saw evidences of it during my short stay. One man said, `come and help make our women better.' Several women said, `We want some one to come and teach our children manners ; we do not have the time' ; and others declared, `We want teaching beyond the fifth grade, so our boys and girls can stay at home. We have no money to send them away.' The women want help, and teaching and instruction in sanitation is especially needed. The waters of the beautiful stream running for miles through the Gatlinburg valley serve as sewer for the settlement. Nearly every woman I met expressed a desire to enter your school. They are a music-loving people and one of my strongest hopes is built upon this. They prefer an organ. Here is an opportunity for several to join together and give one with a pedal bass. I am anxious to have a good one. "About six houses, one church and three general stores comprise the settlement proper, but, the need extends for five miles in every direction. A simple but well-equipped kitchen is needed for demonstration work. The one church has no pastor, Sunday school, nor any organization for special work. A nurse is much needed. Indeed you can think of no, phase of educational or settlement work that is not needed at Gatlinburg. It is a splendid place for your efforts." As Miss Hill says, instruction in hygiene and sanitation is one of the greatest needs of the mountain people. This is to be the especial work of the trained nurse who has gone up to spend three months at Gatlinburg, armed with her outfit of simple remedies and supplies. Some of the best settlement schools have classes in home nursing and find that their most useful work is done by the visiting nurse, whose influence often extends for miles around, bringing untold relief and comfort into many a lonely home. That medical treatment is often badly needed is very clearly shown in the following extract from a circular letter sent out from the school at Hindman, Kentucky, and published in the Quarterly Magazine of the Southern Industrial Educational Association for December, 1911. It is en-titled, "A Mountain Clinic." THE PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL 291 The second week of September Dr. Stucky, of Lexington, came up and held his second clinic at the little hospital of our school. He arrived with his four nurses, also from Lexington, on Saturday evening, and on Sunday gave two delightful and simple talks about the care of the body in the "church-house" down in the village. Miss Butler had sent out word to all the schoolhouses and post offices for miles around, of his expected visit, and that he would treat eye, ear, nose and throat troubles. Monday morning early a crowd of people around the hospital awaited his appearance. And what a crowd! Of course in a region where trachoma is perhaps the most prevalent disease, the majority of cases were eye trouble. There were more men than women men being of more importance in this country. Passing among them, one heard their sad histories. One elderly man, with frightful eyelids, grown fast to the balls, sat beside his daughter, a young woman with a sunbonnet drawn tightly over inflamed eyes, the tears from which dropped upon the eight--months' old baby in her arms. This old man said he had been suffering with his eyes for thirteen years, and was now entirely unable to work. From time to time he would take the baby from his daughter, and it would laugh and crow and pass its little hands over his face a sight to sicken any heart, Aunt Susan Cooper, from Short Fork of Ball, described her trouble as "a scum over my eyes for four years. Some calls it cat-tracks." Another man, nearly blind, being questioned as to how many there were in his family, replied, "Me'n the old woman and eight young 'uns." "How many have sore eyes ?" "Well, about ten of us." An elderly woman in black dress and sunbonnet came in with her husband and two tall daughters in pink calico. All four were in advanced stages of trachoma, and she said the ones at home had it, too. When we remember the use of the family towel and washpan, and the lack of sheets, the only wonder, is that anybody escapes. There were other troubles, too. One mother, with an extremely friendly baby who, as she pleasantly expressed it, "Never sees no strangers," brought a little blind boy, and a little girl who, as she said, "Makes a furse in sleeping of a night. I think there is maybe something in her nose." There was nothing less, indeed, than two huge adenoids. A small boy, being asked what was the matter with him, replied: "I've got a year." "I should think you had," said the Doctor, "with those large adenoids, inflamed tonsils, and a big hole in your ear-drum !" One woman said that the back of her head "felt quare and swimmy all the time." It was found she had an enormous polypus. We were inclined to doubt the word of another woman, when she said she was only thirty-four years old, for her *drawn and haggard face looked at least sixty. But when we saw the turbinate that was removed from her nose, we wondered that she was alive at all. Many, young and old, were "deer from "risings,"--a large number in-curably so. </p>
      <pb ref="arr2830288_0004" seq="04" n="292-293  "/>
       <p>292 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI All day that first day Dr. Stucky worked with greatest speed, examining and operating (besides all the people who came in, every one of the two hundred and twenty pupils in the school had to be attended to) ; but by night the crowd around the hospital was greater than when he began in the morning. Patiently they sat, the women and children on the wide porch, the men in rows on the grass, awaiting their turns, patiently they went away for the night, to come back and wait possibly two or three days more. Never during the week were the porch and the yard cleared, and on Saturday, the last day, numbers were still waiting. In the operating room, any hour during the week, the sight was intensely interesting. With marvelous speed, one patient after another was etherized, laid on the table, and relieved of the affliction that rendered life futile or burdensome. All that science and genius could do was done. In another room, the sore eyes were being treated constantly. Tents had been set up be-hind the hospital for the overflow surgical cases, while the sore-eyed put up in the village and came daily for treatment. Never, perhaps, was more accomplished for suffering humanity in the space of a week. There was a noticeable lessening of prejudice against the surgeon's knife. Last spring many parents refused to have their children operated on, much less themselves. This time only a few balked, though many characteristically left the question for the children to decide. It is an interesting fact that everybody, without exception, wished to pay for treatments and operations. For operations that ordinarily would cost twenty-five or fifty dollars, they were permitted to pay a dollar and a half. Those who had no money invariably brought produce of some kind. . . Every day there were new and strange sights and stories; indeed, so great was the human interest that it was impossible to tear oneself away from the little hospital. Surely no one ever did a more glorious week's work than Dr. Stucky and his helpers, or one more sadly needed. It was like Bible times over again, as one looked at the waiting crowds, scene after scene from the Gospels was brought to mind. . On the editorial page of the same magazine there is a word of explanation saying that this was the second visit paid by this physician to that region. The success of the first visit had been told far and wide, which had evidently increased the number of those applying for relief. Conditions around Gatlinburg are probably not just like those in the neighborhood where this clinic was held, but we know very well that there is a great deal for our nurse to do to instruct in healthful living, and to help the sick and suffering. Surely the time has come when the name of Pi Beta Phi, for so long a symbol of friendship and pleasure to us, fortunate as we are, may grow to be a sign of help in distress, of succor for the needy, and of happiness for those who hunger for the joy of living. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



