<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr2920249_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Our Settlement School</title>
                        <author><name>Miller, Kate B.</name></author>
                        <author><name>Cameron, Gene</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>January 1913</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr2920249_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">January 1913</date>, Our Settlement School</title>
                        <author><name>Miller, Kate B.</name></author>
                        <author><name>Cameron, Gene</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 248-255</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">35</note>
                        <note type="Folder">11</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 29, Number 2 (January 1913), Pages 248-255.</note>
			<note type="document">arr2920249_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">News from Little Pigeon; Our First Pi Phi Settlement School Teacher; Notes from the field</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Founding of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1909-1927</item>
                                <item>Planning</item>
                                <item>Funding</item>
                                <item>School programs</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr2920249_0001" seq="01" n="248-249  "/>
       <p>248 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI into each other, filled with various precious articles. In the center of one room, in a glass case, was a Persian throne of gold inlaid with precious stones. Around the walls were the state robes of the various Sultans from the Conqueror Mohammed down to the present day. One object that attracted a great deal of attention was the image of a man in robes of state sitting on a throne, the whole carved out of a single pearl, being about two and a half inches high. There were gold dishes incrusted with diamonds and rubies, wonderful porcelains, dishes filled with precious stones and many articles of rare value. Our summer was over all too soon and one morning, the last of August, we had to say good-bye to our Island home. Our steamer left at noon and our last sight of Constantinople was in the blaze of the noon-day sun. As we steamed out of the harbor and into the Marmora we watched the city fade away on the horizon and hoped, some day, to visit it again. OUR SETTLEMENT SCHOOL NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON KATE B. MILLER (Under this caption, Miss Miller, the member of the Settlement School Committee who is in charge of Policy and Publicity will give us news of the school from time to time.-Editor) LITTLE PIGEON In the Smoky Mountains in southeastern Tennessee, a little stream begins its way to the ocean. It winds softly for a while and then rushes noisily down rocky beds, being widened by its tributaries as it goes, until it reaches the French Broad river. It flows on with the French Broad, the Tennessee, and the Ohio, into the Mississippi. As a part of that great flood, it sweeps through the Gulf, into the Atlantic Ocean. This stream, hardly large enough in places to be called a river, bears the name of Little Pigeon. Before it reaches the French Broad, it passes the village of Gatlinburg, with its church and its few scattered houses on the flats and the modest Pi Beta Phi cottage on a hill. Then it swings sharply around a curve, and goes on past a hill with the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School on its summit. From the regions of Little Pigeon and its tributaries, scores of children are finding their way to this hill top. As the river goes from its mountain source to pay its toll to the ocean, so will the dwellers on Little Pigeon eventually send out their toll to the life OUR SETTLEMENT SCHOOL 249 of our country. The Pi Beta Phi teachers, by the indirect teaching of their home life in the cottage and their direct teaching in the school house will very largely determine the nature of the toll that will go out from Little Pigeon. THE "CLOSES" OF SCHOOL ON LITTLE PIGEON The "closes" of school on Little Pigeon which were held on Fri-day evening, November 30, were of interest not only to the peo KATE B. MILLER (Iowa Beta) ple of the mountains and the valley whose children were in school, but to private and official friends in Sevierville, the county seat of Sevier county, in Knoxville, the state capital, and especially to Pi Beta Phi the world over. This was the last day of the four months' public school, in which the Pi Beta Phi teacher had been co-operating with the native teacher, Mr. Calvin Ogle. The parents were eager to see what Miss Hill, and the very newest Pi Phi teacher, Miss Gillette, had been doing, and the children were eager to show them. </p>
      <pb ref="arr2920249_0002" seq="02" n="250-251  "/>
       <p>250 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI They had come at night, some of them at half-past six, though that was the bedtime of many of them. They had come from up Baskins' way, on Mill Creek, down Roaring Brook, farther up Little Pigeon, from Holy Top, and Dick's range, over devious mountain trails and rocky, muddy mountain roads of so modest a nature that they were often difficult to find. Most of them came afoot, carrying babies, leading little children, and lighting their uncertain way with lamps and lanterns. Their goal was the school house on the small high nob, which had but one way of rational approach. The per-son who sought to scale the rocky bluff of seventy-five or a hundred feet from the Roaring Brook side or the Little Pigeon and bad road side would have stood small chance of reaching Minerva's temple on top. And so they plodded along the meandering, muddy road, around and up the hill. They were all there waiting when Miss Hill, Miss Gillette, Miss Miller, the fraternity representative, Mr. J. R. Keeble, the county superintendent of schools, and Dr. E. A. Bishop, the president of Murphy College, Sevierville, arrived, after having stumbled their lamp-and-lantern-lighted way down and up the slippery road from the Pi Phi cottage, half a, mile away. By reason of its usualness, the achievement of such a journev was to the mountaineers a thing of no moment, and therefore no way modified their eager anticipation of the "closes". The parental eagerness was so little discernable, however, that, had the community been a more sophisticated one, it would have been called a mere willingness to listen intently. A reporter would have needed few parentheses for applauses ; and the slight handclapping made the visit-ors initiating it feel like "claquers". The absolute quiet during the program was unbroken except by the procession of young and old who passed to and from the end seat near the stove reserved for those who wished to warm themselves, and of the slight shuffling as one and all at various times craned their necks to see how the visitors were receiving the efforts of the children. One frank young man said that he had watched them, and could see that "vou'se was pleased". The "closes" themselves stand out in the memory of at least one of the visitors as unique. The large room, sided with boards, was dimly lighted with the lamps and lanterns which the audience had brought. A small wood stove and its stovepipe burned red in the OUR SETTLEMENT SCHOOL 251 center of the room. A profusion of holly branches heavily laden with red berries decorated the windows and the low platform stretching across the front of the room. Just off the platform, at the left, stood a small reed organ. The desks were of all ages, from new ones just placed to old, scarred ones showing intimate relations with the jack knives of boyish occupaths. The audience itself baffles satisfying description. Little Pigeon has its own fashion standards in matters of manners and dress, of course, but manners and dress are external, and now is not the time for a description of them. The real men and women, their thoughts and their emotions, are not quite easy to understand. Unlike the thousands of illiterate foreign men and women in our cities, these mountain men and women of purest English ancestry, deprived of educational opportunities, do not wear their hearts upon their sleeves or show their thoughts in their faces for the casual observer to read. The program was begun by Mr. Ogle calling on Doctor Bishop for the opening prayer. Thus, at the beginning, was shown the influence of the new teacher. The native preacher had not responded to an invitation to give the prayer, because the usual closing exercises had needed praying for too greatly to make it meet for him to open them with prayer. After the prayer, as Miss Hill took her place at the organ, Mr. Ogle, in his timid way, announced a song. That wonderful organ, to buy which the Washington and Baltimore girls denied themselves so loyally! It produced the enveloping atmosphere of the whole program. The delight of the children in it had led the teachers to devote their time spent in preparing for this evening to trying to teach them to sing and drill to music. Forty-five boys and girls from seven to twenty years of age marched proudly to the plat-form as Miss Hill played. At least they thought that they were marching, but unison of step was too new, and too difficult for them to learn in their short training. Undisturbed by their mistakes, however, they stood swayingly happy in their places, the big ones ranged against the wall, and the littler ones ranged in steps down to the front row. And how they sang! Loudly and mechanically and independently, each one sang as seemed to him best. Fine zest was given to the singing by the successful attempt of Emma Maples to out-sing May Montgomery. The number which seemed most appreciated, though, was a simple </p>
      <pb ref="arr2920249_0003" seq="03" n="252-253  "/>
       <p>252 THE ARROW OF P1 BETA PHI calisthenic drill. Again they all tramped to the platform while Miss Hill played, though it could not be said truthfully that they tramped "to" music. The leader of the drill was Emma Maples, who stood in front facing the platform. She had tow-colored hair., tied with big bows of white ribbon, .and she wore a brilliant red cotton dress. Emma's right arm shot up and down; then her left arm shot up and down ; out and in went her right arm; out and in went her left arm; then both arms at once shot up and down. And on to the end of the few movements her arms went on their appointed way. The boys and girls before her most earnestly imitated her. As she followed a rhythm of her own somewhat different from that of Miss Hill's playing, so each one of them shot arms up and down, and out and in, "in numbers" of his own. Interspersed among the songs and drills were speeches by the visitors. Doctor Bishop spoke effectively of the relation of hard study to success of any kind. He pointed his moral with amusing stories, which were received with the same solemn attention as his most serious words. Probably the speaker most appreciated by the audience was Superintendent Keeble, for, in a few well chosen words, he presented the prizes. To Amber Ogle, among the boys, he gave two prizes, for "head distinction" in spelling and for neatness. To Beulah Bohannan, among the girls, he gave the prize for "head distinction" in spelling. Miss Miller next spoke, first of the purpose of school in general, and then of the Pi Phi school and its teachers in relation to the Little Pigeon community. The singing of America, all standing, ended "the closes". OUR FIRST PI PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL TEACHER Della W. Gillette was born in Traverse City, Michigan, where she spent the years of her school life and especially in the high school, gained a reputation for brilliant scholarship, and was a general favorite with both instructors and students. The year after her graduation from high school she entered the University of Illinois, with the intention of taking the course offered for librarians. Here she was initiated into Illinois Z. When she had been in the university but two years she was offered the position of librarian at the Oak Park branch library in Traverse City. In the few years that she held this position, she built up the library and established a story OUR SETTLEMENT SCHOOL 253 hour; her success in this line is vouched for by the adoring boys and girls that community. In this work she had to deal with a group of very rough boys whom no one else could manage, but they would do anything to please "Miss Gillette". She spent one summer at the University of Michigan, in the summer library school and be-came greatly interested in book making. The position of head librarian in the Traverse City library was offered Dell, but she de DELLA W. GILLETTE (Illinois Z, ex '09) clined, in order to let another girl have it. Two years ago, she re-signed her position, in order to have more time in her home, but she was not allowed to rest for long, as the committee at the head of the Bureau of Charities begged her to take a position as acting head of the Bureau. Into this work she put her whole heart and soul, and accomplished so much in the work that, when she wanted to resign, the committee implored her to keep the position, but she felt that an older woman, trained for that kind of work was needed. She. is the ideal girl to act as our first Pi Phi Settlement School </p>
      <pb ref="arr2920249_0004" seq="04" n="254-255  "/>
       <p>254 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI teacher. This brings this short sketch up to date. All who have met Dell, and felt her charm, learn as they know her better how truly fine, loyal and genuine she is. GENE CAMERON. MRS. E. A. HELMICK CHAIRMAN AND TREASURER 4837 KENMORE AVE. MISS KATE B, MILLER PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL POLICY AND PUBLICITY 112 S. ASHLAND BLVD. MRS. C. W. BARRETT FURNISHINGS 446 ST. JAMES PL. AUTHORIZED BY THE 21ST BIENNIAL CONVENTION ESTABLISHED IN FEBRUARY, 1912 MRS, HERMAN VON HOLST BUILDING CONSTRUCTION 1361 E. 51ST STREET MISS DEMA HARSHBARGER SECRETARY 4727 KENMORE AVE. NOTES FROM THE FIELD On Monday, December 3, the Settlement School was opened by Miss Miller with the two fraternity teachers, Miss Hill and Miss Gillette in charge. Over forty pupils were registered that day, and at present, seventy-five are enrolled. More have since had to be refused admission because of limitations of space and of the teaching force.. One of those who had to be refused was Mr. Ogle, the public school teacher. The serious obstacles confronting the teachers were the lack of grading in the school work and the lack of discipline among the children. Seventy-five ungraded and undisciplined pupils from four to twenty-five years old to be cared for by two teachers! Both of these obstacles are yielding, however, to the systematic planning and actual work of committees and teachers. All Pi Phis are urged to read in the Christmas number of the American Magazine, Emerson Hough's article entitled "Burns of the Mountains". Our situation and work is almost identical. Please note the organization of the Settlement School Committee and be careful to write to the person directly concerned about the branch of the work of which you are inquiring, when writing for information. Mrs. Barrett reports the following gifts to the school since October 1 : A sewing machine from the Franklin chapter; 1 dozen each of knives, forks, teaspoons and IA dozen tablespoons from Miss HOerlocker for the Los Angeles Club; 1 clock from the mother of a Michigan girl; 2 pairs of sheets and 67 bird pictures from Mrs. O. M. Schantz, Chicago, Ill.; x dozen each of napkins and dish towels from Chicago alumnae club; 50 song books from Mr. Percy S. Foster, Washington, D. C.; 1 large U. S. map, 12 yards blackboard cloth and 1 box books, from Miss Frazier, St. Louis ; x dozen damask towels and 1 box of books and pictures from Miss Allyn, for the Boston alumna~ club; pair sheets and pillow cases from Mrs. Carmon of Cincinnati. In response to many questions as to needs, Mrs. Barrett says: "We need MONEY most of all but could use also, a large U. S. flag, some 11 B I pennants, a magic lantern and a Victrola. OUR SETTLEMENT SCHOOL 255 (The following editorial from the Sevier County Republican for December 4, 1912 shows how our school is appreciated locally.--EDITOR) THE GATLINBURG SCHOOL We have had occasion to mention this school before and we do so again because we think it is a good thing for the community in which it is trying to secure a permanent abiding place. It is fostered and controlled by the Pi Beta Phi Fraternity, an organization of college women. Their objects and aims are highly commendable. It is their earnest desire to help to develop the head and heart and hand of those who do not have all the advantages they desire along educational lines. They want to teach the girls to cook and sew as well as to read and write. In short they want to help our people to properly understand the philosophy of right living. Miss Martha Hill was the first teacher sent out by this organization and she has done heroic service as a pioneer in starting the school at Gatlinburg. Her work has been in connection with the public school during the fall term, which closed last Friday. The Pi Beta Phi settlement school opened again Monday with an enrollment of about thirty-five pupils. The advantages of such a school can be seen at a glance. The public school term of three or four months gives the child a poor chance. From now until next fall they have no schooling and forget about all they have learned. With this school the studies can be kept up continuously and many useful things learned not found in the public school course or in text books. This school has grown considerably. Miss Rill has been unable to do all of the work alone and recently Miss Della Gillette, of the University of Illinois, has been there as an assistant. The school is yet in the experimental stage. The fraternity women mean to make it a permanent thing at Gatlinburg provided the people there want the school and proper inducements are offered. They wish to secure a tract of land and erect substantial buildings on it so that the work can be carried on in approved style. In our opinion the people of Gatlinburg should get together and present these good women a building site free. You can mighty well afford to do it. It will increase the value of your land many fold in a few years to have such an institution planted permanently in your midst. Miss Kate Miller, University of Chicago, and special English teacher in Lewis Institute, returned from Gatlinburg Monday. She had gone to inspect the work and incidentally to look over some tracts of land for the buildings. She is pleased with the trip and the prospects of the school. She thinks there is no doubt of the school being located there if the necessary land can be secured. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



