<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr3130385_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>A Pictorial Visit to Our Settlement School</title>

                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>March 1915</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr3130385_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">March 1915</date>, A Pictorial Visit to Our Settlement School</title>

                        <extent>Pages 384-391</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">36</note>
                        <note type="Folder">1</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 31, Number 3 (March 1915), Pages 384-391.</note>
			<note type="document">arr3130385_0000</note>


	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Founding of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1909-1927</item>
                                <item>Facilities</item>
                                <item>Students</item>
                                <item>Teachers</item>
                                <item>Handicraft</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr3130385_0001" seq="01" n="384-385  "/>
       <p>A PICTORIAL VISIT TO OUR SETT F MENT SCHOOL z ,r) 4.1 cf.) aaSSaNNU1, N SV 1I NI SMaI11 'IVDIdAJ. </p>
      <pb ref="arr3130385_0002" seq="02" n="386-387  "/>
       <p>SOME OF OUR PUPILS IN THE HEART OF THE SMOKIES . PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL---DEDICATED JULY 9, 1914 BUILDING USED FOR THE KINDERGARTEN 1913-14 OLD SCHOOL BUILDING USED 1912-1913-1914 </p>
      <pb ref="arr3130385_0003" seq="03" n="388-389  "/>
       <p>~~,~i rf~ // //:,' / //A r i l / o ,"'/' zi-,//'/, v, / 't, r/04t,,,, PROPOSED TEACHERS' RESIDENCE PLANsl3yW;I-SON AND WILSON Cal't4* NEWYORK EXTERIOR OF PROPOSED TEACHERS' RESIDENCE T i4 o o ec N i a) ;2 8'g PLANS FOR INTERIOR OF PROPOSED TEACHERS' RESIDENCE FORDING-A NECESSARY PART OF EVERY MOUNTAIN JOURNEY (Published by courtesy of Zion's Herold.) THE HOME OF PI PHI'S NEAREST NEIGHBOR IN GATLINBURG THE OLD SCHOOL HOUSE </p>
      <pb ref="arr3130385_0004" seq="04" n="391-391  "/>
       <p>COMBINED CHURCH AND SCHOOL HOUSE LOCATED A FEW MILES FROM G MIN BURG WHICH SERVES A COMMUNITY OF ABOUT 300 PEOPLE (Published by courtesy of Zion's Herald.) A TYPICAL MOUNTAIN CABIN-THE HOME OF A FAMILY OF THIRTE: (Published by courtesy of Zion's Herald.) DR. YANCEY OF THE TENNESSEE HOOKWORM COMMISSION WITH MISS POLLARD WORKING AS HIS ASSISTANT IN GATLINBURG (Published by courtesy of Zion's Herald.), </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



