<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr3720177_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Bishop, Evelyn</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>December 1920</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr3720177_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">December 1920</date>, News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Bishop, Evelyn</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 177-180</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">36</note>
                        <note type="Folder">12</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 37, Number 2 (December 1920), Pages 177-180.</note>
			<note type="document">arr3720177_0000</note>


	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Founding of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1909-1927</item>
                                <item>Music</item>
                                <item>Handicraft</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr3720177_0001" seq="01" n="176-177  "/>
       <p>76 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI ative cook whom they taught and whose work they supplemented rom time to time with favorite dishes of their own preparation. It is strong American stomach, indeed, that can stand a year's boarding t a native table. The dishes are uniformly greasy and heavy, with ,lmost no fresh fruits or vegetables to counterbalance. Malaria and typhoid are a real menace here, and only by systematially sleeping under tightly tucked in mosquito nets and drinking )oiled water can they be avoided. For the girl who comes here for a year or two of experience in eaching, or to learn Spanish there are many pleasures which over-)alance the disadvantage of low salary and high steamship fare to Lnd fro which must be met with her own funds. The scenery is ;orgeous, and there are splendid roads to all parts of the island i almost any point can be reached by automobile and the return home wade in a week-end. Every town of any size has its American church vith a scattering of Americans from the mainland and native conrerts. Then there is the beautiful native embroidery to be admired Lnd collected perhaps, the splendid fruits and comfortable climate 'or indoors and on porches; one never experiences the heat of a ummer's day such as of the Middle West. American girls are always nvited to the dances, and every town has its movies, the larger apes having all the best films. In spite of twenty years of occupation and familiarity with Amerimns, however, many of the old customs of the Spanish days hold -ood, and an American girl will do well to remember some of the all ?ervading, if to her strange, notions of social etiquette here. The ?eople as a whole have never become fully accustomed to the inde-?endence and freedom of the American girl, and if she would retain :he respect and good-will of the townspeople where she lives, she nust forego sometimes what in the States are innocent and ordinary ?1easures. Jaunts unchaperoned, with a gentleman escort, give rise :o suspicion of a girl's motives, though several young people of the :wo sexes or a crowd of girls may go about alone uncriticized. Un-'.ortunately, to the Spanish mind, there is but one meaning attributed :o a girl's being alone with a gentleman and out of the sight of )ther people. Many of our girls have not heeded warnings in the natter and before the year is out have found themselves somewhat )stracized by the natives little as they really deserve such treatment. :t is by a careful attitude toward these things that an American girl NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 177 can help a native community, for naturally her influence in the school room is negligible, if her pupils have not confidence in her conduct after she leaves them. Conservative and uncomprehending of our social customs, as the Porto Ricans may be inclined to smile tolerantly at our unintential brusqueness, Yankee hustle, and fantastic sense of honor in business, one feels sure of their sincere if unexpressed approval of developments and growth during our occupation. Somewhat deliberately they take advantage of innovations, but enthusiastically cling to them when won over, forgetting, as is human, the ridicule heaped upon the "crazy Americans" who instituted the change. We some-times find ourselves as regards their opinion of us, in the honorable if not always spicy position of old Sal, the wash-woman who having ceased to be comely, confided to a friend, "Ah knows Ah ain't par: ticular chahmin' to Mose no mo, but Ah reckin he'll stick by long's Ah keep dese heap wash places." Guayama----P. R. NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON BY EVELYN BisHop Two things stand out in a most unique way as belonging definitely to the Southern Mountains and holding charm and interest for every-one who can become at all familiar with them, the mountain ballad, dating back to the old Elizabethan period, and the hand-woven cover-lets, with design as old *as the ballad and the beautiful pattern showing, if we only knew it, as clearly the clan to which it belonged as does the Scotch plaid. We read so much of the mountains and their people these days that one hardly, needs to remind residents of other sections of the isolation, the old, old customs still in use and the splendid people with their quaint ways and speech. Anyone who has ever been in the mountains can readily understand the romance and art that is woven into the songs, the coverlets or the people themselves for trees and streams have spoken to them much more frequently than the human voice and nature's beauties have not been marred or supplemented by anything artificial. A love of music and an ear for it seem natural to nearly everyone. Many times it is the ballad that the child learns first, no Mother </p>
      <pb ref="arr3720177_0002" seq="02" n="178-179  "/>
       <p>178 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI Goose melodies are as familiar and it is strange indeed to listen to a little tot singing of the courtly days of old, the knights and "ladyes" and probably the tragic death of the lover. It is still the custom to have "singings" when a family move into a new house, when the young people want some entertainment or celebrate at holiday time. Christmas or Thanksgiving do riot bring the songs of the seasons but the old songs handed down from generation to generation and some-times I almost regret that we teach in the schools so many new songs and perhaps encourage the younger ones to neglect what belongs so distinctly to them. A few years. ago Mr. Cecil Sharp, of London, visited this section of the country and in talking to the young people in one of our schools gave the history of some of the ballads. After he had sung some, one of the lads told us those were "love songs" the people at his home knew. Mr. Sharp became interested at once and made a trip of eighteen miles back to the boy's home where he found over two hundred old ballads, some that had been partly or entirely lost in England for years but had remained intact in these mountains. To those of us who are acquainted with the country and people his introduction to the English Folk Songs of the Southern Appalachians is most interesting and true to present day conditions. "The present inhabitants of the Laurel Country are the direct descendants of the original settlers who were emigrants from England and, I suspect, from the lowlands of Scotland 4 was able to ascertain with some degree of certainty that the settlement of this particular section began about three or four generations ago, that is, in the latter part of the eighteenth century or early part of the nineteenth. How many years prior to this the original emigration had taken place I am unable to say but it is fairly safe, I think, to conclude that the present-day residents of this section of the mountains are the descendants of those who left the shores of England some time in the eighteenth century. Their speech is English, not American, and from the number of expressions they use which have long been obsolete elsewhere, and the old-fashioned way in which they pronounce many of their words, it is clear they are talking the language of a past day, though of what period I am not competent to decide. Although uneducated, in the sense in which that term is usually understood they possess that elemental wisdom, abundant knowledge and intuitive understanding which only those who live in constant touch NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON with Nature and face to face with reality seem to be able to acquire Physically, they are strong and of good stature, though usually spar in figure. Their features are clean cut and often handsome whil their complexions testify to wholesome out-of-door habits. The: carry themselves superbly, and it was a never-failing delight to not their swinging, easy gait and the sureness with which they coull negotiate the footlogs over the creeks, the crossing of which caused u many anxious moments. The reason, I take it, why these rnountai: people, albeit unlettered, have acquired so many of the essentials o culture is partly to be attributed to the large amount of leisur they enjoy, without which, of course, no cultural development is pos sible, but chiefly to the fact that they have one and all entered a birth into the full enjoyment of their racial heritage. My sole purpose in visiting this country was to collect traditiona songs and ballads--1 naturally expected to find conditions very simi tar to those which 'I encountered in England when engaged in th same quest. But of this I soon was to be disillusioned. Instead, fo instance, of having to confine my attention to the aged as in Englan, where no one under the age of seventy ordinarily possesses the folk song tradition, I discovered that I could get what I wanted fro': pretty nearly everyone I met, young and old. In fact, I found myself for the first time in my life in a community where singing was a common and almost as universal a practice as talking. It is no exalt geration to say that some of the hours I passed sitting on the porc' of a log cabin, talking and listening to songs, were amongst th pleasantest I have ever spent. The mountain singers sing in very much the same way as the ET4 lish folk-singer, in the same direct, straight-forward manner, withot any conscious effort at expression, and with the even tone and clarit of enunciation with which all folk-song collectors are familiar. The have one vocal peculiarity, however, which I have never noticed anion the English, namely the habit of dwelling arbitrarily upon certai notes of the melody, generally the weaken accents. The wonderfi charm, fascinating and well-nigh magical, which the folk-sing produces upon those who are fortunate enough to hear him is to 1 attributed very largely to his method of singing, and this, it shou: be understood, is quite as traditional as the song itself." In closing his splendid appreciation of the mountain people ar their ballads Mr. Sharp calls attention to a most important fact, th </p>
      <pb ref="arr3720177_0003" seq="03" n="180-181  "/>
       <p>180 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI of holding to the best in the old while we are teaching the' new. There are so many things which should be carefully held and guarded lest they entirely vanish as new people, new business and more education come in. To quote Mr. Sharp again: "Remembering that the primary purpose of education is to place the children of the present generation in possession of the cultural achievements of the past so that they may as quickly as possible enter into their racial inheritance, what better form of music or literature can we give them than the folk-songs of the race to which they belong, or of the nation whose language they speak? To put it another way, the aim of educationist should be not to forge the first link of a new chain, but to add a fresh link to the old one." IN MEMORIAM ANDERSON (MRS. R. W.), CELINA C. PLANK, Iowa E, '81, of Pulaski, Iowa, died April 16, 1920 at Graham Hospital, Keokuk, Iowa, Where she had been attending the sick bed of her husband. She was a member of I. C., as were also her two sisters, Mrs. Charles Milligan, Oklahoma City, Okla., and Mrs. W. L. Heath of Webster Groves, Mo. Mrs. C. E. Faeth of Kansas City and Miss Elva Plank of Pi Beta Phi House, Columbia, her cousins, were also members of the same chapter. While Mrs. Anderson was ever faithful to her Lord first in all things, she had pleasure in her fraternity and was a member of Woman's Legislative League of Des Moines, Iowa, and at the time of her death was worthy Matron of the 0 B in her home town. CONAWAY, LAURA COLE, Io'wa r, ex-'16, died at Ponca City; Oklahoma, May 23, 1920, of pneumonia. She was initiated into Iowa T, December 20, 1912. After two years at Ames, Laura transferred her credits to the State Teachers College at Cedar Falls where she was graduated in June 1916. She taught Home Economics one year in the Larrabee public school at Clermont, Iowa, and two years. at Upper Iowa University, Fayette. On November 14, 1918 a message from the government to Laura stated thaf her fiance, Hewitt L. Williams had died in France. Laura had made her supreme sacrifice to her country. Believing that greater opportunities for service would be hers as a hospital die-titian she entered Michael Reese Hospital, Chicago, in September IN MEMORIAM 181 1919 and while receiving her training, conducted evening classes in Chicago Community centers for the American Red Cross. She also received her commission as an American Red Cross dietitian. On March first of the present year she accepted the position of dietitian at the hospital in Ponca City, Oklahoma. Laura was an enthusiastic II id. While residing in Mason City she and her mother were loyal members of the Mason City Panhellenic club. In college days Laura's leadership in the social life of the Y. W. C. A. was an inspiration to all who worked with her. Her beautiful Christian character radiated good cheer and sincerity. To Laura's mother and father, Mr. and Mrs. Freeman R. Conway and her brother, Richard, Iowa I' extends its deepest sympathy. MARY REGINA GRIFFIN died May 3, 1920, of double pneumonia at her home in Pittsburgh, Pa. She was initiated into Pennsylvania A, September 19, 1918, at its installation. The saddest experience that has occurred in the history of the Pennsylvania L. and the Pittsburgh Alumnae Club is the death of Mary Griffin, who was a charter, member of the local chapter. Her death seemed more sad to us because the date of her burial fell on her twenty-fourth birthday. Mary was the reserved, quiet, dignified type of a girl, self-effacing and putting the chapter's interests far above her own. Only those who came in daily contact with her could penetrate the quiet of her and see the sterling woman beneath. She came into the petitioning chapter, the Dianthian Fraternity in her sophomore year and was initiated into Pennsylvania at the time of its installation, September 19, 1918, and served as corresponding secretary during her senior year in college. She was an energetic II 1 worker and held the chapter's interests at heart, Having graduated from Peabody High School, Pittsburgh, Pa., with honors she was, an excellent student in college. Her final record showed that she had missed the cum Zaude by a small percentage. She was a real force in the chapter, and her opinion was always regarded when decisions of moment necessitated. Pi Phis in Pitts-burgh feel her loss keenly. WILKES (MRS. W. W.) LUCY MANN, '20, Washington B, '20, died at her home in Puyallup, Wash., of pneumonia. She was initiated into Washington B at the State College of Washington, March 17, 1917. At the time of her death she was a member of the Ina Smith Soule Alumnae Club in Tacoma, Wash. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



