<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr3940629_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Rugg, Sarah Pomeroy</name></author>
                        <author><name>Dowell, Anna</name></author>
                        <author><name>Higenbotham, Phyllis</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>June 1923</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr3940629_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">June 1923</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Rugg, Sarah Pomeroy</name></author>
                        <author><name>Dowell, Anna</name></author>
                        <author><name>Higenbotham, Phyllis</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 628-646</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">37</note>
                        <note type="Folder">2</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 39, Number 4 (June 1923), Pages 628-646.</note>
			<note type="document">arr3940629_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">A Social Event in Gatlinburg; A Course in Practical Housewifery; Luncheon at Twelve; Nursing in the Mountains; Bibliography on the Southern Highlanders</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Founding of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1909-1927</item>
                                <item>Social events</item>
                                <item>Health care</item>
                                <item>Home economics</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr3940629_0001" seq="01" n="628-629  "/>
       <p>628 THE ARROU' OF PI BETA Pt!! Dr. David Jayne Hill grandfather of Anna Hill, New York A. Author and diplomat. Mr. Hill is a former minister to the Nether-lands and an ex-ambassador to Germany. Burdette G. Lewis husband of Pearl Archibald, Nebraska B. Examiner for Interstate Commerce Commission, which work took him to New York as First Statistician. Appointed assistant to John Purroy Mitchell. Commissioner of Corrections in Mayor Mitchell's cabinet. Is at present State Commissioner of the Department of Institutions and Agencies of New jersey, where he has done a vast amount of very successful work. Mr. Lewis is the author of many articles and of The Offender in Relation to Lazo and Society, published by Harper Brothers. Mr. Bates, Commissioner of Corrections at Boston, says this is the best book on the penal question in the English language. Captain E. D. Stanley husband of Eva Cooper Stanley, Nebraska B, was the first man mentioned by Charles G. Davies in his report to President Harding as having done such efficient work in the navy. He was recently loaned by the United States to Peru to help that country with its finances, and to teach it how to build up and run its navy. Commander Stanley, called "El Capitan" in Peru, previously was with Admiral Caperton's fleet on a diplomatic mission to Buenos Aires, Montevideo, etc. NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON EDITED BY SARAH POMEROY RUGG, Massachusetts A An outstanding feature of the past year at the Settlement School has been the installation of a moving picture outfit. This was mentioned in Miss Bishop's April letter to alumnm clubs but her account of the initial performances of the movies deserves permanent record. A SOCIAL EVENT IN GATLINBURG If I should tell the tale of the first movie ! ! ! I nev( r will forget it and I don't think anyone in this house will. For a whole month we had planned for pictures and the boys and girland did want them so much. At last, after telegrams, letters and everything that we could think of, we completed a schedule for the latter part of March, April, May and June. Films were to come from Atlanta, Chicago, University of Indiana and some from the University of Tennessee. NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 6.29 We had had to give up pictures for the close of school as it took a whole week for a telegram to get to Atlanta and a reply back here. The next movie was scheduled for March 31 and as there were two weeks for the film to get here we thought everything would surely be all right. Saturday came and we could scarcely wait for the mail to come in for Mr. Mattil and Estel Huff wanted to try out the machine and have a little experience putting in the films. But, alas, no films came. I was nearly sick. Just as Walter was going out with the mail I dashed down our lane and told him to meet the next two trains in Sevierville and if the films came to bring them right on .up here. I thought that by four-thirty or five o'clock he would be here and that there would then be plenty of time to make fires in the schoolhouse and get ready for the entertainment. By noon there were quite a good many boys and girls in the Burg and by four o'clock nearly all the school children had arrived, for all were to have free admission that night. I told them that unless they saw Walter come in by five o'cock there would be no use for them to wait but they stayed just the same and at six o'clock the schoolhouse was full. What to do we didn't know. It had been a strenuous day for all here and we thought we never could man-age a social that night, especially on such short notice, but some thing had to be done. While we were eating supper Estel came in with word that Walter had come with the films. It was then between six and seven and the school-house freezing cold but over we went. In spite of weather and inexperience in running the machine we had movies and had all six reels. Nearly everyone stayed for the whole show and between reels would flock into the hall around the fireplace and visit until time for the next one. It was ten-thirty, mighty late for Gatlinburg, when "The End" was flashed on the screen. The second movie night was not so strenuous. Our films came a day or two ahead of time and Friday night the family and Estel Huff went to the schoolhouse for a very select movie. Mr. Mattil has taught Estel to run the machine splendidly and with both of them there they manage quite an expert show. Government films do not allow for admission so a collection was taken that nearly paid express charges. The house was full and several stout people were sitting on the kindergarten chairs and I am glad they are made good and strong. People came Saturday night that hadn't been in the Burg for weeks and I find that movies are going to mean a social time. Aunt Lizzie had seen all the pictures Friday but Saturday night went again and came back with word that she had visited folks she hadn't seen for years. Whole families walked anywhere from one to six miles and back that night. Everyone says that the machine is a beauty, even those who operate it, and they are usually apt to be very critical. I know movies are going to be a great success here. Provision for an adequate cottage dormitory system is one of the problems which our school is facing. Mrs. Dowell who served as a volunteer worker at the school for a portion of last year has been a </p>
      <pb ref="arr3940629_0002" seq="02" n="630-631  "/>
       <p>THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI regular member of the staff this past season with headquarters irk the Mary Pollard Cottage where she has acted as house mother for the little girls who lived there in addition to teaching sewing. Her careful conscientious work has been of great benefit to the girls. A COURSE IN PRACTICAL HOUSEWIFERY Another year of school has passed and it sometimes seems that we have accomplished very little, but when we compare the beginning with the closing of the year we think several things have been accomplished. This has been more noticeable in the sewing classes, perhaps, than in the regular school work. Five girls in the sixth grade and one in the fifth grade completed the year's work and one who entered after the Christmas vacation completed the preliminary work. They learned stitches for sewing, finishing, embroidery and hemstitching; seams, hems, patching on plain, check and striped material ; darning on dress goods and stockings; made aprons, gowns, bloomers, teddys and one or more dresses. The work was excellent for girls from twelve to fourteen years of age who had never done any sewing before. There is one thing these people are loath to do and that is to take anything out when it is not done right. When I insisted they always did it but with very poor. grace. You should see their faces shine when they finally got it right for they knew just as well as I when it looked right. The habit of "any way'll do" and "what difference will it make" practiced by mother and grandmother for generations is not easily broken. The patching and darning was the most difficult as such things are simply not done in these parts. If a dress or stocking gets torn they draw it together with some thread, the color does not matter in the least, and let it 'go at that and after a week or two throw it away and buy new. I have tried to show them that this was extravagant and wasteful when they had so little to begin with, but they couldn't or wouldn't see it that way. The older or rather more advanced class from the high school from twelve to nineteen years of age, had had a little experience in sewing in the homes and after the preliminary work cut and made gowns, teddys, slips, aprons, kimonos and dresses, made lunch cloths and dresser scarfs in embroidery or applique work. They were very ambitious and wanted to make many things too difficult for first-year pupils even with the experience in sewing in the home. Two of the NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON older girls dropped out at Christmas, one to get married and other to attend a school a little more conveniently located for We had six girls in the Mary Pollard Cottage this year and t] were some lively times. One girl was full of fun and mischief w most of the others were not able to take a joke so at times the atr phere would be somewhat thick for May did love to tease and others were not able to "come back" at her. The work was so arranged that two did the cooking, two the d washing and two the sweeping, changing each week. They -s; told at the beginning that they must get up in the morning witl being called and have breakfast in time for the dishwashers to g( school. We nearly always ate breakfast at six o'clock but sev times they were through eating before five. These people get up when they awaken and many have breakfast at four or four-th: Even on Sunday mornings breakfast at four o'clock is no unu thing. They go to bed at dark so are ready to get up early ar will say it is a very good practice, once you get used to it, for you your work done so early and then can "set and think or just set many of the women do when their little bit of house work is finis after a fashion. It is just as hard for the girls to do the housework right as the sewing and if they scrub the floor in the center what differ if the corners and back of the stove and cupboard legs are mi Rinsing the dishes and washing the dishtowels when through i no use whatever. "Can't see no sense in bein' so particular a things, no how." Three of the girls were good cooks and the others were good ers. They prepared breakfast and supper and I was responsibli the noon meal as they were busy in school up to 12 M. 'I however, washed the dishes. Three of them helped with the lunch at school one day a week so during the year ,they lea "quite a bit" about cooking, dishwashing and cleaning. If they just do the work in their homes as they have learned to do it thr the year we will feel well repaid for the effort put forth. ANNA DowE] School lunches which were inaugurated a year ago to meet a real need among the children have been carried on the past s </p>
      <pb ref="arr3940629_0003" seq="03" n="632-633  "/>
       <p>632 THE ARROW OF BETA PHI under the supervision of Irene Linkous whose ,major duty, however, was the teaching of weaving which is a very popular and important course as now (Tiven at our school. dren's lunch each day. Our lunch room equipment consists of an oil stove, a sink, two tables covered with white oil cloth, four benches and necessary cooking utensils borrowed from the Pi Phi Cottage. At present we are using the basement of the schoolhouse for a lunch room. t was impossible, with all the arrangement of classes, for any of the older girls to help with the cooking, so it was necessary for us to use the five girls iii the sixth grade and all of the fourth grade girls. They were all small but applied themselves to their work wonderfully well. At eleven-thirty each day two fourth grade girls and one from the sixth grade quietly left their room and went to the basement to prepare lunch. One is surprised at the amount of responsibility children can assume when it is necessary. When, for any reason, it was not possible for me to be in the lunch room at eleven-thirty, one of the girls would go to Miss Burton's room to find how many children there would be for lunch. They would set the table, put water on the oil stove for dishes and wash the cooking utensils. After the children had lunch the girls would clear the tables, clean the oil stove and wash the dishes. Two children appointed each day from Miss Burton's room swept the floor. Once or twice the children had almost the entire responsibility of the lunch and they did it very well. At twelve o'clock anywhere from eight to twenty-five cllildren filed down the stairsto lunch and found their places at the table, each taking turn as host and hostess. When everyone was seated they bowed their heads and, with Miss Burton, said Grace. We did not supply a whole luncheon, just a bowl of soup, some scrambled eggs, or something hot to supplement what they had brought. We tried each day, except on those days when they had soup, to give each child a glass of milk. LUNCHEON AT TWELVE Schools in all parts of the world are waking up to the fact that children need something hot for their lunch. The Pi Beta Phi School, realizing this need, has something to supplement the chil NEU'S FROM LITTLE PIGEON During these three months the children learned some table etiqu they would not have learned otherwise. One incident that OA\ amuses me came from teaching them table manners. I had asked children not to talk when they had food in their mouths. T found it very hard to remember and quite often someone would : get. It was suggested that all those who forgot should sweep lunch room floor. Five-year old Maisie Whaley was visiting sd that day and heard the suggestion and it evidently "sank in." eral days later, when she was again visiting school, her older si forgot and spoke when she had food in her mouth. Quiet li Maisie, who never spoke or in any way made you aware of presence, beamed and bubbling over with excitement exclain "Oh yes, you have to sweep." The persons acting as host and hostess asked for the children he excused, when all had finished their lunch. Near the close school the "cooks" went up Mill Creek for a picnic and had a worn ful time. They talked picnic so much the younger children bec; thrilled and felt they too must have a picnic, so promptly a school some of the boys went to Miss Evelyn and asked her fc picnic. Of course Miss Evelyn couldn't refuse and it was deci that the next day would be the best time. The following day was wonderful for picnicing, so at elethirty, with our baskets on our arms, we started. This picnic like all others in the respect that we ate and played but it was dii ent in that every member enjoyed every minute of the time. I d think I ever saw children enjoy a picnic more. It would be hard to say who enjoyed, or got more from the sc' lunches, those who prepared them or those who ate. IRENE LINKOU The annual Mountain Workers' Conference held in Knox \ Tenn., is an event of great importance to all who are devoting lives to a solution of the problems of mountain people and . communities. This year our school was represented on the prof by our resident nurse whose excellent and comprehensive paper been sent to THE ARROW by our Head Resident. </p>
      <pb ref="arr3940629_0004" seq="04" n="634-635  "/>
       <p>634 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI NURSING IN THE MOUNTAINS Nursing conditions in different localities vary, but on the whole different mountain sections have more in common than mountains and cities, hence I should have been utterly at sea on coming into the mountains had it not been for the nurse at Hindman whom I visited as I came South, and who went to no end of trouble to tell and show me everything that she thought would be useful, and also Miss Rich whom I visited in North Carolina after I had been in the mountains six months and who helped me straighten out some of my problems, got my head above water and gave me fresh inspiration. A highly developed city nursing association, with the network of allied organizations, abundance of doctors, hospital and clinic facilities, above all its telephone communication and well developed spirit of cooperation and group methods is a far cry to no facilities, no organization at all, no telephone and a firmly rooted individualistic and independent spirit. The people had as vague an idea of a nurse as I had of what comprised nursing in the mountains. Their experience was limited to a few private nurses, so a nurse to them meant someone who would make an indefinite stay and relieve the family of all responsibility a short visit resembled the doctor's consequently as a Public Health nurse I was neither fish, flesh, fowl, nor good red herring; being variously called the doctor, the nurse, the cook or the waiter and since I wouldn't diagnose and prescribe, or go and spend weeks with a typhoid case the people were much puzzled to know of what use I could really be. I have tried all along to let the people take the initiative and send for me rather than to hunt them up in that way I feel they really want what we have to give. So far as possible we want them to feel the need and then try to meet that need rather than force it on them. For example: we haven't accommodation for more than one emergency case or so, but of late there have been several inquiries as to whether we would take in patients, several obstetrical patients would like to have been cared for in the hospital, several feeding cases, etc., and eventually we hope to take in such, but the demand is coming from the people. My education has progressed; if not the people's. I soon found NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 635 the people weren't used to hurrying, and that it takes a long time of patient waiting and general conversation to find out what they have really come for, or to get a history of the cases when making a visit. I have had to get used to getting most of a woman's symptoms from her husband, and not having heart failure when a messenger comes with the news that so and so is "bad off" "about to die" or "got the fever." Also I am not as sensitive as I once was about always being asked, for months afterwards if I was with so and so who died. I used to resent the implication that I had hastened their departure. I was warned not to have my district too large, consequently I try to keep within a five-mile radius when I have to make calls outside of it one visit will often take all day. In the first three months about fourteen nights were spent away from home, but gradually the people are getting more accustomed to the idea of my going in, showing them what to do and returning. Later on it may be possible to emphasize more of the preventive and instructive work, but at present my work is largely care of the sick, and the people are usually sick, too. Infectious diseases are apt to be severer than one 'finds in the cities; for instance diphtheria gains fearful headway before any attempt is made to get help and the antitoxin is seldom given early if at all. As to small pox vaccination, they would much prefer the disease. Coming home after dark one night I found a call to see a baby that the father thought had membraneous croup. It was about the farthest place in another community. Taking all the emergency anti-toxin I had, one of the teachers drove me as far as possible in a Ford, then we walked through the woods to the house and gave the antitoxin by the help of a smoky lamp and a flashlight. The end of the gladd syringe broke on inserting the plunger and I was petrified, as the child needed all I had but fortunately we didn't lose any. The child couldn't have lived till morning so there was no waiting to get a doctor the nearest one couldn't have been gotten under six or eight hours provided he was home when called. In the above cases I charged about what the doctor would as I didn't want them to feel I would make a practice of giving antitoxip.. And the question of fees is a problem that we have still not </p>
      <pb ref="arr3940629_0005" seq="05" n="636-637  "/>
       <p>6 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI en able to solve and the longer I stay the more complicated it comes. The people are not well equipped for caring for the sick. The. Ltient must invariably be cared for in a double bed, the light is )t to be poor (hence a flashlight is one of my most treasured )ssessions), the question of giving a bed bath in winter is a omentous one. They seldom have the utensils and materials for .eparing food for the sick, nor does the patient always take kindly a new, even if more digestible dish. The food question is one of the great problems. There is not lough variety in the diet too much starchy food, corn, potatoes id beans, soda biscuits not well cooked, sorghum and eggs. In ,e season of plenty they are apt to get too much of a good thing. ne of the doctors was called to several cases of honey poisoning. he men had robbed some bee gums, eaten a pound or two each Id been knocked unconscious where they stood. "That's what they ill `eating a mess' " added the doctor. The school children are careless about bringing lunches they .de the lunch along the way rather than carry it to school, conseiently they have nothing from before daylight till after dark, so hool.lunches require oversight. The growing children are apt to we an insufficient supply of milk, due largely to lack of proper ed for cows and the lack is filled with coffee. They are conrvative about trying new vegetables and if they do grow them y don't know how to prepare them. One woman told me about .ising squashes and having the vaguest idea of what to do with em. They seldom can enough during the season of plenty for the ost part some jars of peaches, blackberries, tomatoes and pickled pans used for company though in marked contrast was a home onsisting of husband and wife) where there were three hundred .ns of fruit and vegetables to be moved out of the room we decided use as an operating room. During the apple season (which doesn't happen every year) chil-.en from a few months up, eat quantities a day, green and other-[se, accentuating sores and intestinal disturbances. Being distressed over the lack of vegetables in the diet I wrote [r Representative for a variety of vegetable seeds for about fifty NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 637 school children. He and the Government were nothing, if not generous. To my utter horror and amazement on returning after a few days' absence, I found two mail sacks full of seeds had been dumped out in the back of the store. The school horse was hitched to the buggy and I am not sure the envelopes were not shoveled in, for the buggy was full to overflowing, including the space under the seat, and we filled wash tubs, waste paper baskets and dish pans and gave out seeds to everyone we could for several years. I have never heard' that anyone learned to like carrots or peas in consequence, and now I am patiently waiting for. the department of agriculture to vary the planting of beans and corn and the domestic science department to cultivate the taste for vegetables new and untried. Gradually we have evolved from a few bandages, a roll of adhesive, a box of boric acid and a corner in the head resident's office to a four-room cottage, divided into an office, workroom, bathroom and emergency operating room or bedroom, equipped with running water, oil stove, electric light and our own linen supply a loan cupboard for the people, and an ever increasing stock of medicines on which the doctors are coming to rely more and more. It saves them carrying a good many and also saves the people trips as I keep a list of the medicines they are getting and can re-fill without . bothering the doctor. We have a microscope and some simple laboratory equipment : some instruments for lending when a doctor is away from home and runs on an unexpected case. The cottage was planned as a place for treating office cases, holding clinics, such as tonsil and adenoid, dental, etc., and taking care of accident cases, but in the last four months two and one-half have been spent there, two with a small boy who had a badly infected compound fracture of the leg and who came from a one-room log cabin. It was such a remote place that the doctor felt the leg would have to come off unless he was where it could be dressed daily. Then we had an emergency appendectomy not long ago. These cases have necessitated some member of the school staff staying with the patient while I made whatever trips were necessary, consequently we hope to find some woman who can be trained to help with the cleaning and putting up of supplies and who can stay with a patient and perhaps go into the homes as a practical nurse when </p>
      <pb ref="arr3940629_0006" seq="06" n="638-639  "/>
       <p>38 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI seeded. This may help to solve the problem of having regular ffice hours and of being able to do satisfactory school and lecture vork. At any rate it remains to be seen. I have practically three sets of equipment, one for office use, one 'or my saddle bags and one for the obstetrical bag which I found necessary to acquire a year ago, as sometimes it is impossible for the )eople to get a doctor in time. I have made it a rule not to go in )lace of 'a doctor and have only once broken my rule at the urgent .equest of a mid-wife who wanted me to care for her daughter. had a month or six weeks of such worry that I learned my lesson, L,nd though the problem of caring for the greater number of obstetical cases is still unsolved I never go unless they have attempted o get a doctor. One man wanted to know if I couldn't take obstetrical cases if had a prescription and after racking my brains to know what he rieant I found he had reference to my sending a man for the doctor ,nd to his bringing back a note in which he told me he couldn't ome and wished me luck. First, last, and always, there could have been no running without he loyalty, support and help of the doctors. It was they who, vhile not living here, came into the district when called, who paved he way for a nurse, have stood firm and strong for everything done nd have taught me much that belongs to the sphere of a doctor ,ecause they felt there would be emergencies to be met when they Teren't there. In short when I see one coming up the lane I have :Inch the same feeling I would have if it were my best friend. Nursing in the mountains may sound like nothing but problems nd difficulties but the compensation more than makes up for them. rfirst, the people themselves are wonderful to work with and for; D are the doctors and nowhere does one find such people and such zenery as in the mountains, and the longer one stays the more ascinating the work becomes. PHYLLIS HIGINBOTHAM. The following bibliography has been prepared by Dorothy K. Ieaveland, librarian of St. Lawrence University, at the request of le Settlement School Committee. It is based on the bibliography =piled by Alice Matthews in the early days of our work and on NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 639 others issued in connection with mountain work in other places. The entire manuscript has been revised and brought up-to-date so that Pi Phis may now have a guide for reading on this subject so interesting to us all and a fund of information' available for Settlement School programs. BIBLIOGRAPHY ON THE SOUTHERN HIGHLANDERS BY DOROTHY K. CLEAVELAND, New York F GENERAL BARTON, W. E. Life in the Hills of Kentucky. Oberlin, 1890 Sets forth the religious life of the people. BRADLEY, W. A. "Hobnobbing with Hillbillies." Harpers Magazine. 132: 91-103, December, 1915. Illus. Description of a trip through the mountain sections of Kentucky, Tennessee, and North Carolina. CADY, C. "In the Mountains." Outlook, 69:320-25, Oct 5, 1901. Ill. Description of the mountains and their people in and near* Berea, Ky. *CAMPBELL, J. C. Southern Highlander and His Homeland. N. Y. Russell Sage Foundation, 1921. $3.50. Most exhaustive book on the subject. Reviewed in ARROW, December, 1921, pp. 277-9. The author was for more than twenty-five years a worker among the mountaineers and was at the time of his death secretary of the southern highland section of the Russell Sage Foundation. CANBY, H. S. "Top o' Smoky." Harpers Magazine. 132:573-83, March, 1916. Ill. Article by a Harvard professor describing the mountain people on the North Carolina side of the Great Smokies. Draws a distinction between two classes of mountaineers, valley folk and cove folk. ComBs, J. H. "Kentucky Highlanders from the Native Mountaineer's Point of View." Pub. by author, Ardmore, Okla., 1913. pa. $ 50 COWAN, S. K. Sergeant York and His People. N. Y. Funk, 1922. Sergeant York, a Tennessee mountaineer, performed probably the most distinguished single act by a private in the Great War. This book pictures a community very similar to that around our settlement school. Re-viewed in THE ARROW, April, 1923, pp. 461-2. DAVIES, MARIA THOMPSON. "American Backgrounds for Fiction"--Tennessee. Bookman, 38:394-99, December, 1913. DAVENPORT, FREDERICK M. Primitive Traits of Religious Revival. N. Y. MacMillan, .1905. DAVIS, HARTLEY, AND SMYTH, CLIFFORD. "Land of Feuds." Munsey, 30: 161-72 November, 1903. DAVIS, JOHN M. "Southern Mountaineers." Western Teacher, 18:369-74, June, 1910. DAWLEY, T. R. "Our Southern Mountaineers." World's Work, 19:12704-14, March, 1910. An agent of the U. S. Government gives the results of </p>
      <pb ref="arr3940629_0007" seq="07" n="640-641  "/>
       <p>640 ' THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI an investigation of living conditions among 5,000 mountain people of Tennessee, North Carolina, and South Carolina. :He favors moving the people away to better environments instead of trying to do missionary work among them. EDWARDS, T. A. "Mountain People of Kentucky." Ohio Teacher, 25:380-82, May, 1905. Ill. ELLIOTT, A. S. "Kentucky Mountaineers." Bibliotheca Sacra, 63:487-509, July, 1go6. FELTON, R. A. "Race of Rip Van Winkles is Waking Up." World Outlook, 5 :21-32, November, 1919. FOX, JOHN, Jr.. Blue Grass and Rhododendrons. Outdoors in Old Kentucky. N. Y. 19o1. Illus. (First two chapters published under the title "The Southern. Mountaineer" in Scribners, 29; 1901.) The author of The Little Shepherd of Kingdom Conic describes the country and people which form the background for his novels. "On Horseback to Kingdom Come." Scribners, 48:185-86. Aug., '10 "On the Road to Hell-For-Sartin." Scribners, 48:350-61. Sept., 'to "On the Trail of the Lonesome Pine." Scribners, 48:417-29. Oct., 'to Descriptions of pilgrimages to the scenes of his stories. "Southern Mountaineers." Scribners, 29 :387-89, April 1901; ;56-10, May, 1901. Thus. Forms first two chapters of Blue Grass and Rhododendrons. Out-doors in Old Kentucky. Gives interesting anecdotes and pictures showing the more intimate side of the lives of the mountain folk. FRosT, W. G. "Our Contemporary Ancestors in the Southern Mountains." Atlantic, 83:311-19, March, 1899. One of the early articles on subject. "Our Southern Highlanders." Independent, 72:708-14, Apr. 4, 1912. "Southern Mountaineer, our Kindred of the Boone and Lincoln Type." Review' of Reviews, 21:303-11, March, 1900. Illus. The president of Berea College, Kentucky, makes a plea for Appalachian America. He praises the sturdy character of the people, tells of their needs and of the work of his college. FURMAN, LUCY. "Out by Ox-team." OuHaok 133:655-58, April II, 1923. Accounts of the joys and difficulties of travel in the mountains. "Glimpses of Kentucky Mountain Life Corporal Fess Whitaker tells his tale. Literary Digest, 60:89-100, February 22 1919. HANEY, W. H. The Mountain People of Kentucky. Lexington, .Ky., author, 1906, also Cincinnati. Written by the son of a Kentucky mountaineer, who worked his way through college and taught school within sight of his father's abandoned still. The most cheering part of the book is that on education. The desire for education on the part of the mountain boy and girl is almost insatiable and the educated mountaineer often re-turns to his. native home to help his people. HARLOW, A. F. "Frontier People of the Appalachians." Travel, 39:11-14, June, 1922. M. The Southern mountaineer, our purest racial stock, a surviving segment of the eighteenth century, real "Made in America" NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON goods, our most independent and self-reliant citizens. Article illustrf. with photographs by the author. HARTT, R. L. "Mountaineers Our Own Lost Tribes." Century, n. s. 395-404, January, 1918. Ill. Sympathetic account of the people Appalachian America. Corrects many erroneous impressions from much generalization on the part of many authors. JOHNSTON, CLIFTON. Highways and Byways of the South. Macmillan, lc Pictures of rustic life and nature. *KEPI ART, HORACE. Our Southern Highlanders. New edition, Macmil 1922. $2.50. Original edition, Outing, 1913. New edition contains three additional chapters and new illustratil Describes with much sympathy the characteristics and customs of mountaineers. The author has spent much time among these pco Next to Campbell, probably the most important book on the subject. "Life in the Kentucky Mountains by a Mountaineer." Independ 65 :72-82, July 9, Igoand Quaint autobiography in homely language. 11 "Lighting up the Southern Mountains." literary Digest, 72 :3 March 4, 1922. Illus. A description of the Southern mountain probl MACCLINTOCK. S. S. "Kentucky Mountains and Their Feuds." Amen Journal of Sociology, 7:1-28, 171-87, July, Sept., 1901. Illus. Out the most detailed and best general articles on the Kentucky mountaine "Map Talk on the Mountaineers of the South." Board of Home sions, Presbyterian Church. 5c. MASTERS, V. T. "Mountaineers of the South." Missionary Review, 48:845 November, 1919. MILES, E. B. Spirit of the Mountains. Pott, 1905. Pictures with sympathy, humor, and charm of style the southern m( taineers' primitive customs and mode of living, supernatural bel' old-fashioned religion, real American music, and native oral literat PIERSON, MRS. DELAVEN L. "Mountaineers of Madison County, North C lina." Missionary Review, 20 :821-31, November, 1897. PORTER, LAURA SPENCER. "In Search of Local Color." Harpers Maga 145 :281-94, 451-66, Aug., Sept., 1922. One of the editors of the Wom Home Companion tells of her visits to the mountains. RALPH, JULIAN. "Our Appalachian Americans." Harpers Magazine, 32-41, June, 1903. Illus. Good descriptions with humorous anecdl of home life in the Kentucky mountains. REVERE, C. T. "Beyond the Gap, the Breeding Ground of Feuds." Our 49:609-21, February, 1907. Illus. Experiences of a former membe the U. S. Geological Survey in the Cumberland Gap region of ] tucky, the stronghold of moonshiners and the breeding ground of f( SMITH, J. R. "Farming Appalachia." American Review of Reviews, 329-36, Mar., 1916. Story of a typical farming family in the sout mountains and in contrast the profitable agriculture which the mour farmer of Corsica, who uses no plow, has developed. We should t </p>
      <pb ref="arr3940629_0008" seq="08" n="642-643  "/>
       <p>642 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI our American mountain farmers this mountain agriculture, that he may prosper and his soil remain uneroded. SPAULDING, A. W. Men of the Mountains. Southern Publishing Association, 1915. $1.50. STEPHENSON, F. "Child Life of the Southern Mountaineers." Board of Home Missions, Presbyterian Church. STILES, D. H. "Fighting the Scourge on Troublesome." Survey, 35:726-27, March 18, 1916. A worker in the Hindman Settlement School describes the work of the Public Health Service in combating trachoma. SNEAD, L. U. "Diamonds in the Rough." Golden Industrial Institute, Golden, N. C., 1914. THOMPSON, S. H. Highlanders of the South. Methodist Book Concern, 1910. TouLmIN, H. A. JR. "Charles Egbert Craddock and the Mountain-dwellers' Life. In his Social Historians." Bast. Badger, 1911, p. 59-97. VINCENT, GEORGE EDGAR. "Retarded Frontier." American Journal of So ciology, 4:1-20, July, 1898. Illus. Description of Appalachian America by the president of the Rockefeller Foundation, at the time of writing, Professor of Sociology at University of Chicago. WALDO, FRANK. "Among the Southern Appalachians." New England Magazine, n. s., 24:231-47. May, 1901. Describes the region about Asheville, N. C., the scenes of many of Miss Murfee's stories. The author says she idealizes the ordinary life of the mountaineers, but commends her descriptions and portrayals of character, WILLIAMS, LILLIAN WALKER. "In the Kentucky Mountains." New England Magazine, n. s., 30 :37-45, March, 1904. WiLsoN, S. T. Southern Mountaineers. N. Y. Woman's Board of Home Missions, 1906. Also Revell, 1914. One of the most interesting and helpful books to be found on the subject. Author is president of Maryville College, Tenn. The Home mission boards of the Episcopal, Presbyterian, Congregational and other churches publish helpful material. The Quarterly magazine of the Southern Industrial Educational Association, Washington, D. C., and Cotton, published in Atlanta, Ga., also have numerous articles. HISTORICAL BACKGROUND ALLISON, JoHN. Dropped Stitches in Tennessee History. Marshall, 1897. BRIGHAM, A. P. Geographic Influences in American History. Ginn, 1903. Defines physiographic features influencing industrial and national life. BRUCE, H. A. Daniel Boone and the Wildernes's Road. Macmillan, 1910. FISKE, JoHN. Old Virginia and Her Neighbors. Houghton, 1897. HALE, J. P. Trans-Allegheny Pioneers. Graphic press, 1886. ROOSEVELT, THEODORE. Winning of the West. Putnam, 1904. Portrays advance of pioneer into wastes of the continent. NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 6 SEMPLE, E. C. American History and Its Geographic Conditions. Hought 1903. Study of the dominant influences of geographic conditions successive events of American history. SKINNER, CONSTANCE L. Pioneers of the Old Southwest. v. 18. Chronic of America. Yale University Press, 1919. History of the settlement the trans-Allegheny section. TEMPLE, 0. P. The Covenanter, the Cavalier, and the Puritan. 1897. EDUCATION BARTON, BRUCE. "Children of the Feudists." Colliers, 51 :7-8, Aug. 23, 19 Tells of the foundation of Berea College and the people whom it serN In Colliers, 52:26, Sept. 20, 1913, is a letter by J. W. Carlin, a K tuckian, called "The Kentucky Mountaineer" which comments on B ton's article but is of no great additional value. BRADLEY, W. A. "Women on Troublesome." Scribners, 63 :315-28, Mar., 19 Tells of the foundation of the Hindman Settlement School and conditions which it was organized to remedy. Illus. BURNS, J. A. "Letter from Burns of the Mountains." American Magazi 75;70, May, 1913. How one magazine article is endowing a colle Article referred to is Hough's Burns of the Mountains. CAMPBELL, J. C. "Future of the Church and Independent Schools in C Southern Highlands." Russell Sage Foundation, 1921. CAMPBELL, OLIVE DAME. "Southern Highland Schools Maintained by nominational and Independent Agencies." Russell Sage Foundati 1921. CLARKE, IDA CLYDE. "Living Memorial to Abraham Lincoln." Pictorial view, 24:20. February, 1923. Illus. Account of the Lincoln Memo University in Cumberland Gap. CURRY, J. L. M. "Education in the Southern States." American Review Reviews, 2o:185-7, Aug., 1899. Address before the Educational C ference at Capon Springs, W. Va.; treats the subject generally. DELONG, ETHEL. "Pine Mountain School; a Sketch from the Kentu Mountains." Outlook, 115 :318-20, Feb. 21, 1917. Illus. Story of Ui Williams Creech who gave all he had to establish a settlement sch and of his people. DEXTER, E. G. "Southern States." (In his History of education in United States, 1904. pp. 124-140). FROST, NORMAN. "Statistical Study of the Public Schools of the Soutl Appalachian Mduntains." S'. Bureau of Education Bulletin 11, 1, A detailed study of the educational situation. FROST, W. G. "Berea College" (in the From Servitude to Service. B 1905. pp. 49-79). Shows what can be done with mountain boys girls in the field of industrial education. FURMAN, LUCY. Quare Women. Atlantic Press, 1923. Published first se ly in Atlantic Monthly, May-Dec., 1922. Tells the story of the be ning of the Hindman Settlement, the first rural social settlemen </p>
      <pb ref="arr3940629_0009" seq="09" n="644-645  "/>
       <p>44 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI America, begun in 1899 under the auspices of the State Federation of Women's Clubs of Kentucky. IAYWOOD, A. G. "The South and the School Problem," Harpers Magazine, 79:225-31, July, 1889. View of the general educational situation in the South. Toticn, EMERSON. "Believing and Doing ;" a little story of Burns of the Mountains. American Magazine, 81:15-17, March, 1916. "Burns of the Mountains ;" the story of a southern mountaineer. American Magazine, 75 :13-20, Dec., 1912. Illus. Both articles tell of a mountaineer who went away for an education and came back to serve his people by founding the Oneida Baptist Institute. TUDSON, IRENE. "The Schoolmarm of Sandy Ridge." Atlantic, 127:11-22, Jan., 1921. Actual letters written by a worker at Sandy Ridge Mission in Knox County, Tenn. qEVE, F. W. "Virginia Mountain Folk." Outlook, 93:825-29, Dec. H, 1909. The archdeacon of the Blue Ridge tells how his first mission house and home for workers was built. He claims that industrial schools train the people to make the most and best of what they have, to build better homes, and deal with conditions surrounding them in a more intelligent and successful manner. ^.YDER, C. J. "Our American Highlanders Problems and Progress." Education, 18:67-82, Oct., 1897. `School at Rabun Gap." Outlook, 123:319-21, Nov. 12, 1919. Tells of the Rabun Industrial School, a farm and industrial school at Rabun Gap, Ga., founded in 1908. ;1TOCKEL, B. H. "Chang:ng Conditions in the Kentucky Mountains." Scientific Monthly, 3:105-31, Aug., 1916. Illus. Treats of the topography settlement, changing conditions with respect to the chief national re-sources, manufacturing, transportation, and people, with reference to their characteristics, condition, institutions, customs, and future. "Southern Mountain Workers' Conference." Report, 1914. 20 p. 7ouNo M. V. "A Problem and An Opportunity." Educational Review. 51:97-8, Jan., 1916. A plea for aid to the settlement schools and colleges in the southern mountains. VENRICK, L. A. "Teaching the Mountaineers of Tennessee." Missionary Review, 45:811-12, October, 1922. INDUSTRIES ?,RSKINE, R. "Craftsmanship of the Mountaineers of the Blue Ridge." Craftsmen, 13:158-67, Nov., 1907. Spinning, weaving, basket-making, pottery-making, etc., as practiced among the mountain folk. 'ALMER, ESTELLE. "Mountain Industries in the South." Country Life. 27:69-70, Dec., 1914. NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 645 LANGUAGE AND LITERATURE BRADLEY, W. A. "In Shakespeare's America." Harpers Magazine, 131:436-45, Aug., 1915. A comparison of the language, holiday celebrations, and superstitions of the Southern mountaineers with those of the English in Shakespeare's time. "Song Ballets and Devil's Ditties." Harpers, 130:901, May, 1915. Interesting article on the old folk songs of England which have survived among the mountaineers. CAMPBELL, OLIVE DAME, AND SHARP, CECIL J. English Folk Songs from the Southern ApPala.chians. Putnam, 1917. Contains 122 songs and ballads and 323 tunes which the editors collected in the southern highlands. CAMPBELL, O. D. "Old Songs and Ballads of the Southern Mountains." Survey, 33 :371-74, Jan. 2, 1915. Illus. One of the compilers of English folk songs of the Southern Appalachians shows the changes which have crept into the ballads since their origin in England. Gives various parallel stanzas. CHILD, FRANCIS JAMES. English and Scottish Popular Ballads. Houghton, 1904. Old folk songs found in England and in our own country. "Hunting the Lonesome Tune in the Wilds of Kentucky." Current Opinion, 62:mo-10t, February, 1917. Experiences of Miss Wyman and Mr. Brockway in collecting folk songs. MASON, DANIEL GREGORY. "Folk songs in America." Arts and Decoration, 14 :122. A discussion of Mr. Howard Brockway's 'settings to the folk songs of the Southern Appalachians. NORMAN, H. D. "English of the Mountaineers." Atlantic, 105:276-8, Feb., 1910. Comparison of the mountain dialect's with' the English of Shakespeare. "Rescuing the Folk-songs." Literary Digest, 54:403-4, February, 17, 1917. Discusses the work of the folk song collector, especially Miss Wyman. WYMAN, LORAINE. Lonesome Tunes: Folk Songs of the Kentucky Mountains. N. Y. H. W. Gray, 1916. Twenty Kentucky Mountain Songs. Ditson, 1920. For both these volumes the words were collected by Miss Wyman and the melodies collected and piano accompaniment addect by Howard Bmekway. FICTION BARTON, W. E. A hero in homespun, a Tale of the Loyal South. N. Y. 1897. Story of the mountaineers' part in the Civil War. CARTER, M. N. North Carolina Sketches. Chicago, 1900. Short stories. Fox, JOHN, JR. Little Shepherd of Kingdom Come. Scribners, 1903. Trail of the Lonesome Pine. Scribners, Igoand Novels dealing with the life in the Kentuckv mountains. Christmas Eve on Lonesome and Other Stories. Scribners, 1904. Short stories depicting life of the Kentucky mountaineers. FURMAN, LUCY. Mothering on Perilous. Macmillan, 1913. Published serially in Century, Dec., 1910-July, 1911. A young woman who has lost </p>
      <pb ref="arr3940629_0010" seq="10" n="646-647  "/>
       <p>646 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI her friends finds happiness in a settlement school in the Kentucky mountains mothering a dozen small boys. Sight to the Blind. Macmillan, 1914. More of Kentucky mountain life by the interesting author of Mothering on Perilous. Title story published in Century, 84 :390-7, July, 1912. GIELOW, MRS. MARTHA S. Old Andy the Moonshiner. Washington, 1909. Tells of the sacrifices made by Old Andy and his wife to send their little grandchild to an industrial school for mountain children. MACGOwAN, ALICE. Judith of the Cuinberlands. Putnam, 1908. Shows the nobler side of the mountaineers' character. MALONE, J. S. Songs of Vengeance. N. Y., 1903. A tale of the Cumberland highlands. MULLINS, ISLA MAY. "Boy from Hollow Hut." Munsey, February, 1923. MURFREE, MARY NOALIES (Charles Egbert Craddock, pseud.) Despot of Broomsedge Cove. Houghton, 1889. Miss Murfree's best example of character drawing among the mountain people. In the Clouds. Houghton, 1887. Gives the most perfect mountain atmosphere of any of her stories. In the Tennessee Mountains. Houghton, 1884. Eight studies of dwellers in the Great Smokies. Prophet of the Great Smoky Mountains. Houghton, 1885. In the "Stranger People's" Country. Harper, 1891. Story of the Tennessee mountains. Young Mountaineers. Houghton, 1898. Stories of boy life and ad-venture in the Tennessee mountains. PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL HELMICK, ELIZABETH CLARKE. History of Pi Beta Phi. Chapter on Settlement school. ARROW of Pi Beta Phi, 1912 to date. Nearly every number has an article about the school and its work and needs. Pamphlets published by the fraternity on the history and work and needs of the school. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



