<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr3610035_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Bishop, Evelyn</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>October 1919</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr3610035_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">October 1919</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Bishop, Evelyn</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 34-35</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">36</note>
                        <note type="Folder">10</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 36, Number 1 (October 1919), Pages 34-35.</note>
			<note type="document">arr3610035_0000</note>


	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Founding of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1909-1927</item>
                                <item>Teachers</item>
                                <item>Handicraft</item>
                                <item>Funding</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr3610035_0001" seq="01" n="34-35  "/>
       <p>34 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON BY EVELYN BISHOP, Head President Interest is again centering around things in our own country and this was forcibly felt this summer at the Centenary in Columbus, Ohio. No matter how attractive were the foreign people with their odd garments and homes, people flocked to the American building which showed so many of the needs of our American people. While Pi Phi did not stand as a denominational school, we did have an exhibit there and one might have thought the little cabin set in between the hills, the large family of bright children, and even "Ma and Pa Simpson," had come right from Little Pigeon Valley. Our spinning wheel and loom were there and in use much of the time. One young lady from North Carolina wove and spun and told of the mountain work. She had never been in a church or schoolhouse until she was past sixteen and in seven years finished her sophomore year in college. It was a surprise and inspiration to everyone to see the bright mountain young people who were there. School has opened with good attendance and spirit. Ruth Sturley, Washington A, is with us and has charge of the upper room. Abbey Runyan, who finished Mrs. Prickett's term last year, is back again and Emily Burton, for the third year, is working with the little tots. Miss Runyan lives in the cottage with the girls and plans their work and looks after them. We think our "Country Home" is going to be splendid. The girls bring their supplies from home, do all their house work during the week, then Friday afternoon are glad to pack up again and start for home. I am especially pleased to have a place for boys this year and a good man to be with them. Mr. Crestwell will teach manual training, have charge of the industrial department, NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 35 and teach mathematics. He is just out of the army and I hope will have lots of enthusiasm and interest in the boys. They have a base-ball team but so much, need someone to help. with their sports. Every Saturday and Sunday there is a crowd of young fellows wanting somewhere to go and something to do. We greatly need a clubroom for their special use this winter. Within two weeks of time for school to open one of our teachers found she could not possibly come. I tried to locate another Pi Phi for her place but the applications were not in shape for me to know how to reach the girls or for what they were specially fitted. Will girls who are thinking of teaching here please send for application blanks to Miss May Keller, Westhampton College, Richmond, Va. I am anxious that we have Pi Phis in our school, the people like Pi Phis and I feel our girls should have a great deal of interest in the school. So many times this summer other fraternity people have spoken of our work down here and reminded me that our fraternity is outstanding in this splendid undertaking. Mrs. Richardson visited us during this summer, Miss Langmaid was here, Miss Mabel Abbott and parents of Chicago spent several weeks in Gatlinburg, Miss Armbiister and parents of Norman, Okla., spent one day with us and the second week of school we had a visit from Mrs. Helmick. It was her first in two years and people were so glad to see her. We had open house at the cottage one afternoon for the ladies and for the young people in the evening. Then the following night Har Reagan and Amos Trentham made music. Everyone had such a good time. Mrs. Helmick's interest and enthusiasm is contagious and we all felt more like doing a big year's work after her stay with us. This year we plan to have more boys and girls living here in the school, more work done around the place by the boys, and this reminds me that we are trying to have our little farm produce as much of our living as possible. As we have more boarding students there will come a call for individual help, for many young people cannot go away from home and pay their board and tuition. If anyone feels interested in doing for the boy or girl individually instead of collectively I shall be glad to correspond with them. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



