<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr3020149_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Miller, Kate B.</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>December 1913</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr3020149_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">December 1913</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Miller, Kate B.</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 149-151</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">35</note>
                        <note type="Folder">13</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 30, Number 2 (December 1913), Pages 149-151.</note>
			<note type="document">arr3020149_0000</note>


	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Founding of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1909-1927</item>
                                <item>Land</item>
                                <item>Facilities</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr3020149_0001" seq="01" n="148-149  "/>
       <p>148 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI At six o'clock we held an initiation in the chapter house at Boulder. Jean McGuire of Colorado B and Zula Simons of Colorado A were initiated, following this came a cooky-shine and we want to thank the alumnm again for that delightful spread. Of course we danced afterwards, who wouldn't with such perfectly good floors, so much room and such excellent II cl) talent? The main feature of the evening however was a formal meeting. Pi Phi's extension policy was discussed and the girls showed a wide Lunch at "The Alps" During the Province House Party awake interest in this matter. We discussed our chapter lives and the ways in which we could help each other, especially here in the state The meeting was extremely interesting and beneficial. Sunday we had a relay breakfast, of two laps and that was our last meal together as every one had scattered by noon. I want to say how sorry we all are that Texas A could not be with us. We sincerely hope that we can all take part in our next Province house-party. Every-one present says that this one was a great success, but we would like more delegates next time because "the more the merrier" especially when they are Pi Phis. Beside our fun we had our serious moments. We realized that NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 149 such a house-party could be of great help to every chapter and we can become familiar with the life of the different chapters. In this case, the girls who met Colorado A's splendid chaperon, saw her fine supervision of the house and the splendid influence exerted over the lives of the girls with a true woman like our Mrs. Chittenden at the head. The bonds of friendship were greatly strengthened too, by meeting and knowing the girls. Intimate friendships were begun and the life of each one, I know, was broadened thereby. This is what every 4) needs, for we all want to know each other better. Lets advocate a house-party for every province and we truly hope that Epsilon Province can make an annual house-party a steadfast tradition. NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON BY KATE B. MILLER A S announced in the last issue of THE ARROW, the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School is now housed in its own buildings on its own land. The teachers live in the three-roomed cottage and the school is being conducted in the old school house situated on the thirty-five acres purchased from Mr. Ephraim E. Ogle. The mountaineers themselves gave $1,200 of the purchase price, making but one condition, that we should maintain a school for ten years. At the end of that time, their lien ceases to exist. It was this raising of a sum so large for a mountain community that led our friends in the South to call the whole transaction a miracle. And a dream went to the making of the miracle, too, a dream that came to one of these mountain women, Mrs. Andrew .J. Huff, whose children are in school. Mrs. Huff, a slender, delicate-faced, frail woman of about twenty-six, whom we have all grown to love dearly, came into, our cottage kitchen the morning of the day which was to decide the fate of the school. We had said that we would leave that day unless the community coOperated to the extent of giving land for the school. The men, women, and children of that mountain region were more excited than they had ever been before, they told us. They had not seen how they could raise the money for the land, and they could not now see how they could let "them wimmen go." There-fore, when Mrs. Huff dropped into a chair in our kitchen as we were washing dishes that morning, and said ; "I am all hope-up this morn</p>
      <pb ref="arr3020149_0002" seq="02" n="150-151  "/>
       <p>.mraa n, s~). </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



