<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr3210073_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Report on Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, 1912 - 1915</title>
                        <author><name>Helmick, Elizabeth A.</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>October 1915</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr3210073_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">October 1915</date>, Report on Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, 1912 - 1915</title>
                        <author><name>Helmick, Elizabeth A.</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 72-80</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">36</note>
                        <note type="Folder">2</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 32, Number 1 (October 1915), Pages 72-80.</note>
			<note type="document">arr3210073_0000</note>


	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Founding of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1909-1927</item>
                                <item>Funding</item>
                                <item>Land</item>
                                <item>Budget</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr3210073_0001" seq="01" n="72-73  "/>
       <p>72 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI ARROW subscriptions. Foundations have been laid and I trust the future will show the results of my endeavor. I wish to express my thanks to the active chapters for their inspiration, cooperation and for the ideas they have given me which have been of valuable asistance in learning how to plan the work to be carried forth. I have deemed it a privilege to visit the active girls in their chapter homes and have carried away with me greater love and sympathy for the splendid efforts they put forth in their college and fraternity life. A grateful expression is due our Grand Vice-President, Mrs. Lardner, for her kind suggestions and helpful letters and to Miss Sophie Woodman for her splendid efforts and promptness in desiring united effort for the Ainiow subscriptions and alunanee reports. Lava IHIORLOCKER. REPORT ON PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL, 1912-1915 At the Twenty-second Biennial Convention, it was voted to place the management of the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School in the hands of the Chicago Alumna; Club. I was made chairman and treasurer of the committee, which was composed of Kate B. Miller, Iowa B, Lulu Alvord Barrett, Mich*gan A, Dema Harshbarger, Illinois A, and Lucy Hammond Von Hoist, Colorado B. For one year this conunittee met every week and gave much time and thought and study to the school business. In August, 1912, the school's second session opened with Miss Martha Hill, as recommended by the retiring committee, our teacher, working with Calvin Ogle, the native county teacher, until December, when (the county funds having become exhausted), we sent our first Pi Phi, Dell Gillette (now Mrs. T. B. Morgan), Illinois Z, to assist Miss Hill. Miss Gillette was a very earnest, charming young woman. To this day, "Miss Dell" is lovingly spoken of, and there is not a person in Gatlinburg who doesn't hope she will come back to visit them. This session, which began with seventy-two (72) pUpilS, closed with one hundred and thirteen (113) scholars, some of whom had moved to Gatlinburg in order to attend our school and others were walking ten miles daily to attend. Cooking, sewing, mother's meetings, Boy Scout movement, football and occasional entertainments were attempted during this session. In July, 1913, Miss Miller and I went to Gatlinburg to pursuade the people to give us land, and we came away with the deed for thirty-five acres, under the promise that the Fraternity would maintain a school for ten years and that we would build a new school house and provide good teachers. On the land were the following buildings : (I) a three roomed cottage, (2) old school house at the junction of Buskins creek and Little Pigeon river, (3) an old store. The last two were put in good repair during the year and are in excellent condition now. In August, Abbie B. Langmaid, Minnesota A, assisted by Helen Bryan, New York B, opened the Pi Phi School in our own building, upon our own land, and since then we have been independent and with only Pi Phi teachers. In September, Miss Langrnaid resigned, and on October Mary O. Pollard, Vermont A, succeeded her. Our schoolroom was very crowded and our teachers worked under a heavy handicap. In November, it seemed necessary that one of the committee who had the work in charge should go down to hasten the building of the new school house for which plans had been accepted. I went, and the contract was let to C. R. Williams, of Sevierville, with A. J. Huff as his bondsman, and a promise secured that the work would begin at once. The lumber was already sawed. Faithfully submitted, REPORTS OF OFFICERS 73 In December, our work having increased to such proportions, Miss Pollard requested two additional teachers, and Leah Stock, Michigan A, and Edith Wilson, Indiana A, volunteered their services, and reported for duty January first. We closed this session on April 3, with 127 pupils, and the feeling that the year had been a very satisfactory one. About the middle of April the new school house was finally completed. It is a fine six-room building, heated by hot air furnace, and with plenty of windows and ventilation. The total cost came to $3,735.30. Miss Pollard didn't care to leave Gatlinburg during the spring and summer, and remained on, organizing the first Tomato Club of the county and with the State Hookworm Specialist at the school, waged war against this ever present pest among these people. During the first week of July the Grand Council were the guests of the School, and on July 9, with proper ceremony, the new building was dedicated in the presence of eight Pi Phis and several hundred people. With one exception, it is the largest school building in the county. In June, 1914, I ceased to be a resident of Chicago. On June 15, the Chicago Alumnae Club asked me to "retain the Directorship of the Settlement School regardless of residence", and since that time I have managed the School practically alone. On August 10, 1914, the fourth session of the School opened with Miss Pollard as head resident and Edith Wilson and Marie Ditmars of Indiana A and Margaret Young of Illinois E as assistants, with 134 pupils. For the first time, the Sevier County School Board voted to turn over to the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School the district's appropriation for schools for the year which amounted to $375. On April 2, 1915, we closed the most profit-able session in the history of the school, with an enrollment of 158 scholars. This spring, at the State Teachers' examinations in Sevier county, out of 107 who took the examination, only 35 passed, and out of those from our district only seven passed, among the seven being three of our students the only ones who tried. In May, Caroline McKnight Hughes, Minnesota A, a graduate from the University of Minnesota in '94, from Cooper Union School of Art in '95, from Prang Normal in '97, was engaged to take charge of the business and industrial work and she is now at the School. This will make Miss Pollard free to give all of her time and thought to the duties of the schoolroom, where she has shown herself so very successful. Miss Ditmars will return in charge of the younger children and a fourth teacher will be engaged before school opens. It is gratifying to report that many Pi Phis have offered their services and that we have never suffered for want of Pi Phi workers or for money for running expenses. Today, we have one very urgent need and that is a new teacher's residence. This necessity so eclipses every other need, we must concentrate all our money-getting energies upon it. During the past whiter Miss Pollard slept in the cottage where all cooked, ate and lived, while Miss Wilson, Miss Ditmars and Miss Young slept in one of the unused schoolrooms. This arrangement was not pleasant nor comfortable. The Misses Wilson, Iowa members of the New York Alumnae Club. have drawn working plans for a new residence, which will cost between $5,000 and $6,000, completed, and this residence should be built this coming year without fail. We owe it to our Pi Phi workers there. The community needs a hospital and a trained nurse. It is planned, when a new residence is built to convert the three-roomed cottage into a small hospital, to be known as the Jennie Nicol Memorial Hospital. For this purpose the Founders have already contributed $200, and when the cottage </p>
      <pb ref="arr3210073_0002" seq="02" n="74-75  "/>
       <p>74 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI is available they plan to contribute enough to complete the furnishing as a memorial to their beloved co-founder Jennie Nicol. If Miss Celeste Janvier is available at that time, she has expressed a willingness to become our first Pi Phi nurse in charge. I have spoken of the industrial work. It must be apparent to every serious thinking Pi Phi that we assumed when we went among these people a heavy obligation to them. We are teaching them to read and write ; to play and sing; to dress better live better; to think and to hope. Our Pi Phi teachers have been models to them; we have aroused in them ambition. Our young men and our young women will not be contented living the vacant and ambitionless life of the indolent and the door-step gossip. Only a very few may become school teachers. We must provide for them a means of earning a livelihood at home and we must make every effort possible to keep them from going away by developing their home industries and resources in such a way that they will be pleasing, profitable and acceptable. To this end, we are to be congratulated upon securing Miss Hughes, a woman of strong, sterling qualities, a Southern woman and familiar with Southern life and traits, well equipped ,and qualified to restore many lost arts and industries of the mountaineers, and above all a Pi Phi and a good example of Pi Phi virtues. She hopes in time to win for Pi Phi a reputation in the world of arts and crafts and home industries which will create a demand for all that our people can make. She knows how to do it and I have faith that she will succeed. This will in a measure fulfill our duty to these isolated people and make them happy and home loving. I cannot speak with too much appreciation of our Pi Phi workers at Gatlinburg during the past three years. Each teacher has had her special strong point and mission, and every teacher has performed her duties faith-fully and cheerfully, many times under very trying conditions. Zeal, earnestness and untiring effort have characterized their daily life. There is not a single teacher whom we have sent among them who would not be welcomed back by them. We have reason for being proud of our Pi Phi teachers. The foregoing is a brief account of what the fraternity has done thus far through her representatives. It is recognized that it is only a beginning. It is recognized, also, that in the beginning results appear greater in proportion to the efforts put forth than during later periods of work. Enthusiasm is kindled with the very newness of the work, and with the realization that we, as a Fraternity, are pioneers in this field. From now on the Settlement School should cease to be considered as an experiment. It should be looked upon, in part, as a reason for our existence as an organization as a means for preserving and strengthening the life of the alumna! as a body. It is proper, therefore, to consider what steps should be taken to insure the permanency and growth of the School. Thus far,. as has been stated, the Fraternity has delegated the responsibility to a single alumnae club, and the club has in turn delegated this responsibility tb a committee. This served well enough as a temporary measure and afforded time for trial and experiment while searching for something better. It is not believed advisable, however, to charge any one club, or committee, permanently with the conduct of such an important work, the responsibility of which rests equally upon all. That the responsibility does rest on all alike will hardly be questioned. Therefore, it is believed that the direction of the Settlement School should lie in the Grand Council. Under the Constitution the Grand Vice-President's duties include the care and oversight of the alumna organizations, and by virtue of her office, she is in touch with all alumnae clubs and their members. She is also a member of the Grand Council and is in intimate relation with the governing body of the Fraternity in fact, is part of it. The Grand Vice-President, therefore, would appear to be the logical repository for the REPORTS OF OFFICERS 75 responsibility for the general direction of the affairs of the Settlement School, while the head resident at the school should be charged with the details of the local conduct and administration. There is another important matter which should receive the consideration of this Convention, viz., the question of the financial support of the school. Thus far, the liberality of Alumnae Clubs and indivival alumnse have been very gratifying. Here, again, the enthusiasm of a new work has doubtless been an important factor in its success. While it is hoped that this enthusiasm can be kept alive and increased, still it is only logical to assume that with time it may grow less ardent. It is only proper to state, also, that the kindling of this enthusiasm and the conversion of it into financial support has required no small effort. Thousands of circulars and letters to clubs and individual Pi Phis have been sent out, giving information of the work of the school and making appeals for its support. Innumerable letters, acknowledging receipts of individual remittances, while a pleasant task, have unduly consumed valuable time. As an expedient of the early days of the school, this method has served its purpose well, but it is too prodigal of labor to be made permanent. If, as has been assumed, the responsibility for the work and the success of the school rests on all alike, then the financial support should come from all alike; and if this be true, the logical method of obtaining this support would seem to be through the imposition of a per capita tax on the members, or if deemed preferable, a tax on the alumna clubs. This is an important matter and one which the Convention is alone competent to solve. With the general direction and the local management of the School permanently fixed and its financial support arranged in some such manner as outFned above, it is believed that the Convention will have discharged its obligations and that there should be little reason for fear as to the permanency and future success of the school. In line with the above, it is therefore recommended: (1) That the general management of the affairs of the Settlement School, including the duties of the treasurer, be placed in the hands of the Grand Vice-President of the Fraternity. (2) That the immed:ate control and administration of the School at Gatlinburg be placed in the hands of the Head Resident, who shall, in all things, be responsible to and under the Grand Vice-President. (3) That the financial support of the School shall be obtained by means of a per capita tax on the alumnae, or by means of a tax on alumnae clubs. (4) That Article IX, section 2, paragraph b of the Fraternity Statutes be amended to read: "Every alumnae club shall hold at least four meetings a year: one of which shall be devoted to the interests of the nearest chapter or chapters, one to the study of the Constitution, the historical documents and the yearly examination questions, one to the Settlement School and one to the observance of Founders' Day. Respectfully submitted, ELIZABETH A. HELMICK. Director and treasurer, Pi Beta Phi Settlement School. LIST OF ALUMNA, BY CHAPTERS, SHOWING PERCENTAGE GIVING TO THE SUPPORT OF THE SETTLEMENT SCHOOL (a) Vermont A, with 68% ( 6 ) Minnesota A 21% ( 2 ) Michigan A 50% ( 7) Maryland A 20% (3) Missouri 38% ( 8 ) Massachusetts A 18% (4) Washington B 26% ( ) Columbia A 16% (5) Indiana A 21% (10) Iowa A t5% </p>
      <pb ref="arr3210073_0003" seq="03" n="76-77  "/>
       <p>76 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI Iowa B 14% (30) Illinois Z 4% Nebraska B 13i% (31) Texas A 3.3% Pennsylvania r 13% (32) California B 3% Vermont B 12% (33) Florida A 3% Michigan B 11% (34) Wyoming A 3% New York B z 1% (35) Wisconsin A 3% Illinois E To% (36) New York A 2Wo Indiana r 9% (37) Illinois A 2% Iowa r 8i% (38) Kansas A 1.7% Ontario A 8% (39) Colorado A 1.6% California A 8i% (40) Missouri A 1.3% Pennsylvania A 8% (41) Louisiana A 1.3% Pennsylvania B 8% (42) Missouri B r~Q Ohio B 8% (43) Oklahoma A 1% Indiana B, with 7% (44) Washington A, not listed Ohio A 6% (45) Illinois B, not listed Colorado B 4i% (46) Arkansas A Iowa Z 4% (47) Virginia A Illinois H 4% (48) New York r a total average of 10.27% of all alumnae. STATEMENT The following is a summary statement of receipts and expenditures of the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, at Gatlinburg, Tennessee, from the Evanston Convention of lgl2 to July r, 1915: a detailed report is made elsewhere: RECEIPTS From Mrs. A. J. Branson, treasurer $2,209.19 From Alumna Clubs of Pi Beta Phi 3,841.19 From Individual pledges and gifts, Pi Phi 2,400.71 From Active Chapters and their Alumna` 2,150.90 From Citizens of Sevier County, Tennessee 1,200.00 From Grand Treasurer, Pi Beta Phi 750.00 From School Board of Sevier County, Tennessee 375.00 From Founders, for Jennie Nicol Hospital 200.00 From Persons not Pi Phis 186.82 From Interest Account 1x0.01 ExPEND1TURES Total cost of new building (school house) $3,735.30 Salaries of teachers 1,905.00 Cost of 35 acres Land and Buildings 1,800.00 Living expenses of teachers 1,019.87 School furniture and equipment, 1914-15 724.41 Travel Account 593.81 Running or Incidental Expenses 524.20 Labor Account 235.58 Houee and School Furnishings, 1912-13 222.74 Repairing Buildings, #1, #2, and #3 99.50 Bank Collections of checks 17.85 Balance Cash on hand 2,545.66 $13,423.82 (II) (12) (13) (14) (15) (16) (17) (18) (19) (ao) (21) (22) (23) (24) (25) (26) (27) (28) (29) $13,423-82 REPORTS OF OFFICERS 77 Above Balance on deposit as follows: Bank of Sevierville, Sevierville, Tenn $1,500.00 Sheridan Savings and Trust Bank, savings, Chicago, Ill. 200.78 Sheridan Savings and Trust Bank, checking, Chicago, Ill. 844.88 Total $2,545.66 LIST OF ALUMN.iE CLUBS, WITH AMOUNTS, CONTRIBUTING TO THE PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL AT GATLINBURG, TENNESSEE ALPHA PROVINCE '12-'13 Baltimore, Md $ 6.00 Boston, Mass 16o.00 Burlington, Vt Northern New York New York City 94.96 Rhode Island Syracuse, N. Y 10.00 Rochester, N. Y Toronto, Canada Washington, D. C 22.00 Western Massachusetts Total Alpha Province $292.96 '13-'14 '14-'15 Totals $ 3.00 $ 9.00 27.00 $29.50 216.50 115.70 I 26.00 1 236.66 20.00 31..00 31.00 17.25 47.40 121.40 12.48 ' $133.90 $664.29 Io.00 17.25 52.00 12-48 $237.43 BETA PROVINCE Ann Arbor, Mich $ 27.00 $ 35.50 Athens, Ohio Carlisle, Penn Cincinnati, Ohio Cleveland, Ohio 18.25 32.00 Detroit, Mich Hillsdale, Mich Lewisburg, Penn 6.00 11.00 Wooster, Ohio 25.00 50.00 Philadelphia, Penn 154.36 97.00 Pittsburgh, Penn 12.00 44.23 Toledo, Ohio Total Beta Province $242.61 $269.73 $ 10.00 $ 72.50 159.25 5.00 10.00 17.00 109.00 373.36 69.73 25.00 $840.84 109.00 5.00 10.00 34.00 122.00 13.50 25.00 $328.50 GAMMA PROVINCE Carthage $ 10.00 $ 20.00 Chicago, Ill 20.00 114.05 Central, Ill Decatur, Ill Franklin, Ind 27.00 19.50 Galesburg, Ill 96.50 Indianapolis, Ind 43.00 Madison, Wis 20.00 Minneapolis and St. Paul 45.00 Total Gamma Province $ 57.00 $358.05 DELTA PROVINCE 31.25 31.25 69.00 115.50 70.00 166.50 49.61 92.61 20.00 40.00 45.00 $804.36 $1219.41 $ 10.00 554.50 $ 40.00 688.55 Ames, Iowa Burlington, Iowa Columbia, Mo $ moo moo $ 6.00 10.00 $ 35.00 lo.00 $ 52.00 31.00 </p>
      <pb ref="arr3210073_0004" seq="04" n="78-79  "/>
       <p>78 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI ` Des Moines, Iowa Fayetteville, Ark Indianola, ''''''''''''' Iowa City, Kansas City, ~.~ ^^^ City ^.._.m Lawrence, Kan. ~'.".".".' Topeka, ''''''''''''''' Lincoln, Neb Little Rock, Ark Louisville, Mt. Pleasant, __ Omaha and Council Bluffs St. Joseph, Mo Springfield and Mo. Gamma St. Louis, "."."." Sioux City, Iowa Total Delta Province $ 47.00 $ 29.00 30.00 23.00 11.00 25.00 17.00 25.00 27.25 15.00 50.00 $ 34.75 $110.75 35.25 67.25 40.00 93.00 16.90 27.90 25.00 4.00 32.00 57.00 25.00 77.25 15.00 37-no 70.00 70.00 50.00 140.00 $254.75 $334.90 EPSILON PROVINCE Austin, Texas $ 6.0o $ 6.00 Boulder, Colo Dallas, Texas Denver, Colo ~ 20.00 25.00 25oo 70.00 Houston, Texas lo.00 zo.00 Laramie, Wyo zzoo moo Sioux Falls, _ Tulsa, Okla / 5z0 ! / ! sxm Waco, Texas Total Epsilon Province $ 35.00 $*2.00 $ 25.00 $102.00 ZETA PROVINCE Los Angeles, Cal No. California Portland, '''''''''''''' Seattle, '''''''''' Wash. Spokane, '''''''''''''' Total Zeta Province Grand Total $ 10.00 $ 75.00 $ 10o0 $ 95.00 10.00 10.00 10.00 10.00 85.00 85.00 12.00 12o0 $ 10.00 $ 85oo $117.00 $212,00 $850.57 $I246.96 $1743.66 $384I.19 LIST OF ORGANIZATIONS, WITH AMOUNTS, CONTRIBUTING TO THE SUPPORT OF THE SCHOOL, GATLINBURG, TENN. ALPHA PROVINCE '12-'13 `13-'14 ^14-7`s Total Ontario A $ 50.00 $ 15.00 $ 65.00 Vermont A and Alumnm 15.00 43.00 386.so 444.50 Vermont B 50.00 50.00 Massachusetts A New York A New York B 39.00 39.00 New York r8z Alumnae Maryland A 30.00 30.00 Columbia A and Alumnm zo.00 127.00 41.00 178.00 Virginia A ! 7.50 7.50 Florida A 15-90 15.90 Total $ 75.00 $474.00 $829.90 REPORTS OF OFFICERS 79: BETA PROVINCE Pennsylvania A 1 $ 84.58 I $ 17.00 Pennsylvania B Pennsylvania r Ohio A Ohio B Michigan A and Alumnce Michigan B Total $ 84.58 GAMMA PROVINCE Minnesota A $ 15.00 $ 29.00 Wisconsin A Illinois B 21.50 21.50 Illinois 25.00 25.00 Illinois E $ 25.00 25.00 Illinois Z 61.15 63.00 124.15 " Illinois H 16.00 16.00 Indiana A 47.00 4.00 51.00 Indiana B 10.00 18.00 28.00 2.00 18.00 56.00 Indiana r 1 23.00. 53.00 Total $110.00 $112.15 $193.50 $415.65 DELTA PROVINCE Iowa A Iowa B and Alumnae $ 53.00 $ 12.50 50.00 $115.5o Iowa r lo.00 I 10.00 Iowa Z Nebraska B and Alumni 72.00 36.00 26.00 134.00 Missouri A Missouri B J 9.35 9.35 Missouri r Kansas A 20.00 I 20.00' Arkansas A Louisiana A 50.00 50.00 Total $134.35 $118.50 $ 86.00 $338.85 EPSILON PROVINCE ....... $ 12.00 52.00 $ 25.00 25.00 I 64.00 50.00 25.00 139.00 ZETA PROVINCE California A California B Washington A Washington B 22.00 Total Zeta Province $ 31.92 Grand Total $467.93 $881.97 $801.97 AMOUNTS OF ANNUAL INDIVIDUAL PLEDGES to the PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL Pledges due since 1913 and 1914 $125.00 5o cents $ .5o 43 $1 43.00 4 @ $2 8.00 $ 27.0.0 $128.58 ....... 249.25 14.75 $392.58 79.00 $xo6.00 170.25 14.75 $202.00 $ 44.00 . .... ............... ..... ......... ..... ......... Oklahoma A ... Texas A Wyoming A Colorado A Colorado B Total ... ....... ....... .............. .......... . . . .......... . ... ... $ 12:00 102.00 25.00 $ 25.00 $ 9-92' 22.00 $ 31.92 $2150.90 </p>
      <pb ref="arr3210073_0005" seq="05" n="80-81  "/>
       <p>80 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI 3 @ $2.50 7.50 2 @ $3 6.00 lo @ $5 50.00 I @ $10 10.00 $125.00 Good Pledges still due on 1915 $414 00 2 @ 50 cents 1.00 125 @ $1 125.00 27 @ $2 54.00 3 @ $3 9.00 29 @ $5 145.00 2 @ $10 20.00 @ $6o 6o.00 $414.00 Pledges paid 1915, due in 1916 $628.75 $1167.75 1 @ 25 cents 25 4 @ 50 cents 2.00 154 @ $1 154.00 50 @ $2 100.00 1@$2.50 2.50 42 @ $5 210.00 10 @ $10 100.00 1 @ $15 15.00 1 @ $20 20.00 @ $25 25.00 $628.75 Total amount of Individual pledges, independent of Clubs $1167.75 MONEY ASSETS REAL AND ESTIMATED Good Pledges still due $ 414.00 Balance in Bank July 1, 1915 2490.70 $2,904.,70 Estimated from Alumnae Clubs, 1915-1916 1,500.00 Estimated from Active Chapters 800.00 Estimated from Gifts, Subscription Agency, etc 1,200.00 Total Assets estimated for year 1915-1916 $6,404.70 LIABILITIES OR BUDGET 1915-1916 Estimated Cost of Salaries $1,200.00 Estimated Living Expense, 8 months @ $6o 480.00 Estimated Labor Hire, including freighting 320.00 Estimated Cost of Fitting up Industrial Work 300.00 Estimated Repairs on Cottage and upkeep cost 200.00 Estimated Printing, postage, etc 200.00 Estimated Travel in connection with School 200.00 Estimated for Furnishings 50.00 Estimated for School Supplies 50.00 Total estimated cost for running the School 1915-1916 $3,000.00 Balance available for building new residence $3,404.70 REPORTS OF COMMITTEES 81 REPORTS OF COMMITTEES REPORT OF COMMITTEE ON FRATERNITY EXAMINATIONS July. 1914-.hay,, 1915 The Chairman of the Committee on Fraternity Examination begs leave to submit the following report: During this last year of the work of this committee, there has been one change in our personnel, Miss Hope Cleveland, Colorado A, '14, taking the place of Mrs. Worcester, and having in her charge Epsilon and Zeta Provinces. As in previous years, quizzes have been' inserted in the Bulletins for study by the chapters in preparation for the examination. On these and THE ARROWS and subjects of general fraternity interest the questions have been based. The quest'ons for this year were as follows: Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Twenty-First Annual Examination 1914-1915. This Examination is conducted by the Examination Committee. Every Active Member is expected to participate. Send answers to the member of the Committee designated in Letter of Instructions. Members who have taken four fraternity examinations will please answer Questions Nos. 11, 15, 16, 25. FRESHMEN 1. Give briefly your reasons for choosing Pi Beta Phi as your fraternity. Discuss your responsibility to the whole fraternity as to high scholarship and high social standards. 2. What is the fraternity magazine? How many issues are published during the college year? For what purpose are the Bulletins published? When did all initiates first become life subscribers? Do you read the fraternity exchanges in your college library? 3. How is the fraternity governed' Name the Grand Council. Name the President of your Province. Which officer of the fraternity has charge of the mailing list of our magazine? To whom should any change of address be sent? 4. When was our fraternity founded? What is the day called? How is it observed? Give number of founders, and name four. Give words of four songs, including the Anthem. 6. Describe the Coat of Arms, and explain symbolism involved. Give the Symphony. 7. Where was the last convention held? With which chapter? Where will the 1915 convention be held? How do conventions benefit a fraternity? Do you plan to go to the 1915 convention? 8. Tell what you can of the work of our fraternity in the Settlement School. 9. Give the chapter roll by provinces, naming chapter, college and city. 10. Name three notable alumna and state the field in which each is eminent. FRESHMEN desiring to haze their name on the "Honor List" in the eeanziaation must answer also Questions Nos. xi and 12. ALL MEMBERS EXCEPT FRESHMEN 11. What officer of the fraternity has charge of all subscriptions to our magazine? To whom should all changes of address be sent? Why should such changes be sent promptly? To whom should personal items for the magazine go? When did all initiates first become life subscribers? To whom do you send for an extra copy of the magazine, and how much does it cost? Discuss advantages of large percentage of alumna subscribers. 12. What are the duties of the Custodian of the Pin? 13. Give a brief sketch of the work done in the Settlement School, covering the following points: a. When was the work first suggested? b. Its beginning. c. Dedication of new building, (1914). d. Present condition and prospects. 14. Where will the next convention be held? Give personnel of convention? What power has convention? How are delegates chosen? What are the duties of the chapter delegate? How does a convention benefit the whole fraternity body? 15. Tell briefly of the Loan Fund Of the Graduate Fellowship and the disposition made of it this past year. Discuss the relative importance of the Loan Fund and Graduate Fellowship. 16. What does Pi Beta Phi stand for in your life? How can fraternity women help raise the standard of the drama? of music? Does your chapter carry out these ideals? </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



