<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr3630335_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Langmaid, Abbie B. </name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>March 1920</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr3630335_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">March 1920</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Langmaid, Abbie B. </name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 335-339</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">36</note>
                        <note type="Folder">11</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 36, Number 3 (March 1920), Pages 335-339.</note>
			<note type="document">arr3630335_0000</note>


	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Founding of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1909-1927</item>
                                <item>School programs</item>
                                <item>Government</item>
                                <item>Education</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr3630335_0001" seq="01" n="334-335  "/>
       <p>334. THE A.R,ROTY OF PI BETA PHI.' The work of the alumna! chapters is very diverse, including the serving of lunches, aid given to Needlework Guild and city nurses, kindergarten work, etc. II. War Work During the war Chi Omega undertook the support of two workers in the devastated areas of France. In addition to this the individual chapters did Red Cross work and aided in the sale of bonds. SIGMA KAPPA I. Altruistic Work Educational work in the Maine Seacoast Mission. I T. War Work A fund of several thousand dollars was distributed one-half to the American Red Cross Recreational Fund and one-half to the relief of French orphans. Each active chapter has adopted a war orphan. ALPHA OMICRON PI I. Altruistic Work Work, heretofore, carried on by chapters. The fraternity is now beginning a systematic course of national welfare work. War Work Put $2,050 into relief work in the Chateau Thierry district. ZETA TAU ALPHA I. Altruistic Work National scholarship fund to aid worthy college girls not necessarily members. Chapter scholarship funds. Members seek to aid and inspire the lives of less fortunate girls by a spiritual adoption. II, War Work Chapters and individuals supported fifteen war orphans, did Red Cross work, bought bonds, had charge of Food Work in several counties. As a fraternity, sent Grand President to France as a doctor. ALPHA GAMMA DELTA I. Altruistic Work Alpha Gamma Delta has assumed the maintenance and management of a summer camp for children. The full details will be completed summer of 1920. II. War Work Active and alurnm:e chapters raised a fund for the Red Cross. Usual work done by all. DELTA ZETA Altruistic Work Different chapters have worked with local social agencies. . NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON . 335 IL War Work Every chapter did the regulation war work which included Belgian Relief, Red Cross, adoption of orphans. ALPHA DELTA PI I. Altruistic Work Child welfare work. II. War Work Armenian Relief. Practically every club and chapter adopted an Armenian orphan. KAPPA DELTA 1. Altruistic Work Each chapter, active and alumnre, undertakes some service work. The fraternity as a whole maintains a students' loan fund for members. II. War Work Each chapter had its own work. The fraternity owns the limit in War Savings Stamps and also several Liberty Bonds. PHI Mu I. Altruistic Work Is under the direction of a national Philanthropic Board which super-vises the work of the various chapters. Each chapter decides upon its own work, such as, endowing bed in childrens' hospital, adopting poor families, supplying milk for free milk station, giving free music or sewing lessons at orphanage, etc., etc. IL War Work The fraternity established a nurses' but at one of the Base Hospitals and placed a Phi Mu there as hostess. NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON BY ABBIE B. LANGMAID, Chairman of Settlement School Board Having planned to go to Gatlinburg during October, I was gratified to find in the Vindicator the announcement that East Tennessee would hold the annual educational conference in Knoxville the last week of the month. There were several things I had been wanting to find out about Tennessee school taxes, etc. A very large number were in attendance. It seemed to me all the teachers from East Tennessee must be there. State Superintendent Williams, new, to his office but progressive and energetic; gave some interesting statistics. For instance, out of twelve thousand teachers the state has over four </p>
      <pb ref="arr3630335_0002" seq="02" n="336-337  "/>
       <p>336 THE ARROW OF PI BE TA PHI thousand teaching on temporary certificates, which means that they are lacking in Tennessee's requirements for teaching, no normal and probably no high school training. One county, because of no better material available, was obliged to hire a teacher who had misspelled every word in the list of twenty-five given in examination. Seven Tennessee counties have schools of only three months during this year. An attempt is being made to fix seven months as the minimum school vear for the state, and also to raise more school funds by increasing taxes. The Pi Phi Settlement School receives eighty-five dollars per month for the five months of "county school," this being its full share of money from Tennessee. Governor Roberts' ad-dress regarding the industrial situation, for Knoxville was under the guard of U. S. troops of infantry, marines, and cavalry because of the streetcar and mine strikers, was a fearless, vigorous, patriotic speech. One evening, President Bryan, of Colgate, gave an excel-lent address, and Professor O'Shea, of Wisconsin, was remarkable in his scholarly psychological discourses. The convention closed on Saturday and, in company with Mr. and Mrs. Bishop, I left for Sevierville. It rained, as it had a way of doing whenever I fared forth into Tennessee, so I stayed over night in their home which is always hospitably open to Pi Phis on their way to and from Gatlinburg. Next day Harrison met me in Pigeon Forge, with "Dan" and Mr. Huff's buggy. (Now the Pi Phis have one of their own to replace the historic "hack" which went to pieces "all at once and nothing first" some time ago.) We had several apparently hair-breadth escapes when we sat on the side of the mountain at an angle of near 90 , waiting for a lumber wagon to pass us. "I reckon we won't fall out," said the driver, but we both lost no time scrambling to sit on the part of the buggy highest up on the mountain side. Then there were some mud holes! But they did not quite engulf us, and during the next six weeks I learned they could be worse. Miss Evelyn and I formed the habit of walking out in preference to riding, although we were not sorry to be "picked up" by Professor Watson, Dr. Massey, or Mr. Huff, as we were sometimes. Yet we never did get over our preference for walking over certain stretches near "Gum Stand." For our consolation we could see the railroad ties and rails laid on the opposite side of the Little Pigeon to within four or five miles of Gatlinburg. So if we do not get a "pike" we may sometime have a railroad into the NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 337 burg. The Vindicator states that it will be giving pas'senger service to Gatlinburg next year, but that may be pure optimism! After all, however, one gladly endures the discomforts of the road for the glimpses afforded of the beautiful mountain scenery. Throughout November the autumn coloring was the most wonderful it has ever been my privilege to see, the colors constantly changing, until we reached the rare mahoganies of the latter part of the month. Upon arriving, after dark, at the Residents' cottage, I was greeted cordially by Miss Sturley, Miss Bishop, Miss Burton, and Miss Runyan, our most efficient workers in the settlement and school work, and by our good Aunt Lizzie and Mrs. Proffit. Mr. Creswell I met later. Miss Freeman of Iowa was a guest at the house and added to my welcome. After Sunday evening lunch, like the wise virgins we started out with our lamps trimmed and burning, for B. Y. P. U. Right here was my first revelation of the influence of the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, for B. Y. P. U. holds a meeting every Sunday evening which could put to shame many of the Sunday meetings of young people held throughout the country where opportunities for development have been greater. It is attended by a large number for a . country meeting, sixty to a hundred, and the boys and girls who have had the school's advantages "take part" in a simple, well-poised, and thoughtful way that is very gratifying. On Friday evenings debates were held, young and old discussing Tennessee's compulsory school law (which is not enforced), farming questions, etc., in a way both entertaining and admirable. One Friday evening a basket supper was held. Mr. Charlie Ogle and one or two other philanthropists bought several baskets and resold to the small boys at a 75% loss or thereabouts. Everybody had a good time and the sale of baskets netted twenty dollars which, together with an equal sum from the state, will be put into new library books. Other special features were the splendid Thanksgiving program and the Christmas entertainment. Miss Sturley's room gave Miles Standish for the former occasion, and very beautifully. It was not difficult to find John Aldens and Priscillas among Gatlinburg people nor a real spinning-wheel and straight-backed, splint-bottomed chairs. Miss Burton's little folks were no less pleasing in their many appearances. (Mr. Creswell and his boys had made the stage which can be stored away between entertainments.) The songs were a </p>
      <pb ref="arr3630335_0003" seq="03" n="338-339  "/>
       <p>338 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI significant part of' the program. All the boys and girls love to sing under the inspiration of Miss Evelyn's leadership, for her music has the charm of natural ability with rare, cultivation. Its quality makes itself felt and brings quick response. The Christmas program was less elaborate, the wonderful tree from Pi Phi Hill being almost .sufficient in itself. Miss Runyan's boys and' girls furnished music for pretty tableaux and the voices in the Christmas songs were. very appealing. Syracuse, Detroit, Rochester, and Cleveland alumnae de-serve thanks for the lovely tree decorations which brought out the beauty of the big hemlock. They also sent some pretty gifts. Dolls, ribbons, nice new books, and writing paper seem to be favorites with the girls, while the boys enjoy their neckties, games, knives, etc., and there were some of each. There never does seem enough dolls with "real" clothes to satisfy the little girls who are so hungry for them. Miss Evelyn "aims" to have each child receive one good gift. Stress is laid upon "giving" at Christms, so that the school boys and girls may not miss their part of the blessedness of Christmas. Some forty toys were made by Mr. Creswell's boys in manual training, painted by the older girls, and given the younger brothers and sisters. .Mistletoe, holly, and dainty little baskets were some of the gifts of the older pupils to the Pi Phi residents and guest. Other gifts came later but too late for this Christmas. They will be ready to help out for next year. Lilly Treadwell, Wisconsin A, sent fifteen dollars to be used for the pleasure of the children, a most opportune gift. Outside of school activities were still other enjoyments wonderful walks, and much, very much visiting. Miss Sturley and Miss Burton make frequent over-night visits, and Miss Evelyn and I had the pleasure of an "over-night" with the Crocket Maples, going' home with their boys, Ephraim, Rellie, and Bruce, eating corn popped over the open fire in one of. Gatlinburg's lovely fireplaces, and, later in the guest chamber, sleeping soundly between the bursts of mountain storm, for as usual it rained! Another night was spent at the home of the gobd Pi Phi friends, Mr. and Mrs. Huff, when we all sang songs with the children for a while and then talked until after midnight. In the morning Miss Evelyn and I, having left the porch door open to listen to the usual rain accompaniment of our visits, looked out upon a. crisp, white world for the rain had turned to snow! Mrs. Steve Whaley entertained us all one evening BOOK REVIEWS 339 at a delicious supper, where Preacher Connor was also a guest, a delightful conversationalist, and Miss Evelyn and I stayed long after the rest had gone to debate, listening to him. Mr. and Mrs. Lawson Reagan invited us all one evening and we were well served with a wholesome meal including string beans canned by the "cold pack method." Dr. Massey and Mr. Huff gave 'us several rides among the mountains, through peaceful Wears Valley, where at the Baptist School, Miss Evelyn, Dr. Massey, and I all gave "talks"; to Green Briar where at one curve in the road the mountains stand out in all their grandeur; Lillard Maples was chaffeur for us all one Sunday when we went up to "Sugarlands" to see Mr. and Mrs. Prickett and their adorable babies. Altogether my stay in Gatlinburg, although it was full of number-less details, of planning for the present and future, gave me much pleasure. There is satisfaction in realizing the splendid energy and devotion to work of the resident and their cooperation for the general welfare. The school is in splendid condition, attendance better than usual, and the friendly interest shown by the people is growing steadily. BOOK REVIEWS What America Did By FLORENCE FINCH KELLY (MRS. ALLEN) Kansas A, '81 (Published by Dutton.) One of the volumes which have come as an aftermath of the great war, recording the achievements of our own country during the period of conflict. Leave It to Doris By ETHEL POWELSON HI.TESTON (MRS. W. J.) Iowa A, '09 12MO. 'Bobby Merrill Co., $I.50 This volume by the author of the popular Prudence of the Parsonage is a successor to the other books in the same series. . The interest, as In the previous stories, is centered upon four charming girls who take charge of the _parsonage and look after their father, the minister. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



