<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr3110091_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Report of committee on Settlement School</title>
                        <author><name>Helmick, Elizabeth A.</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>October 1914</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr3110091_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">October 1914</date>, Report of committee on Settlement School</title>
                        <author><name>Helmick, Elizabeth A.</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 91-94</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">35</note>
                        <note type="Folder">15</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 31, Number 1 (October 1914), Pages 91-94.</note>
			<note type="document">arr3110091_0000</note>


	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Founding of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1909-1927</item>
                                <item>Budget</item>
                                <item>Salaries</item>
                                <item>Teachers</item>
                                <item>Facilities</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr3110091_0001" seq="01" n="90-91  "/>
       <p>90 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI Number of Alumnie Bulletins distributed, 350. 97 Recapitulation Club members Non-Club members 139 Isolated alumnie 316 Total 552 Total number of ARROW subscribers 249. Respectfully submitted, EMILY M. MILLER, Epsilon Province Vice-president. REPORT OF ZETA PROVINCE VICE-PRESIDENT July I'913, to July, 1914 Zeta Province Vice-president submits the following report to the Grand Council of II B (I,: While we seem to have a very large territory on the Pacific coast and over five hundred alumna! are scattered over this vast province, there are only three organized chartered clubs. In several of the cities there are from ten to twenty alumna members and they meet and have social programs, and express interest in Pi Phi, but do not seem to have felt the desire to take a charter which would give them more direct recognition in the Province. May we not hope that in another year they may appreciate the advantage of being identified by holding a charter as an organized club? Alumna: in northern and southern California are expressing a desire to be very active and well informed in alumna' affairs, in anticipation of Convention. Their appreciation of our needs and advantages will mean great good to our province. Los Angeles has had a splendid year. Alumnre have responded in large numbers to the monthly meetings in which a charming social side has been expressed. There are eighty members from many different states. A visit to the northern alumna: club in San Francisco found them well organized under their newly acquired charter, and taking keen interest in the active chapter work of Berkeley and Stanford, cooperating with Mrs. Carney, the Province President, in her well-formed plans for a better understanding and relationship which she believes should exist between alumnae and active chapters, as relating to the larger national organization. On a visit to Salt Lake, Zeta Province Vice-President found over twenty Pi Phis living in and near the city. They had organized in hopes of obtaining a chapter in the University of Utah for the Gamma Phis a local. They did not wish to take a charter as an organized club unless they had an active chapter there for whom they might work and give their special interest. The Pan-Hellenic organization holds a bond of interest for all Greeks, in place of separate club meetings. Seattle has a chartered club with a large membership, offers excellent pro-grams and is stimulated in its progress and activities by the active chapter in the University. An endeavor has been made to reach all isolated members by circulars throughout the province, but few have responded. Many Pi Phis in the province seem to pay their alumnre tax through former college memberships. A card list of the alumnae has been made and revised. This has indeed been a long and difficult task, but it is now quite in shape for future reference. Many thanks to the excellent system of our alumna editor and the province vice-presidents who have assisted in forwarding the names and changes of addresses of eastern Pi Phis who have come to reside on the Coast. This has been the first attempt to definitely and accurately organiz-e Pi Phi interests in this new province, and we will be grateful for the assistance and cooperation of all Pi Beta Phis in reporting promptly of their change of address, ARROW subscriptions and alumna': dues, that we may have a complete record and good standing in our report at convention out here in 1915. We ANNUAL REPORTS OF COMMITTEES 91 wish to show ourselves truly loyal in genuine Pi Phi spirit and numbers to welcome our Eastern sisters. ZETA PROVINCE ALUMN.E REPORT April 1914 Resident Alumna ARROW SubscriberslAmt. of Clubs Charter Paid Members NonLife Annual Al. Tax Dues member! paid Gr. Treas. Los .Angeles 1906 20 120 27 20 $10.60 Northern Calif 1914 112 8.00 Portland, Ore 12 Seattle 1907 91 Spokane .. 29 Salt Lake .... 19 San Diego .... 10 Fresno _ 11 ISOLATED ALUMNI ARROW Subscribers States Life Annual Arizona 6 3 California 54 91 Idaho 11 7 1 Nevada 6 2 Oregon 11 15 1 Utah 5 3 2 Washington 49 82 12 203 44 Number of Alumna Bulletins distributed, 200. 342 Recapitulation Club members Non-club members 62 Isolated alumnae members 142 Total alumnae 546 Total ARROW subscribers 247 Respectfully submitted, LETA HOERLOCKER, Zeta Province Vice-president. ANNUAL REPORTS OF COMMITTEES REPORT OF COMMITTEE ON SETTLEMENT SCHOOL 1913-July, 1914 The chairman and treasurer of the committee on Settlement School submits the following report to the Grand Council of II B The Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, at Gatlinburg, Tenn., closed its third year on April 3, 1914, with 128 pupils enrolled. The year has been marked by greater activities and more permanent gain that all the previous years put together. It has been the first year in our own buildings and with entirely Pi Phi teachers. Our property now includes thirty-five acres of land; a new six-roomed, furnace heated school house, completely equipped; the old school building at the junction of Baskins creek and Little Pigeon river, where we have held our classes the past year the small store building, used as a kindergarten, and the three-roomed cottage on the hillside. Hereafter, all classes will be held in the new school building, and the two old buildings, which have been extensively repaired, will be used for industrial and demonstrating work for the boys and girls as goon as we can equip and prepare for them. The young orchard has been pruned and cared for, the gardens </p>
      <pb ref="arr3110091_0002" seq="02" n="92-93  "/>
       <p>9 2 .THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI have been planted and are being worked "on shares", and our teachers have exerted great energy and care in developing the external beauty and thrifty appearance of our grounds as well as the internal welfare of our young institution. The working staff during the year has been composed of Abbie B. Lang-maid, Minnesota A, from August to October 1, succeeded by Mary O. Pollard, Vermont A, who is at the school at the present time as head resident; Helen Bryan, New York B, was assistant throughout the year, with the exception of a forced sick leave in the winter; Edith Wilson, Indiana A, and Leah Stock, Michigan A, joined the school staff in January, when our number of pupils increased, and gave their services until the close of the school year. The work of these earnest and enthusiastic Pi Phi sisters has been in every way highly satisfactory and they have won the appreciation and devotion of our mountain wards as well as Pi Phis for their sacrifices and conscientious efforts. We have engaged for the coming year, Mary O. Pollard, head resident, assisted by Edith Wilson, Indiana A, Marie Ditmars, Indiana A, and Margaret Young, Illinois E. The first three are graduates and experienced teachers while Margaret Young is new to the work. The Agricultural Department, at Washington, through the courtesy of Mr. P. P. Campbell, M. C., from Kansas and Senator Lea, of Tennessee, has furnished us with a liberal supply of bulbs, shrubs and seeds, which were planted with great care and brought forth fair results. We have received favorable and gratifying letters from Dr. Bradford Knapp and Prof. O. 13. Martin, of the Farmers' Co-operative Demonstration Work, Bureau of Plant Industry, Washington, and are anxious for our plant to grow in size and strength when it will be possible for us to add this splendid work to the Pi Phi School for our young men of the mountains. Miss Virginia Moore, state organizer of Tomato Canning Clubs for girls, visited our school, and with Miss Pollard, organized a small but enthusiastic Tomato Canning Club the only one in the county and the results have been far reaching and satisfactory. Dr. Yancy, the state hookworm specialist, made three visits to us and examined and treated our people, finding 6o% of them infected. In this work, our Mary Pollard deserves special commendation. She remained at the Settlement all summer, giving her time and strength, walking miles and miles to tell the people beyond us of their danger and urging them to come in to the free treatment at the Pi Phi school house. She personally assisted Dr. Yancy from early morning until night fall, in his examinations, helping to give out medicines and make explanations. There is probably not a better known woman, nor one more honored and beloved in these mountains than our Mary Pollard of the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School at Gatlinburg. A great need, and one which will appeal to those who have suffered or been in the sick room, is a hospital, or dispensary is a visiting nurse. A fund has been started by three of our founders, and $150 is now in the bank for the establishment of the Jennie Nicol Memorial Hospital at Gatlinburg, in loving memory of our first initiate, Dr. Jennie Nicol, who died in Switzerland in 1881. What better gift, in memory of those who have suffered and passed to the Other Life can we make than to this? Last winter, our four teachers lived in our small three-roomed cottage. It will be impossible for them to do so another winter. It wouldn't be right if it were possible, for they suffered from the cold and exposure. We must provide for them a comfortable and suitable building. Plans have been drawn by the Misses Elmina and Aida Wilson, Iowa P, and the building of this has been voted the especial work of the committee for the coming year. The new building will have a living room, with open fireplace, dining-room, kitchen, small library or office and the head resident's bedroom on the first floor, with five bedrooms and a bath room on the second floor, and a basement and furnace below. The house will be equipped with as many of the simple ANNUAL REPORTS OF COMMITTEES 93 necessities and comforts of a country home as we can raise the money to pay for. This building is clearly a necessity and our mission for the year. The school house and cottage as it is now are well provided with all things needful, and our greatest necessity and wish is for money to pay for labor and materials. We wish that individuals, instead of trying to make things for the school, would make things for a "sale" for the benefit of the school fund. We urge every Pi Phi to send her magazine subscriptions, to Miss Reisinger, 235 E. Lafayette St., Baltimore, Md., for the commission adds materially to the treasury and does not cost you a cent more. It is planned and hoped that each club will pledge a certain sum to the school at the beginning of the club year, and plan and work to raise that sum. I earnestly appeal to every Pi Phi who may read this report to make a strenuous effort to help us make this year a banner year for pushing forward our splendid undertaking. I would like to recommend to your thoughtful consideration the scheme tried by the Chicago alumnae club for raising money. Thirty five women promised to earn $10 apiece, and most of them did it, and then gave a luncheon party to tell everyone in the club what fun they had in doing it, and the satisfaction to them. I have a long list of suggestions for earning money which I will gladly furnish anyone wishing to undertake the promise. This year is going to tax the money giving and money getting ability of each of us, and we must put our strongest effort out and pull together, and the result will surprise everybody. The following is a statement of the financial condition of the school, from April 15, 1913, to April 15, 1914: RECEIPTS Balance on hand, April Is, 1913, $2,729.27 From Alumnae Clubs, $1,589.84 " Active Chapters, 500.32 " Individual Pi Phis, 1,475.35 " Citizens Gatlinburg and Sevier County, 1,200,00 " Other sources, not Pi Phi, gifts, 134.63 " Interest on Savings Bank Account, .... . 40.01 4,940.15 Total receipts during the year from all sources, $7,669.42 EXPENDITURES Travel Account, Miss Hill, $ 14.35 , Miss Gillette, 30.00 ,, Miss Miller and Mrs. Helmick, 121.64 Miss Langmaid, 138.31 Miss Bryan, 83.00 Miss Pollard, 22.89 , Mrs. Helmick, 69.40 ,, Miss Wilson, 31.40 $ 510.99 Salaries, Miss Langmaid, 2 months, Iso.00 " Miss Pollard, 6 months, 450.00 " Miss Bryan, 5 months, 125.00 725.00 School and Cottage Furnishings, 86.o5 Cottage Household Expenses, 382.52 Cost 35 acres land wtth improvements, 1,800.00 In full for new School Building, 3,500.00 Repairs on old buildings in use, 175.30 School Committee's running expenses, 142.66 Chairman's travel and itemized expenses, given by her, ... 100.00 Total expenditures for the year, $7,422.52 Balance in Sheridan Trust and Savings Bank, Chicago, 246.90 </p>
      <pb ref="arr3110091_0003" seq="03" n="94-95  "/>
       <p>'94 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI The committee wishes to take this opportunity to thank those who have assisted in the work. The teachers have worked hard and conscientiously, under trying hardships at times, and to them the whole Fraternity owes a debt of gratitude. We would like to take this time to especially thank Miss Leah Stock and Miss Edith Wilson who gave their services. To you, who have sent us your money and cheering words we thank you again. Respectfully submitted, ELIZABETH A. HELMICK. Chairman and Treasurer. REPORT OF CHAIRMAN OF COMMITTEE ON EXTENSION 1913-Jidy, ION The Chairman of the Committee on Extension submits the following report to the Grand Council of II B ',I,: i. At the last Grand Council meeting this committee was authorized to inquire into conditions in some schools, suggested by the chairman of the committee on fraternity examination, where Pi Phi is not represented, but where a Pi Phi is a member of the faculty or intimately interested in the school. In reply, Phoebe Bishop, Texas A, whose father is president of the school, reported no opening at Southwestern University at this time, and Ethelwyn Miller, Indiana A, replied that a group in Miami University had been working under her direction for two years and were now ready to petition. They have met all preliminary requirements and Beta Province President has visited them. 2. At the suggestion of the Grand President, conditions were investigated in Agnes Scott College where it is desirable for us to be represented. At the present time fraternities are prohibited. 3. Letters of inquiry have been received from the following schools, where nothing further developed: Southern Christian College, West Point, Miss.; New England Conservatory of Music; and the University of Pittsburgh. 4. A group at Cornell University wrote for instructions, but Helen Heath Gage, Michigan B, wrote that they had decided not to petition this year. II A (I) of Illinois Wesleyan University, Bloomington, Ill., was denied admission, as neither school nor group met our preliminary requirements. 5. The group in the University of Utah which was discouraged last spring has been so strongly indorsed by twelve resident Pi Phis and so strenuously aided by them that they have sent in a petition. K 1) at Kansas State Agricultural College has also continued its efforts. They are herewith sending a petition for a charter. 6. Within a very few days of each other came requests from three small colleges in the south: a group combining I' 0 LE and A P at Hollins College, Hollins, Va.; I B, combining B 0 and 4 H r at Brenau College, Gainesville, Ga.; and a group in the Florida State College for Women at Tallahassee. These groups all seem to be laboring under the delusion that a charter may be granted on a two or three weeks' investigation, or less. This idea seems to be the result of the hasty methods of at least two nationals, who have even offered charters to some of these groups. All three groups seem to stand well in their respective schools. All were discouraged; Brenau on account of their annual income, Hollins because there are too many fraternities for the number of college women, and the Florida group because the school is too small to maintain a society of twelve members of their present high standard. The latter two schools have shown great persistence; the obstacles to meeting our preliminary requirements are not unsurmountable; and they present some favorable recommendations. Hence they have been encouraged to wait until the Grand Council meeting to know whether it is worth their while to proceed further. In closing her report, the chairman of the committee on extension suggests that the powers of this committee be enlarged to include obtaining from a ANNUAL REPORTS OF COMMITTEES 95 petitioning group some statistics required by the investigating officer, such as list of resident Pi Phis, and list of applicants, with degree for which they are candidates, scholarship report, etc. If these records, together with the correspondence and recommendations which have come in, are received by the investigating officer before she visits a group, she can accomplish more. Coe College, Cedar Rapids, Iowa, is the only school suggested by the chairman of committee on fraternity examination from this year's papers. Maria Leonard, Iowa r, is dean of women there. Is investigation of this school desired? Respectfully submitted, ELDA L. SMITH. REPORT OF COMMITTEE ON SCHOLARSHIP July, 19X3-July, 1914 The chairman of the committee on scholarship submits the following report: The standard of scholarship in Pi Beta Phi for the session 1913-1914 shows a gratifying improvement over that of the preceding session. Unfortunately, however, the scholarship of some chapters is of a character far from worthy of the fraternity. Epsilon has the honor of being the ranking province, with Beta a close second, Alpha third, Gamma fourth, Zeta fifth, and Delta sixth. Pennsylvania B ranks highest of all the chapters. To New York B, Columbia A, Florida A, Illinois A, Iowa B, and Missouri ,A is due special commendation for concluding the year's work with neither a failure nor a condition to mar their record; to Vermont A, Virginia A, Ohio A, Michi,;an A, Indiana P, Iowa A, Wyoming A, and Colorado B, for concluding that of one semester without failure or condition; to Indiana A, for completing that of two terms ; to California B, for the excellent recrd of its freshmen; and to California A for successfully making up up 52 of the 67 hours left incomplete at the close of the first semester as a result of the severe illness in the chapter house. In order to obtain the numerical grade and the rank of each chapter the committee adopted the following system: Each hour of Grade I work 2 points Each hour of Grade 2 work I point Each hour of Grade 3 work (below passing) = -1 point The resulting sum to be divided by the total hours registered. It will be noted that rank 45 is the last given, no grades being obtainable for Maryland A, two chapters having tied for rank 28, and two for rank 37. In cases where the report for the second semester could not be obtained, the grade for the first semester has been used in ascertaining the rank of the chapter and the average of the province. Statistics for the session 1913-1914 agai; show conclusively that the scholar-ship of the freshmen is the weak point in the record of the majority of the chapters. The committee urges, in consequence, that each chapter formulate definite regulations governing the study of its freshmen and that supervision and instruction in the art of study be given them. It also recommends similar regulations and supervision in the case of other members of the chapter whose scholarship is below standard. The statistical reports for each province follow. Each college registrar was requested thus in giving the record of each member of the Pi Beta Phi chapter represented in his institution: 1. Record only the number of hours receiving the highest grade given by the institution, e. g. "excellent", "honors", "above go%", etc. 2. Record, the number of hours having grades between 1 and 3. Record the number of hours not resulting in credit toward graduation, g. "condition", "failure", "not passed", etc. Please give names of subjects under "Remarks". 4. If total does not equal the sum of 1, 2 and 3, please explain under "remarks" </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



