<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr3530401_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Bishop, Evelyn</name></author>
                        <author><name>Prickett, Norman R. </name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>March 1919</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr3530401_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">March 1919</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Bishop, Evelyn</name></author>
                        <author><name>Prickett, Norman R. </name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 400-406</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">36</note>
                        <note type="Folder">9</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 35, Number 3 (March 1919), Pages 400-406.</note>
			<note type="document">arr3530401_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Our Boys in Service; The Fireside industries of the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Founding of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1909-1927</item>
                                <item>Military</item>
                                <item>Handicraft</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr3530401_0001" seq="01" n="400-401  "/>
       <p>400 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON (So many clubs have asked for information about the particular Gatlinburg boy whom they adopted last winter, that Miss Bishop was requested to prepare this account of our representatives in the army. It has been difficult to secure the information as the home letters are few and infrequent. EDITOR.) OUR BOYS IN SERVICE By EVELYN BISHOP. Head Resident Major Frederick Palmer says in America in France: "The division which should have been most at home racially with the British was the Thirtieth, commanded by Major General Lewis, which came from the mountains of North and South Carolina and Tennessee. Ninety-five per cent of the men were pure Anglo-Saxon. No division is so truly American, if generations of ancestry on our soil count for being American. There was no difficulty in finding men who knew horses or mules or corn-planting in their ranks; but if you sought tailors, electricians, lacemakers, butlers, brass workers, or card-index experLs. you had come to the wrong market. Tall, lean, and corn-fed isn't that the proper phrase to use about them? When the King of En-gland came to a British front they marshalled a company of the tallest as an example of American manhood, with impressive results. "You might depend on it that the men of the Thirtieth could shoot, for hunting game had not died out in their home country. In their day some of them had had feuds; now they had a common feud against the Huns. Silent and polite men, used to solitudes, thinking definitely and simply in old-fashioned terms of life and death, they were touched with the crusade spirit from their very origin more sentimentally and more intensely than dwellers in the cities. . . The aeroplanes whose hum the men of the Thirtieth overheard in the darkness, they named `night riders.' I think that the concluding lines of a letter which one mountaineer wrote home deserve mention as a gem of sententiousness : `I must close now, mother. I've got to go out and kill a Hun. Love to father. Joe.' " Most of our Gatlinburg boys who have gone overseas belong to this division and Major. Palmer's Pcharacterization of them is true to life. They have gone out from these mountains, serious and quiet, with a full knowledge of what war really means for the effects of our last war have not yet died out in this part of the country. While NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 401 they appreciate the advantages of training and travel, almost without exception they write of longing for home again. One wonders how much it will mean to our community to have them back again with their new vision of life. Following is our Pi Beta Phi roll: Otis Trentham Enlisted in Knoxville, sent to France from training camp, and writes enthusiastically of things abroad. Arlie Watson Left in September for Camp Wadsworth, transferred to Camp Sherman, and sent abroad after a short training. Quartermaster's Department. Charlie Clabo Sent to training camp last spring and now in France. Dallard Ownby Training camp, overseas service. This was the first time he ever had been away from home and he writes of wanting to get back to the quiet of the mountains and asks how the hunting and trapping are this year. He left a little wife of about sixteen who was in our school for a time. Elder Ogle Enlisted in the navy April 5, 1917. Trained at Nor-folk. In two weeks was sent aboard the Louisiana. Is now on a transport. Daniel King Called in the summer. Sent abroad almost immediately. Killed in action. Left widow of fifteen years. Zimmry Trentham Called May 27, 1918. Camp Pike until August. Killed in action in France October 11. Left wife and baby. Zimmry was a charter pupil of the school. Sam Ogle Overseas service, wounded but would not take his discharge. His captain wrote that he would go on regard-less of wounds. Killed in action soon after. Oscar Bohanan Trained at Camp Gordon, now in France and expects to return soon. Reed Ogle Reenlisted when war was declared and went on the Louisiana, has been transporting troops since the armistice. Elmer Ogle Enlisted August 2, 1917. Camps Oglethorpe, Custer, Mills, Merritt, Dix, and Gordon Cook and Baker. Non-commissioned officer. Returned home at Christmas time. Arlier Watson Called to Camp Wadsworth in September, sent overseas after very short training. </p>
      <pb ref="arr3530401_0002" seq="02" n="402-403  "/>
       <p>402 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI Richard Carr Enlisted August, 1917. Camp Oglethorpe, Camp Devens, now in France, Quartermasters' Department, Bakery C, 307. Mitchell Carr S. A. T. C., Carson-Newman College, September, 1918. Albert Clabo Enlisted in the navy soon after war was declared. Was on the Delaware, now in Charlestown Navy Yards. Evert Reagan Called in the summer and sent abroad very soon. Eli Wilson In the first call, overseas service. Gassed and severely wounded, and at first, reported dead. Expects to return soon and wants to enter school again. Loy Reagan Called October 22, Camp Wadsworth, transferred to Newport News and is being retained in the Utility Department be-cause of his carpentry work. Minnis Ogle Medical Department, Camp Greenleaf. Had not had much education when he left here. Came back on furlough and gave a splendid talk at the school when the service flag was raised, is now in France. Following are the only letters received by the Editor in response to her request in the January Bulletin for letters written to clubs by Gatlinburg boys in the service. These were written by Richard Carr to the Boston Alumme Club. August 26. . My trip across was interesting but there was very little excitement. The sea was.very calm almost all the time. I saw some very beautiful country on my way from the port here. I wish I could have gotten some pictures of some of it. , Practically every foot of land in France where I have been is being tilled. The grain crops looked good on the way here and there were lots of vineyards, also. I am near a city that is quite interesting and I hope to be able to learn more about it while I'm here. November 21. I am still at the same place and am getting along fine. We aren't baking now. We do a little other work but not very much. I guess the best news everywhere is that the fighting has ceased and there are good indications that we shall soon have peace again, but it will possibly be delayed some on account of there not being any very stable' government on whose word we can rely, in Germany at present. I think it is impossible for `hem to begin fighting again though now. I like France very well and I find many interesting things here, but I guess I won't get to see the things that I would rather see. FROM LITTLE PIGEON 403 I visited a friend of mine out in a small village last Sunday and it was quite interesting to see the French customs. One of the odd customs was that his father and another visitor always ate with their hats on. Their ways of cooking are very rude. I have been in some few French homes and I haven't seen a modern cook stove or range as almost all American homes have. 'Every-thing is done the longest and hardest way it seems to me. The Frenchmen say that they certainly have learned a lesson from the Americans in the way of doing things quickly. December 13. We had quite a time celebrating here. Our company was not working at the time (when the armistice was signed) and we could get passes and we were in the city every afternoon and night for three or four days. It certainly was an interesting sight to see the French people so changed from their 'daily appearance. You should not have gone to the trouble of having a box sent to me for Christmas although I appreciate it very much and I wish I could return the favor, but it is quite inconvenient for sending anything from over here. It does not seem that it is almost Christmas as it is warm here yet. It has been raining 'and the roads in camp are very muddy. We have boots so we don't mind it much. , The censorship has not been completely lifted and I guess there is not much that I can tell you except that I am in Dijon, the old famous capital of Burgundy and I have seen, several old, historical things, one the famous statue of Napoleon, by Rude I believe. It is the most interesting thing I have seen. I also saw a reproduction of his prison on St. Helena. There is quite an interesting museum in Dijon also. SERGT. JOHN RICHARD 'CARR. THE FIRESIDE INDUSTRIES OF THE PI BETA. PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL By NORMAN R. PRICKETT, Head Industrial Departnzent I have often wished that I might have a round table discussion with Pi Beta Phis regarding the baskets and other home industries of the school. Again I thought it would be a good thing to send you a circular letter, but they usually find their way, unopened, to the wastebasket, so I decided to tell you something about the "Fireside Industries" in the pages of THE ARROW. The objects of which I shall write are made in the homes around the hearth, principally during the colder weather, hence the name, "Fireside Industries of the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School." In some </p>
      <pb ref="arr3530401_0003" seq="03" n="404-405  "/>
       <p>404. THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI of the homes chairs of black walnut are made, in others split bot om chairs; and in others still; baskets, "Kivers," "County Pins," and many articles of household use. Later we hope to have a greater variety of the things already being produced and to add others whose sale will aid both the home and the school in a material way. The process of home manufacture under the supervision of the school gives us a common interest and is often the needed "entering wedge" for the school. Owing to the recent demand for wool for army use only a very few "Kivers" have been made. With the great advance in price of the raw materials, wool, cotton, and dye-stuffs, which go into one of these A HOUSE WHERE MANY BASKETS HAVE BEEN MADE FOR THE PI PHIS covers it did not seem wise to attempt to turn out any this year. We hope it will only be a short time before the supply of needfuls will be normal. It has been said that almost a year of the woman's life goes into the making of one of these covers. This takes into consideration the facts that she raised her own cotton, spun, twisted, and doubled it, raised her own sheep, sheared them, washed, spun, twisted, and dyed the wool, grew her own indigo, and made her own. dyes. Of necessity we omit the raising of cotton fOr the cotton part of the "kivers," as cotton will not grow here in the mountains, and it is much simpler to get the thread from the factory ready for use. NETT/5' FRON LITTLE PIGEON 405 Even so, the making of a cover is no simple matter, the weaving alone takes days and days. The most popular patterns have been "Rattlesnake" "Gentleman's Fancy" and "Little Bow Knot," and are made in any color, but navy blue is the only substantial color which will stand wear and light. The "draft" is still used in the making of the "Kiver" and some of these drafts are more than a hundred years old. The "draft" is drawn off on paper about thirty inches wide and consists of lines, spaces, and numbers, and its appearance is much more mystifying than the base clef is to a beginner in music. Our baskets are made from the following materials: hemlock bark, willow switches (reeds), willow bark, white oak splits, and corn husks. In some sections the baskets are colored, but we have not SOME OF THE BASKET-MAKERS made a practice of coloring our baskets as it seems to cheapen their appearance, and they are much prettier in their natural color. _The hemlock bark comes in twelve and twenty inch wall pocket and one-half bushel size, round top market basket. They are priced $.75, $1.50, and $1.25, respectively. The willow reed baskets come as follows: small crochet (holding about a quart), $.40; willow darning basket (holds about a gallon), $1.00 and $1.25 ; willow sewing in sizes from 10 inches to 16 inches, prices from $.50 to $1.25 ; willow waste, price $1.25 to $2.00. In white oak split (W.O.S.) we have square and round top market and fireside baskets in peck, half bushel, one, two, and three bushel sizes with prices from $.75 (round top peck) to $5.00 for the three bushel fireside. We take special orders for bassinets. </p>
      <pb ref="arr3530401_0004" seq="04" n="406-407  "/>
       <p>406 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI It is now more or less difficult to get real baskets for there are few good makers and, of course, they get the best prices for their baskets. We sometimes buy baskets that are not up to our standard for the simple reason that we want to encourage the maker and increase the output. But the makers feel that they do not get justice for their work, if they are paid less than the experienced workers, and will not put their time on them. However, just as fast as conditions justify it, we are increasing both buying and selling prices, and at present our baskets are able to hold their own in comparison with baskets made in other sections. There are several children who are interested in making baskets and of course, in time will become expert makers. Just now their attempts are rather crude but they show great talent. These baskets may be had at a much lower price than the regular baskets. The time is at hand when we will have to face the question of shortage of materials, for only the hemlock is plentiful. We hope to interest the children in growing their materials for future basket-making. Until recently :we have been fifteen miles from a railroad and the baskets have had to be transported over rough roads to Sevierville for shipment. If a large basket order is received we simply have to pick our chances to get the bundle to the express office. Of course, the smaller bundles can be handled by parcels post. So if your pack-age does. not get to you just when you think it ought, just be patient, for many times the basket has to be made to order even from the cutting of the timber and this takes time. Too often the baskets are not ordered until only a short time before they are wanted, consequently we are unable .to fill many orders. Orders for Christmas received later than December first are very apt to go unfilled. But with all the ups and downs in basketdom, we have sold in the neighborhood of one thousand per year and this income not only helps the native workers, but is helping to equip the school with some very necessary things such as supplies for the cooking and sewing classes, and a few new tools for manual training. *So let the orders keep coming and we will do our best to supply your needs. *Address all orders as follows: Head of Industrial Department, Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tenn. WHAT A FRATERNITY GIRL THINKS 407 WHAT A FRATERNITY GIRL THINKS ABOUT WAR-TIME WASHINGTON COLUMBIA ALPHA IN WAR TIME When the call went out from Washington for war workers, Columbia A, both active chapter and alumnm, responded almost to a girl feeling that they had found right here at home opportunity of service for their country. The housing problem has been worse than anyone outside of Washington realizes, and the resident girls knew that by working they were helping a bit in the solution of this problem. They still continued their college work in the late afternoon classes, and busy as they were, they had not so much time for fraternity life as formerly, but interest did not wane. It has been a real pleasure in these war days to meet many Pi Phis from other chapters, and we have felt proud of our sisters who have come here from all over the country to engage in every sort of war work. They have been with us at chapter meetings, at cooky-shines, at alumnm meetings, at various Pi Phi parties and Red Cross activities. Columbia A. feels that she has gained much in knowing these Pi Phi sisters from other chapters and meeting them under such circumstances as have brought them here to Washington. ELIZABETH WILBUR PARKS, Columbia A. As VIEWED FROM THE FOOD ADMINISTRATION Together with hundreds of other girls, among whom were several Pi Phis, I found myself during the war in a corner of the great temporary structure which is the home of the Food Administration. Often, after working over hours devising ways and means to make the rest of you eat less and save more, I would wonder if it were all worth while and what good I was really doing. When I was so tired I could work no longer, I would go out and try to get something to eat. Generally, it was a case of more try than get for usually I had to content myself with a sandwich for which I paid about three times what it was worth. Then I would wait and wait for a car which, when it finally came, was overcrowded. But how quickly all my tired, cross feeling vanished when one of our boys just back from over there jumped up to give me his seat, bowed politely and limped away. Then the happy feeling that I too was doing my little part would rush over me, and I would go back to work </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



