<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr3230439_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Helmick, Elizabeth A.</name></author>
                        <author><name>Hughes, Carolyn McKnight</name></author>
                        <author><name>Pollard, Mary O.</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>March 1916</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr3230439_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">March 1916</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Helmick, Elizabeth A.</name></author>
                        <author><name>Hughes, Carolyn McKnight</name></author>
                        <author><name>Pollard, Mary O.</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 439-463</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">36</note>
                        <note type="Folder">3</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 32, Number 3 (March 1916), Pages 439-463.</note>
			<note type="document">arr3230439_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Improvements and Accomplishments During This Year as Seen by Our Chairman and Treasurer; Our Industrial Work at the Settlement School; Our Work and Our Needs; Before and After; The Experiences of Our Assistant Teacher; Our Visit to the Settlement School; As Others See Our Settlement School; Song Composed for and Sung at Mt. Pleasant Alumnae Club Settlement School Meetings, The School of My Heart</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Founding of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1909-1927</item>
                                <item>Curriculum</item>
                                <item>Teachers</item>
                                <item>Handicrafts</item>
                                <item>Living conditions</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr3230439_0001" seq="01" n="438-439  "/>
       <p>438 THE ARROTT/ OF PI BETA PHI supervision the students direct the work and are responsible for the production, but they work in cooperation with the faculty. A question arose concerning the dangers of amateur coaching as the coaches are apt to fall behind in their work, but the point system used in many colleges prevents this. The conclusion was that professional coaching may destroy the initiative on the part of students but the semi-professional or faculty coach saves valuable time of the students in the necessary routine work and through cooperation gives an opportunity for undergraduate development. But this question can-not be settled by any iron-clad rule but depends upon the organization and nature of the production. ' In the second discussion concerning the basis: of membership for college organization the general opinion seemed to be that some restrictions, some standards of excellence are bound to raise the standing of the organization to a higher degree than can be accomplished when they are unrestricted. Competition is necessary for incentive and with a standard of excellency it is bound to develop efficiency. The restriction in most cases is that of scholarship. The third problem on credit for non-academic work was very interesting. Most of the speakers seemed to consider credit for non-curriculum work to be necessary. Some of the leading arguments for this credit were that we are in college for intellectual training and why not use this intellectual training while we are getting, it ; by bringing together the daily life and curriculum one is not over-emphasizing one's faculty, but taking all and developing the rounded individual ; this unity also would tend to break down class barriers since everyone would be out for some kind of activity and all students would be thrown together. The main argument against this credit was that it would lessen the value of the four years college work and there would be danger of students substituting non-academic work for academic. Besides the training given by extra-curriculum can be received every-where in the outside world, especially in schools given over to such training, but the college offers a unique training, and so why detract from it? These objections seem, however, to be offset by the plan known as a point system and of requiring this credit to be added to the present number of credits required for graduation. In this way the advantages and benefits of college would not be reduced and no one person could monopolize the college honors for each one f:, NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 439 would be required to do and engage in some activity so the man of the world, the well-rounded and developed individual would graduate. The chief benefits of this student conference came from the fact that it was a gathering of active young people from many leading colleges and universities, all of whom had many new and interesting ideas. In the discussion of their plans, experiences, and ambitions, each delegate was able to view his plans from all viewpoints and profit from it. All college students have approximately the same difficulties and so the interchange of. ideas was most beneficial. H. LOUISE PARSONS, Massachusetts A., ex-'17. NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON IMPROVEMENTS AND ACCOMPLISHMENTS DURING THIS YEAR AS SEEN BY OUR CHAIRMAN AND TREASURER The fifth session of the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School opened on August 3, 1915, with Caroline McK. Hughes, Minnesota A, as Head Resident, Mary O. Pollard, Vermont A, as Principal of the School, and Marie Ditmars, Indiana A, and Bernice Good, Indiana B, assistants. Miss Hughes has been primarily the manual training instructor, but also has taken charge of the business of the Gatlinburg end of the school and the responsibilities of Head Resident. Miss Pollard has had the entire management of the school work together with school discipline and school activities. Miss Ditmars has been our successful and popular kindergarten and primary teacher for two years now, and Miss Good, our youngest teacher, has assisted both Miss Pollard and Miss Ditmars as needed. At the request of the Principal for a fifth teacher, Miss Plank, Iowa Epsilon (I. C. chapter at South Iowa Normal School), offered her services and reported at the school on January tenth. The enrollment for the first half of the year has been one hundred and thirty students. Each summer, the water supply in the cottage well has been exhausted early in the school session, and we have been obliged to bring our water from the neighbors' wells or springs. This fall we put in a new sixty-foot well which we hope will never "run dry," and furnish both cottage and school-house with a generous supply for all time. </p>
      <pb ref="arr3230439_0002" seq="02" n="440-441  "/>
       <p>440 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI When it became evident that the new teachers' residence could not be built this fall, it seemed absolutely necessary for the comfort and health of our workers that more sleeping room be provided and the teachers be housed under one roof. The wisest plan seemed to en-large the cottage. This building needed a hew chimney, a new roof, fresh paint and minor repairs, so this opportunity was seized to add two sleeping rooms over the main building, to widen the front piazza to ten feet, the back piazza to eight feet, to add a porch on the east for storage and' closets, and to make the necessary repairs. We have now a fairly comfortable cottage where our teachers may enjoy a few more home comforts of living and be together under one roof. This cost $450 and has put the building in good shape for immediate use for the Jennie Nicol Memorial hospital as soon as the new residence is built. Early in the fall, a beginning was made in furnishing the manual training department. We purchased $168 worth of equipment of Hammacher, Schlemmer and Co., of New York, and since then the Springfield, Missouri, alumnEe club have added $100 for buying looms. This department has started auspiciously toward opening up a new and most valuable departure in our mountain school work, and we hope the time is not far distant when we will be helping large numbers outside as well as within the school to making a better livelihood as well as benefiting ourselves to a small per cent. In this connection, it has developed that the people cannot be induced to work on if they are not paid as soon as the work is completed. They cannot understand our scheme of being their agent in selling their wares, but insist upon "spot cash," "hand-go, hand-come" money, or they will not work. They do not seem to care enough about having those comforts of which they know not, which their work would eventually bring to them, to work and wait for its sale, This paying in advance for their weaving and industrial work has been a large item in our expenses this year which was not anticipated at Convention, but if we should stop paying our money for their work, they would stop working, so it seems wise until we have succeeded in establishing ourselves, at least, that we continue buying their products. Next year this should be included in our budget. Through the generosity of Mrs. H. B. Wilbur, Eta Province Vice-president, who visited the school last year with her husband, Miss Pollard was given the money to refurnish her room at the cottage, NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 44'1 which makes her very comfortable and happy. Five hundred dollars have been paid upon lumber, cut, and stacked on our land, for the proposed new residence. It seemed good business to buy this lumber now and have it carefully stacked where it could not check, thereby saving $3.50 per thousand for kiln drying later on, and especially as the saw mill was being hauled away to a new and remote location. We have received from the County School Board the entire appropriation for schools for this place, amounting to $360, and the County Superintendent, in speaking of the school, has said that it was "the best school in the county." It was voted in the alumnT session of our last Convention that "the Settlement School be placed under the control of a Board of Managers, appointed by the Grand Council." Mrs. Allen, Grand Vice-president, ex-officio, to represent the Grand Council, the seven Province Vice-presidents, and Mrs. Helmick as ,chairman and treasurer, were named to compose this Board. I believe this combination, composed of members whose duties bring them in close touch with the organized alumnm, is making the strongest "team" the school has ever had. More alumnae clubs have worked this year for the school than ever before and the spirit and results have been very gratifying. Elsewhere in this issue will be found short sketches by each of the workers of the school. NO Pi Phi can read these reports and not be impressed with the earnestness and devotion of our Pi Phi sisters in this estimable national endeavor to help our fellow coml.,-trymen in the mountains. ELIZABETH A. HELMICK, Chairman and Treasurer. Donna, Texas. OUR INDUSTRIAL WORK AT THE SETTLEMENT SCHOOL By Caroline McKnight Hughes, Head Resident Caroline McKnight Hughes, the new Head Resident of the Settlement School, was initiated into Pi Beta Phi Fraternity on January 14, 1893, at the University of Minnesota. She jokingly speaks of her early days having been spent in association with "America's first families" because of the fact that in her early childhood home, her playmates, included Indians and half breeds, on the shores of Lake Superior in Minnesota. Her family interests being divided between the east and the middle west, there were many moves up to the time of her entrance to the University of Minnesota in 1890. She </p>
      <pb ref="arr3230439_0003" seq="03" n="442-443  "/>
       <p>442 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI writes that once, when her grandfather McKnight was, asked where she was "raised," after thinking a moment, re-plied, "in a sleeping car," and, she adds, "that really tells the tale in a few words, for we were going or coming most of the time." The year following her graduation from the University of Minnesota, she was graduated from Cooper Union School of Art, New York, and in 1897 she was graduated from Prang Normal, and directly 'after entered upon the duties of a teacher of art, manual training and construction. She first taught at the State Normal School at Stevens Point, Wisconsin, and then at Michigan City, Indiana. At the last place, where she was supervisor of industrial work with very large classes and heavy re sponsibilities, her ambition was greater than her physical strength, and before the year was completed, she was forced by a nervous breakdown to give up the work and seek an entire rest. We next find her in Meridian, Mississippi; but here her work was cut short by illness in her family, and for five long, anxious years she was the patient nurse attending her parents in a lingering illness at their family home near Fairfax Court House, Virginia. Miss Hughes went to Gatlinburg last June to familiarize herself with conditions and people before the opening of school in August. She has installed a modest manual training equipment for the younger boys, and has taught cooking and sewing to the young girls, and under her talented supervision the school has been instrumental in reviving among the older women that almost forgotten art of spinning and weaving. This year has seen the beginning of an industrial activity which it is hoped will be developed into a splendid industry. That our new head resident has impressed these people with her skill and ability may be judged by the remark of one of our mountain friends who laconically ex-claims: "Miss Hughes sure can do wonderful things !" Miss Hughes is the embodiment of dignity, and possesses a quiet, even disposition which inspires confidence; she is very artistic and practical, thorough and painstaking, and the Fraternity is fortunate in securing this experienced gentlewoman in this important work at our school. E.A.H. CAROLINE MCKNMHT HUGHES Minnesota A NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 443 It had been noised about that "them women," meaning the Pi Phis at the Settlement School, were going to "teach tools," and the curiosity of the people of the "Berg" was so great that they ran down the county road to meet the wagon bringing in the tools. All they saw were some boxes, nailed up tight, and some crates with they knew not what inside. The excitement and curiosity was equal to a circus coming to town, and when the five benches were in place, with the tools set out, every man and boy able to come to the school did so. Apparently no one knew much about tools, except the saw, plane and hammer, and the first day of class work was a queer one. The younger boys were all excitement and ready to learn; the "big fellows" were not. The hardest part of this work has been keeping the older boys and girls interested. They do not know "how to do" and do not seem to care to learn. This may be inertia, but more likely is "plum laziness" which is a very popular complaint in this part of the country. All the woodwork has been so far of a very elementary order, owing to the lack of tools, and many of the boys did not know the difference between "wet" and "dry" wood, so that much of the work had to be worked out the second time. The little fellows in the third grade have made tables, chairs, cupboards and quilt presses for the doll's house, and they also helped make the dishes, using what is called "pipe clay" here. The rest of the boys began with pencil sharpeners and cord winders, then on to table book-racks, flower-pot holders, umbrella stands and wall cabinets, and in all the work the boys of the fourth and fifth grades have handed in better work than the older ones. The third grade girls have made dishes, rugs, bed covers, sheets, pillow cases, hammocks and cardboard furniture, also the outfit for the doll complete, even to the hats. They have also made a few small "husk" baskets. As the girls have furnished their own materials, all sorts of things have been made, i. e., aprons, underwear, handkerchiefs, waists (many of these have been embroidered), bags, large and small, towels with designs in cross-stitch, and small table covers. We have also made all sorts of possible and impossible things with a crochet hook. The cross-stitch work did not appeal to the older girls, but it did to the younger ones. </p>
      <pb ref="arr3230439_0004" seq="04" n="444-445  "/>
       <p>444 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI I believe that our industrial work should go beyond the school, taking in the families of the scholars, and "good goods" we can always dispose of for them. These people have such beautiful wood to work with that it seems a shame not to place it upon the market. Many of the men have come to me with "wooden ware" and most of it has been sold through the clubs. In the "yesteryears" this country was a community of weavers, but after the war, "store cloth" was cheap so that one woman after another put the old loom aside, but many of our neighbors today know how to spin and weave though it has been "a tol'able long spell" since any of them have done such a thing. One woman, not far from the school, has her old loom up and is able and willing to make "kivers," and these are very dear to the hearts of old-timers. Many of the women still use the big hand wheel to "twist stocking yarn" but the little wheel for flax has about disappeared. Everyone is using Diamond Dyes to color their yarn but a large per cent know how to make "ooze" out of barks, roots, weeds, etc. All the loohls about here are either the one "great grandpap brunged from Car'liny when he coomed in" or are copies of these old ones, and of course one and all are crude homemade affairs. They are clumsy and big and all the weavers are old women. "Up yander in the mo'tains" there are many looms in use, and the women have little or no use for "store cloth," but down in our Berg all are fond of it. Tastes differ here as well as elsewhere. Cloth can be made forty inches wide down to the width of a belt. No one seems to know anything about the old-time double "kiver" that was really two in one, or of "flax" (linen) cloth. The old "kivers" were made with flax "chain" (wrap) and woolen filling; now, the chain is of cotton, so that the coverlids of today are rather coarse. The "drafts" or patterns have come down from mother to daughter. Many of the marks have faded so that the weaver of today is apt to "skip" part of the pattern, making the "kiver" much askew. If one expects the work to be like that that comes from up-to-date looms, such as are used in factories, they must not buy goods "turned off" of these old looms. After seeing one in use, we cannot help wondering why the patterns "match at all." Down here one does not "match" colors; she "gets" them, and I hope the time is not far off when the softness of the homemade dyes will appeal NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 445 to all more than the bright hard hues of the commercial dyes now in use. Before Christmas, we had a "spinning bee" at the school. All the older women were asked to come with either cards or wheels. Quite a bit of wool was carded and spun, and. at the last the women worked for prizes ; the winners went home happy, but the rest were "in the dumps." All seemed interested and "holpt" we would have another one soon. As a whole, these people are most indifferent, so "spinning bees" may wake them up, and we will resort to almost IN FRONT OF THE SCHOOLHOUSE A Picture of those at the December, 1915, "Spinning Bee" anything to keep up their interest. The people of the "Berg" are not the real mountaineers. In fact, we have only one, and she tells most interesting tales. Imagine a cabin made of immense logs, no windows perhaps, but always with two doors on opposite sides of the room and an immense chimney made of mud and stones: the walls were always chinked with mud also. The "chimney board" (mantel piece) was well up from the floor and below it was an opening large enough to take in great big logs. Candles were used a bit, but more often knots of "fat pine," but much of the time the firelight answered all purposes. At night, as soon as the cabin was "rid up" after the evening meal, out came the cards, and the children, boys as well as girls, were "put </p>
      <pb ref="arr3230439_0005" seq="05" n="446-447  "/>
       <p>446 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI to them" to get the wool in shape for the spinner. just in front of the fireplace or "flue" stood the big spinning wheel, as the wool "works" better when warm. Back and forth, with the right 'hand out to keep the wheel turning, and the thread held in the left hand, walked the spinner, and often the wheel "whirred" far into the night, as it was a matter of personal pride to spin so many "cuts" of yarn a day, and they knew just how many "broches" were needed to make a "cut." The "whirring" of the spinning wheel was all the lullaby the mountain children had. A "broche" is made by wrapping a bit of corn husk about the spindle of the spinning wheel and the spun thread is wound upon it. The next time you buy a pound of yarn notice how many times the threads are separated and tied. Each one of these divisions is a "cut." After the wool was spun, dying it was the next thing, and the "ooze" was made of bark, roots and weeds. The bark and roots of the black walnut, white walnut (butternut), maple, chestnut and hickory, as well as many others, were used, "set" with alum or copperas, as a rule. Next, came the "setting up" of the loom, i. e., stringing the chain, then the "sley" fastening the thread to the "cloth brain" in front, then winding up the rest on the "warping beam" at the back of the loom. This process takes two people two days, and for each "draft" or pattern, the thread is pulled through the sley in a different way, so it is hardly worth while to "set up" a loom simply to make one "kiver" from a draft. Each "kiver" has from five hundred to seven hundred threads passed through the sley. I want the industrial work of our school to be given a thorough trial for I believe it will be the salvation of these people. They have spent long years "jest setting" ; now we want to teach them to work, using both hands and head together. All summer, everyone works out of doors, but after the "crap" is "put away" they are in the habit of passing the time doing nothing. So many of them do not even think now-a-days, but "jest set." The Tomato Clubs and Corn Clubs have done much for the boys and girls, but that work ends with the summer, and the industrial work, well managed, should use up the time during the winter months. We need many things to help the work along, as well as "ready money" for helping to develop the work. In fact, "ready money" in this case will spell success. In other localities in the NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 447 Appalachian Mountains this work has been successful, namely, East-ern Kentucky, and the western part of both North and South Carolina, and why not in Eastern Tennessee? In all four states one finds the same class of people, so what has succeeded in one should succeed in the other. As we think over this part of our work it will always be well to remember that "Rome was not built in a day." OUR WORK AND OUR NEEDS As Seen by Mary O. Pollard, Principal of the Settlement School I think that the first thing that impresses everyone who comes to Gatlinburg is the feeling that what she has read in books about the Southern Highlanders does not apply here to any great extent. We are here in the midst of the mountains, and we are among mountaineers, but in characteristiCs and character and ideas and thoughts they are rather "country people" than what we usually picture as "our contemporary ancestors." They live primitively, some of them in log houses and in one-room cabins, but on the other hand, most of those who send their children to the Pi Phi School live in frame houses with from two to eight rooms; they buy "store clothes" and the young men order suits from Chi cago, while some of the girls get silk waists from Knox ville and wear ready-to-wear suits. The girls still work in the fields to some extent, as do also the women, but the men generally send the women to church on horse or mule back, ;with the baby, while they walk beside to' see that there MARY O. POLLARD </p>
      <pb ref="arr3230439_0006" seq="06" n="448-449  "/>
       <p>448 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI is no possible accident. If, as you sometimes see, the woman is walking and the man is riding with the baby, it is generally because the woman prefers to walk to rest her arms from the weight of the child. The people have as few superstitions as we would find in any country place in the North, and both men and women have an inborn refinement and gentleness of speech and a courtesy that is a thing of the heart. The young men are quick to pick up the ways of outsiders, and in manners and appearance are quite like any country young men. The girls adopt new things now as easily as do the boys. At first, it seemed as though the girls were more conservative and were well satisfied with their old ways, but now they are eager to know new ways of doing things and ask questions and drink in information that we give. When they go to church or school, the girls, as a whole, are as well dressed, and as well appearing as any girls in any country place. They dress their hair well and tastefully; they look bright and intelligent; and best of all, they look happy. When we first came here, the young folks looked as though they were not in the habit of having a good time. Now, they look bright and cheerful; they smile easily and laugh heartily; they not only are interested in their own affairs but are getting interested in things outside. Several of the older ones are reading and they are asking for good things to read. One of the boys who was in School last year, and has been teaching, has read Scarlet Letter, House of Seven Gables, Last of the Mohicans,, Autobiography ,of Franklin, and several other books this year. We are encouraging the little folks to read too, and this morning Cora brought back Alcott's Lulu's Library, the first book she had ever read through outside of the schoolroom, and she went off smiling with What Katy Did, and she reported that her brother Elmer was reading his book today and could read two pages to her one. Elmer is reading With Lee in Virginia in connection with his United States history, and it is the first book he ever took home to read. Cora is eleven and Elmer is nineteen. One of our greatest needs is for good books, standard books, such as young folks and older folks ought to read; not simply the cast-offs that no one finds interesting. We have almost no standard books for older people, like Dickens, Cooper, George Eliot, Thackeray, Howells, Warner, Dumas, and Scott. Very largely I have had to NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 449 supply those books from my own library because I was anxious 'that they have a chance to read the best when they were ready to read it. The set of Alcott sent us last year has proven a blessing indeed, and all the girls, big and little, love Old Fashioned Girl and Rose in Bloom and Eight Cousins, and now the little folks are reading Aunt Jo's Scrap Bag. But how would you feel when you had loaned a boy Scott's Rob Roy, and he brought it back with the "That's a fine book; got any more like it ?" and the best substitute you could give was one of Henty's? We have received a number of boxes this fall, and they have added materially to our supply, and we certainly appreciate them, and not only we appreciate them but so do the children and the town people. Our library is one of our strong assets, and we have the beginning of a practical library but do not forget us, for reading as they do now the supply soon becomes exhausted. We want to give them as many good things to read as they will assimilate. To me one of the greatest needs of the place here is a trained corps of teachers for the country schools. As long as roads are as rough and steep as they are now, it will be.impossible to have consolidated schools such as we would like. Therefore, the best that can be done is to put into these back schools teachers with as good a training as possible, and with the present salaries in the county (from $27.50 to $50 a month for five months) , it will be impossible for the teachers to save enough to go away for normal school. But any of them could attend our school at small expense, and what we could give them in ideas and ideals and in methods, and most of all in ambition, would do more to lift the country schools to a higher plane than what we can, simply with our own little circle who live within reach of our schoolhouse. We have reached these well and efficiently, and added brightness and joy to their lives. But back up in Sugarlands and Upper Little River and up on Baskins and Spruce Flats and Mill Creek and Little Dudley are the children who are now being taught by those whom we might easily reach and help to a new ideal of education. I shall not be satisfied with what we are doing here until we can do something to interest the local teachers and to help them in their work with the children whom we cannot personally reach. The church has just completed another series of special meetings. The new pastor has been pastor of a Knoxville church for some time and gave up his place there to come back to put his life into this </p>
      <pb ref="arr3230439_0007" seq="07" n="450-451  "/>
       <p>450 THE ARROW OF P1 BETA FIJI county where he was raised. He is interested in our school and its work, and his coming will help us. The Baptist Young People's Union has been revived this fall and is prospering; a junior Union is to be organized in the near future and I am to have oversight of it with the help of some of the young people. The Sunday School and the new pastor are talking of grading the Sunday School classes. There seems to be a general onward impulse and we are hoping earnestly that our school may have a large part in helping to shape the direction of the advance, as we feel that it has had a large influence in bringing about the desire for the advance. BEFORE AND AFTER By Marie Ditmars Each of us at the Pi Phi Settlement School is writing for this ARROW and we are wondering which little phase we will give you. There is so much of interest that one scarcely knows where to begin and what to tell you. We take turns doing the cottage housework, the school work and visiting. It is the little tots at school, however, who get most of my time. How they have changed in the two years I have been here! And how they must have changed since Miss Hill and "Miss Dell" first had them, and since Miss Bryan corraled them in the little old "store house" around their small tables 1 They are now happy little children, with bobbed hair, dressed as other little children of their means are dressed. You could never stand the coarse little shoes they wear when cold weather makes them put their free strong feet under cover, and their stockings are most all of that scratchy homespun, homeknit wool. Some stockings are left natural color, some colored brown, some bright blue or green and some bright red. It looks queer to see a little boy 'in "store clothes" with a pair of bright red or blue wool stockings. Sometimes the color scheme is picturesque. One of my little girls wears a black wool dress, trimmed in red braid, red stockings and red toboggan cap, and with her glowing cheeks, as she comes hurrying in from her two-mile walk in the frosty morning air, makes a dear picture. I can't see that these children are so very different in school now from those country children I have taught in Indiana. It is when I go into their homes with -them that I notice the great 'difference. But you have heard so many times about their homes! BEFORE OUR FIRST SCHOOLHOUSE MISS HILL AND CHILDREN IN 1912 </p>
      <pb ref="arr3230439_0008" seq="08" n="452-453  "/>
       <p>AFTER OUR PRESENT SCHOOL BUILDING THESE CHILDREN ARE IN THE 1912 PICTURE NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 453 I have had four classes, or grades, this fall the primer, first grade, second grade, and third grade. These keep me busy every. minute during school hours. The first month this year I had between forty and fifty almost every day. Then whooping cough took the whole room by storm and for two months my average was between twenty and thirty. Many never came back in again, while others straggled back just before Christmas, so that I had between twenty-five and thirty-five. The loss worried me because I believe that every single little child above six years should be in school, but when their parents are indifferent, what can we do? In my room the children started industrial work with weaving tiny rugs, mats and hammocks while preparing for a playhouse. The third grade boys made little tables, cupboards, shovels and knives out of wood, in the manual training room, while the girls of that grade made shuck pillows and mattresses, sheets, blankets, pillow cases, and they all made cardboard chairs, beds, cribs and stools for the doll house. When these things were done, the box-house was brought in and the two rooms, one above the other, were furnished. One whole week of delight was spent moulding clay from a nearby bank into dishes, pans, pots and kettles for the kitchen. Then when their teacher went to Knoxville and came back with a five cent jointed doll (which they named Minnie Belle) interest and excitement was intensified. We at once began making clothes for the doll. What do you suppose they made first? Aprons ! Aprons of all kinds ! This is not surprising when you consider that the, women here wear aprons even to church. Minnie Belle's little underclothes even were trimmed with feather stitching. Miss Hughes gets beautiful results from the most careless. Our children design and make the cutest bonnets and hats for the doll out of corn shucks. The house was complete in every detail and inhabited about Christmas, and when we found a little stove had come in a box from New York our delight reached the bounds! Miss Good has one of my classes now fourth grade geography and Miss Pollard had third grade arithmetic almost all fall. The children love to march into the big room for a recitation and they come back beaming. 'Please will some good Pi Phi 'who can sing come and take them for next year. Our children love to sing and I cannot belt) them. </p>
      <pb ref="arr3230439_0009" seq="09" n="454-455  "/>
       <p>454 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI THE EXPERIENCES OF OUR ASSISTANT TEACHER [Bernice Good, our youngest assistant at the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, was born in Warren, Indiana, and was graduated from the Warren high school in 1910. The following year she went to Glendale College, a girls' school near Cincinnati, from which she was graduated two years later. After a year at home, she entered Indiana University, at Bloomington, in September, 1913, as a junior and soon after became a Pi Phi. She graduated from the University in 1915, receiving her A.B. degree. Her major work was in the English department. During her college course she was active in athletics, being on the basketball team during her junior year. She was also a member of the Y. W. C. A. cabinet. This year she is teaching at our Settlement School, assisting in the higher grades.] We have been having revival meetings in the Church House since Christmas vacation, and this has disturbed the school these first two tiff eeks. The revival came to a close last Thursday, and we are now getting down to good work this week. Our school is smaller than it was before Christmas because of tuition being charged, but we have a good school. Those who are most interested and progressive are the ones who are coming, and these are the children who naturally make the work most interesting, although perhaps we are not reaching the children who need it most. Last term our term enrollment was one hundred and thirty six. It is too early to tell what the enrollment will reach this term. Our school has been very successful this year. Several children who have been indifferent before, and who came irregularly have BERNICE GOOD Indiana B NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 455 this year come almost every day, and they have taken a different attitude toward their work. They want to learn to write, and ask for written lessons while they used to miss school at the time for written work. They are learning to take what we offer them with-out questioning every new thing. They are using the dictionary and encyclopedia freely. We have compulsory school laws in Tennessee, but they are not enforced in this country, and many of the children do not come on time or with regularity and the parents do not feel the necessity for regular and prompt attendance, and there is no public sentiment on the subject. The children have learned to play all kinds of games. The younger girls love to play "Farmer in the Dell" and to "jump rope" (which is here a grape vine). The boys are also practising "jumping." In the fall, the older boys had a good baseball team and there were some spirited games. We played tennis. Last year we had basket-ball for both the girls and boys. The parents and people did not approve of the girls playing in bloomers just as they disapprove of our riding a horse astride. The older pupils, especially the boys, love to sing, and they spend most of their time at recess and noon singing hymns. We are planning to have a literary program on Friday afternoons, and we are inviting the parents to come and visit the school on those days. We are in need of material for programs and any old "speakers" will be welcome. The children read the books from the library and seem to understand and appreciate and enjoy them. I will giVe you our schedule for the upper grades so that you may see what we are doing. We follow the course of study prescribed by the Tennessee Board of Education. This is our schedule: </p>
      <pb ref="arr3230439_0010" seq="10" n="456-457  "/>
       <p>456 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI 5th Grade 6th Grade 7th Grade 8th Grade Opening Exercises, consisting of Bible reading and the Lord's Prayer ........ ........ Arithmetic Tennessee Arithmetic Manual ........ History Training, Latin Sewing ........ and Grammar ........ Drawing Grammar Recess Recess Recess Recess Spelling ........ ........ Arithmetic Language ........ ........ Arithmetic Spelling Spelling Spelling NOON ' Manual 12 :30 to 12:55 Training, Arithmetic Literature ........ 12:55 to 1:20 Sewing ........ ........ Grammar and 1:20 to 1:45 Drawing Writing ........ Literature History 1 :45 to 2:00 Recess History Recess Recess Recess 2:00 to 2:25 Reading Reading ........ Grammar 2:25 to 2:50 Writing ........ History History 2:50 to 3:15 ........ Geography Geography Geography 3:15 to 3:40 Geography ........ ........ ........ W'e had a "Rally Day" and "Field Day" the latter part of October, which were well attended and were quite a success, but the Christmas entertainment was most popular of all. For this, the school building was crowded. They began coming at 7 o'clock while the program was not scheduled to begin until 10 o'clock. We had a big spruce tree, which Mr. Andrew Ogle got for us, and it looked beautiful after we 8 :3o to 8 :45 8:45 to 9:15 9:15 to 9:40 9 :40 to 10 :10 [0:10 to 10:25 [0 :25 to 10 :50 10:50 to 11:20 I :20 to 1 I :30 NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 457 got it decorated and loaded with the presents. We put on a stocking of candy and a present for each pupil, and the other things they put on for one another. This was the first year that they have had a general exchange of presents among themselves. The girls made presents of' sewing baskets, crochet bags, aprons, towels, handkerchiefs, etc. For the Christmas entertainment, we had a little play by the older ones and dialogues, readings and songs. The week before the Christmas tree was a very strenuous one with the extra school work and getting ready to "go home for Christmas," but we lived through both and came back well rested after our two weeks at home. I wish that you could all come down to Gatlinburg and visit and see for yourselves our school. You would be delighted with the wonderful mountain scenery. Today everything is covered with snow and it is a lovely picture. January 18. OUR VISIT TO THE SETTLEMENT SCHOOL By Leda P. Wilbur, Eta Province Vice-president We were bound on one of our trips from the extreme west to the far east, and were taking a route new to us from St. Louis through the Blue Grass region down to Knoxville, lured hither by the fame of the Pi Phis School up at Gatlinburg, and also a bit, I must confess, by the fascination of these southern mountains. It was fortunate that my husband was quite as enthused as I over Little Pigeon reports in in THE ARROW! Because our morning express was late into Knoxville, we were obliged to take the afternoon train for Sevierville, which necessitated our remaining at the hotel there over night. I was not keen about attempting this particular thing, but it proved not really so bad, especially as we were rescued for the evening by Evelyn Bishop, New York A, and taken to her home. Her father is president of Murphy College, Sevierville. We also had the pleasure of meeting that night a charming girl, a native of the town, who could recall the stagecoach communication with Knoxville days not so long ago Much was said especially to picture for us the life of the locality. Most of the village had departed on a possum hunt, on this gloriously moonlit night. Their moonlight is famous one did not wonder that they prefer it for the chase! Next morning, a lovely October day, we started off, with a mountain team and wagon, past the statue of John Sevier, for the drive to </p>
      <pb ref="arr3230439_0011" seq="11" n="458-459  "/>
       <p>458 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI. Gatlinburg. I shall never forget the first view as we came over the ridge and in the sight of the tiny hamlet with the school standing out prominently in the background, nor the vistas up to the cottage as we stopped at the gate and Miss Pollard came running down to meet us with her cordial welcome. Those hours at the Pi Phi School were enchanted for us ! Fortunately it was on a Saturday and Sunday, so that the teachers were free to show us the wonders of the place, and to take us into many of the homes and introduce us to the people. It was not long till we were pledging our undying enthusiasm, and wishing that such and such things might be done to assist in the spendid work that has been so finely launched. GATLINBUKG, TENNESSEE With the II B cl) Schoolhouse on the left, center We longed most for the comfortable home for the teachers, with water inside and the comforts that accompany it, a furnace installed as in the school, and an acetylene plant that would do away with lamps everywhere. These things would help greatly, but there would still be the days of strenuous life, up early for housework, the day at school, with all the additional problems of an ungraded and irregular attendance, with the settlement idea always first in the minds of the teachers, then the journeys to often distant homes visits this same settlement work incurs and then to the cottage again and more housework! It made the life of a teacher in the city school one, of idleness .in comparison. Each of these girls did this fine NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 459 thing through love for it, giving in part her services. Surely ought not we other Pi Phis in the comfort of our modern homes for any home among us would be luxury beside the cottage ought not we every one to deny ourselves some added pleasure each year in order to give this undertaking of which we are so proud, some additional support? The perfect beauty of this valley, in the blaze of intense autumnal coloring, with its riches of hardwood forests concealing delightful haunts for the botanist, the silvery windings of the Little Pigeon through green fields, the rounded verdure-crowned summits of the A PI PHI REUNION AT THE SETTLEMENT SCHOOL From left to right Helen Carruthers, Edith Wilson, Evelyn Bishop, Mrs. Wilbur, Miss Pollard, Margaret Young, Marie Ditmars, and Helen Bryan. mountains as they rise on and on to the higher Smokies far away in the distance all this wonderfully perfect setting made us think soberly of the obligation we have assumed with this people, of how we must help them to cherish the virtues that they have, and, if we may, bring to them something new of virtue and of happiness. By the development of the natural industries we should lift them out o their intense poverty and aid them to live comfortable lives in this peaceful and favored land. Precious moments fled all too rapidly ! Much visiting there was, for it happenedthat Helen Bryan, New York B was back from Barea College for, a _day or so and Helen Carruthers with her, and </p>
      <pb ref="arr3230439_0012" seq="12" n="460-461  "/>
       <p>460 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI that the excitement was too much for Miss Bishop so that she joined us, making eight Pi Phis The day was so full that Miss Pollard had to sit up with us more than half the night in order that we should find out some of the things we really so much wanted to know. We cannot sufficiently emphasize our gratitude to Miss Pollard and the girls for their generous hospitality, nor adequately express our appreciation of the magnificent work we found them doing. The whole trip was the most unique thing we have ever done, as removed as our western mountain peaks from the beaten paths of travel, and then, in addition to that, with the throbbing interest of a big human problem. As OTHERS SEE OUR SETTLEMENT SCHOOL (The following paragraphs were taken from an unsigned article entitled "Among the Southern Highlanders," which appeared in The New York Christian Advocate for December 23, 1915. Those familiar with our school, recognized the description of Pi Phi's nearest neighbor. The cut of the home as it appears today is published through the courtesy of The Christian Advocate. -EDITOR.) Among the Southern Highlanders Back fifteen miles from a railroad and in the towering mountains lives a typical mountaineer. In his one-room log cabin were born eleven children, out of, which death took a toll of five young lives. All through the Southern mountains the large number of little graves bears silent testimony to the presence of the grim monster, his first assistant being ignorance. For years this family lived as thousands of others are living, on the coarsest fare, with scant clothing, knowing little or nothing of sanitation and with no hope of anything better. That they sprang from the best Scotch-Irish stock, that in their veins flows the purest blood, that they are of the class from which we draw our strongest and best American citizenship promised nothing for their future, either in alleviating their hardships or in opening up avenues to broader living. Millions of these people are shut in by the mountains from the currents of modern life from their cultural, inspirational and uplifting influences, from a broad, sane and true vision of life. They live the narrow, hard and discouraged life and die before their allotted time. "Where there is no vision the people perish." Four years ago the Pi Beta .Phi Fraternity established a mountain school near this home and placed college-bred women in charge. To ANDY OGLE'S HOME, 1912 ANDY OGLE'S HOME, 1915 (Courtesy of Christian Advocate) </p>
      <pb ref="arr3230439_0013" seq="13" n="462-463  "/>
       <p>462 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI the entire community has come a remarkable uplift. In this particular home the transformation is marvelous. Ignorance and indifference are giving place to vital interest in education; light is chasing away gloom and discouragement has gone out the back door as hope stepped up on the front porch. The whole family is catching a true life vision. Mother is taking her rightful place as homemaker. The oldest girl is a member of the Girls' Canning Club and hopes to realize $40 annually from the berries she picks and from the tomatoes and beans she raises on one tenth of an acre of hillside. To have seen her and heard her talk plans for this work last spring would have sent a thrill through any soul. When the oldest boy entered school, three years ago, he was not prepared for the third grade. He has completed the sixth and is this year taking studies in the seventh and eighth. Soon after he entered school he began going to Sunday school and a little later gave his heart to God. At eighteen years of age he is a fine specimen of young manhood. In the meantime the spirit of progress has reached the parents as well. Their patch of land shows the effect of good cultivation. In front of the old log cabin, which is now used as a storehouse, they have builded a modern four-room cottage. The family and their surroundings stand as proof that these Christian college women have not labored in vain. SONG COMPOSED FOR AND SUNG AT MT. PLEASANT ALUMNIE CLUB SETTLEMENT SCHOOL MEETINGS THE SCHOOL OF MY HEART Air: Tipperary CLARA C. MCADAM, Iowa A, Mt. Pleasant, Iowa I. It's a long way to the Appalachians, It's a Tong, long way to go, But Pi Phi thought leaps the distance To a mountain school we know. Then Hip! Hip! Hurrah! for all the Pi Phis Who in this School work share. It's a long way to the School we founded But my heart is there. BOOK REVIEWS 463 IL Hurrah! Rah! Rah! .arrow Arrow! Speed ye through the air, Carry forth a blessing To our workers everywhere. Bid them raise their voices, Let music fill the air, Sing Hurrah for our School in the mountains ! For my heart is there. We belong to Iowa Alpha A long, long way out west, But to help along the school work We'll do our level best. Come join the Iowa chorus Ye Pi Phis everywhere, Sing Hurrah, for the School in the mountains! For my heart is there. BOOK REVIEWS Prudence of the Parsonage. By Ethel Hueston, Iowa A. The Bobbs Merrill Co., Indianapolis, Ind. Price, $I.25. Few books for girls in recent years have enjoyed a greater popularity than Prudence of the Parsonage, the charming story of four bright, fun-loving girls and. their sister-mother who early met the responsibilities of bringing up a family. The story is replete with laugh-provoking incidents and the characters have the charm of individuality. The story has been compared to Miss Alcott's Little Women by more than one reviewer.. In one respect the two books are similar for they both have a background of reality and like Miss Alcott, Mrs. Hueston has quite evidently woven into her story anecdotes and circumstances from her own experiences in parsonage life. The following extract from the Literary Notes of the Boston Herald explains some of the circumstances which enriched Mrs. Hueston's experience. Ethel Hueston, author of that very wholesome and popular story, Prudence of the Parsonage, has put into it much of the spirit that surrounded her as a girl when she was left fatherless at the age of 18 one of lo other children. Her father was a Methodist preacher in Iowa, and married her mother when she was 15. The large family born to them received finished educational </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



