<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr3330339_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Helmick, Elizabeth A.</name></author>
                        <author><name>Wallace, Mary O.</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>March 1917</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr3330339_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">March 1917</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Helmick, Elizabeth A.</name></author>
                        <author><name>Wallace, Mary O.</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 338-339</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">36</note>
                        <note type="Folder">5</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 33, Number 3 (March 1917), Pages 338-339.</note>
			<note type="document">arr3330339_0000</note>


	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Founding of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1909-1927</item>
                                <item>People</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr3330339_0001" seq="01" n="338-339  "/>
       <p>338 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI and entertaining. There will be a vestibule entrance into the club-room. The clubroom is 32 by 19, and is built like a sun parlor because of its southern exposure. The fireplace in one end has a terra-cotta panel with the letters II B cl). There are two smaller rooms to be used as cloakrooms which open into the living-room by big arched doorways. The kitchen is on the west and has two entrances. We have not finally decided on the interior decorations, but they will probably be in tans and blues. The brick work is white with sage green roof and trimmings. We are looking forward eagerly to the time when we will be in our new house and able to entertain the visitors and delegates to Convention on their way through Denver. We are sorry not to have a picture of the new bungalow to send, but it is not yet far enough along. As soon as it is completed we will send some pictures to THE ARROW. NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON Our readers will regret to learn that a telegram from Mrs. Helmick was received by the Editor when most of the copy for this issue had gone to the publishers, stating that, on account of illness, she was unable to furnish the usual Settlement School article at this time. The following items of interest in connection with Gatlin-burg and our work there seem to belong appropriately under this heading. Mrs. Edward Layport (Laura Adella Trumbo), California A, 1895, writes from her home in Columbus Grove, Ohio, that she has in her home one of the brightest and most promising young men from our Pi Phi Settlement School at Gatlinburg, Tenn. He had been there since July, 1915, and is now a junior in high school. He made a visit to Tennessee in August. He is nineteen years old "and we think a great deal of him." (Elder Monroe Ogle.) Mrs. M. D. Dissosway (Elda P. L'Hote) Illinois E, '12, writes to the Alumnae Editor. "I would be glad to have my change of address noted in THE ARROW with the statement that I would be so glad to have any Pi THE NEWEST CRUSADE 339 Phis going to or from the Settlement School stop with us. I believe they all have to go through Knoxville to reach it. I am hoping to visit Gatlinburg soon and see the new house. Mrs. Dissosway is located at 1933 West Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, Tenn. Mrs. Helmick would like to hear from all Pi Phis who wish to offer their services to the Settlement School during the coming year. All pledges to the Settlement School for 1917 will be due on March 31, to Mrs. E. A. Helmick, Fort Sam Houston, Texas. Provisions will be made at the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School for camping parties who might care to visit Gatlinburg during the summer and board themselves. It is hoped that this opportunity will be embraced by those especially interested in the work. For particulars, write Mrs. E. A. Helmick, Fort Sam Houston, Texas. THE NEWEST CRUSADE Henrietta Roelofs, Executive, Commission on Household Employment, National Board of Young Women's Christian Association. Life has lost its thrill. There seems to 'be no idea that is new enough to be startling. A young college senior may mount a soap box and harangue the crowd on woman suffrage and the passer-by will hardly raise an eyebrow. To be a militant and smash windows might cause a slight excitement, but who wants to copy England? Alas, there is nothing more original to do in the suffrage movement. It is also respectable today to be a Prohibitionist, and even millionaires are beginning to believe in the eight hour day. It may seem discreet to refrain from mentioning feminism too openly before one's uncles and aunts at vacation time, but' that little flavor of naughtiness which made it so delightful to be termed a feminist seems to be disappearing. What will have been the use of a college education if one has not found a new cause to champion? To graduate, to return home, and be swallowed up by propriety and neutrality, takes away all reason for having embarked on the quest of knowledge. Is there no one left to be shocked and is there nothing to shock with? Is there no </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



