<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr3110025_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Good News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Pomeroy, Sarah G.</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>October 1914</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr3110025_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">October 1914</date>, Good News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Pomeroy, Sarah G.</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 25-29</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">35</note>
                        <note type="Folder">15</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 31, Number 1 (October 1914), Pages 25-29.</note>
			<note type="document">arr3110025_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">The Dedication of our Settlement School Building</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Founding of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1909-1927</item>
                                <item>Facilities</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr3110025_0001" seq="01" n="24-25  "/>
       <p>24 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI Annual Chapters Letters Song Book Calendar Chapter Supplies Loan Fund Fines Installation Chapter Stationery ....^ ".".".".'," $ 3,886.17 Balance on hand August 1, 1913 77.07 $3,963.24 EzPENmEs Annual Chapter Letters Song Book Salaries Traveling Expense Calendar Scholarship Settlement School Grand Council Expense Loan Fund Office Expense Chapter Supplies Catalogue Installation _ Pan-Hellenic Chapter Stationery Overdraft August z' 1914 $ 821.94 ALUMNIE FUND RECEIPTS Club Dues ....' "..."."..".".$ 479. EXPENSES I/2' Salary Grand Vice-president $ Salary Alumnm Editor Office Expense Circulars and rostalm Azuorm Conference Deficit Balance on hand August 1, ,91* rg4-64 788.18 750. 682.76 412. 250. 250. 217.15 200. 181.70 109.15 52.85 a9-so 27.75 23.50 GOOD NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 25 CONVENTION FUND RECEI PTS Active Dues $ 2,345. Balance on hand August 1, 1913 2,784.97 Balance on hand August 1, 1914 $5,129.97 RECAPITULATION Life Membership Fund.. .$ 14,578.10 Warrants and Loans $ 14,000. Convention Fund 5,129.97 Cash in Banks 3,639.02 Emergency Fund 1,273. ARROW Fund 2,395.15 Alumn,'. Fund 133.59 Contingent Fund 821.94 Due from Chapters 258.55 $ 21,114.66 ,$ 21,114.66 Respectfully submitted, ANNE STUART, Grand Treasurer. GOOD NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON THE DEDICATION OF OUR SETTLEMENT SCHOOL BUILDING Late in June our Settlement School Committee sent out attractive invitations to the dedication of our new school building which was to take place at one o'clock, July ninth. Long before the appointed time on that sultry summer day, the guests from a distance began to arrive; they came on foot and on horseback ; a few rode in buggies or mountain wagons but the vast majority patronized the "shoe leather express", walking five, eight, or even ten miles to be present at the great occasion. In the Pi Beta Phi Cottage, Miss Pollard, as usual, was early astir, superintending the last touches necessary to make the building ready. The seats, desks and other school furniture' had already been placed, and the fire-place in the entrance hall was banked with ferns and wild flowers, for every effort was made to decorate our building as a northern school building would be decked on a similar occasion. The five members of the Grand Council who were guests at the cottage were also busily preparing for the guests of the day whom they expected to entertain at luncheon. The first to arrive were Miss Evelyn Bishop (New York A, ex-'I3) and her friend Miss Walker, who had driven up from Sevierville. Then came a surprise. So far as Miss Pollard knew, Miss Bishop was the only </p>
      <pb ref="arr3110025_0002" seq="02" n="26-27  "/>
       <p>26 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI Pi Phi within reach who could attend the exercises so everyone was amazed as well as delighted when Vera Kerr Kessler (Massachusetts A, '00) appeared upon the scene unannounced. Lieut. and Mrs. Kessler whose present home is Key West, Florida, were spending a few days at Wonderland Park, a mountain resort some nine miles from Gatlinburg, and hearing of the dedication the day previous, came over to Gatlinburg with two friends, Miss Oldman and Miss Hazard. Lieutenant Kessler was warmly greeted by the men of Gatlinburg and has the distinction of being the first Pi Phi husband to visit the Settlement School. The next to arrive were Miss Daly, principal of the school at Wear's Valley and her assistant, Miss Webb and they were soon followed by Professor Keller of the University of Tennessee, formerly of Iowa, and his friend, Mr. Rail. As soon as everyone had arrived, the Pi Phis at the cottage served a simple luncheon and then everyone crossed the field to the school building where an immense crowd had already gathered. The day had been almost unbearably hot and by this time the mutterings of an approaching storm were growing more frequent. For this reason, the exercises were opened at once, a little before the appointed time but in a few minutes the deafening crash of the thunder and the constant patter of hail-stones made it necessary to "adjourn the exercises until the storm had abated". The visiting Pi Phis were surprised at the size of the audience which included representatives of every family within a radius of six miles of the "burg" and was made up of people of all ages and conditions from many tiny babes in arms to old men and women. It was undoubtedly the largest gathering the community has ever held, but many expressed themselves as disappointed because it was not larger and afterwards it was learned that many people had to take refuge along the road and were prevented from reaching the school building by the fury of the storm which was one of the most violent of the season. Our Grand President, Dr. Keller, presided and called on the Rev. J. F. Hale to open the exercises with prayer. This was followed by music. From the very first those in charge of the program had desired our mountain friends to have a part and when it became known that Mr. Atchley and Mr. Ellis, associate authors of The Pilot, the new hymn book recently adopted by the Gatlinburg church were to be in the neighborhood conducting a "singing school", GOOD NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 27 the week of the dedication, it was decided to ask them to furnish two musical numbers for the great occasion. The selection which followed the prayer was for men's voices and had been chosen by the singers. The words are given as follows: "Sinner is thy heart at rest? Is thy bosom void of fear? Art thou not by guilt oppressed? Speaks not conscience in thy ear? "Can this world afford thee bliss? Can it chase away thy gloom? Flattering, false and vain it is; Tremble at the worldling's doom! "Think, 0 sinner, on thy end, See the Judgment Day appear! Thither must thy spirit wend, There thy righteous sentence bear. "Wretched, ruined, helpless soul, To a Saviour's blood apply; He alone can make thee whole, Fly to Jesus, sinner, fly !" During the enforced intermission made necessary by the storm, our friends sang several more songs and we were grateful to them for their cooperation in the program. When the formal exercises were resumed, Miss Keller made a brief speech accepting the keys of the building and the response was made by Mr. Drinnin, former county superintendent. Afterwards Miss Keller read congratulatory telegrams from Miss Miller and M,rs. Helmick." Then Professor Keifer of the University of Tennessee followed with a splendid address in which he voiced some plain truths in such a manner that they gave no offense to anyone. Then the Tomato Club Girls sang "When I Was a Student at College" with true Pi Phi spirit and Mrs. Lardner gave the dedicatory address for the fraternity. The full text of this address will be found elsewhere in this number but perhaps a word of ex-planation will be appropriate. The lurking suspicion in regard to Pi Beta Phi's motives which has existed in the community from the first, found utterance even during dedication week when one of the </p>
      <pb ref="arr3110025_0003" seq="03" n="28-29  "/>
       <p>28 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI forerhost men of the community was reported to have inquired "What is there in it for them wimmin" ? Consequently Mrs. Lardner was asked to explain to them as directly and simply as possible why we were working among them and what was the nature of our organization. It was imperative that she clothe her talk in the simplest language and use local illustrations, hence the comparison of the fraternity with the Odd Fellows (the only secret organization which is known in Gatlinburg) and other illustrations which may seem a bit odd to the casual reader. No one who has not been at the Settlement School can fully appreciate the difficulty of Mrs. Lardner's task but the Council felt that she "did herself proud" and the enthusiasm of her local hearers was expressed by many, most typically, perhaps, by the woman who told her "that was the beatenest speech I ever did hear". Following the address, Dr. Keller introduced each Pi Phi individually to the audience. telling where each one came from, where she was born, and where each one joined the fraternity, and, as so many distant states were thus represented, this ceremony was of special interest to the audience. Then our mountain friends sang again and this time both men and women joined in singing a favorite hymn in Gatlinburg, "At Your Post Be Found". The writer wishes that every reader of THE ARROW could have heard for themselves the ringing chorus sung with a will : "At your post be found as the days go by, For the needed strength on his grace rely; At your post be found, when the Lord shall come, And with him you'll share endless joys at home." Then Miss Pollard offered a simple earnest dedicatory prayer and Reverend Hale and Reverend Wright spoke words of appreciation for the county. The eight Pi Phis sang the Pi Beta Phi Anthem and gave as an encore, "When I Was a Student at College" supported by the Tomato Club girls. Then everybody sang "America" and, as the rain had ceased, all adjourned to the front of the building for the flag raising. Two days previous a splendid flag pole had been placed in front of the building and Major and Mrs. Helmick had sent a beautiful new flag to the school as a dedication gift. As Old Glory was flung to the breeze, each and every Pi Phi present felt that nowhere under our flag are there truer hearts than beat in Gatlin GRAND VICE-PRESIDENT'S ADDRESS 29 burg and that no community is more worthy of our interest and assistance than this tiny "burg" among the beautiful mountains of Tennessee which we have made peculiarly our own. SARAH G. POMEROY. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



