<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr3940647_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Living Motion Pictures</title>
                        <author><name>Compton, Helen Harrington</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>June 1923</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr3940647_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">June 1923</date>, Living Motion Pictures</title>
                        <author><name>Compton, Helen Harrington</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 646-648</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">37</note>
                        <note type="Folder">2</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 39, Number 4 (June 1923), Pages 646-648.</note>
			<note type="document">arr3940647_0000</note>


	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Founding of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1909-1927</item>
                                <item>Programs</item>
                                <item>Promotion</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr3940647_0001" seq="01" n="646-647  "/>
       <p>LIVING MOTION PICTURES The Washington Alumna Club decided to invite the public to its nnual Settlement School Meeting. Since we have so often asked he public to support our card parties, sales, etc., we wanted them to ee our school just as it really is. The meeting was held in the chapel of our largest Presbyterian "lurch. Miss Kate Miller, chairman of the Settlement School Committee, utlined in a few words the connection of II B (I) and the school LIVING MOTION PICTURES 647 at Gatlinburg, then said that as she told the story of the school, living moving pictures would show what really had happened. AcT I. Scene .r. Shows the original committee meeting called by Emma Harper Tu'rner on a Sunday afternoon in February, 1910. The meeting is the result of a great urge to do something for others, latent in the hearts of all but active first in the heart and mind of Miss Turner, a former Grand President. To this little group of Washington Pi Phis comes the happy inspiration of our own Appalachian Mountains with mountain boys and girls waiting for someone to bring to them education. After discussion the little group feels that this is too big a thing and that it must be presented to the entire fraternity. Scene 2. Emma Harper Turner presents the plan to Swarthmore Convention (using active college girls as delegates to convention. Ribbons across their breasts show the chapters from which they came.) The Grand President presiding, recognizes Miss Turner who then lays the Washington plan before convention. She is greeted with instant enthusiasm. Michigan A says she'll give a year as teacher. Texas A gives money. Vermont B asks to go as a nurse, etc. Scene 3. Grand Council meets to decide on location of the new school. A large map is put up and finally Gatlinburg, Tenn., the location having the fewest schools for the population in the United States, is chosen. ACT. II. Scene z. The Pi Phis go to Gatlinburg and find: A typical mountain cabin. One room with crude fireplace, old four-poster. Spinning wheel, tow wheel, whiskey jug, old quilt and baskets. Grandmother is smoking. Two girls slovenly dressed are doing nothing. Mountain boy comes in with gun and rabbits. Every-thing disorderly and "down at the heel." Scene 2. The spirit of II B enters and takes in the whole scene, then beckons to those outside. First comes the teacher with books, then the industrial worker who starts the loom and spinning wheel and teaches the people to make baskets like the one by the fireplace. The nurse enters and holds a clinic for the two "puny" children on the bed. Then follow lessons in canning and carpentry. The scene has gradually changed so that the room is neat and attractive girls with clean dresses and combed hair are all busy with their work. </p>
      <pb ref="arr3940647_0002" seq="02" n="648-649  "/>
       <p>64S THE ARROW OF PI BETA FIJI Next comes the 11 B I) agent who buys their rugs, baskets and "kivers". and takes them to 'Washington so that the money may be used to change other mountain cabins. After this the slides of the real school are shown and a splendid display of Gatlinburg handiwork. HELEN HARRING'T'ON COMPTON, Ohio P. CAMP PANHELLENIC Many fraternity women have shared the summer's joys of Camp Penhellenic on picturesque Washington Island, Wis. Gladys Dixon, Wisconsin A, 1244 Stone St., Chicago, is the director of the camp. The following song dedicated to Camp Panhellenic by Olga Achtenhagen, K A, expresses the spirit of its associations: r can feel the cool lake breezes from the harbor blowin' free, can hear the tent flap flappn', and it's there that would be; Where the campin' grounds a-callin', I can hear it callin' me To Wisconsin's island forest, to Michigan's blue sea. Come ye north by road and sail, Follow north the same old trail- You will see the sky blue water dance and toss itself to spray--Oh. the breezes laugh and play, O'er the harbor, lake, and bay, And the dawn comes up a promise o'er the lake at break of clay. r can see the campfire flicker, I can hear the banjo strum, can see the stars a-shining through the pine trees one by one; can hear the sound o'singing, and the chorus comes to me "We've come north to Camp Panhellenic we are one fraternity," Oh, whate'er our emblems be, We are one fraternity We are going to work together just as well as we can play While the breezes laugh and stray, O'er the harbor, lake, and bay, And the sun goes down a glory o'er the hills at close day. CAMP MORTAR BOARD Summer does not seem so far off, and already vacation plans are taking shape. After the long year in the rush of city life the longing comes for the open country and a chance to play a need which is hest answered by camp living. CAMP MORTAR BOARD 649 On the rocky shores of Big Bay de Noc of Lake Michigan is Camp Mortar Board, directed by three Pi Phis: Ruth Siefkin, Kansas B, ex-'18; Martha Gray, Michigan B, '16, and Katharine Harrington, Illinois A, '19. From late June to early September, college girls, active and alumna throughout the country, will gather for the exhilaration and rest of out-of-door living. The long days of warm sunshine are filled with sports for which provision has been made and instruction CAMP MORTAR BOARD provided. The horseback riders canter along the bridle paths, logging trails of long ago; hard clay courts invite the tennis enthusiasts; the hikers go off to tramp shores and to explore the smoke-blackened caves of their predecessor campers, the Noquet Indians, who it is said, left behind them buried treasure when they followed their valiant leader, Black Hawk, southward in search of further conquest in 1678. Twice daily a merry crowd of bathers cuts through the woods to the sheltered southern harbor of Sac Bay, with its shining white sands and clear calm waters ; there's a bathhouse, a fine level beach, gently </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



