<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr3610029_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Our Settlement School</title>
                        <author><name>Langmaid, Abbie B.</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>October 1919</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr3610029_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">October 1919</date>, Our Settlement School</title>
                        <author><name>Langmaid, Abbie B.</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 29-34</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">36</note>
                        <note type="Folder">10</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 36, Number 1 (October 1919), Pages 29-34.</note>
			<note type="document">arr3610029_0000</note>


	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Founding of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1909-1927</item>
                                <item>Facilities</item>
                                <item>War </item>
                                <item>Health care</item>
                                <item>Funding</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr3610029_0001" seq="01" n="28-29  "/>
       <p>28 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI EXPENDITURES Delegates' Expense $6,905.04 Board and Room 1,771.00 Founders' Expense 546.g4 Lecture 267.53 $ 9,637.51 Balance July 31' 1919 '. $1,543-63 AcoMN.,-E FUND RECEIPTS Alpha Province $,18.00 Beta Province 131.50 Gamma Province um.00 Delta Province 55.50 Zeta Province 173.50 Epsilon Province loouo Eta Province 6o.5o Theta Province 22.50 Iota Province +ouo Kappa Province 42.00 $82o.5o EXPENDITURES Alumnx Editor $loo.00 Grand Vice-president / lom.00 Cataloguer Salary (%) 50.00 Alumna Editor 72.00 Grand Vice-president 53.00 Province Vic-president Expenses 17.76 Balance July 31, 1919 $1,350.88 RECAPITULATION RESOURCES Investments $5y,0oo.0o Liberty Bonds 1,500.00 Contingent Fund _-'_ Cash in Savings 1,812.78 Due from Chapters 438.89 $eeraoo/ LIABILITIES ARROW Endowment $52,800.19 Suspense Fund 4,10*.73 Emergency Fund 1,931.09 Badge Fund 1,691.10 Convention Fund 1,543.63 ARROW Fund 1,49+13 OUR SETTLEMENT SCHOOL 29 Fellowship Endowment 1,391.07 Alumnm Fund 1,35038 Loan Fund 456.25 $66,768.o7 Respectfully submitted, ANNE STUART. OUR SETTLEMENT SCHOOL By ABBIE B. LANGMAID, Chairman, Settlement School Committee Six years ago, my acquaintance with Gatlinburg began, when the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School was in its infancy. In June I made my second visit, at Mrs. Richardson's request. Although THE ARROW has faithfully recorded the successive steps in the development of the institution, I was unprepared for the wonderful change which had taken place since the fall of 1913. Only among such a people, "uneducated but highly cultured," and only with the zealous, wise, untiring work of many Pi Phis could results such as these have been accomplished. The people from the beginning were more than ready, they were anxious to have for their children and their community the teaching of the school and the influence of the settlement. This open-armed receptivity means speedy accomplishment. Also it would seem that the greater part of the people are clear, straight-forward thinkers, so, when opportunity offers, their education is accomplished in an exceptionally short period. Witness the fact that several of our most noted divines in this country and abroad were mountaineers from this or neighboring regions who began their "book learning" at a mature age and completed college and theology in ten years' time! Gatlinburg people are worthy of our best efforts in expenditure of time, of money, and of clear thinking and planning to bring about expeditiously far-reaching educational development for both children and grown-ups. The war taught us, as nothing else could have, the blessedness of service, service for all our fellow-men, in place of the self-centered or family-centered existence of pre-war days. To a greater extent than ever before, Pi Phis are ready and glad to take their share of the responsibility for the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School. This, coupled with the fact that locally the time is ripe for great strides </p>
      <pb ref="arr3610029_0002" seq="02" n="30-31  "/>
       <p>30 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI ahead in the work at Gatlinburg, promises well for the future of the institution. Many boys called into the service from the mountain regions found themselves at great disadvantage. Big, splendid fellows physically, for they ranked above the average in this respect, their suffering when they had to reveal their inability to read .or write can only be imagined. These men now are anxious to do all they can for the advancement of schools and community life, and in Gatlinburg our problem now is to make it possible for ALL, including the grown men and women, to get what they so greatly desire. This year provision will be made for older boys to earn their "schooling." Ready money does not exist where living is so severely simple as it is in mountain communities, so if an occupation can be provided we may be able to keep the older boys in Gatlinburg and in the school. A mill equipment for the making of furniture has been purchased and the question of a mill, power, and location is under consideration. This equipment has cost comparatively little, due to the assistance of Mr. Lawson Reagan of Gatlinburg. Four adjoining districts wished this summer to give up their county schools which they recognize are inferior to the Pi Phi school in equipment, length of school year, and quality of teaching, and to send all the children to our school. Owing to lack of accommodation and funds for adequate teaching force for so large and sudden an addition, only one of these petitioning districts could be admitted. Next year provision must be competent to meet local desires. This means a larger building, more teachers, more equipment in every respect, and that, of course, means more money to be raised. However, it is the most worth while opportunity that presents itself to many Pi Phis this of raising or giving money to the Pi Phi Settlement School. Most Pi Phis are unable personally to go into social work. They have been accustomed for the past three or four years to give all their spare time to Red Cross or some other branch of work for others. The war necessity is gone, but here is the chance to give for others of time and thought and money. We all feel that our own education and self-advancement is of little avail if it is not put to use. Pi Phis everywhere are asking "What is needed at Gatlinburg? What are the plans for future work, for enlargement? What can we do ?" So here are the needs in detail. OUR SETTLEMENT SCHOOL 31 More land. One piece facing the present Pi Phi property and across the Little Pigeon, with only the road and river between, is available at $2,500 or $3,000. This contains about seventy acres and has on it some very valuable timber excellent for the making of furniture in our new factory. Another piece of land directly back of the school property and joining it is priced at $4,000. This is about the same acreage as the first, is better for agricultural purposes, and has much timber. Land values elsewhere are increasing by leaps and bounds and, should the railroad reach Gatlinburg, and the indications are that it soon will do so, these two pieces of land would find ready sale to someone else undoubtedly, and the Pi Phi School would be crippled. Not only is land needed for agricultural purposes but also for building sites. Provision must be made for the housing of those pupils who are coming in from outlying districts. Pi Phi will get option on one or both of these tracts, if possible. An electric light plant is advisable. Grown men and women, occupied with households and farms during the day, have only the long evenings in which to attend school. A night school is a necessity, and that can be more successful as can the many evening activities already established, if the entire grounds are lighted. Several of the families wish to cooperate in this, and after power for a factory has been in-stalled, the whole plant for lighting will be a comparatively in-expensive venture. The community must have a visiting nurse. Child welfare has not made the progress that it has in our northern states and sanitation, except in the immediate vicinity of the school, is unknown in all its phases. A county nurse, the solution in many northern communities, would be quite inadequate in Gatlinburg. Transportation is always difficult, sometimes impossible in a country so mountainous. More-over, the field within small radius of the school demands all her services. Two hundred and fifty dollars is definitely available to start the work of a nurse, so as soon as one can be secured, the experiment will be made. Report has come of considerable amounts promised for similar work several years ago. This will be investigated and the money obtained, if these promises still hold good. Also, I understand, we have the beginning of a hospital fund, the Jennie Nicol Memorial Fund, of $200. The county schoolhouse, of two rooms, is available for hospital use, and the doctors of Sevierville and Pigeon Forge are ready to assist in this work. </p>
      <pb ref="arr3610029_0003" seq="03" n="32-33  "/>
       <p>32 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI Money for building is needed. Our school naturally is too small to meet present requirements, since during the war such changes could not be made. Before next year accommodation must be made for the children of the other three districts which have asked for admittance this year. County money from these districts, about forty dollars per month for each school, will help on expenses during the four months of "free school," but will not be available for the remaining four, of course. The school building quite readily can be enlarged and at comparatively small expense, due to its having been constructed wisely with the necessity for expansion in view. Farm stock, cows, swine, poultry, goats, or sheep, also the raising of alfalfa and of fruit, all as aids to a self-supporting institution, will be introduced if found adapted to Sevier County, as soon as our income permits. Owing to rise in price of all commodities, increased salaries, repairs postponed by the war and now imperative, our budget for 1919-1920, as you see, will be larger than heretofore. The furnishing of the boys' cottage, some additional furniture for the girls' cottage, dressers and tables for the residents' cottage, the telephone, the summer expenses, our mill equipment, must all be added to rgular expenses of former years. Our estimate totals approximately $8,000 for the year of twelve months. If gifts can be sent in the form of money without specific designation as to purpose, it will eliminate much correspondence and delay. In this way immediate needs for expenditure may be met promptly by the committee. Also, if amounts can be sent in as soon as collected, it will assist greatly, for our bills must be met each month and not annually. All sums are to be sent direct to Mrs. Richardson, who will remain in charge of the finances of the Settlement School. It is the present policy of the fraternity to accept gifts from Pi Phi friends or others for the Endowment Fund or other special funds. The Endowment Fund we hope to make appreciably larger this year. Miss Bryan will be the member of the committee in charge. Miss Keller will locate teachers for the school and keep on file their applications which will be made on blanks furnished for that purpose. Together with Miss Beggs, she will supervise the school curricula. One thing every Pi Phi, active or alumna, can do. This is to send EVERY magazine subscription, new or renewal, to our own Magazine Agency, addressed to Miss Blanche G. Reisinger, 235 E. Lafayette OUR SETTLEMENT SCHOOL 33 Ave., Baltimore, Md., manager. This last year, Miss Reisinger sent $185 to the school, her commission from subscriptions. And this was from only TWO HUNDRED subscribers! Can you not readily estimate what we might get if all Pi This would patronize their own agency? They could solicit from friends also. If each, one of us would do her part, this one venture alone might easily realize us from ten to twenty thousand dollars annually. Let us make a campaign for this purpose and not send in a single subscription to a magazine except through Miss Reisinger. Above all may none of us be guilty of buying any magazine regularly at the news stands. In closing, my word to all P1 Phis is this: The Pi Beta Phi Settlement School is ours, not yours nor mine but ours. It was form-ally presented to the fraternity as a whole at last Convention, after its pioneer existence had proved its worth, its ability to satisfy the needs of its people in Gatlinburg. These needs are increased now and our obligation increases proportionately. The success of the school and of the settlement work rests as never before on ALL Pi Phis, active or alumnx, rich or poor, old or young, and there is something for each one of us to do toward making it the greatest success possible. It will be as self-supporting as it can be made to be, and doubtless will continue to have the loyal support of the splendid people for whom it was established, but all but a small portion of the maintenance and promotion of the institution must be furnished through the support, financial and otherwise, of all the Pi Phis. It belongs to each of us, I repeat, and so I wish each of you to remember this often and think of the four or five hundred children who should be given their chance next year. Enrollment this year may reach two hundred but there will be many who cannot begin their school work as they wish because they live too far away to walk or ride the distance and they have no place in which to stay near the school. So, please think of our problems often and do not be satisfied except with material results from your thinking. The committee will be glad to receive suggestions frcm you. If your idea is not feasible, it may suggest to someone else a plan that is feasible. I have said the time is ripe. It is just that. With our whole country awake to necessity for reconstruction work; with the strong backing of the community; with Miss Bishop as head resident, efficient and life-trained in social work; with so many grown or half-grown boys idle and longing for occupation and training; with whole </p>
      <pb ref="arr3610029_0004" seq="04" n="34-35  "/>
       <p>OF PI BETA PHI asking for admittance which the war pis year to deny, we cannot wait. Our things big in entirety, but small if 'ort of every Pi Phi taking hold and lay think and work and get results for Beta Phi Settlement School. 35 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



