<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr3640455_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>A Brief History of the Settlement School</title>
                        <author><name>Helmick, Mrs. </name></author>
                        <author><name>Richardson, Mrs.</name></author>
                        <author><name>Langmaid, Miss</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>June 1920</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr3640455_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">June 1920</date>, A Brief History of the Settlement School</title>
                        <author><name>Helmick, Mrs. </name></author>
                        <author><name>Richardson, Mrs.</name></author>
                        <author><name>Langmaid, Miss</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 455-465</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">36</note>
                        <note type="Folder">11</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 36, Number 4 (June 1920), Pages 455-465.</note>
			<note type="document">arr3640455_0000</note>


	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Founding of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1909-1927</item>
                                <item>Planning</item>
                                <item>Facilties</item>
                                <item>Curriculum</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr3640455_0001" seq="01" n="454-455  "/>
       <p>THE ARROW VOLUME XXXVI JUNE, 1920 NUMBER 4 A BRIEF HISTORY OF THE SETTLEMENT SCHOOL [From 1002 until the present time three Pi Phis in succession have been chairman of the Settlement School Board. Mrs. Helmicka Mrs. Richardson and Miss Langmaid have cooperated in the preparation of this historical survey, each a in turn writing of what seems to her the most important pof the phases development of the work under her leadership. Eoxroe. ] The Pi Beta Phi Settlement School found its s inception in the Washington Alumnx Club at a time when several magazines had published graphic descriptions of the primitive life and deplorable ignorance of the sturdy race of American mountaineers living within ~ a day's ride of the national capital. At the Swarthmore Convention, on June 29, Emma Harper Turner, the Washington club's delegate, ate1 and a former Grand President of the Fraternity, appealed to the National Alumnm Association to sanction the proposed establishment of a school for alleviating the distressing conditions in the Appalachian Mountains. The plan included the presentation of the school as a Thank-offering to our Founders at the fiftieth anniversary of the birth of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity. The project was received with enthusiasm, and Anna Pettit-Broomell. Pennsylvania A, was named chairman of the committee to carry the proposition to the National Convention at its morning session sion on June 30. Convention gave the plan hearty endorsement and a committee of ten was named to inaugurate the work. After nearly two o years of correspondence and studY, the site for the school was selected d by process of elimination. At the Department of Education in Washington it was found that the states of North Carolina, Kentucky and Tennessee were the most illiterate in the Appalachian Mountains. The committee investigated conditions in each of these states with the result that Tennessee was found to be the most needy. A personal visit to the State Board of Education showed that Sevier county fewest schools. The county the had </p>
      <pb ref="arr3640455_0002" seq="02" n="456-457  "/>
       <p>456 THE ...4RROTP OF PI BETA PHI Superintendent, at Sevierville, eagerly fell in line with the scheme and conducted May Keller, Grand President of the Fraternity, over the district which seemed to offer the greatest field for work ; thus the decision was made in favor of Gatlinburg. On February 20, 1912, the first session of the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School was opened in the little old school house at the junction of Baskin's creek and Little Pigeon river, with Miss Martha Hill, A GLIMPSE OF LITTLE PIGEON RIVER of Nashville, Tenn., an experienced mountain worker, in charge and thirteen small children in attendance. Four months later the school closed with an enrollment of thirty-three. In August the second session opened in an abandoned Methodist Church, with Miss Hill, cooperating with a native teacher employed by the county school board, and seventy pupils in attendance. On December 1, the County's funds being exhausted, Pi Beta Phi sent Dell Gillette, Illinois Z, '08, (now Mrs. T. R. Morgan), the first volunteer Pi Beta Phi teacher, who with Miss Hill taught in the new county school building on the hill overlooking the village. This was HISTORY OF THE SETTLEMENT SCHOOL 457 the beginning of the infusion of Pi Beta Phi's own personal influence into the lives of these people, and resulted in bringing one hundred and thirteen pupils under, our teaching. At this time the first American flag unfurled in the 'community was sent to the school by the young son of Carrie Flagler-Schantz, Iowa 0, '85, and the first Christmas tree was placed in our school room. Sewing, cooking, industrial work, 'sanitation, a small dispensary, and house-to-house visits kept our two workers busy early and late. One incident in Dell Gillette's experience shows the disposition of the people and their cooperation. The school gave an entertainment to which parents and friends flocked and the house was crowded. It had recently rained and the mud from the country road was freely tracked in much to "Miss Dell's" disgust. At the end of the entertaimnent, without having mentioned the matter to anyone, she announced to the gathering that, "There will be no further school in this building until the men of the village have built a, board-walk from the road to the school door!" The audience was astonished at such an unheard-of demand from a woman, but not a word was said to her. However, soon afterwards there was a fine new board-walk, two planks wide, along the highway and up to the school. This walk was soon followed by others along the most used roads. Gatlinburg. at present is the only mountain. village I have seen with plank side-walks along the roads. BUILDING USED FOR THE KINDERGARTEN, 1913-14 In July, 1913, our people were told that if they would give of the land which they possessed, we would build them a comfortable school house, and give them of the education which we possessed. Eagerly, </p>
      <pb ref="arr3640455_0003" seq="03" n="458-459  "/>
       <p>458 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI and at the most unusual gathering the village had ever witnessed, they gave us the deed to thirty-five acres in the heart of the "Burg" and the choicest building site in the district. In August, the third session began in fraternity owned buildings and with a staff of Pi Phi teachers. Ground for the new six-room school building was broken in the autumn and on July 9, 1914, the building was dedicated in the presence of the entire Grand Council and several hundred people. 1i:L1ring the 1913-14 session the first canning club of the county was organized with Mary O. Pollard, Vermont A, '96, in charge of the county work. A large supply of seeds, bulbs, cuttings, plants, etc., were sent from the Agricultural Department at Washington, and distributed among the people, introducing new and unheard-of plants to them. The state hookworm specialist was brought to the school and a house-to-house canvass made to battle against, and to exterminate this enemy of the mountain people, with the most gratifying results. The fourth session opened August 10, 1914, with four Pi Phi teachers and one hundred and thirty-four pupils eager for the year's work. Baseball, football, basketball, tennis, a debating club and other school activities aroused a new spirit in the children and their people took pride in their work. THE NEW SCHOOL BUILDING The special effort during 1915 was to make the industrial work common to the mountains among the older people more popular and profitable to the younger generation. The weaving department was equipped : spinning bees and quilting parties .were given with the hope of reviving those almost lost industries. The services of an experienced manual training teacher were engaged and a splendid work shop was equipped with the best tools on the market. As a result HISTORY OF THE SETTLEMENT SCHOOL 459 many useful articles were made for the home. We now had five Pi Phi workers which made it necessary to add another story to the original three-room cottage which had served as teachers' residence up to this time. One hundred and thirty pupils were now enrolled. During the autumn of 1916, a ten-room teachers' residence, planned by Aida and Elmina Wilson, Iowa r, was built and occupied at Christmas time. This house has furnace heat, running water, bath and is a modern and model home in the mountains. All materials, except the lumber, were freighted over the rough roads from the "outside." The carpenters' work was done entirely by mountain men under the guidance of an experienced builder, imported for the occasion. From far up the mountains, curious men came to watch the progress upon this house. The building of the basement was especially attractive to the "I knowd it" spectators for our building was entirely different from theirs. One cold, frosty morning, about sunrise, one of the oldest inhabitants and his wife awoke the Pi Phi worker from her sleep. Upon going to the door, she found that they had come to unburden their fears. With genuine anxiety and solicitude, the good, old man began, "Martha and me cain't stand it no longer; we said we would come to you and tell you that it don't stand to no reason that that ere watery stuff they is putting in them walls will hold up any house.". . . He had been watching the pouring of concrete into the forms for the basement walls. After explaining to them how it be-came as hard as clay did in their chimneys, he was taken to the finished wall and told to rip off the lower boards, and beheld the hardened walls. Astonished and surprised, he exclaimed, "I'll be darned," and rushed off to tell the community that it was all right. About this time the county ,built a pike road to a point six Miles below Gatlinburg, and public spirited men succeeded getting bridges built across the Little Pigeon river and a fairly good dirt road over the balance of the way, making it possible now, at some seasons, to leave the railroad at Sevierville and reach the school in a couple of hours' ride by motor. Gatlinburg was made the distributing point of seven rural delivery routes and our .citizens' names began to appear in the county papers. We built a grand stand on our athletic grounds and had a fine, uniformed school athletic team. When our country entered the war, Elizabeth Clark-Helmick, Michigan A, who had been the very efficient chairman of the Settlement School Committee for five years was forced by home duties to </p>
      <pb ref="arr3640455_0004" seq="04" n="460-461  "/>
       <p>460 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI give up the position. Her resignation was accepted by Grand Council in October, 1917, and the new chairman, Waneta Bunting-Richardson, Nebraska B, began her duties about December first. The school had been progressing nicely that year under the super-vision of Marjorie Jackson, Wisconsin A, '14, assisted by Mr. and Mrs. Prickett, experienced mountain workers, Ruth Meacham, Illinois A, '14, and Emily Burton, a trained kindergartner who is not a member of the fraternity but a graduate of the Emma Willard School, Troy, N. Y., and formerly connected with Hindman Institute, Hindman, Ky. During this year, Marshall Ogle, a native of Gatlin-burg, was given charge of the cultivation of the cleared land and was generally handy man about the cottage and school, tending to the furnaces, livestock and garden for the teachers.. He and his family lived in the Stuart Cottage and his wife, Mary, helped with the work in the Residence. The Stuart Cottage, an attractive bungalow built by Mrs. Helmick for her occupancy during the months while she personally supervised the building of the Residence,. was subsequently purchased and given to the Settlement School by Misses Melinda and Anne Stuart, Nebraska B, and makes the fourthof the group of buildings now located on the school property. QN THE WAY TO SCHOOL HISTORY OF THE SETTLEMENT SCHOOL 461 Special attention was directed towards the awakening of more general interest on the part of the parents in what was being done for the children in the school. For this purpose a lyceum course was held in the schoolhouse every two weeks. These entertainments were well attended by the people who, although undemonstrative to a degree, almost approached enthusiasm. By this time the war was felt to the extent that all were restless and anxious to be doing something personal in a definite way. Because of the isolation, it was impossible for a time to get materials and directions for the bandage and knitting work. Finally a Red Cross Chapter was organized in Sevierville, fifteen miles away, and immediately Gatlinburg followed and in a short time all women and children were at work, all other interest s being sacrificed. When, at the close of the year, Miss Jackson found she could not return in the fall we were most fortunate in securing for Head Resident Miss Evelyn Bishop, ,New York A, and school opened in August, 1918, with the following corps of workers: Miss Bishop, Mn and Mrs. Prickett and Miss Burton. Several abnormal donditions interfered with the school work during the fall months. A number of the older girls had left for munition work and all the boys of registration age were in the army camps. Added to this "flu" made its appearance and, while not so prevalent as in neighboring communities, continued so long that school had to close after Christmas for nearly two weeks. To add to our trouble, Mrs. Prickett's health made it necessary for her to discontinue her work in the schoolroom, and, February first, Mr. Prickett unexpectedly tendered his resignation. Through all this upheaval Miss Bishop was equal to the Occasion and by reason of her familiarity with local conditions (as she had been in close touch with the school since its early days) and her wide acquaintance, she was able to fill all vacancies immediately and the work went on. The epidemic proved the urgent need of a resident nurse for this community so far away from outside help and we have since been formulating plans whereby this may be accomplished. Twenty-two boys from the community went into the national service, two of them laid down their lives for, their country, and the flag which had been familiar to Gatlinburg only since it was first unfurled there in 1912 had a new and personal significance for the people. As the year progressed it became increasingly evident to the Pi Beta Phi workers that a new spirit of progress imbued the neighborhood and </p>
      <pb ref="arr3640455_0005" seq="05" n="462-463  "/>
       <p>462 THE ARROW0? PI BETA PHI the Settlement School would now have to work to supply new needs as demanded by the awakening intelligence of these primitive but purely American people. Two OF OUR BOYS IN UNIFORM . Having steered the work successfully through the war period, Mrs. Richardson felt ,she could no longer assume the bevy responsibility and upon her resignation in: August, 1919, Miss Abbie Langmaid, Minnesota A, became chairman of the committee. The same month school opened with Miss Bishop, Miss Burton and. Miss Runyan continuing their duties, Miss Ruth Sturley, Washington A, in charge of upper grades and first year high school, and Mr. Creswell for manual training and boys' leader. During the year the quality. of the work in all departments has been excellent, with a spirit of harmony and cooperation among teachers and community that has brought satisfactory results. A debating society has met frequently with enthusiastic discussions on questions of local interest. The "dramatics," tableaux, etc., given at Thanksgiving, Christmas, and close of the year, have been valuable, and very satisfactory to the community. HISTORY OF THE SETTLEMENT SCHOOL 463 The total enrollment has been 119 pupils, including four in high school. This is very good considering the effects of the war, and the general unrest . of the tithes which is felt even in Gatlinburg. Attendance has greatly improved this year in spite of much rain and consequent excessively bad roads and swollen creeks (and creek beds often form the roadways for the school children) , measles, the "flu" in light form, and finally small pox, all of which caused the loss of only two days of "books" throughout the school year. The Stuart Cottage has been simply finished. upstairs to accommodate several boys who came to the Pi Phi School after the county school near their homes had closed. Mrs. Proffit, a motherly mountain woman, has MRS. PROFFIT AND "AUNT LIZZIE'' REAGAN, Two MOST IMPORTANT MEMBERS OF OUR STAFF kept house, here, for Mr. Creswell and these boys. "Aunt Lizzie" Reagan, another mountain woman whom all Pi Phis regard with great respect and affection, has chaperoned and mothered the resits dents in the "big cottage." Miss Runyan and her girls who stay at </p>
      <pb ref="arr3640455_0006" seq="06" n="464-465  "/>
       <p>464 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI A SPINNER IN THE SUN (No visit to Gatlinburg is complete without a call on "Aunt Lydia Whaley," pioneer basket-maker, and staunch friend of our school. Her ability as a spinner of wool is only equalled by her inimitable spinning of tales from pioneer days.) ROLL OF WORKERS IN SETTLEMENT SCHOOL 465 the school from Monday till Friday have occupied the "old Cottage." Aunt Lizzie, Miss Bishop, and Mr. Creswell will remain in Gatlin-burg for the most part throughout the vacation months. Harrison Proffit will continue his care of garden and clops, which though not comprising many acres, have been scientifically seeded by one of the schoolboys under Miss Bishop's direction. Fences have been built this last year, some work done on the grounds and driveways, an orchard planned and a very complete garden. The latter furnishes the main food of the residents and thus keeps living expenses, under efficient management, exceedingly low. A local advisory board has been appointed consisting of Mr. Andy Huff, Mr. Charlie Ogle, Mr. Steve Whaley, all of Gatlinburg, and Dr. Massey and Mr. E. E. Connor, of Sevierville. The appointment of this board whose function is merely advisory on questions .requiring knowledge of local conditions has increased the interest and cooperation in the community. Schoolboys have been enlisted to work at the school this summer under supervision, painting the school house, etc., some to pay their tuition and some giving their time. Attempts have been made repeatedly this last year to secure a nurse, Pi Phi preferably but at least a Red Cross county nurse. In the fall and winter none was available but we feel now that 1920 will see a nurse installed. Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, assured of the continued and in-creasing support of its loyal endorsers, seems to be emerging from the handicaps of the war with promise, greater than ever, of wide and lasting usefulness to the people of Gatlinburg and surrounding districts </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



