<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr4510025_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Settlement School Reports</title>
                        <author><name>Freeman, Gertrude B.</name></author>
                        <author><name>Bishop, Evelyn</name></author>
                        <author><name>Curryer, Ethel</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>September 1928</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr4510025_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">September 1928</date>, Settlement School Reports</title>
                        <author><name>Freeman, Gertrude B.</name></author>
                        <author><name>Bishop, Evelyn</name></author>
                        <author><name>Curryer, Ethel</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 24-50</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">37</note>
                        <note type="Folder">13</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 45, Number 1 (September 1928), Pages 24-50.</note>
			<note type="document">arr4510025_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Report of Chairman of Settlement School Committee; Report of Director of Settlement School, 1927-1928; Report of Treasurer of Settlement School</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Land</item>
                                <item>Funding</item>
                                <item>Health care</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr4510025_0001" seq="01" n="24-25  "/>
       <p>THE ARROW OF' Pi BETA PHI Report of Chairman of Settlement School Committee The Settlement School continues to maintain its healthy and vigorgrowth that growth which is the sign of vitality and usefulness. member of 11 B should ever feel that we can rest content on the s of our accomplishment. The demonstrated fact that we can carry an altruistic work of such scope, whose worth is recognized and ised by those in touch with similar enterprises, should but spur us toward the larger fields of usefulness constantly opening before our rper vision and keener insight. Miss Bishop's report gives a clear, 1plete picture of the School in all its phases this past year. It rits and will well repay a careful reading hy every member of the ternity. The title of Head Resident has been changed to Director as being re indicative of the position and the authority inherent in To position Miss Bishop brings experience, ability, tact, and insight the highest order and to her we owe the smooth working of a many eted undertaking. The question of whether we are pauperizing the people and doing them what they should do for themselves, which frequently occurs thoughtful members, is rather fully answered by the following facts : competent authority says we do less of it than any other school which he knows and have the most justification for existence. Last .r the contributions from state and county toward the support of :linburg and Sugarlands schools totaled more than $5, OO. The foster-of home industries such as weaving and basket-making is giving the ^ple a means of support, the School acting as agent and providing narket through the clubs and chapters. More than one hundred allies are self-supporting by means of this work. Tuition and nurse's s are always charged where they can be paid. Dormitory pupils rk out their board on the farm or in the house. The people of the ununity are buying the chairs and a piano for the new auditorium. a boys and girls always work to raise the money for such things as ketball uniforms, etc. Under the supervision of the Agriculture cher various farm projects were worked out with the boys and men different communities which netted the workers a total profit of !e than $1,200 for the year. A marked advance was made this sum-r by having the women in the community Domestic Science class e charge of the class in turn. Bit by bit initiative and self-depen-Lce are brought to the surface and the ability inculcated to earn a ter living from the materials at hand, but everyone who thinks we step out abruptly and leave the people to carry on entirely alone .s to grasp the scope and ramifications of our work. What the future REPORT OF CHAIRMAN Or SETTLEMENT SCHOOL 25 will bring forth we do not yet know, and we are watching with intense interest to see what influence the opening of the Great Smoky Mountains National Park with its influx of visitors will have. It cannot fail to influence the entire community and mountain population over a vast area, and the trend of our plans for the future must wait upon its event. In the School proper the biggest step forward was in having a man principal, a thing long desired by the people but which until recently we had not felt justified in affording. The wisdom of the step is exemplified in the increased attendance in the high school classes, and the securing of state certificates for our teachers, which assures us of accredited rating and proper financial return from the county. The total enrollment last year was 159 with five academic teachers and three special teachers. The Sugarlands school has had a successful year with more than eighty pupils and two teachers in its new schoolhouse built by the county. The Agriculture and Domestic Science teachers give instruction there once a week in community classes as they do in other sections remote from Gatlinlburg. The teachers' cottage, built from the Hazel Todd Meaden fund, has been a comfortable and attractive home and a much needed center for community activities. The land on which it stands now belongs to the fraternity by deed of the Sugarlands people, as we have fulfilled our part of the contract by maintaining a public school there for four years. The new industrial building has occupied much of the time and thought of the committee and School staff. The building itself is finished and paid for, but it is not equipped with heating, plumbing, desks, etc. These we hope to be able to install this coming year through the continued generosity of our members and friends. The cost has been kept around $1S, 00 or $1,500 below the rough estimate. This saving has been due to the careful planning of Mr. John Turner, the contractor, and Mr. Mattil, our Agriculture teacher, and to the generous reduction in his legitimate commission made by Mr. Turner. To Ooth of them we owe a debt of gratitude for the most kindly and helpful interest. To Mr. James White, architect for the University of Illinois, are also due our heartfelt thanks for the time and effort he spent without charge to us in drawing plans suited to our means and location. And to Mrs. Stark, whose generosity and persistent effort during her term as chair-man of the committee made the building first a practical possibility instead of a hopea for dream, go our deepest thanks and praise. The committee has been a smoothly functioning body and to its members I extend my thanks for their capable help and the pleasure it has been to work with them. We have missed the efficient leadership of Mrs. Stark and the enthusiasm of Mrs. Turner, but rejoice in the good work they are doing for the fraternity along other lines. The committee suf</p>
      <pb ref="arr4510025_0002" seq="02" n="26-27  "/>
       <p>26 THE ARROW 0V PI BETA PHI fered the loss of another experienced and faithful member through the enforced resignation of Mrs. Genre because of her husband's death. Dr. Edith Gordon took up her work with the isolated alumn and reports that fifty-four have paid dues and received the Gatlinburg News this year. Mrs. Blanche Curtis has edited the "News from Little Pigeon" for THE ARROW and has acted as secretary. By June 15, she reported eighty-seven letters of thanks written to clubs and chapters sending contributions to the School. Marguerite Ellis reports a fairly smooth working schedule by provinces for the slides and films, and hopes it will 'be even better the second year. She is giving them a thorough revision in an effort to bring them up to date and to make them more clearly understandable and interesting. To Ethel Curryer I think we all make obeisance for doing well a job involving figures at which most of us shudder and turn away. To the Grand Council and all officers with whom contact has been so pleasant and so profitable, go my sincere thanks for their help and cooperation. Among the greatest pleasures in working for the School are the generous response and interest manifested by everyone who comes in contact with it, whether in the fraternity or not. A gift of $50 from Mr. Collier, our insurance agent, after a brief visit of inspection for the purpose of accurately allocating insurance on the different buildings, is another outstanding example of friendly interest from one not in the fraternity. And to those within its far-reaching borders whose generosity and work have made the whole School possible, what more thanks can any of us want than that inner gratification which comes from the contemplation of an ideal vision made manifest in an actuality? GERTRUDE B. FREEMAN. REPORT Or DIRECTOR or SETTLEMENT SCHOOL 27 Report of Director of Settlement School 1927-1928 In looking over the report of last spring one wonders if it can be possible that only one year has passed since it was written. Changes are coming so rapidly it is hard to keep abreast with them. Added to these changes on the outside has been a heavy building program for the School, making us feel we lived two or three years in one. Read the reports of five years ago In regard to roads and means of transportation in and out of here then think that today a fifty-foot highway is being constructed from Knoxville, through Sevierville, Gatliniburg, Elkmont and connecting with Maryville. You can now come from Knoxville to Gatlinburg comfortably in an hour and a half over a hard-surface road. The changes in roads are significant of changes in almost everything. Gatlinburg in all probability will be the gateway to the Great Smoky Mountains National Park. There is little likelihood that it will be in the Park, however. Tourists already are coming here in large numbers, hotels are open winter and summer. Fortunately, the great majority of people stopping here are of a very fine type, with an appreciation of the mountains, and in many cases, of the mountain people. Time after time I am asked by visiting Pi Phis or by interested people who are writing us, "How much longer are we needed in "Gatlinburg?" Our help in maintaining a day school may not be as necessary as it was a few years ago but in other ways the responsibility of the School to the people is greater now than ever. To many .1 have said that the School right now is the only stabilizing force in this rapidly developing district. A moment of thought and one sees that the School must continue until the church or some other strong moral force can cope with the situation. A country church, with a preacher coming forty miles once a month, pogstbly not that often, is not likely to be as progressive as it should be. Personally I look forward to having the county take over the grades within the next few years. There will still be plenty for us to do. Our health, industrial, home economics and agriculture, as well as community and extension work would make a full program. A second question is often asked, "Does the county help financially This year the county has paid us for maintaining the day school, $2,860.00. The state has paid for agriculture, $1,500.00 and for Domes-tic Science community work about $600.00 The teachers in the Sugar-lands School are entirely paid by the county. In every way Tennessee is making rapid progress in education and doing as much as we ever could ask any state. While there is a great deal yet to be done we could scarcely ask that any state do more in eight or ten years than Tennessee has. </p>
      <pb ref="arr4510025_0003" seq="03" n="28-29  "/>
       <p>28 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI The Staff has been: Evelyn Bishop Head Resident W. B. Overton Junior High 'School Teacher Catherine Kibler Junior High School Teacher Alice Kiewit 5th and 6th Grades-Music Mrs. Chapin ;r'd and 4th Grades Emily Burton Primer, 1st and 2nd Grades O. J. Matill Smith-Hughes Agriculture Katherine Watson Smith-Hughes Home Economies' Winogene Roddhig Weaving LaDene Allen Arrow Craft Elizabeth Cooke Bookkeeper Ruby Ryman, Florence Howard Nurses Lillie Reagan Assistant to Nurse Mrs. E. A. Bishop Supervisor Girls' Dorm. Man. Boarding Dept. Mrs. Anna Dowell Supervisor Boys' Dorm. Eva Hathaway Sugarlands School Cora McCarter iSugarlands School Otha Reagan Supervisor Student Labor, Farmer Leander McCarter General Labor Minnie( Ogle Cook Mrs. elinda Seaton Cook SCHOOL It is with real satisfaction I commence the school report by saying that the school work proper has received its full share of time, money and attention. It has not been slighted for any new department and the increased allowance and labor have borne very evident results, Tn years gone by our county did not need to ask for teaching certificates from us as we were not reimbursed on the basis of their qualifications and the county recognized that all of our teachers had l~acl educational advantages beyond most of the other teachers in the county. This has now changed and each teacher must have a state certificate and we must have all credentials, reports, etc., on file before any county reimbursement can be obtained or state certificates granted. To some this has looked small, knowing there were many teachers in the county still using the certificates granted before these strict requirements, but to those who really look further there is a recognition of a great effort on the part of the state department and we should do all possible to cooperate, even in the smallest detail. Mr. W. B. Overton, University of Tennessee, was elected principal of the school and teacher of mathematics in the four upper grades. He came not only with his B.S. and M.S.Ed. degrees, but with exper REPORT Or DIRECTOR Or SETTLEMENT` SCHOOL 29 fence in teaching and preference for rural school work. Not only has the school gone smoothly, classes doing a very creditable grade of work but attendance has improved this year. It was not easy to obtain teaching certificates but before the year was over all except one had ;been received and the county had paid us $2,800.00 Remember that ten years ago that check would have been $300.00. Another accomplishment-our pupils completing the second year of high school received state certificates admitting them to any state high school without examination. This means a good deal to our pupils, for several go on to other schools each year. This past year we have had one in Murphy Collegiate and two in the Sevier County High School, Sevierville, two in Maryville College, one in the University of Tennessee, and two in Lincoln Memorial University. To have work recognized it was necessary to teach general science, and have some laboratory work. These classes were held in the -old school house where the agriculture was until that building was entirely taken over by the Arrow Craft, then the science classes met in the domestic science room on the afternoons when there were not community classes. Some more laboratory equipment and a certain number of reference books had to be obtained and quite a little school equipment had to be replenished. The additional expense of salary for school principal was necessary. But to offset these expenditures there was $700' more from the county than last year, the work was accredited and we had an increase of twenty-five or more in the upper grades of the school. The grade work was divided as in other years: Katherine Kibler taught English in the seventh, eighth, ninth and tenth grades and some other grade subject. Alice Kiewit had the fifth and sixth grades, teaching music when she could find a few extra minutes for it. Mrs. Chapin had her same work again, the third and fourth grades. Emily Burton finished her tenth year with the little folks, teaching primer, first and second grades. Domestic science was given in both first and second year high school classes having one double period each day. Agriculture and Farm Shop work were given in the seventh, eighth, ninth and tenth grades. No weaving was taught in the school as domestic science was required and it was not possible to find a place on the schedule for the weaving. We hope to have it elective in second year high school next year. A few pupils had piano lessons from Alice Kiewit. Another year we hope still more can be done in music. Our enrollment has increased from 131 to 159. The increase has been in the first and second year high school classes. The attendance the past year has been unusually good. </p>
      <pb ref="arr4510025_0004" seq="04" n="30-31  "/>
       <p>30 THE ARROW or PI BETA PHI Last year the chairman of the county school board and Miss Chew talked much of a supervisor for the little schools up the creeks, especially in this district. There did not seem to be any way of obtaining state or county; funds for this so we finally gave it up. This spring word has come that the state will pay $600.00 of the salary of a supervisor. There is no doubt of the value of such work and were Miss Chew able to take it, or someone else equally interested and familiar with conditions, I would recommend at once that we cooperate with the state and county in this. School opened on August 15 so we were able to close the first six grades early in April. They gave very pretty plays and of course the children did well. The four upper grades closed May 3. A play was given May 2 and the exercises the following night consisted of an address by Professor Phillips of the University of Tennessee and the awarding of certificates to seven eighth grade pupils and second year high school certificates to eight pupils. It was a joy to have these closing entertainments in the new auditorium. Can any of you who have been here imagine being able to practice 'for plays and conduct' examinations at the same time? It was done this year. We cannot boast of a great year in athletics. All fall and winter the only place for basketball was the outdoor court and after winter started that was not inviting as we had weather that would have done credit to northern territory. The minute the boys could use the new building they started basketball with a bang and had some good games. Beside the school team there was a community team that played quite a good many games and the girls came in strong at the very last, winning second place in a preparatory school tournament. DOMESTIC SCIENCE This year Jean Steele went the way of Phyllis Higinbotham the year before. The State Department took her. During the year she has been Supervisor of Rural Home Economics. Her place was filled by Katherine Watson, University of Tennessee, whose people have a home here and who is familiar with the country and people. She had carried on practically the same program as Jean Steele did, having high school classes here in the mornings and doing community or "evening school" work in the afternoons and one night each week. During her vacation this summer the evening school classes were continued, different women in the community having charge. Next year Katherine will teach in the school both morning and afternoon and after January 1, Jean Steele will be back for full time evening school work, the state paying all of her salary. . REPORT OF DIRECTOR Or SETTLEMENT SCHOOL 31 One of the big projects this year was a Demonstration Better Home. Katherine Watson took a little cabin in her father's orchard which looked hopeless indeed and with her high school girls, the evening school class and Mr. Mattil's boys, planned and completed a most at-tractive piece of work. It included everything from planning the changes in the rooms to putting clothes closets, shelves, bathroom, making kitchen cabinet (from materials at hand) to weaving curtains, staining and painting inside and out, planting shrubbery and garden and making a really attractive home. For one week the house was open every day and was visited by about 300 people. Different women took turns acting as hostess. Programs were planned for each day, speakers coming from the University of Tennessee, our nurse giving a Home Nursing demonstration with some of her school girls, and women even exchanging flower and garden seeds. The high school girls had home projects on exhibit at the Gatlin-burg Fair, had one Style Show in the school, and the usual number of luncheons and dinners. AGRICULTURE The schedule for Agriculture corresponds to that of Domestic Science classes in the school during the morning, community work of all kinds in the afternoon and very often at night. ClaSses were taught in animal production and in farm shop work. In addition to this each boy had a home project he carried all the year. A II B 1 local school chapter of the Future Farmers of Tennessee was organized. In addition to the usual exhibits by the older peoplef at the Gatlinburg Fair the Agriculture boys always put on some very good educational exhibits relating to fruit growing, poultry raising, gardening, etc. The latter part of the winter Mr. Mattil moved his shop and class work into the new building and although it was pretty cold managed along with the aid of an oil stove. The boys spent part of their shop time in making tool cases, putting up shelves, etc., in their new shop. In addition to the Gatlinburg classes, Junior Poultry Clubs were organized in four communities, work ending with a poultry show in each place, both rilOon and cash prizes being given. There was also one class in Poultry Production in a community some miles from here. During the spring and early summer there was a tomato growers class in Gatlinburg. the men having instruction in planting and caring for their crop that goes to the Sevierville cannery. The calls for Mr. Mattil are many and varied, anything from sick cows and horses to plans for new homes. But in addition to all this, much time had to be given to the new Industrial Building and to the </p>
      <pb ref="arr4510025_0005" seq="05" n="32-33  "/>
       <p>i2 THE ARROW OP PI BETA PHI remodeling of the Arrow Craft Shop. In spite of all these extras this year the State Department of Vocational Education has ranked Mr. ilattil's Smith-Hughes work sixth in the state. The school and community course for boys, girls, men and women in these two departments are very practical and more and more the people are taking advantage of the opportunities offered them through these teachers. GIRLS' DORMITORY It is a joy to bring such good reports of the boys' and girls' dormitories. While we have been too crowded to take care oe all who have wanted to come, those here have made a family any school could be proud of. The girls' dormitory had eight girls in it the entire year. The girls carried out much the same schedule of work as last year, caring for the housework in all cottages, helping with the ironing, dishes, sometimes with the cooking and keeping mighty busy from morning to night. Mother has had charge of the girls' dormitory again this! year and of meals for the entire family. The Pollard Cottage could not take care of all the girls so several roomed in the Stuart Cottage. This cottage also had three teachers in it. Mrs. Dowell has been on the hill with the boys again. She is very faithful and always there to keep good watch over the boys. As the cottage is too far away from the School for the boys to go back and forth often we have used the kitchen and dining room of the Teachers' Cottage for a dressing room and a club room. This isn't ideal 1)ut a great improvement over the laundry, where the boys used to have their dressing room. The boys take care of the chickens, pigs, horses and cows and help in many ways around the place. This year they cleared and seeded about twelve acres of hill land for pasture, fixed' not less than seventy-five cords of firewood, did practically all the grading around the Arrow Craft Shop and the new school building, helped some with the painting and with other work on the new building. Both boys and girls keep daily records of their work, these records being approved twice a month by Otha Reagan and Mr. Mattil for the boys, and mother for the girls. These then are turned into the office and each month they know just how their accounts stand. After school closed several boys and girls stayed to work. There was a great deal to do and the boys and girls were anxious to do it. They wanted all their bills paid before a new school year started. While the boys have been at the outside work the girls have been house-cleaning, canning, picking 'berries and helping in various ways. REPORT Or DIRECTOR Or SETTLEMENT SCHOOL 33 Otha Reagan has continued to look after the school boys out of school hours. He does this under Mr. Mattil's planning and the results this year have been good. The farm is a big expense as we cannot pos silly raise enough feed for as much stock as we have. The farm, how-ever, produces more and more each year. It provides not less than $1,500.00 toward the living, supplying us with eggs, chickens, vegetables, potatoes, some fruit ; in addition to food raised there is always quite a large crop of hay, amounting this year to $650.00 in value. The gardens, furnaces, and an endless number of daily errands are looked after by Leander McCarter who has been with us several years. As some departments of the School grow easier to care for the dormitory one is bound to grow more difficult. All pupils coming in need to work and usually want to. This means that those in chaxge of the girls and boys have a responsibility. This year we have another problem. Practically every pupil will be back in the dormitories. We have not room for more than we had last year. There will be a number of eighth grade and first year high school pupils who cannot en-ter this year because we cannot take care of them. The, Pollard Cottage serves not only as a dormitory for part of the girls but also as central dining hall for all. Two rooms are used for dining rooms. The kitchen is just the same size it was years ago when four people lived in the house. The stove is the same size. The equipment is for a small family. Conditions are such as to make. the work difficult. If a kitchen can be added, the present kitchen being thrown in the dining room, the other little dining room can be used for another bedroom. The one dining room could seat all the family and the kitchen work could be done much easier and, better. In two years mother has been able to save from her house allowance a good sum, in the hopes that it could be used toward these impiovements. The question of discipline in the dormitories is not a hard one our problem is where to put the boys and girls who want to come. WEAVING The weaving department continues to boom. While no school class,s have been held, there has been a class three afternoons of each week for girls and women of the community. We have eight looms available for classwork and they were all busy. The class has been in the old place, under the porch of the Stuart Cottage and will not move into its nice new quarters until vacation time. Beside the looms in the weaving room there are warping jbars and reels that are used by a good many. The letters coming to Miss Redding asking for a chance to weave are many and varied. Each woman has the best reason in the world </p>
      <pb ref="arr4510025_0006" seq="06" n="34-35  "/>
       <p>THE ARROW OE' PI BETA PHI she should weave for the School and it is not easy to divide the k so the largest number of families can be helped and at the same keep on with those who have been weaving for us so many years. Each year it is necessary to acid several new articles for Christmas le and already the looms are busy with the new scarfs, shawls, els, etc., for the winter sales. Weaving is the big industry of Gatlinburg and surrounding counand were we able to handle all that could be produced I expect rly every man, woman and child would purchase a loom and set to k ARROW CRAFT The Arrow Craft report works so closely into the weaving report mrcely know which heading to put the reports under. I must begin the report by saying that at least the Arrow Craft artment has a place of its own to do business in. To you who have I here in past days and seen us trying to carry on in the attic, ement, offices, garage and every possible place, you will thoroughly reciate the force of the statement that at least all business, pro-Ls, sale rooms, etc., are under one roof. Last fall it was necessary to build at once a store room as so much Liture and baskets were being damaged by dampness and dust. The ttion had to go where the shop was to the, so the old schoolhouse moved back from the road one hundred feet and a nice new addibuilt. At the same time a store room was made over both the old new part. The new room was so attractive the girls .at once fixed p for the sales room and have used it all winter. Mr. Mattil could move out of the old part until the building was practically finished as soon as he could move the Arrow Craft Shop took possession of entire building. The location is splendid for the Gift Shop as it is near the main 'way. It may seem strange to you to know that it is necessary to the shop open the year around. Since the grading has been fin-d and the yard seeded it is the most attractive spot on thei whole e. Labelle Allen has been in charge of the Arrow Craft business since first of last September. For the summer Lois Rogers will be here In. It has also been necessary to have a local girl help with the ?ral daily work. One, and some of the time two looms have been 7 in the shop making dress patterns and doing special weaving. The Arrow Craft business should show a profit each year and but the necessity of having the Shop adds a good deal of over Then of the $25,000 sent out more than $5,000 is returned, some REPORT Or DIRECTOR Or SETTLEMENT SCHOOL 35 of it in rather poor condition. The main object of the business is to provide work for the people and the $18,000 invested in weaving means that a large part of the amount goes to families up the creeks where ready cash has heretofore been an unknown thing. The clubs have responded well to all our suggestions made necessary because of the increased business. Accounts have been settled more promptly, the clubs have handled a great quantity of the pro-ducts and we cannot say too much for their cooperation. But for-their interest there would be no possible way we could market such a large production. HEALTH The health department has been woefully handicapped this past year. When Ruby Ryman came back we thought that we were settled again, but illness obliged her to leave and after a month we decided to fill her place, so Miss Howard, of the Minneapolis Health Department came. I wonder many times how we possibly could have survived iall these changes if Lillie Reagan had not have been here, constantly on the job. I really feel the burden of the Health Center has been on her shoulders. Instead of being the assistant, many times she has had to be the whole dependence. The usual clinics have been held, three for tonsils and adenoids, the usual ones for typhoid innoculations, toxin, antitoxin, and smallpox vaccinations. The dentist continues to come one Saturday in each month, the doctors continue their office visits each week. With better roads, telephone connection and taxi service the people are not as dependent on the nurse as they used to be. It is much easier to get a doctor than it used to be. Also we need to keep fewer drugs and other supplies on hand. In the fall two truck loads of our school boys and girls were taken to Sevierville to have their eyes examined by a Knoxville specialist. This was much simpler than taking them to Knoxville. One baby is now in a Nashville hospital receiving treatment for its club foot. Another little girl who has been in the Shriner Hospital in Louisville, Ky., has returned. She was there a year on account of club feet and is now cured. COUNTY HEALTH UNIT We continue to cooperate with the county in maintaining a health unit and the program is much the same each year. The county health doctor who assists in the examination of theschool children, even in our </p>
      <pb ref="arr4510025_0007" seq="07" n="36-37  "/>
       <p>THE ARROW or PI BETA PM let, is very willing to assist in the clinics and the state continues Tnish the vaccines and to reimburse us for some of our expenses ransportation and for supplies. The County Unit had a May Day program on May 11, girls from in Forge as well as Gatlinburg taking part. Me state was anxious to put a Sanitary inspector into the county year but the county court failed to vote the necessary appropria NEW SCHOOL BUILDING ['he ,big achievement this year has been the erection of an indushigh school building, the much talked of building that has been A. for so long to take care of two high school rooms, the domestic ce, agriculture, weaving and also the auditorium-gym. At the an-meeting last year several plans were talked over. Mr. White, of ersity of Illinois, sending down two blue prints. These proved to be laborate so a plan more in keeping with the other buildings and within our financial possibilities was submitted by him. Mr. Turner and Mr. Matti worked on these during the summer and le time the chairman and one other committee member came for fall visit to the School there was something definite to take action While they were here the site was staked off, arrangements coin-1 for Mr. Turner to take the job, and work really begun. The rock was done by local men. [he building stands practically completed as far as exterior is med. Interior is done with the exception of shelves, etc., heating, ng and plumbing. The heating will be a heavy expense as all that this is the time to make plans for a central heating system, ag the two school buildings under the same system at once. The in in the old schoolhouse needs working over and can, without a deal of added expense, be made very satisfactory if connected with Lew boiler. Lights have been put into the auditorium so that we f have basketball, entertainments and movies. Preliminary wiring lone as the building was being constructed. The plumbing will not complicated nor an extremely expensive proposition. The old ing does not have any indoor toilets or wash rooms but the new Inc,. should be provided with bath. Eventually we hope to use the arnace and fuel room of the old school building for toilet rooms. plans have yet .)een made for furnishing the building except for aiding chairs bought by the local people for the auditorium and a started by them for a piano. f funds are too low this summer we can continue using the domes deice room in the old schoolhouse although we would like that REPORT or DIRECTOR Or SETTLEMENT SCHOOL .37 basement room for an indoor playroom for the little folks in wet weather, Two classrooms and the office will have to be furnished if we have classes in that building this coming year. The farm shop and agriculture classrooms have been in use since early spring. Part of shop class time was spent in finishing up the shop room with tool racks, etc. The classroom will need running water as it will be used for general science as well as agriculture. The weaving room can be used as it is but the supply room will need shelves as: soon as they can be put in. To add light, water and heat and do the most necessary furnishing will cost between $10,000 and $12,000. The building as it stands now has cost about $20,000. It could not have been done for this but for the untiring work of Mr. Turner and Mr. Matti. Mr. Turner gave not only much time and thought but in the final settlement gave a cash discount, of practically $1,000. The ibuilding is one to be proud of and should meet our needs for a long time. It cannot be used during the fall and winter unless heat is installed. We very much hope it will be possible to arrange for this during this summer vacation. EMMA HARPER TURNER CENTER-SUGARLANDS The Sugarlands can report a successful year. A good standard of work has been maintained and there has been practically nothing to interrupt a steady term of school. When Miss Chew found it impossible to return we wondered where we could look for someone to take her place. We were most fortunate in having Eva Hathaway, Iowa B, come. She is a splendid teacher and added to that has a real interest and understanding of the people. Her ability to meet any kind of situation means a whole lot in Sugarlands. Cora McCarter came back for her fourth year. She leaves us this year, however, to enter the University of Tennessee. The classes in home economics and agriculture were not held as regularly as last year. Mr. Mattil's time was very much taken up with the new building at Gatlinburg and Katherine Watson had other community classes during the fall, starting Sugarlands work after Christmas. During the summer all of these classes are continuing. No adult classes were held. The people discontinued them before Miss Chew left and it did not seem wise to start them again last year. It seemed better for the two girls to devote their entire time to the regular school work. Each year we have hoped to have an older lady with the two girls, not only to give them a little protection (although they never have seemed to need it) but also to look after much of the housework, The </p>
      <pb ref="arr4510025_0008" seq="08" n="38-39  "/>
       <p>THE ARROW or PI BETA PHI Is have a heavy teaching schedule as well as an interest in Sunday Tool and different kinds of community work. The entire care of the Ise added to that makes too heavy a program. The past year a elve-year-old boy has lived at the cottage and has proved to be a of help. In return the girls have ,given him a good home, so the ungement was entirely satisfactory. Next year Miss Hathaway returns and Emily Burton leaves the tlinburg school and goes to Sugarlands in Cora McCarter's place. other standby goes, too. Mrs. Dowell is to be there. She will care the house and also teach cooking and sewing, under the supervision the Gatlinburg Home Economies teacher. The financial burden of ,Sugarlands has not been heavy this year. th teachers were paid by the county. As the cottage was new, there re not many expenses for it. Another year we will have the salary of extra worker and some new furnishings will be needed. No doubt the school will eventually be in the National Park area, will be at least a year, probably two or three, before we will know at the boundaries of the park will be. If the school is taken by the rk we will be reimbursed for our cottage and land. In the mean-Le there is no reason why we should not continue to go right on with work, ADMINISTRATION AND PUBLICITY With the Arrow Craft Shop in its own ui.1ding and a full-time per-L in charge of it the bookkeeper and I have had more time for other rk of the School. Letters to clubs from the offices have gone out regrly with monthly statements of their accounts. The student labor :ounts have been a great deal of work but as all students want to )w how they stand with their accounts from month to month the keeper makes every effort to have statements ready and they in n try hard to do enough work to balance the account. Several have yed during the summer to finish paying their board and tuition. The Gatlinburg News has gone out each month to the local people I to all fraternity officers, to those on our "Isolated Pi Phi" list and alumme clubs or individuals who have expressed a wish for it. : hundred copies go out, two thirds of these to people: outside this nty. With each copy going out I have enclosed a letter from the Lool in an effort to keep clubs and interested individuals in touch h what is going on down here. On my vacation I was privileged to visit the Philadelphia, New sey, and Washington Clubs. I regret to say that no teachers visited other schools this past year. encourage especially the new members of the staff in observing work REPORT or DIRECTOR Or SETTLEMENT SCHOOL 3? in other mountain schools and hope another year to make a better re-port along this line. Several of the staff attended the Mountain Workers' Conference in Knoxville in the spring. In checking over last year's report it is a satisfaction to note that each important thing listed in the recommendations was done. PREMANENT IMPROVEMENTS AND REPAIRS MADE 1927-1928 Industrial high school building, with auditorium-gym, built. Arrow Craft building moved, addition and storage room built, grading, staining, etc., done. Garage built. Full time person in charge of Arrow Craft Department. Experienced principal in charge of the school. New truck purchased. New electric light poles set and outside wires restrung to new transformer. RECOMMENDATIONS FOR NEXT YEAR Remodeling the Pollard Cottage to provide more kitchen and dining room space. Basement of Stuart Cottage remodeled to provide coal room, more laundry space. New water heater and hot water tank installed in Stuart Cottage. Cottage reroofed. Central Heating plant to take care of the two school buildings, the cottages to be placed on same system when practical. Lighting and plumbing for new building. Cottages have needed paint for the past two years and should be done this fall if labor and money are available. In order to 'make the fifty foot highway through Gatlinburg it has been necessary to give from five to twenty-five feet all along the front of our property. The law suit of two years ago has finally been settled, the court giving a decision in our favor and reestablishing our property lines as they had been. In closing my report I want to thank the Committee and, staff for their continuous help and cooperation. This has been a pleasant year and I believe a profitable one, with the best of spirit between all. The officers and committee have kept the clubs interested in the School and the splendid response to our needs has made possible whatever has been accomplished at the School. EvELYN BISHOP. </p>
      <pb ref="arr4510025_0009" seq="09" n="40-41  "/>
       <p>THE ARROW OV PI BETA PHI Report of Treasurer of Settlement School Pursuant to the instructions of your treasurer, Miss Ethel Curryer, we ve made an audit of the records kept at the school' and also the general )ks kept by Miss Curryer for the period ending May 31, 1928. The re--t which is submitted herewith shows the consolidation of the two sets of ords. We have verified the Investment account and the bank balance and tify as to their correctness. The inventory figures were furnished tO us the School. The Accounts Receivable balances were not verified by cor-pondenee but are correct according tc the record as near as we can .ermine without further checking. We hereby certify that the information contained in this report was :en from the records of the school unless otherwise indicated and that )ject to the comments contained in the foregoing text and all other :es and notations wherever they appear reflects the result of operations for period indicated and the financial conditions as of May 31, 1928, to the ;t of our knowledge and belief. Yours very truly, HAYES AND WHITAKER. By O. Hayes. Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, Active Chapters' Contributions Period ending May 31, 1923 GAMMA $ 25.00 Florida A 25.00 137.75 Florida B 42.00 40.00 Maryland A ........... 60.00 115.00 Virginia A ............. 5.00 25.00 Virginia r ............ 55.78 342.75 DELTA 187.78 25.00 Indiana r 10.00 15.00 Indiana A 5.00 100.00 Kentucky A ........... 25.00 52.00 Michigan A ............ 26.75 75.00 Michigan B ....... . . 135.00 125.00 201.75 392.00 ALPHA ssachusetts A w York A tario A rmont A rmont B BETA io B io A insylvania A msylvania B insylvania r st Virginia A REPORT Or TREASURER Or SETTLEMENT SCHOOL 41 EPSILON Illinois B 25.00 Illinois A 25.00 Illinois E 10.00 Illinois Z 100.00 Minnesota A 20.50 North Dakota A 15.00 Wisconsin A 89.00 Wisconsin B 50.00 334.50 ZETA Iowa A 30.00 Iowa 13 17.00 Iowa 79.00 Missouri A 50.00 Missouri B 50.00 Missouri r 70.00 South Dakota A 32;00 ' 328.00 Colorado A 100.00 Colorado B 75.00 Kansas A 226.20 Kansas B 100.00 Nebraska B 100.00 Wyoming A 128.75 729.95 THETA Arkansas A 50.00 Louisiana A 53.00 Oklahoma A 50.00 Oklahoma B 45.00 Texas A 25.00 Texas B 45.00 268.00 IOTA Idaho A 50.00 Montana A 25.00 Oregon A 15.00 Oregon B 30.00 Washington A 49.00 Washington B 48.00 KAPPA California J 110.87 California A 100.00 210.57 217.00 ETA Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee. Alumnae Club Contributions Period ending May 31, 1928 ALPHA Boston Mass 405.00 Buffalo, N. Y 100.00 Burlington, Vt 30.00 Connecticut 106.75 New York, N. Y 1,900.00 New Jersey 30.00 Northern New York 15.00 Portland, 25.00 Rochester, N. Y 249.91 Syracuse, N. Y 125.00 Toronto, Canada 112.25 3,098.91 </p>
      <pb ref="arr4510025_0010" seq="10" n="42-43  "/>
       <p>THE ARROW OF' PI BETA PHI BETA )14 Ohio ral, Pa innati, Ohio ksburg,' W. Va eland, Ohio ware, Ohio isburg-Lancaster, Pa oning Valley, Ohio . ni Valley, Ohio ;antown, W. Va , delphia, Pa burgh, Pa do, Ohio GAMMA Ita, Ga Lmore, Md nd, Fla ai, Fla ado, Fla L Beach, Fla mond, Va 'etersburg, Fla iington, D. C DELTA Arbor, Mich nington, Ind tanooga, Tenn )it, Mich City, Louisville, Ky Wayne, Ind klin, Ind ,napolis, Ind ,yette, Ind Memphis, Tenn 155.75 265.00 1860.58 82.00 190.00 EPSILON 62.00 2,245.25 Beloit, Wis 20.00 30.00 Carthage, Ill 50.00 175.00 Central, Ill 50.00 44.00 Chicago, Ill 355.16 125.00 Decatur, Ill 220.00 25.00 Duluth, Minn 75.00 18.00 Edgewater, Ill 36.4 875.00 Elgin, Ill 36.00 224.45 Gales;burg, Ill 150.00 250.00 Illinois Zeta Alumni Club 50.00 4,610.70 Milwaukee, Wis 225.00 Minneapolis-St. Paul 394.93 Monmouth, Ill 55.50 Springfield, Ill 88.00 W. Suburban, Ill 151.00 100.00 Wisconsin Alpha Alumnae 257.50 Club 100.00 50.00 100.00 2,057.06 100.00 7.00 170.50 ZETA 75.00 1,600.00 Ames, Iowa 177.81 Burlington, Iowa 40.00 2,460.00 Carrollton, Mo. --es 10.00 Cedar Rapids, Iowa 70.00 Chariton, Iowa 30.00 Columbia, Mo 275.19 Des Moines, Iowa 400.00 55.00 Indianola, Iowa 50.00 20.00 Iowa City, Iowa 40.00 100.00 Kansas City, Mo 450.00 650.00 Mt. Pleasant, Iowa 125.00 50.00 Sioux City, Iowa 40.00 20.00 Springfield, Mo 50.10 70.00 St. Louis, Mo 990,00 689.83 50.00 2,748.10 REPORT or TREASURER Or SETTLEMENT SCHOOL 43 ETA Albuquerque, N. M 50.00 Boulder, Colo 100.00 Casper, Wyo 100.00 Cheyenne, Wyo 45.00 Denver, Colo 100.00 Lawrence, Kans 177.45 Lincoln, Neb 150.00 Manhattan, Kans 100.00 Omaha, Neb 150.00 Poudre Valley 10.00 Pueblo, Colo 50.00 Topeka, Kan 25.00 Utah 25.00 Wichita, Kans 200.00 Wyo. Alpha Alumme Club 94.75 1,377.20 THETA Ardmore, Okla 30.00 Austin, Tex 214.00 Dallas, Tex 100.00 Fayetteville, Ark 10.00 Ft. Smith, .Ark 37.45 Houston, Tex 300.00 Little Rock, Ark 50.00 Muskogee, Okla 30.00 New Orleans, La 100.00 Norman, Okla 28.00 Oklahoma City, Okla 50.00 Ponca City, Okla 55.00 Tulsa, Okla 92.00 Shreveport, La 40.00 1,136.45 IOTA Boise, Idaho 50.00 Corvallis, Ore 10.00 Eugene, Ore 60.00 Portland, Ore 1,000.00 Seattle, Wash 318.38 Spokane, Wash 100.00 Tacoma, Wash 120.00 Yakima, Wash 50.00 1,708.33 KAPPA Berkeley, Calif 575.16 Honolulu 32.00 Low', Beach, Calif, 206.25 Los Angeles, Calif 1,413.25 Pasadena, Calif 153.00 Phoenix, Ariz 65.41 Reno, Nev 75.00 Sacramento, Calif 5.45 San Diego, Calif 71.10 San Francisco, Calif. ... 357.75 2,954.37 Active Chapters Alwnme Clubs Total Alpha 3342.75 $3,098.91 *3,441.66 Beta 392.00 4,610.70 5,002.70 Gamma 187.78 2,460.00 2,647.78 Delta 201.75 1,860.58 2,062.33 Epsilon 334.50 2,057.06 2,391.56 Zeta 328.00 2,748.10 3,076.10 Eta 729.95 1,377.20 2,107.15 Theta 268.00 1,136.45 1,404.45 Iota 217,00 1,708.38 1,925.38 Kappa 210.87 2,954.37 3,165.24 $3,212.60 $24,011.75 $27,224.35 </p>
      <pb ref="arr4510025_0011" seq="11" n="44-45  "/>
       <p>44 THE ARROW 0V PI BETA PHI EXHIBIT "A" ASSETS CURRENT ASSETS: Fletcher American National Bank 6,255.53 Bank of Sevierville 486.09 Petty Cash 50.00 Accounts Receivable 3,827.51 Industrial Inventory 8,362.66 Live Stock Inventory 1,710.00 INVESTMENTS : Real Estate-First Mortgage Loans, 5 I:4 % 1,800.00 Real Estate-Venders Liens, S% 2,400.00 Arsenal Building and Loan Asso. 3,517.72 Fletcher Ave. Saving and Loan Asso. 2,085.70 9,803.42 LIVE STOCK INVENTORY $ 400.00 Horses Cattle 1,000.00 Chickens 160.00 Hogs 150.00 1,710.00 PERSONAL ACCOUNTS: 1,400.57 Evelyn Bishop Anna Dowell 219.32 Pig Club 32.35 1,652.24 TOTAL CURRENT ASSETS: 32,147.45 FIXED ASSETS: 7,900.00 Real Estate Buildings 42,374.18 Water System 633.07 Equipment and Fixtures 2,600.70 Heating Plant 2,917.75 Electric Light Plant 1,872.09 Permanent Improvement 1,996.69 Total 52,394.48 Allowance for Depreciation 12,617.12 39,777.36 REPORT Or TREASURER Or SETTLEMENT SCHOOL Auto School Books TOTAL FIXED ASSETS: PREPAID EXPENSE: Unexpired Insurance TOTAL PREPAID EXPENSE TOTAL ASSETS: LIABILITIES APPROPRIATED RESERVES School Building Fund 16,626.33 School Endowment Fund 19,583.42 Hazel Todd M~aden Fund 1,151.36 Total Unappropriated Development Reserve . TOTAL LIABILITIES AND RESERVE: CONTINGENT LIABILITIES All current bills unpaid EXHIBIT "B" DISTRIBUTION OF NET INCOME School Building Fund School Endowment Fund Hazel Todd Meaden Fund Unappropriated Development Reserve Total ANALYSIS OF DEPRECIATION Buildings Equipment and Fixtures Heating Plant Electrict Light Plant Water System Total 681.10 158.16 404.75 </p>
      <pb ref="arr4510025_0012" seq="12" n="46-47  "/>
       <p>THE ARROW OF' PI BETA PHI omE : 722.41 [nterest 179.40 Board Refund Living Expenses . 375.02 Sevier County School Board 3,390.00 tuition 83.00 [ndustrial 18,759.31 Hospital 603.94 Christmas Fund 2.88( 'School 593.58 TTRIBUTIONS Active Chapters 3,212.60 Alumm, Clubs 24,011.77. [ndividuals 1,912.00 [solated Almnme 7.75 29,144.12 ['AL INCOME: 53,853.66 PENSES 4,568.89 COST OF INBUSTRIAL SALES Inventories- Industrial 5-16-28 Live Stock 5-16-28 122.10 TOTAL 4,690.99 Industrial Salaries 1,285.00 Miscellaneous 22.01 Baskets 2,750.57 Chairs 1,853.20 Weaving 9.,073 01 Weaving Supplies 4,369.33 Expenses 597,91 Farm 2,782.58 Brooms and Books 478.35. Shop 3.90 Refunds 114.40 Arrow Craft Shop 10.00 TOTAL 28,931.25 Inventory- Industrial 5-31-28 8,362.66 Live Stock 5-31-28 1,710.00 10,072.66 COST OF INDUSTRIAL SALES 18,858.59 CALS--CARRTEp FORWARD $15,858.59 $53,853.66 ERHEAD EXPENSE 1,830.00 1tate Health Unit REPORT OP TREASURER Or SETTLEMENT SCHOOL 47 Insurance Interest Living Office Expense Salaries Smith Hughes Traveling Expense Publicity Transportation School Fuel Dormitory S. S. Treasurer Auto Expense Repair and Upkeep Hospital TOTAL-OVERHEAD EXPENSE TOTAL EXPENSES NET GAIN FOR PERIOD EXHIBIT "C" CASH ON HAND MAY 16, 1927 RECEIPTS School Treasurer 14,182.24 Weaving Supplies 912.31 Hospital 603.94 Farm 735.22 Publicity 19.52 Baskets and Weaving 3,987.74 Living 179.40 Christmas Fund 59.60 Railroad Fare Advanced 137.00 Miscellaneous 124.03 Tuition 83.00 School 593.o8 Permanent Imp (Salvage) .. 12.90 Collections on Account 13,595.14 TOTAL RECEIPTS 724.98 87,90 2,637.70 479.62 9,711.25 779.00 1,492.24 459.34 451.90 710.40 694.30 310.50 150.00 644.07 927.65 453.59 26,453.90 45,312.49 8.541.17 216.77 35,225.62 TOTAL RECEIPTS AND BALANCE-CARRIED FORWARD $35,442.39 </p>
      <pb ref="arr4510025_0013" seq="13" n="48-49  "/>
       <p>4$ THE ARROW or PI BETA PHI DISBURSEMENTS Baskets 2,750.57 Chairs 1,853.20 Weaving 9,973.01 Transportation 451.90 Living 2.037.70 Office 436.60 School 710.40 Weaving Supplies 4,360.33 Fuel 694.30 Sugarlands 266.00 Lights 417.50 Administrative 65.96 Furnishings 213.41 Labor 108.88 Gatlin burg Fair Fund 50.00 Sugarlands Cottage 80.32 Domestic Science 27.00 County School 552.00 Legal 38.80 Moving Pictures 21.15 Athletics 51.41 Discounts 19.1 0 Bad Debts 20.91 Depreciation-Auto 215.60 Dep.-Bldgs. and Equip 1,761.42 Industrial Expense 582.91 Dormitory 310.50 S. S. Treasurer 150.00 Auto Expense 644.07 Repair and Upkeep 927.65 Permanent Improvement 2,000.59 Hospital 453.59 Sugarlands 266.00 Farm 2,782.58 Publicity 478.86 Lights 417.50 Administrative Expense 65.96 Brooms and Books 478.35 Shop 3.90 Furnishings 213.41 Railroad Fare Advanced 137.00 General Labor 108.88 Gatlinburg Fair Fund 50.00 Miscellaneous 46.74 REPORT or TREASURER or SETTLEMENT SCHOOL Athletics Sugarlands Cottage Domestic Science Christmas Fund County School Legal Expense Refunds Arrow Craft whop Moving Pictures ToTAL BALANCE ON HAND MAY 31, 1928 SUPPLEMENTAL REPORT Contributions (Received after books closed May 31, 1925) Active Chapters ALPHA PROVINCE Maine A $ 15.00 Ontario A 35.00 GAMN A PROVINCE Columbia A 50.00 DELTA PROVINCE Tennessee A 25.00 Total Alumna!, Clubs ALPHA PROVINCE New jersey $450.50 Springfield, Mass 2.00 BETA PROVINCE Columbus, Ohio 18.00 GAMMA PROVINCE Jacksonville, Fht $ 20.31 mikuni, Fla 50.00 51.41 50.32 27.00 56.72 552.00 35.80 114.40 10.00 21.15 </p>
      <pb ref="arr4510025_0014" seq="14" n="50-51  "/>
       <p>THE ARROW Or PI BETA PHI DELTA PROVINCE zu Arbor, Mich mz5u/m rand Rapids, Mich ...'."...".'.'..'^..'." 27.00 EPSILON PROVINCE 4cago ' $ 70.75 ,rth Shore, 111 ".' 145.66 .oria ' ' 56.00 $272.41 THETA PROVINCE aw Orleans, La ' $zoo/x/ moa City, Okla. .."....'."...." ' 24.00 aloa, ukla...." ' 75.00 $199.00 KAPPA PROVINCE Lendale, Calif. "37.50 DS Angeles, Calif 30o0 cu Diego, Calif. 08o0 $135.50 rovince Active Alumn(T Total Lpha $ 5o.0n $452.5m $5m2.5o eta ' z8.00 18.00 Emma 50.00 '." 70a1 120.31 elta 25.00 190/06' 215.06 psilon ".".".' 2n2.4z 272.41, u*ta zeo V 199o0 appa 135.50 .' " 135.50 REPORT OF CATALOGUER 51 Report of Cataloguer CATALOGUE The 1927 Directory of Pi Beta Phi was completed in December. The issue contains 644 pages, including 17,860 names, catalogued (1) by chapters, (2) by geographic location. On account of cost, the alphabetical division was omitted, although it is hoped that the next edition may include this useful classification. Coinpilation, typing, printing, and proof-reading occupied the summer and fall of 1927, with eight stenographers working six weeks at typing, and three clerks and the Cataloguer proof-reading and checking for two months. Would that it might have been perfect, but this is not humanly possible, for instance, in the two months after the books were finally closed, 2,000 new ad-dresses came in. It contains a practically complete list of membership, however, which may be used as a working basis. This edition of 4,000 books should last until 1930. Once each year the Central Office revises the entire membership of the fraternity, by means of lists received as follows: lists from alumna, club secretaries arrive on' January 1 ; complete lists of active and alumna members arrive from chapter vice presidents on January 10; and lists of active and inactive members arrive from the chapter corresponding secretaries on October 1 and February 1. Tardy lists cannot receive immediate attention, as the regular schedule of each day is a necessity where thousands of changes take place each year. It was a real source of pride to be able to tell National Panhellenic Congress that the active chapters of Pi Beta Phi had sent in complete, accurate lists of alumna., 100 per cent on time. The return cards sent out by active chapters to alumnae actually make possible a report in January for every alumna, either that she has or has not sent the chapter her correct address in the month preceding. The beautifully typed lists submitted by chapters contained name and ad-dress of every alumna, or a question mark for each one not heard from. Chapters spent nearly $400 and much labor on their search for the correct names and addresses of their alumna this year. Surely chapters deserve the minute of time it takes to fill in the reply card which is sent to each alumna. We could know where every member is located, if everyone would simply fill in this card. The Central Office now has a complete roster of members, showing for each one whether she is a member of an alumnae club, a national member only, whether she is an Anuow subscriber, life or annual, and what her permanent and temporary addresses are. Each member may be located either by maiden or married name. Only 600 members can-not be found, most of them older ones, who may not be living. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



