<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr4920187_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Arrow Crafters </title>

                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>November 1932</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr4920187_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">November 1932</date>, Arrow Crafters </title>

                        <extent>Pages 186-187</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">38</note>
                        <note type="Folder">9</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 49, Number 2 (November 1932), Pages 186-187.</note>
			<note type="document">arr4920187_0000</note>


	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>
                                <item>Weaving</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr4920187_0001" seq="01" n="186-187  "/>
       <p>.111111111.1111.111111111100111.11.11111. *I n.,11.11111111111111111.111.11111111.1111.11.111111111101.111.111111113111111111.8. owc AFTE OFFE FOR INEXPENSIVE CHRISTMAS P ESENTS 1. Rose path wool runner for small end tables, black background, pattern in many color combinations. Size, 8 by 14 inches. Price, 85 cents. 2. Linen bag, white ground, pattern in red, blue, green, black, orange, and other colors. Size 8 by 7 inches. Price, 75 cents. 3. Wool scarf, plaid of white and red, white and blue, and red, blue, and white. Size, 45 by 8 inches. Price, $1.35. 4. Hooked hot mat, made of silk knitted material. Many color combinations and designs. Size, 6 inches. Price, 50 cents. 5. Beverage napkins, all linen, white ground with rainbow stripes. Size 4 by 6 inches (not including fringe) . Price, 20 cents each or four for 60 cents, six for 90 cents. 6. Pot holders in blue, green, orange, yellow, red, white, or brown. Size, 6 inches square. Price, 25 cents. 7. Chenille bath mat, white center, rainbow stripes on ends with green, blue, lavender, yellow, peach, or rose predominating. Size, 18 by 26 inches. Price, $1.50. 8. Chair tidies, three piece set, white ground, colored borders in blue, green, black, red, or orange and brown combination. Size, arm tidies, 12 by 7 inches, back tidies, 12 by 13 inches. Price, $1.25 for set. 9. Azalea guest towel, colored linen with borders and hems of three shades in same color. Woven in blue, green, lavender, peach, rose, and yellow. Size 23 by 15 inches. Price, $1.00 each. 10. Hot plate mats, woven of heavy white cotton. Small size 7 by 6 inches, price 25 cents. Large size 7 by 9 inches, price 35 cents. These and many other inexpensive and attractive articles may be obtained from the Arrow Craft Shop. All postage extra. BUY A, Least ONE CHRISTMAS GIFT From ARROW CRAFT Price list sent on request </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



