<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr4320183_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Turner, Agnes Miller</name></author>
                        <author><name>Taylor, Harmo</name></author>
                        <author><name>Rogers, Lois</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>November 1926</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr4320183_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">November 1926</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Turner, Agnes Miller</name></author>
                        <author><name>Taylor, Harmo</name></author>
                        <author><name>Rogers, Lois</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 183-194</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">37</note>
                        <note type="Folder">9</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 43, Number 2 (November 1926), Pages 183-194.</note>
			<note type="document">arr4320183_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">A Visitor's Impression; Arrow Craft Shop; Cookin' n' Sewin'; Mountain Mothers</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Founding of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1909-1927</item>
                                <item>Handicraft</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>
                                <item>Home economics</item>
                                <item>Alcohol</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr4320183_0001" seq="01" n="182-183  "/>
       <p>182 THE ARROW OV, PI B1'rA PHI HISTORICAL RELICS Have you Pi Phi relics of historical value? If so, won't you please send them to Mrs. Sigler, national historian. Relics, old letters, items from old scrap books! Our Grand President has just sent to Mrs. Sigler two interesting Pi Phi antiques. She says, "I was in Monmoyth this spring and the Pi Phis there gave them to me for the fraternity. The piece of sheet music was written by the father of a Pi Phi then I. C. and was published sometime along in the early SO's. The father also published a piece dedicated to the Kappas. The gavel is made from the walnut stairs in the first college building at Monmouth College. The building burned some years ago, but these walnut stairs were torn out and saved. Mrs. McMichael, the wife of the president, had some of the wood made up into gavels and gave this one to Mrs. Kilgore. Upon Mrs. Kilgore's death, Mrs. Hutchinson returned the gavel and Mrs. McMichael has now given it to Pi Phi." Mrs. Sigler has just found an item in an old scrap book be-longing to Ida Cheshire Barker a founder of Iowa B, which gives an account of the Convention of 1878, the only account of this Convention found to this time. We beg of you to give this matter your special attention. See that families of I. Cs. who are gone do not destroy things which are priceless from our viewpoint. Again we beg of you to respond to this appeal and if enough things of interest come in we may have an exhibit at Convention. Send all articles, items, or information concerning such to National Historian, Mrs. F. C. Sigler, 703 W. Ashland. Indianola, Iowa. NEws FROM LITTLE PmEoN 183 stamumiumminiolnIninloammIusumumnlulululostamminsullmlugunsmausnonInammmsuln NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON Edited by AGNEs MILLER TURNER (Mrs. J. R.), 458 Rodney Ave., Portland, Ore. A. VISITOR'S IMPRESSION w HEN driving Uhr the Tenessee mountains this summer, about a half-mile out of Gatlinburg commenced seeing Arrows ,with the words "Arrow Craft Shop" on them. Wanting souvenirs of that perfectly gorgeous part of the country, we decided to follow up the ar rows, and see what we could see We found out presently that the Arrow Craft shop was in connection with the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, and to get to it, one must follow a winding drive up around other buildings of the school till one came to the eunningest cottage of all, and we found it to be the Arrow Craft Shop. The most adorable rustic porch ran all across the front, vinecovend, and with peepholes in the vines, through which a lovely mountain view could be seen. The porch had furniture made by the natives, and painted wine and blue, which we afterwards found to be the Pi Beta Phi colors. Flowers were everywhere and a tiny, portable Victrola was on a blue table right under the Arrow Craft Shop sign. Of course, observing all this took just a few seconds, and in a few more we were ushered into the Shop proper by two girls. We told them we were looking for just some little thing to take home with us, and there began the trouble. We just couldn't decide what to...buy! In the first room were every kind, shape and form of baskets . waste baskets, flower baskets,. fire baskets . . . everywhere, on the mantel over the stone fireplace, on the floor,. on the window-seat, and on the tables. There were chairs, hooked rugs, woven trays with mats to match, and darlingest of all, tiny doll furniture! Everything, we were told, was made by the people around the vicinity. Through the doorway we saw into another room, and there we found the loveliest things imaginable. Laid out on and hung over the most attractive bed, which looked as though it had about 200 years to its credit, were scarfs, towels, pillows, and bags, all handwoven, and of the finest linen nand wool with the loveliest patterns and colors. On a corner cupboard were draped more scarfs of different varieties, and it was topped with an old ship, making a very picturesque corner. Rugs and coverlets were on the floors and chairs, and curtain mater</p>
      <pb ref="arr4320183_0002" seq="02" n="184-185  "/>
       <p>News FROM LITTLE PIGEON 185 ial was hung suggestively at one of the windows. A table laden with the most exquisite linen guest towels, table runners, and balsam-filled boudoir pillows, especially appealed to me. An old spinning wheel and little chest of drawers completed the room. Well! It is needless to say that we had the hardest time imaginable trying to select things from such a display . . . but finally decided on a dozen guest towels to use as 'Christmas presents, and a darling wood-basket. We left, promising ourselves to stop the very next time we went through, and to tell all our friends to do the same. ARROW CRAFT SHOP "Is this the Arrow Craft Shop?" This is the inevitable question as a prospective customer approaches, whether it be by the back door route in a car or by the front porch and on foot. This is closely followed by: "What an attractive porch you have and how cool it is. Where did You get those cunning birds?" The porch is vine shaded and furnished with some of the hand made furniture produced here, painted in silver blue with trimmings of very small wine colored arrow heads. Besides this we have a Victrola, a "passel" of new records, thanks to Mr. Stark, and some precious love birds that Mr. L. S. Hall, of Knoxville, Tenn., gave us. We might as well say right now that without Mr. Hall's interest and help with the Shop we would never have had as successful a summer as we have. Someone said that the only .way to learn anything was by asking questions. It seems as if all tourists have taken this as their motto for we spend a large portion of our time answering various inquiries. In ease the Arrow readers may be interested in the very same things that our visitors are, we will invite you to go through the Shop with us. "Why, we really just love it here you see we are kept rather busy and we just never think about or have time to be lonesome." After a careful inspection of the 'porch and the view from it we are ready to enter the living room of Stuart Cottage, which has been converted into a basket market. "No, the fireplace isn't for sale----we just couldn't do without it. These are Aunt Lydia baskets. Here is a picture of her. No, she is not my real aunt. As you can tell, she is very old, somewhere around eighty-five or ninety. She is quite a remarkable character. To while her quote the Bible is a revelation. Don't dare go to see her while dressed in knickers as she considers them and bobbed hair 'an abomination of the Lord. Her home. is up a hollow from the old Elkmont road and is a one room house with one wee window about eight inches by twelve inches. If you have time you should go up to see her as she </p>
      <pb ref="arr4320183_0003" seq="03" n="186-187  "/>
       <p>186 THE ARROW Or PI BETA PHI is one of the last of the sturdy old type of mountain woman that you read about. "Let me get it down for you, it is an Oriole basket named that because of its similarity to an oriole's nest. It can be used for flowers, darning. eggs or just anything. Here is another interesting basket called the Hornet's Nest, named also because of its shape. It is made out of pine bark by a man called Broom Tying Richard Ogle. He is quite interesting and quite tempermental. We just never can tell whether he will bring no brooms or fifty. The last time he was here he told us that he thought he would be able to tie us some this week because he might be able to get some broom corn from a neighbor since his son had married the neighbor's daughter the Saturday before. "He told us a very interesting story of how he learned his trade. When his father was a young man he passed a huddled figure one day as he was riding home. When he stopped to investigate he discovered it was an Indian who was taking the fever and was suffering quite a bit.. Mr. Ogle took the Indian home and nursed him to health. While he was recuperating he taught his benefactor the trade he had learned from his forefathers basket making and broom tying. Mr. Ogle handed the art down to his son. "Yes, the last few days have been rainy, but you see these are Dog Days and we always have a lot of rain during that time." "We have waste baskets in willow, pine and hickory splits. These in splits are so stout that the man who makes them, a six footer, can stand on them." We never are able to let this remark pass without giving a demonstration. "Harrison McCarter makes these baskets and he is to go with us to the Tri-State Fair at Memphis and demonstrate basket making in the booth that the School is to have. "Yes, the napkin rings are small, but they are for children. They were made by Jim Huskey in the Sugarlands. He makes all of these whittled things with his pocket knife. The little log cabin cigarette boxes, letter knives, salad sets out of rhododendron, toasting forks and doll furniture are all made by him. He is a preacher as well as cabinet maker. When he was a child he 'wasn't able to go to school so now he attends regularly the night classes at our extension school in the Sugarlands. "Let me wrap them all up for you. The fan is made out of pressed rye stalks. Goodness, you have so many tiny packages you really should have a basket to carry them in. Which do you want? Why, this one is only $1.25. All right, I'll just put everything in it. "No, Miss Rogers and I are not sisters, but we do live in the same place in Texas. We didn't even go to the same college. "Right in here you'll find the weaving. Oh yes, everything is handmade no, we thank you just the same, but we didn't make them ourselves They are all made here in the community. Weaving is taught NEws FROM LITTI4 PIGEON 187 in the School, but most of these things are made by women who have been in the school and are now helping to support their own homes. "Yes, Ma'am, I've been in the School for the last year. "Oh, I wasn't in any grade, I taught the 5th and 6th. "Those are $1.50. "No sir, that's a pillowtop, not a bag. . . . Yes, those are towels, in the homedyed linen. . . Well, they are rather small, but that makes them much daintier for guest towels!! "I don't 'believe we have a black and white roving bag, but this green one matches your dress perfectly . . . Oh, there are lots of things they can be used for . . anything from 'a beach-bag to a book-satchel . . that's why they are such lovely gifts for ANYONE' ! "Everything is woven on the old wooden hand-looms. No, I'm afraid I can't describe one, but I'll be glad to take you down to the weaving-room as you leave. It is in the basement of this cottage, there are seven looms, and nearly all of them are threaded up, ready for use, for some of the girls weave here during the summer, on special orders and such . "No, son, the ship model and the tennis racquet are not for sale! "Pi Beta Phi . capital P-i capital B-e-t-a capital P-h-i! "No, its not an 'agricultural society, it's a national fraternity ; yes, ma'am, this is the only School it maintains . "It doesn't look like it's possible to make all these bright things by hand, does it? . . but they're all made that way. Miss Redding, the weaving teacher, works out most of the color schemes . . . she is a wonderful teacher, and has the finest sense of color. No, she doesn't live here, she is from Massachusetts. "That's balsam that you smell right here in these little pillows . . oh, it's grand for linens, . . . and headaches . . we get it right off the tiptop of LeConte. You say you want this one? "Those are little dollsets . . coverlet and two pillows. One of the school children, Edna O'wnby, a twelve-year-old girl, weaves them, and her mother makes the bath mats you see .over there in the cup-board. "This flaxwheel? It's not for sale, nor the corner cupboard either. They are only for atmosphere! Yes, indeed, they're both old pieces . . you would have thought old, if you had seen them before they were done over!! "The runners you asked about, with the orange stripes, are what we call the Isorie runners, because Isorie Connor, a woman up Baskins Creek, makes 'em . . . The roving bags are $1.00 . . yes, any shade . "How do you do, Mrs. What-Not Oh, no indeed, you can't come too often for U'S . . . </p>
      <pb ref="arr4320183_0004" seq="04" n="188-189  "/>
       <p>188 THE ARROW Or PI BETA PHI "The hooked rugs? Well, the one on the wall was made in Asbury community, Knox County . . these others were made by Mrs. Par-ton, over in Cartertown "Shall I wrap these? . . . All right thank you, . . all of you come back . . good bye . That's an idea of a twelve-hour day of grilling! We DO try to know the answers to most of the questions, but we might as well admit that those we don't know we make up as fast as anyone asks us! But it's been wonderful . . just to be in the house with so many lovely things! . . Honestly, we used to just RESENT anyone buying at first, because we hated to see the things leave the Shop! Every single clay something different happens some :wandering Pi Phi will drop in, Harrison Mc-Carter will come with a load of baskets and visit for a while . . Isorie will come in with some new scarfs and runners . . . or 'customers, custom ers!! . of every possible age and station. It hasn't always been so nice for instance, the Sunday we both had to stand in the door to keep about fifteen people from swarming in, who apparently thought we were joking when we announced "no Sunday selling." Or at 5:30 a.m. when we would hear, from our "attic apartment," much loud knocking which meant "Mack" or "Verdie" or someone had come with baskets. But such occasions as these would be made up by other times, such as when the dearest bride and groom from Nashville, after buying some things, just insisted that we ride up to the orchard with them. Or when Mr. ^Hall brought over the Gauts, who left us a big box of candy Or when Miss Curryer and Mrs. Fletcher "kept store" for us, and we went on an all-day picnic! . . . Or when the Governor and Mrs. Peay dropped in one afternoon, throwing us into such. a panic that we couldn't even talk and shook all over with excitement, not having had any Govnor-customers before! It's too bad we haven't kept a register of all the distinguished visitors we have had, Pi Phis 'and "otherwise." But among the number are:The Grand Council of Pi Beta Phi, Governor and Mrs. Peay, Mass Ethel Curryer and her mother, Mrs. Curryer, Mrs. Carl Fletcher and family, Mrs. Hadley, Mrs. J. C. Wier, Mrs. Correll, Mrs. Daniel McIntosh. Mr. Orpheus Schantz, Mr. Jens Jensen, Noble Webb, Mrs. Eugene Mays, Ralph Hubbard, son of Elbert Hubbard, Mrs. 'Douglas Corner, Dr. and Mrs. Cale, the Chicago Prairie Club, and last but not least, our own two fathers, who had the best time of anyone! HARMO TAYLOR, Texas A LOTS ROGERS, North Carolina A NEws FnoM LITTLE PIGEON 189 COOKIN'N' SEWIN' The Cookin' n' sewin' teacher at the Burg has lost fifteen pounds since she began her summer's work. Any one can lose the same amount. No cutting down on diet is required, no setting up exercises at morning or night, in fact' I guarantee that two helpings at every meal and to bed at S:30 every night will still not add any extra pounds. Do you want my formula? Well, here it is. Monday. Arise at 6 or 6:30. Do the hundred and one things always to he done, as washing or darning stockings, writing letters or weaving 5 or 6 inches on my linen. From 9 to 11 o'clock teach a sewing class of from one to fourteen children, the number depending on the ripeness of the blackberries or the number of cases of measles, or the number of gardens to be hoed that morning!!! Everything from doll clothes to silk dresses are cut out and made. In the afternoon a cooking class is held for alder women in the Burg. At this time ,of year canning is going on. I wish you might see the lovely cans of beets, beans, carrots, rhubarb, spinach, etc., that are ready to exhibit at our fair this fall. Tuesday. Arise at the usual hour. Pack my patterns, needles, tape measure, thread, scissors and a sandwich in my saddle bags, and if "Shot" is too busy to take me in the yellow truck I get Pink or Otha to saddle Lady and at 10 o'clock I ride off to Laurel Lick. Laurel Lick is fourteen miles distant from the Burg, but Lady can make it in two hours and that *gives me plenty of time to rest under a big tree and eat my sandwich. If, when the class is over and I am not too tired and it is not too late, T take a jaunt a little out of my way to make calls. Sometimes I go part way up the Starkey Town road and then home by Canny Creek. Generally I arrive home just in time for supper. After a twenty-eight to thirty mile horse-back ride, besides teaching a class, two big helpings of potato salad and three or four slices of Aunt Lizzie's good bread and butter and raspberry jam only help to put me on my feet again ! !! ! Wednesday morning I have off. Wednesday afternoon I mount Lady again and ride off to Cartertown, about four miles distant, to teach a sewing class. Often times I get home in time from Carter-town to take a cooling dip in the river. BARBARA DEWELL Iowa I' </p>
      <pb ref="arr4320183_0005" seq="05" n="190-191  "/>
       <p>190 THE ARROW Or PI BETA PHI Thursday. Up before the usual hour as I must be in the Sugar-lands in time for a cooking class at 8 o'clock. Riding along on a, beautiful horse in the cool of the morning is about one of the most pleasant things a person can do, and remember all this while those extra pounds are slipping away!! ! Thursdays are always one of my pleasant days for I spend the day and night in the Sugarlands with Helen Chew and Cora McCarter. In the morning I have a cooking class of about four-teen young girls. In the afternoon I am supposed to have an adult sewing class, but very often the women are "hoein' their crap," or watching their bees and can't come so I take a walk, just to keep my muscles in trim, and call on them while they are at work. Friday morning early I am up and on my way back to the Burg where I have a sewing class in the morning and one in the afternoon. On Saturday and Sunday, if I feel I have not had enough exercise, during the week, a bunch of us will hike to Indian Gap Hotel or climb LeConte or ride horseback up Roarin' Fork or Baskins, or take a trip somewhere. If you want to lose weight try this formula, but I'll tell you now that you will have the best time of your life doing it. BARBARA DEWELL MOUNTAIN MOTHERS By HELEN CHEW The tragic and the beautiful in the life of the mountain women, mothers of the present generation, are so mingled as to escape the superficial observer and bring only an impression of indifference and inertia to the passer-by. The unnatural self-control becomes dumb ac-quiescence and emotion once loosed transcends all bonds. The woman of fifty or more is the last of the pioneers who fought with Nature for life and hearth. Experience has taught her the lesson of quiet acceptance of life. The new will pass her by. But the young, in whom an awakening to the possibilities of the material world is coming, are straining every nerve to adjust themselves to a situation which demands sterling character and pure blood. Slaves of environment in the past, they become products of inheritance in the future. The younger woman presents a problem which may be tragic or not in its solution. The older woman, for whom the give and take of life is nearly passed, has back of her years filled with all the tragic and beautiful possible to cram into one existence. Not all mountain women can be pigeon-holed. There are those whose natures are so simple, to whom spiritual and material needs are so few that they give and receive little. There are those who suffer and know not why there are those who suffer and know. As in all places there is every degree from the poverty of shiftlessness, to the NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 19 cleanliness of richly endowed natures. It is always the exceptional tha makes the impression. The typical is difficult to recognize. And ye if beauty comes through sacrifice and service in losing oneself in th life of others, in asking or taking nothing for self that others ma have, in finding something to love where others see only the brute, the: the life of the average mountain woman is beautiful. If the tragic lie in the suppressed and trampled existence, the silent acquiescence o the mountain mother can hardly be surpassed. The past history of mountain life is filled with such stories of f delity and sacrifice. Yet the present is not lacking entirely in oppo] tunities to throw into relief against a background of seeming medioc city, characters which almost fill one with awe. About two months ago in the Sugarlands a tragedy was repeater that is fast becoming almost a legend in local history. No story o mountains has been complete without an atmosphere of liquor and i has formed the background of comedy and tragedy alike. The result ea] be nothing but tragic as long as one of the basic institutions of a com munity is the whisky still. If the result is not neglect, poverty o crime, the undermining of moral fiber is so apparent that each genera don comes into the world less able to bear the strain of mere existencE Perhaps no family in the Sugarlands shows the ravages of thi hereditary cause more than the Huskeys. Seven generations ago ther settled in this community one known as Old Uncle Billy Huskey. Freon that day to this the offspring of this progenitor has found its way int^ half the present homes. One generation ago four brothers became tiff heads of as many homes, and fathers of large families who form a large per cent of the citizenry today. They are supposed to have mated wit] the Indians in early days, adding a lawless defiance to an already ad venturous blood. Stories of mental and physical wrecks dot their hiE tort'. One of these brothers, Aaron Huskey, married Nancy McCarter, th daughter of an old fashioned Baptist preacher. Though narrow am no doubt ignorant, her home atmosphere had been one of pious devo tion and restraint. Aaron made liquor. No doubt she knew it, but attached very little importance to it. I meant the usual line of action to her, and the question of inheritanc, in her own children was not a part of the social conscience. Liquor am men were synonymous and the question of mating had nothing to d, with it. That the question of rearing children had a good deal to d, with it has taken her forty years to find out, years that would hav crushed any but one from the sturdy Scotch of pioneer days. A num ber of children were born into that home, some with the McCarte turn, some with the Huskey, but all followed the same path until child hood and youth were past. If they could then rise above their inheri tance, all right, if not they went down. So far one has risen. Tha some of them were girls did not protect them and the first one to g </p>
      <pb ref="arr4320183_0006" seq="06" n="192-193  "/>
       <p>2 THE ARROW Or i .BETA PHI vn was Mary, about six years ago. A pretty girl, as beauty goes, married to a man with an intemperate nature she went down and vn. This is the mother's story and the details of Mary's life would y lay bare the 'ugliness of a life that could hardly escape its fate. died a young woman from the terrible effects of alcohol, leaving ee boys, one of 'whom is in the Gatlinburg school today. Following close succession came the father, a son, Bruce, and this summer, Will. Aaron, the father, carried a slight limp from early days, when one lit the revenue men surprised him at his still. This meeting did not luence the use of liquor in the home, which was poured out at the ally table like milk. Though never cruel or neglectful, Nancy used dread his return from gatherings where men passed the bottle. All s was expected of women and to rebel was disloyal and the mark the "no 'Count." Thirty years of it finally came to an end when one morning, while ;lug before the fire, his heart could bear the strain of the constant nulant no longer and he fell to the floor. To know the deliberate waste of vitality and intelligence made the ther's sorrow uo easier, but the need of her family gave her poise 1 control almost superhuman. The old people of the settlement led it a judgment from God when following Aarons' death the land ich had been purchased with money earned from the illicit selling liquor, was taken from them in payment of a debt incurred through dishonesty of a son-in-law. Nancy was given a homestead right to place, but at her death the younger children would be homeless. r only hope now is to live until the youngest, a girl of thirteen, is vided for. Punishment and suffering have limits beyond which there is no ling. As if to give a final kick to make more complete the defeat hope, hardly another year passed until Bruce was brought home one aday night and the following morning taken to the little graveyard the hill. Bruce, in his ignoranee,had many times told an old woman o tried to show him his mistakes, that he could not escape. No ever on earth could save him, he said. He was the next oldest and 14 after night the mother prayed for the good Lord to take him be t he followed his father's footsteps. As if in answer to her prayer from a footlog into the river and the fall upon the rocks was al. As soon as the liquor died within him he died. Again the mother prayed that Jim would never return from the r unless his eyes could be opened in the big world outside to a larger of usefulness. But Jim came back a comfort to her older years :1,1.ife seemed to settle down for her into something resembling peace. w and again a woman suffers as much as Nancy Huskey has and nes out refined and beautiful in character, ,On a casual acquaintance appears .a lack of feeling, a makeup which can not be touched, and a way it is for Nature has a way of protecting against that which NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 193 kills. But a closer friendship reveals the mask of sheer will power and faith in the Divine will and purpose of God, which cannot be destroyed. Not a sound escapes, or physical control shaken, .but a suffering too deep for 'words can sometimes distort the peace of her features when she mentions her lost ones. Just to go and sit with her is to come away. refreshed and strengthened for you know that here is a woman who has suffered to the uttermost and lives. After much per-suasion she began to learn to write and for the first time in her life she could read the addresses on letters left in the mail box. In her halting way she could send messages to those of her children away. She read the life of Lincoln and Washington in simple form and came to night school when we had lantern slides of foreign countries. She even looked happy and you felt she was. But life had more in store for her as if to eke out a punishment for an intentional crime of hers. Everyone knew Will had made liquor and was making it now. All summer ^when runs would be made the whole population of the settlement made daily visits to his cabin. It was no secret, but no man would deliberately inform upon another. Twice this spring the authorities made unsuccessful searches at his cabin. All it needed was the word which all men know was justified to get the case in court. Had this been done he would have been alive today. His mother pleaded with him and his brother Jim tried to influence him, but to no avail. He and his wife both started to night school and those interested in the ease began to have hope. He had the finest head for mathematics in the group. Just turned thirty, six feet tall, yellow hair combed back from a high, broad forehead, and when sober, eyes of clear blue. At times his appearance was remark-able. You were impressed with the power locked up or finding expression in such a devastating manner. One stood almost in awe of him and any man in the Sugarlands could have been approached with more ease. The weeks during which he made off a run of liquor showed a noticeable falling off of attendance at night school. It was becoming a contest which could hold out the longer. He was beginning not to come so regularly himself. One Tuesday five came to school in various stages of intoxication, an unprecedented event. It was either the school or the still. His brother Jim suggested that, with his mother's help the facts be laid before him, in such a way as to make him realize he was undoing all the good any institution, church or school, could do. The sharpness of his intellect made it necessary to be armed with more than sentiment. One needed facts and his unapproachable nature made this difficult. The next Saturday he sat flushed and bleary eyed outside the store house and about six o'clock he staggered home. Just before dark a party of young men passed on their way to the Huskey cabin. The next morning the tragedy was discovered. A quarrel had developed over </p>
      <pb ref="arr4320183_0007" seq="07" n="194-195  "/>
       <p>194 THE ARROW Or PI BETA PHI the pay for the liquor involved. When Williamson left the house Will followed him out into the yard. The quarrel continued and William-son's rock struck him in the head, laying open an ugly wound. With-out the liquor in him he would no doubt have died instantly, but it was not until about five o'clock next morning that he lost consciousness. He went like Bruce, with a crushed skull from a rock. And like Bruce, .when the liquor died in him he died. They were both too young yet to meet their father's fate. They were not given a chance to see how long their physical bodies could stand the strain. No words can describe the calmness of the mother as she sat there beside the bed or the excruciating pain which distorted her face 'when his body was laid to rest. Not a sound did she make, but a few tears fell down her cheek. In the presence of the whole community Jim stood up and called the people to bear witness to the awful toll that liquor had taken from their family. He pleaded with fathers and mothers to make a stand against the curse of the mountain country. He pointed to his mother as an example of those upon whom the suffering is placed and cursed any man who would give the two younger boys left under his mother's roof a drink of the ruinous liquor. Raising his arms to the heavens, in the manner of preachers of bygone days, he invoked the mercy of God on his brother's soul, whom no man can judge. Nothing but a power outside human understanding could help that mother lift her head again. But she lives on, hoeing her corn after the manner of mountain women, going to meeting and reading the Bible, out of which her father preached to the mountain people of the past generation. WHAT MICHIGAN BETA DID The Settlement School Committee wishes to bring to the attention of all active chapters the splendiid work done by Michigan B as described in the following letter: My Dear Miss Bishop :- I am enclosing a check for a hundred and thirty-two dollars ($132.00) as Michigan Beta's contribution to the Settlement School fund. There are forty-four members including pledges, and we each earned three dollars. We earned this money by utilizing our individual talents. One of the girls made waffles on Sunday morning for fifty cents each; another gave water waves and manicures; an ingenious sophomore interpreted dreams; our artist to be, who really has remarkable talent, drew charcoal portraits; 'beads, dresses, fur coats, and shoes were rented. Everything in the house became commercialized! In actually working together we have come to appreciate the real spirit of our Settlement School. ELEANOR VERDIER, Chairman of Committee BooK Noes BOOK NOTES BY DOROTHY K. CLEAMAND, Nzw YORK r State Teachers College, Tahlequah, Oklahoma. "G. Stanley Hall: A Biography of a Mind", by Lorine ette (Mrs. Douglas Fryer, Tenn. A). New York D. App and Co. 1926. Apparently the truth of the old adage that truth is sty than fiction is appealing more and more to both authors and : ers if one can judge by the great increase in biographical wi and the fact that the new biographies often attain the state "best sellers." Among the outstanding recent books of this class is "G. ley Hall: A Biography of a Mind," by Lorine Pruette. Pres Hall was a unique and gigantic figure in the educational IA In Miss Pruette's interpretation, we have a most fascinating chological study of both the-man and his work, one which w read with interest not only by edii-ca-tors_and psychologists also by all interested in the life of a great contemporary. author was privileged to be one of President Hall's grad-u-ab dents at Clark University, attending his lectures and setn: and after that, visiting him frequently and keeping in close with him until his death in 1924, so that she had ample o tunity to know her subject, and the book is warmed by the er iasm of a disciple. The story of the man is dramatic in itself, the countr: who became a leader in the new science of psychology, autl such standard books as "Adolescence," founder of the first chological laboratory; and builder of Clark University, WI ter, Mass. Twice he saw his life work destroyed by those t to appreciate his vision, twice he saw his home life disri once by death, once by a tragedy even greater. But this biog </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



