<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr4620307_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Curtis, Blanche Charlton</name></author>
                        <author><name>Redding, Winogene B.</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>November 1929</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr4620307_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">November 1929</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Curtis, Blanche Charlton</name></author>
                        <author><name>Redding, Winogene B.</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 306-311</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">38</note>
                        <note type="Folder">3</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 46, Number 2 (November 1929), Pages 306-311.</note>
			<note type="document">arr4620307_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">The Province Vice Presidents Visit Gatlinburg; On Old Art Modernized; </note>
                        <note type="Additional Information">Some material from the August-September issue of The Handicrafter</note>
	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Weaving</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr4620307_0001" seq="01" n="306-307  "/>
       <p>rAvRAvRmemPAt'RAvAniTfiltPlifa .2g:491t491CO91.vae.491Cit.91C* .4 4 CAW'S edited by Blanche Charlton Curtis OVi Vice Presidents Visit OW o C ainburg EVER since the Province ?residents have made regular to their alumni clubs it has the dream of the Settlement 1 Committee that some day night visit the school and then irectly to the alumna some of ;piration that is bound to come first-hand knowledge of the And this year that dream true! On August 30 and 31 rand Vice President and six n.ce Vice Presidents, repre Alpha, Epsilon, Zeta, Eta, and Kappa provinces, were tlinburg for two days of in-'e sightseeing. o days seemed woefully short .e staff and committee but s to perfect weather, a pro-carefully planned by Dr. Gornd Miss Evelyn, and complete eration on the part of the visiit was possible to give them usually comprehensive idea of :hool, the countryside, and the The Pi Phi Man reral arrived on August 29 and :vening listened to an informal )y Mr. Orpheus Schantz, who to be known locally as the "Pi Ian." [Mr. Schantz' interest in :hool dates back to those early when the Chicago alumnae club, . the most efficient leadership 'rs. Helmick, did so well the difficult pioneer work for the school. His wife, Carrie Flagler, Iowa Theta, was actively interested from the first and so enthused him that he has rarely missed making one or more trips a year ever since.] He gave a survey of the history and racial heritage of the mountain people, together with some interesting data on the geological and botanical side of the country. The next morning was devoted to going over the entire property the farm, the Health Center, the dormitories, the teachers' quarters, the two schools, the Arrowcraft Shop, and even the powerhouse. Every-one attended assembly, where the committee, as well as the Province Vice Presidents, heard for the first time the entire school sing their Pi Phi school song. It was too much for most of them and tears streamed down their faces as they realized just how deeply Pi Beta Phi is in-stilling its ideals of loyalty and friendship and service into the hearts of these boys and girls. The afternoon was spent at the Emma Harper Turner Center at Sugarlands. There each visitor was asked to give a little impromptu talk about her particular part of the country a marvelous opportunity for California ! But Alpha Province Vice President with her winter home in Boston and her summer home near Plymouth Rock rather The November ARROW 307 had the advantage as far as material of historic interest was concerned. When it came to inspecting the work the pupils were doing, one of the committee decided that it might be well if her own daughter could attend the school the quality of the work was so much better than in similar grades in some of our city schools. After school was dismissed there was a trip up the mountain road to within five miles of the North Carolina line and many were the exclamations at the beauty of the country. And there were cabins here and there. to show the new-comers just how isolated these people were before the road came through. A picnic supper on the rocks down by Little Pigeon completed this day and the committee noted with great satisfaction that here, even after so strenuous a day, each Province Vice President was busily chatting with some member of the staff, asking numberless questions and eagerly gleaning every possible bit of information. Aunt Lizzie Entertains A walk up Baskins occupied the next morning and included calls on some of the people where much was learned of the homes, the speech, and the hospitality of the mountaineers. The poise with which they greeted a group of unexpected guests and their willingness to ex-plain their weaving or to sit on the porch and sing ballads made a deep impression. A business meeting filled the afternoon and a picnic supper on the porch of Aunt Lizzie's little hill-side cabin completed two perfect days. Some stayed on for further exploration, attending church at Gathnburg on Sunday morning and revival services at Banner in the evening visiting up some of the other creeks and becoming more enthusiastic every hour. They all agreed that the two days.' visit had been most worth while and unanimously chose Louise Richardson, Alpha Province Vice President, to write the following account of the trip: According to the Province Vice Presidents the two days spent in a little cottage in Gatlinburg were some of the most enjoyable and most valuable days in their experience. New adjectives were coined ; unusual similes were heard; note-books were filled with what was seen and heard, from the information that story means a lie to the fact that the Settlement School teachers are decidedly good looking. Again was proven the fact that Pi Phi means friendship California and Nebraska vied with each other as to the number of mouth-melting biscuits which each could devour ; Iowa and Minnesota ate honey and watermelon to their hearts' content ; Texas and Massachusetts were friends from the start, although one insisted on Ictffing, the other on larfing. Although each day began at six-thirty, when blue haze hung over those glorious Smokies, and closed at eleven-thirty, when fraternity affairs were settled at a negligee conference, time was too short for all those two good friends, Doctor Edith and Miss Evelyn, had planned for their guests. Sightseeing Far exceeding the wildest fancies of the Province Vice Presidents was the beauty of the region, the </p>
      <pb ref="arr4620307_0002" seq="02" n="308-309  "/>
       <p>The November ARROW any of the community, the of the teachers, and the value work. Who would not revel towering chimneys and the ess of the stretches of forest, shrub with the fascinating Hearts Bursting with Love ich obliging Mr. Mattel picked hose who rode in his staunch Ford over the old trail abound-' bumps and ruts and rocks out .garlands! Who could forget c,orgeous ride in the rumble with the learned chairman of Settlement School committee the winding new road border-a deep gulleys through the new anal Park nearly to North Iina ! Then there was the picnic le roaring fire made by those 2nt teachers of Sugarlands ; the nbling up the. rocks in the y darkness; the stumbling i a narrow trail, the teeter-^ver those perilous scream-pro-'g bridges with three tiny flash 3 shared by twenty picnickers. ho can ever lose the memory hose friendly contacts: that on the porch of Aunt e's mountain-perched home e it was decided between big hfulls of jam sandwiches and that Aunt Lizzie should keep ne for ancient Pi Phi spinsters d. even weary wives. And was the trip with thoughtful Smith up Caney Crik to give Lance to the sick cow, and the ant chat with its owner who "er callers to shame when she she'd overslept that morning lot risen till four-thirty ! What hat sunny morning when the e crowd husband and alled up Baskins to visit Izora in lower surrounded house here as that Nebraska and Texas proudly assisted Izora in her weaving and to hear Myrtle tell of the Harp Singing and sing those old ballads, "Judge and Jury" and "Barbara Allen" and close with "America." What a thrill that gave the visitors! Friendships The Province Vice President will long cherish memories of the eager, enthusiastic Doctor Edith, the level headed, sweet-spirited Rebecca, and the conscientious, merry Blanche: how they insisted that each Province Vice President trail over to the hotel in decided undress for a hot bath, how they feared lest some-thing be left undone, and how they filled all with a new love for Pi Phi. Perhaps the Settlement School committee in turn will remember the well-poised Lillian of Epsilon Province who had such a good Pi Phi husband and attractive musical daughter, the charming Florence of Zeta, the efficient Vera of Eta, the versatile Frankie of Theta who insisted in kissing the cheek which had once been kissed by the former First Lady, the gracious Bernice of Kappa, and the broad a'd Louise of Alpha. From the fun of the picnics, the thrill of the mountain rides, the joys of association with splendid Tennessee men and women and with some of the finest Pi Phis in the country, has come to each of those Province Vice Presidents who were given the privilege of a visit to Gatlinburg, a desire to publish where-ever she may go the fact that there is no work more worth the time, the strength, and the money of every Pi Phi than that being done in the heart of the Great Smokies in the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School. AT o N TIO N T Members of the Grand Council, Emilie Margaret White, Lois Franklin Stoolman, Amy Burnham Onken, and Gail DeWolf "at ease" along the walks of the Hotel Huntington. Grace Post, Washington B and California A, successfully executed the duties of Guide and was appointed treasurer of the Settlement School Committee. </p>
      <pb ref="arr4620307_0003" seq="03" n="308-309  "/>
       <p>ince Vice Presidents picnicked on the banks of the beautiful Little Pigeon River, :d the Sugarlands and were feted everywhere during their visit at the Settlement Dl in' August. Blanche Curtis and Louise Richardson tell the story. (Page 306.) The November ARROW 309 An Old Art Modernized This interesting story of weaving at Gatlinburg and the part that the Pi Beta Phi Settlement school has played in reviving it was written for the August-September issue of "The Handicrafter" by Winogene B. Redding who resigned front the Settlement School staff in June after four years of devoted and faithful service. The Editor wishes to acknowledge her appreciation to the Emilie Bernet and Sons Company, publishers of "The Handicrafter," for permission to reprint this story. . By WINOGENE B. REDDING THE revival of weaving in Gatlinburg is at an interesting stage in its development. In this mountain section of East Tennessee, where a large part of the population still lives according to age-old customs, the weaving strikes a modern note that is curiously different and a little out of keeping with the fast disappearing log cabin days. It seems as if we should expect the woman who still lives in a picturesque log cabin to be weaving coverlets made of her own home-spun, indigo dyed wool on an old heavy beamed sled loom instead we find her. weaving bright colored scarfs or modernistic towels of fine linen on a small, modern homemade loom whose only claim, as far as looks are concerned, with the old loom long relegated to the loft, is the string heddles. About twenty-five years ago the home industry of weaving went out of style around here, so to the younger mothers it is a new and strange art. It is to their grand-mothers we go for stories of weaving in the romantic age for it seems like romance to those of us who can only gaze at the gloriously colored pieces of weaving that are brought out of an old trunk for us to admire. It became much more simple to buy a few yards of dress materialat the new store than to spend the many months of hard labor that it took to raise a small patch of cotton or flax or to prepare wool from the time it was sheared from the sheep until it was finally woven into cloth for family use. Grandmothers' Tales How strange we think the tales of these grandmothers. One tells me with pride that when she was young she used to weave seven yards of blankets or four to five yards of jean in a day; another how she would gather walnut roots to dye wool for suiting for her man and how it would grow darker in color the longer it was worn; the next one, how her mother would raise a patch of flax and how much beating it took to separate the fibers and then the tow was used to fill bed quilts; and another, how long it took to prepare a blue pot and how difficult it was to know when it was just at the right stage to dip the wool. One woman told me recently of seeing years ago, her grandmother's and grandfather's church clothes that her grandmother had woven. The dress was made of very fine dark brown homespun wool and fashioned with a series of ruffles, short and full, down the entire length of the skirt. The </p>
      <pb ref="arr4620307_0004" seq="04" n="310-311  "/>
       <p>310 The November ARROW man's suit was much more gay as the trousers were woven of colored striped homespun and the woven cotton shirt was made with a ruffle around the vest-like front. They were beautifully sewed with tiny, wee stitches, the happy result of months of work. The weaving days must have. been strenuous ones, too, for one woman told me how she used to dread to have her mother sit down at her loom for then two of the children had to sit under the loom, one on each side, to catch the shuttle when it went flying to the floor. Thus was weaving when our country was young and the family clothing and bedding depended upon the ingenuity and art of the womenfolks. This is the way it was preserved in the homes until our clay and for our appreciation in these remote mountain regions. Now these grandmothers watch their daughters weave with an ease, that they never imagined possible--even their weaving language is not the same. The "chain" of their time is now a warp, the "gears" are harnesses, "quills" are bobbins, sleys are no longer numbered from 400 to 700 sley eyes to each one, according to the way the cane pieces were fastened in, but are steel affairs, uniformly made and numbered by the inch. The reason for weaving has changed as completely as the times for now it is done from choice and not from necessity. It is true that we use the same old patterns, none lovelier could be found, but our adaptations, color schemes, and the uses to which they are put are so different that they hardly seem the same designs. Weaving In Vogue Once more weaving is the thing to do in the homes, in fact one might call it the chief indoor sport of Gatlinburg and the surrounding country. There are at least seventy-five women steadily employed at their looms and one can hardly pass a house for miles around without hearing the thump, thump of the beater. Economically it has distinct advantages for the money earned is put to good use. Several women have helped to build and furnish new homes, children are being sent to school, three young girls are earning enough this summer to go to high school again in the fall. It helps to pay for the family car and Victrolas and pianos are invested in because the mountain people are lovers of music. Artistically it is equally important. Every woman takes pleasure in watching a fabric grow thread by thread. That is perhaps the greatest 'reason why weaving has such a human appeal. It is a joy to discover a woman who lives way up a creek develop a keen sense of color and see her eyes shine when she is given a basket of different colored yarn and told to weave it up into things she thinks are pretty. In this way her love for color is satisfied the year round for every mountain home is surrounded by flowers in the summer and it is the women who care for them patiently and carefully so the gaily colored skeins of yarn hanging against the dark weathered plank wall trans-form a dark wintry day into one of brightness and cheer. Some women take special pride in making new designs out of old threadings, a thing which is encouraged. And so The November ARROW it goes, each woman giving her weaving an individual touch for no matter how many are making the same kind of towels or runners each one is different from the other. When the weaving was first encouraged and taught by the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, which selected Gatlinburg for its location seventeen years ago, the industrial department had a small and humble beginning. Now the department reaches nearly one hundred homes through the weaving, baskets, and furniture making. The people are taught individually and entirely in the homes with the exception of a few girls each year who study weaving in the school. We reach some of the homes by automobile, when they are situated on the new state highway that goes by our very door, for we are fortunate to be located at the entrance to the proposed Smoky Mountain National Park. Other homes, in picturesque settings which we find up this creek or in that hollow, can only be reached by horseback or walking over steep, rocky roads that are still very rough as good roads come very slowly to us. Gift Shops have been opened to sell our wares to the tourists who come to view the splendid scenery. One is sponsored by the school, others by energetic mountain womenwho learned weaving in the in the early days. True Revival The women are once more , ing dresses for themselves of I colored yarns that were not go to make in a home dye pot, own linens and curtains fo home, for the new houses many windows in place of th little window the old time cabit These young women are eag learn, responsive to suggestion: give their whole hearted co-o tion. They know that without things no project can be a sup They realize, too, that the ar they weave have to meet a cliff need in their homes ,as well the homes of others and so necessary to give up the spl^ but hard ways of their g: mothers and adopt new styles methods that are in keeping our modes of living in this gee tion. Now we find ourselves pit into the rapid revival of an of which is done easier and qu and is already taking on me aspects that unfortunately c duplicate the richness of colot wearing qualities and the quain. fashioned charm of the labo products of our ancestors. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



