<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr4020285_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Convention Chronicle</title>
                        <author><name>White, Emily Margaret</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>December 1923</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr4020285_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">December 1923</date>, Convention Chronicle</title>
                        <author><name>White, Emily Margaret</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 284-288</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">37</note>
                        <note type="Folder">3</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 40, Number 2 (December 1923), Pages 284-288.</note>
			<note type="document">arr4020285_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Excerpt about Settlement School</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Founding of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1909-1927</item>
                                <item>Health care</item>
                                <item>Funding</item>
                                <item>Programs</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr4020285_0001" seq="01" n="284-285  "/>
       <p>284 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PM at the Clatworthy Studio. The owner of the studio, Fred Payne Clatworthy, a member of B II, Dennison University, has been in Estes Park many years and has made photography his life work and study. Mr. Clatworthy is recognized as an artist of note. On Tuesday evening, Mr. Clatworthy gave an ecellent auto-chrome lecture at Con-'yention Hall in which he displayed photographic slides of Colorado mountain scenery. That group of pictures which he recently showed be-fore the National Geographic society was published by them at a cost of $65,000 and it is considered the finest collection of colored scenic pictures ever shown. Pi Beta Phi was also complimented i n being the first to be shown some of the very latest results of Mr. Clatworthy's picture taking tour through California and the Grand Canon. The pictures were produced by a slow and intricate process and far surpass the painter in reproducing the lavish coloring of the Rocky Mountain beauties. No ordinary photograph can do full justice to the beauties of Nature's coloring and in perfecting this French coloring process, Mr. Clatworthy has made a great advance for science and art. For twelve years, Mr. Clatworthy has conducted a Panhellenic register at his studio in Estes Park. Mr. Clatworthy's sister is a member of A A A. As a Convention souvenir, Mr. Clatworthy gave to every Pi Phi at Estes Park, a card bearing the two views which are being Fred Payne Clatworthy CONVENTION CHRONICLE 285 used at the beginning and end of this article. He also has very generously donated many of the pictures which are being used in this issue. 0 In many ways Mr. Clatworthy assisted members of Pi Beta Phi during the Convention and we acknowledge with deep appreciation these courtesies of another Greek. On Tuesday night, June 27, the Settlement School program held its listeners at attention from the beginning of the showing of stereoptican pictures of "Little Pigeon" to the close of the splendid play of "Pi Beta Phi In the Highlands." One of the privileges of Convention was to meet and to know Evelyn Bishop, Head Resident of the School, and Phyllis Higginbotham, Head Nurse, and it was a delight to hear the explanations concerning the stereoptican slides as made by Miss Bishop to whom "Aunt Lizzie," the Reagans, the Ogles, and the Huskies are living, breathing persons. The play which was originally written and produced by the Washington alumnae club and which appeared in the June, 1923, ARROW, was revised for Convention by Elizabeth Shepard Lough, Wisconsin A, and Kate B. Miller, Iowa B, of the New York alumnae club. It was directed by Emilie Margaret White, Vice-president of Gamma-Delta Provinces, and a member of the Washington alumnae club. The programs bearing an excellent picture of a mountain Our Right Hand Men-Stanley Hotel Photo by 'Woodman </p>
      <pb ref="arr4020285_0002" seq="02" n="286-287  "/>
       <p>256 THE ARROW OF PI BETA. PHI woman and a huge basket which she had made, were presented to convention by the New York Alumnae Club. Those who assisted in the presentation were: CAST OF CHARACTERS Grandmother Combs, Blanche Charlton Curtis, Vice-president, Iota-Kappa Province Young Mother . .Helen McCargo Geppert, Vice-president, Zeta Province Dollard Marion Baker, Vice-president, Beta Province Marthy Lelah-Bell Davis, Vice-president, Epsilon Province Sally Edith Valet Cook, Vice-president, Alpha Province Arlina Kathleen Little, Vice-president, Theta Province Teacher Evelyn Bishop, Head Resident Nurse Phyllis Higinbotham, Public Health Nurse 'leacher of Agriculture, Frances Carpenter Curtis, Settlement School Committee Teacher of Fireside Industries, Nita Hill Stark, Settlement School Committee Pi Beta Phi Visitor .. Melinda B. Stuart, Settlement School Committee Spirit of Pi Beta Phi Anna Nickerson, Grand Vice-president Members of the National Council of Zeta Tau Alpha, who were in conference at the Y. M. C. A. grounds, were the guests of II B 4) at this program. The following items which appeared on the Settlement School aol.l.lLutuoo TootpS "1.11 aApo'e .m.ott urea2oad was in bringing Gatlinburg to Estes Park. The Agricultural Department Exhibition arranged by the Director, 0. J. Mattil. Fireside Industries Exhibition of baskets, weaving and other articles arranged by the Head Resident and Irene Linkous. Sewing Exhibition of dresses and other articles arranged by Anna Dowell. The Community Exhibition of pictures showing community life and various school activities. Sale of Articles from Gatlinburg and other articles for the benefit of the school, in charge of Frances Carpenter Curtis and Melinda B. Stuart. Auction All articles not sold during the Tour will be auctioned off. Make your choice early and get what you want, but don't go until you have helped bid off everything to the greatest possible financial profit of your own PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL The exhibits of the School attracted widespread attention and CONVENTION CHRONICLE 287 Indiana Alpha's Prize Winning Exhibit everyone who attended Convention returned home with new zeal to work for Little Pigeon. An interesting souvenir of Convention was "Montgomery's Vindicator," the leading newspaper of Sevierville, Tennessee for Wednesday, June 13, 1923. This issue of Montgomery's Vindicator contained an excellent panoramic view of Gatlinburg and a splendid write-up concerning our Settlement School. "In 1912 when the Pi Beta Phi Fraternity located a Settlement School at Gatlinburg," says the editor, "no one dreamed of it playing such an important part in the educational interests of Sevier County. Since that time this institution has been one of the leading schools of this section and to say it is appreciated in the community it serves is putting it mildly." Such recognition is most gratifying when we look back and IMOUSiOkligAAttOtiAiRNA021ali.M6ti'%VIAgOagooi.i.istoto :.,,l, ,, rO truth and seek it above material things, t imotAe ;Intl b.' enobW t jell:.Sit; ar, oNIt m1:1,i to N,'aiuG eitcIz,31rIvIne to 6 ,,t them </p>
      <pb ref="arr4020285_0003" seq="03" n="288-289  "/>
       <p>288 THE ARROW OF PI BETA Pin ,.,msmsmsaasitgoegizsgtgmtf .'.,,,,-: ..,:.. . ,.., A neuc'te'''r mmoorEr taime2vor.ts rn';IE , :;4 think how skeptical the people were when Dr. Keller made her first trip of inspection up there near the foot of the Smokies. In the spare moments between sessions, jaunts and meetings CONVENTION CHRONICLE 289 the Exhibit Hall buzzed with spectators for there on the walls hung the trophies of fifty-seven chapters. So many exhibits had never before been displayed at any II (I). Convention and it is with great regret that we cannot print the pictures of everyone of them. After a trip. of inspection, the committee consisting of Elda Smith, Nina Harris Allen and Pauline Turnbull, awarded first prize to Indiana A. The award of the committee was made upon the representation of the chapter in social, dramatic, athletic, musical and other activities ; representation of the college or university; artistic effect. All chapters in Alpha, Zeta, Eta, Theta and Kappa Provinces were represented with exhibits among the fifty-seven entered. Stunt night, one of the most popular features of each Convention, which came as a fitting climax to our day of recreation, proved no exception to the rule and the display of dramatic and vocal ability, as well as pep and originality was greatly appreciated by those who crowded every available foot of space in the Casino. California A and Cailfornia B in characteristic songs presented the "Pi Beta Phi of Yesterday and of Today." "The Ideal Pi Phi," was a clever one act play presented by Beta Province. "Who's Crazy Now," was the skit chosen by Iowa B. Epsilon Province gave their province song written by Illinois E which was a decided hit. The song told how the girls of the Middle West love their pigs and corn. The singers were dressed like farmer folk with the girls in gingham dresses, half socks and hair bows and the boys in overalls. ' A fter the song, the Illinois B delegate, with marked talent, very cleverly presented "The Missionary Man," by Zeta Province which told of the difficulties of the missionary man in teaching English to little Japanese maidens who only say, "I want to be a Pi Phi." Carol McConnell of Oklahoma B gave an interpretive dance which was followed by a "Mexican Bull-right," by Arizona A. The feature of the Arizona stunt was the disguise of Sir Bull and the costumes of the fighters. Tiny maple sugar bars in wrappers tied with wine and blue ribbons were the gifts of Vermont A and B and oranges wrapped in "greetings" wrappers were distributed by California T. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



