<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr4820303_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Frost, Mary Cooper</name></author>
                        <author><name>Moore, Frances</name></author>
                        <author><name>Stone, Edna</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>November 1931</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr4820303_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">November 1931</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Frost, Mary Cooper</name></author>
                        <author><name>Moore, Frances</name></author>
                        <author><name>Stone, Edna</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 303-307</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">38</note>
                        <note type="Folder">7</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 48, Number 2 (November 1931), Pages 303-307.</note>
			<note type="document">arr4820303_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">The Gatlinburg News; Accomplishments of Settlement School Committee; Frances Moore; The Children's Rest Hour; Parent Teacher Association; A Summer Trip to Gatlinburg; A Contribution to Art</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Planning</item>
                                <item>Health care</item>
                                <item>Arts</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr4820303_0001" seq="01" n="302-303  "/>
       <p>MA3,v,P,MP/tAlvFAVAMiPWAMEWAvRAVinsio,l''AW.RM oi.c4.91c49R.''Piq491c4-.91491coa4viWic,49itow4vii 1.I *VMS { W r rl LIIUILIJ " edited by Mary Cooper Frost The Gailinburg News THE latest, one hates to ay last, number of Gatlinburg News s out just as THE ARROW goes to )ress. This little sheet has been pub ished for seven years by the frater lity, its editors being the school staff. k1though it has cost fifty cents a year outside Gatlinburg, it has gone free to )eople of the community. In its col m1ns they could read about everything when to spray the apple trees end what to feed the cow to who had he newest baby. It has given pul) icity to and supported every enter prise of the district as well as of the school. It has advertised coming events like weavers' meetings, basketball games, and elections. It has disseminated important health information and given timely notice of clinics at the Health Center. It has been invaluable for the news that it carried, and the fact that its method of spreading news taxed the school staff least is of no little consideration. The moderate sum necessary for its continuance was one of the last ones pared from the current budget. accomplishments of Settlement School Connuittee THE Settlement School :omrnittee in session, August 20-27, at 'Jatlinburg: 1. Authorized the Chairman to an-1ounce through the Province Presilents and the Province Vice-presi lents vacancies on the school staff 2. Reduced valuation on buildings ,ecause of the decline in property slues, due to the depression, upon the ecommendation of the insurance aduster ; 3. Contracted to rent to Mr. Mattil or three years the producing wood-raft shop, the generous gift of Mr. ,ouis Voorheis, but looked forward in more prosperous future to using the uilding for educational work; 4. Authorized the chairman to invesgate manual training projects simiir to the one planned for the school nd to present at the next meeting a tentative program for the manual training department; 5. Recommend that Province Vice-Presidents be instructed to urge club Settlement School sales chairmen to hand on their records to their successors and to keep accurate accounts; 6. Considered the possibility of opening a tea shop in the Arrow Craft Shop during the summer months; 7. Put all teachers' salaries on a complete cash payment basis to replace the former arrangement of cash-boardtravel payment; 8. Discontinued the Gatlinburg News after one more issue because of lack of funds; 9. Found it necessary to cut the bud-get of 1930-31 by $3,075 for that of 1931-32, even though in the past year actives and alumnae have continued their support in spite of hard times; The 'November ARROW 303 10. Decided that no new projects would be possible during the current year except the building of a bull pen, which is necessary for the safety of the farm workers, and a machine shed, without which implements would deteriorate very rapidly; Franees Moore FRANCES MOORE, the school nurse since November, 1928, left on October 15 to accept a position with the Teachers' College at Johnson City, Tennessee, just rounding out three years of service in Gatlinburg. A graduate of the University of Chicago and of Cook County Hospital, she brought a very high type of training to the community. Linked with this, and enhancing it, was a remarkable knack with the people. Her patience, tact, and tirelessness paved the way for trust and love. Up the "cricks and 11. Was deeply impressed by the fine spirit of the entire staff ; 12. Refused absolutely to accept the resignation of the director, Evelyn Bishop, whose devoted efforts over a period of many years have led to much of the success of the school. hollers" when her automobile refused to go farther or when the trail was too rocky and tangled even for her horse, Frances found her way afoot to the most isolated cases of sickness. The confidence she inspired has added to friends of the school many mountain families who would have had little or no contact with it otherwise. Pi Phis who have gone with Frances on her rounds, the staff, of which she has been such a devoted member, and the entire community feel keen regret at her leaving Gatlinburg. The Children's Rest Hour By FRANCES MOORE OUR most serious health problems among the mountian children are the finding of tuberculosis contacts and providing adequate care for them and for other undernourished children. There is much tuberculosis in this mountain section, and we are now able to determine which children are infected by means of the tuberculin tests. Since lack of time prevents the county health officer from testing all school children, we select those who are known to have familial contacts and those who show definite symptoms of malnutrition. A surprisingly large number of children have shown positive reactions. The next problem is to make the families understand the importance of this reac Lion and the need of giving their children special care. At the beginning of this school year we decided to arrange a way for a small group of these children to have rest periods at school. This would be beneficial to the selected group, and we hoped it might also serve as a demonstration of the treatment for malnutrition. At first we were able to take only six little girls as our space was limited to one small room in the Health Center. We had the hospital bed, one cot, and the examining table. Since all our children were little folks from the primary room, we economized on space by putting one child at the head of the bed and another at the foot. One of the dormitory girls </p>
      <pb ref="arr4820303_0002" seq="02" n="304-305  "/>
       <p>304 The November ARROW was placed in charge of the children. Recently our rest room was transferred from the Health Center to the library in the grade school building. We now have six cots and can take care of twelve children. The children come into the room as soon as they reach school in the morning. Dresses and shoes and stockings are removed, placed on a chair, hands and feet are washed, then each little girl lies down for her rest period. If she has come to school early, this may be as long as half an hour. If she gets there late, it may be only ten minutes, but at least it gives an opportunity for relaxation. When the first bell rings, the children jump up and put on their clothes, obediently swallow the teaspoonful of cod liver oil, and scamper out to play for a few minutes before school begins. The same procedure is repeated at noon. The children come as soon as they have finished their lunches in the school lunch room and rest until time for the first bell. Talking during rest hour is forbidden, but of course we can't' prohibit an occasional giggle. In spite of the children's protests thatthey aren't sleepy, we find that some of them do go to sleep. Most of them are up at dawn and there are some in the group who walk one or two miles to school. At the beginning of the year all sorts of coaxing and bribes were necessary to induce the children to come for the rest hour. They had a hundred good reasons for not coming. They weren't tired, they had slept all night, they wanted to play, their mothers didn't say they had to come, why didn't Kate or Hazel have to come, and so on. In a few days the attitude was entirely changed. It became a matter of competition to see who would be invited to join the rest group. Children began coming to the Health Center to ask if they, too, weren't underweight. The youngsters who have been chosen now feel that they are an especially privileged group. The children are weighed once a week. Their steady gains and their cheerful, responsive attitude have made us feel that the rest hours are going to prove a successful experiment, and that the influence will be spread into many homes. Parent Teacher Association THE P.T.A. of Gatlinplan to sell candy at the basketball burg, at its recent bazaar, raised about games to add to their fund. People of $65. ARROW readers will remember that the community are being asked to give this organization was formed for the fruit, vegetables, and milk again. This public-spirited purpose of providing a year, Mrs. Rush Rawlings will prepare hot dish at lunch for the school chilthe food, which is of such great health dren who cannot go home. The women value to the children. A Snnnner Trip to Gatlinburg By EDNA STONE, former member of the Settlement School Committee IT -WAS in a holiday school ever since I had helped to start spirit that I went to Tennessee last it nearly twenty years ago, but just the June with Sarah Kemmerer and her right time and reason never seemed to brother for a week in Gatlinburg. I come until this summer when our Po-had always meant to go to visit our tomac Appalachian Trail Club of The November ARROW 305 Washington took a mountain-climbing trip to the Great Smokies. Our stop-ping place was Mr. Huff's pleasant Mountain View Hotel in Gatlinburg, which village Is now the gateway to the Smoky Mountains National Park. No words of mine can describe the beauty of those mountains in June, with their wealth of rhododendron, laurel, azalea, and other flowers, their splendid forests and dashing streams. Guided by members of the Smoky Mountain Hiking Club of Knoxville, our party visited the more important peaks of the region. The first and second days of our stay were spent on the trip up beautiful Mount LeConte, nearly 7,000 feet above sea level, and on the third we took a lovely and much easier walk on the trail down from Indian Gap. On the following days, while the hard-boiled members of our party visited Clingman's Dome or Mount Guyot, Sarah Kemmerer and I were glad to rest, to see more of Gatlinburg, and to visit the School. Unfortunately it was vacation time and most of the students and teachers were away, and so we saw only the frame of the picture, the setting of the play which is acted with such spiritand devotion every year. This setting impressed us very much. The number and variety of the buildings, the excellent condition of land, gardens, roads, all cared for by some of the young farmers whom we saw at work, showed loving care and efficient management. We would have liked to see the primary children lined up for their hand-washing and cod liver oil, as described in a recent ARROW ; we were sorry not to see the housekeeping and weaving classes at work, but Miss Hathaway, who was our guide, made the school life so real to us that hearing her was almost as good as seeing it. We made a special pilgrimage to the Emma Harper Turner Center, which was closed for the summer. Of course we lingered long looking at the lovely things in the Arrow Craft Shop. Much of the pleasure of our visit was meeting and talking with Mr. and Mrs. Huff and their charming daughters. As one of the residents of the village remarked to us, the real and continuing need for the School in the community can be realized only by seeing the people in their homes, and we had little opportunity to visit </p>
      <pb ref="arr4820303_0003" seq="03" n="306-307  "/>
       <p>306 The November ARROW mountain homes. But every voice spoke in praise of the School and the work it is doing. Like others who have heard of the changes which time and the park development have brought about in the neighborhood of Gatlin-burg, we had wondered if the school had nearly finished its usefulness to the mountain people, some of whom are moving away, but we are now convinced that it is still greatly needed by the newer as well as by the older population. A number of years will pass before this need will lessen, and as Sophie Woodman said, in THE AR-ROW of November, 1930, "To slacken would be bad business as well as poor humanity." A Contribution to Art By LADELLE ALLEN PI BETA PHI has made a large contribution in the field of art through the revival of the hand weaving and hand-made furniture. This fact never occurred to me until we were asked to exhibit in the Exhibition of the Decorative Arts by American Contemporary Artists, Montclair Art Museum [Montclair, New Jersey]. We have stressed, rather, that which was being done to help the people. But it appears that what has been done has served a twofold purpose. The director of the Art Museum wrote us that there was nothing in the exhibition that created more interest that the things from the Tennessee Mountains. The New York Times Magazine carried a picture of our en-tries with its article on the entire exhibition; the New York Sun had even a larger cut of our exhibit and its article was headed "Native Arts and Crafts Shown." A part of the article was as follows: "Unfortunately, not a few will feel that the most accomplished and mostesthetically pleasing work shown is so markedly the result of foreign influence that the only native feature about it is the fact that it was done in this country. In consequence, one turns with a certain hopefulness to the cruder, more primitive work that unquestionably smacks of the soil. "In this field th.ere is nothing more interesting in the present display than the showing from the Tennessee Mountains. . . "Another purely American venture into craftsmanship, which though modern in itself, harks back to old-time native handiwork, is furnished by Pi Beta Phi Settlement School at Gatlinburg in the Tennessee Mountains. .. Native motifs, laurel and rhododendron, and simple geometrical de-signs predominate to produce results distinctly pleasing. A walnut rocker with a corn-husk bottom, and a ladder-back chair of cherry wood that emphasizes the native note are also shown among the outstanding features of this part of this display." Eighty-five alumn2e clubs, six active chapters, twenty-one shops, and two hundred twenty-one individuals have sold during 1930-31, $22,005.01 worth of Settlement School products, only $498.46 less than was sold during 1929-30. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



