<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr4940445_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Frost, Mary Cooper</name></author>
                        <author><name>Post, Grace </name></author>
                        <author><name>Hill, Frankie C. </name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>May 1933</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr4940445_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">May 1933</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Frost, Mary Cooper</name></author>
                        <author><name>Post, Grace </name></author>
                        <author><name>Hill, Frankie C. </name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 445-449</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">38</note>
                        <note type="Folder">10</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 49, Number 4 (May 1933), Pages 445-449.</note>
			<note type="document">arr4940445_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">The School; No, We're Not!; The Health Center of Zeta Tau Alpha; My Evening School Work; For the June Bride; Weaving Meeting Day in Gatlinburg</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Funding</item>
                                <item>Government</item>
                                <item>Weaving</item>
                                <item>Home economics</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr4940445_0001" seq="01" n="444-445  "/>
       <p>444 THE MAY ARROW MU PROVINCE California Alpha Mary Della Callahan, a senior has contributed much to both chapter and university activities during the two years that she has attended Stanford University. Entering the chapter house as a junior transfer pledge, Mary Della performed all her offices or special work with such care and efficiency that the chapter members have elected her as president of the house for the spring term. She was chosen by the campus men as the most beautiful co-ed at Stanford. Starting as a reporter on the Stanford Daily, she has recently attained the position of night editor, one of the highest offices to be gained, and a fairly rare honor for women. Utah Alpha Elizabeth Ida Dern, initiated into Utah A in April, 1933, is the daughter of former Governor George H. Dern of Utah, and now Secretary of War in President Franklin D. Roosevelt's Cabinet. Elizabeth remained in Salt Lake City in order to finish her sophomore year at the University of Utah ; and this chapter is particularly happy in being able to initiate her as she expects to be in Washington next year. Mary Alice Meagher graduated from the Law School of the University of Utah in 1932. She has the distinction of being a member of the firm "Seare, Meagher, and Seare" Salt Lake City, which is reputed to be the only women's law firm. Her pre-legal schooling was at St. Mary's in the Woods, Indiana, and George Washington University. She is also a talented pianist, having been a student in the Music Department of St. Mary's on the Wasatch while attending Law School. Mary Alice is a member of (1) A A, Women's International Legal Fraternity. J. \ \ "THE A LAST fall six Pi Phis of Alberta A interested in basketball decided to enter the House League, under the name of "The Arrows." Under the splendid management of the captain, Gwen Nixon, the team carried off the E. Bakewell Trophy. These Pi Phis en joyed keen competition at the games. The team consisted of: centre, Mary OWS" Macbeth; forwards, Gwen Nixon, Hazel Wilkinson, Jean Irving; guards, Margaret MacDougall, Margaret Smith. This is the first year that the E. Bake-well Trophy has been offered and the chapter is very proud of its team for having captured it. We hope the girls will continue their good work next term and retain the trophy. NE VS7 S M LITTLE PIGE C*j N Edited by MARY COOPER FROST THE SCHOOL The bank of Sevierville, in Sevierville, Tennessee, with which the Settlement School has been doing business for seven or eight years closed its doors on January 20. In this bank we carried an account for the Arrow Craft as well as one for the general running expenses of the school. Arrow Craft has, in round figures, $3600 tied up in the bank and the school $246. No statement has been issued by the banking department as to the probability of this bank's reopening or as to its financial condition. At the present time we are doing business with the Sevier County Bank, which is carrying on business with no restrictions. The bulk of the Settlement School funds, which amounts to $1400 at present, is carried in the First National Bank of Pasadena, which opened for business on March 14, without restrictions. (Signed) GRACE POST Treasurer of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School Grand Council and the Settlement School Committee have very carefully considered the problems of the school and have made a survey of every phase of its work. We did not find it necessary to cut down on the activities during this school year which was so nearly over when the bank closed, but we haveoutlined curtailments for next. We feel we have the loyalty and interest of the alumnae and the active chapters, and with their support the work in Gatlin-burg can continue. There has never been a time when we needed the devotion of Pi Phis any more than we do now, and we believe you will continue to work for the school just as loyally as you have worked during the past twenty years. Labelle Allen, manager of Arrow Craft, has received many letters from clubs telling her that they were in-creasing their efforts to sell Arrow Craft products. With this spirit to en-courage them, the workers will succeed in their undertakings, and the progress of the shop will not be impeded. Many families in the community depend for support almost entirely upon their weaving and basketry. The money which clubs and active chapters give to the school is sent to Grace Post, Treasurer Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, through their respective Province Vice-Presidents. On behalf of the school, the Settlement School Committee asks the fraternity to continue the work built up in the mountains of southeastern Tennessee. (Signed) FANKIE C. HILL Chairman Pi Beta Phi Settlement School Committee NO, WE'RE NOT! The State of Tennessee provides elementary school education in rural districts; hence, the grade teachers at the Settlement School are on the county payroll. (This actually means that theyare paid in warrants.) The county has also been paying the Settlement School annually about $195 toward the fuel bill for the grade building. Yet even with this monetary assistance, the Pi </p>
      <pb ref="arr4940445_0002" seq="02" n="446-447  "/>
       <p>446 THE MA Beta Phi Settlement School staff has been and is expending a tremendous amount of energy on the elementary school. We are not giving up our philanthropic work in Tennessee. However, it has long been the opinion of Miss Evelyn Bishop, the director, that since the county is really required to provide elementary schooling for its children, the fraternity should more and more turn its attention to the high school and THE HEALTH CENTE' ARROW vocational work that cannot be provided in any other way. Believing Miss Bishop was right and feeling that the community should have ample notice of the contemplated change, the Settlement School Commit-tee at the 1932 meeting voted to in-form the school district that Pi Beta Phi hoped soon to turn over the elementary work to the community and to devote itself entirely to advanced training. OF ZETA TAU ALPHA I* \ By SHIRLEY KREASAN KRIEG, Editor of "Themis" Long before the recent presidential election coined the term "the forgotten man," Z T A began its work in the "forgotten mountains" of Virginia, home state of the fraternity, as a memorial to its founders. Health Center, a picturesque log cabin in Curren Valley, Smyth County, serves as head-quarters for a registered nurse who travels in a car bearing the initials ZTA. The next units planned are a school of crafts and a hospital room. Zeta's nurse officiates at "bornins" makes day or night calls anywhere along the mountain trails; holds tonsil, dental, anti-typhoid, tubercular, and pre-school clinics; toothbrush drills; inspects school children; holds classes in home hygiene, sewing, and cooking. She also conducts sales of old clothing which, in order not to pauperize the people, is offered at ridiculously small sums. Zetas from all over the country donate old and new clothing, and people walk many miles to attend Health Center sales, parties, and clinics. In thesummer recreational workers are added to the staff. The children down this way have not even known how to play. Since 1929 there have been 2147 calls made, since 1930 more than 2148 children have been inspected, and there have been 3739 requests for clothing. In one school of 118 pupils the Zeta nurse found nine normal children generations of intermarrying, deprivation, and hardships have taken their toll. Christmas donations from Zetas are always heavy, and since 1929 more than 1100 individuals have been re-membered with useful gifts and necessities. Nowhere in the United States is there a people more interesting than these original Americans whose ancestors just "dropped off" into the secluded mountain hollows there to be engulfed, receding farther and farther within themselves and farther from the great outside world. Their story is picturesque, but pitiful. Zeta's work will take time, courage, and patience. MY EVENING SCHOOL WORK By JESSIE BRANHAM Miss Jessie Branham, who has been teaching home economics at Gatlinburg this year, is a recent graduate of the University of Tennessee and is a member of A A A. I organized in October four classes for evening school work. Older girls ofthe grammar grades and others no longer in school come to the classes which, strangely enough, do not meet in the evening but in the afternoon. Miss Evelyn was interested in carrying o. this work into some communities THE MAY ARROW 447 where there had been no such classes before. I organized one group in the Glades, which is about five miles from Gatlinburg. The eleven girls who formed it seemed intensely interested in the work and have, I think, proved to be my best class. The attendance has been good and the cooperation excel-lent. The school where we meet is a little one-room building with a big stove in the middle of the floor and an assortment of long battered desks. The one teacher has all the children, from the beginners to the eighth graders. On Monday afternoons when I take my class to one side of the room, he continues with his work on the other. I started here with a sewing unit. The girls first made aprons and blouses from flour and sugar sacks. We made an excellent cutting table by turning two desks back to back. The girls were very eager to have a cooking class. At first this seemed utterly impossible, for there was no equipment. I could not even take with me the things I wouldneed, because the roads were impassable so much of the time that I had to make the trips on horseback. When a woman who weaves for the Arrow Craft shop and lives near the school consented to let us use her kitchen, we were delighted. My problems were not solved though, for this kitchen offered little equipment. The makeshifts I had to use were quite funny; for ex-ample, we made a dandy double boiler by fitting a small lard bucket into the top of the teakettle. The girls bring the materials from home for cooking, and I have yet to have a girl forget the things asked of her. This proves convincingly that they are interested in the work. I have had three similar classes in other schools, two of them in one-room buildings; each has offered interesting problems. Three weeks ago I started my fifth class, one in clothing construction with the women here in Gatlin-burg. This one will continue until the close of the high school on April 21. AR \ OW C h\ AFTE is \ S Because of Labelle Allen's illness and absence from Gatlinburg the usual page devoted to the Arrow Crafters has had to be omitted from the May issueof the ARROW. However, the production of attractive and inexpensive articles is being expanded. F0 \ THE JUNE By HELEN DOLL TOTTLE, Maryland A 1*'\ 1 IDE "Yes," said Aunt Elizabeth, in answer to a neighbor's question as they met at the village drugstore, "the wed-ding and the honeymoon are over and Anne's gone to housekeeping in Haver-ford." "Plenty of wedding presents too, I guess, to help furnish her home?" "Well, hardly," was Miss Elizabeth's retort. "Silver and glassware are what 'most everybody gives the bride nowadays, and they're something you can get too much of. Why, Anne took with herall the glass and silver she could ever use and still there were two barrels of such presents left behind in her father's cellar." This conversation set me thinking why not buy the new homemaker some-thing individual and artistic, a present not likely to be duplicated? The Arrow Craft Shop at Gatlinburg is full of suggestions for gifts of this kind, and whether you wish to spend two, five, or twenty dollars, there are exquisite things for every room in the </p>
      <pb ref="arr4940445_0003" seq="03" n="448-449  "/>
       <p>448 THE MAY ARROW house. Such articles carefully selected years to come. By no stretch of the imwith reference to the bride's taste in agination could you picture them stowed color and design will be a delight for away in a musty cellar. WEAVING MEETING DAY IN GATLINBURG By WINOGENE B. REDDING, Teacher of Weaving Weaving Meeting days are big days in Gatlinburg. They come once a month, on the second Wednesday. Early in the morning the faithful fiveand-six-mile-away weavers begin to arrive, taking advantage of meeting day to bring in their weaving and get a new supply of material. While these meetings are intended primarily for the forty-six women who weave at home for the Arrow Craft Shop of the Pi Beta Phi School, they are open to all, and many are glad of the opportunity to come. By one o'clock in the afternoon the weaving room is full, and our meetings begin. We sing from the Old Harp sometimes; other days we try ballads, but more often old friends living miles apart would rather just sit and visit for a little while. Our weaving meetings have years of history behind them, for their growth has been gradual. Eight years ago the weavers were invited to the Teachers Cottage for a tea. A few brave ones at-tended and enjoyed it so much that they asked to have another the next year. We had a coffee the following spring which was much more successful as far as refreshments were concerned. The third year we tried a few informal meetings, giving general talks on weaving. From then on the meetings became more regular; the women began to look forward to them as they grew more accustomed to gathering at the school. By that time we had acquired a new high school building and in it a lovely large weaving room and office which the women consider their own private domain. The bashful ones began to come, irregularly to be sure; but it was an encouraging beginning. For the last three years the meetings have been well attended and have become one of the social events in the Burg. Last fall the group organized under the name of the Gatlinburg Weavers' Guild. Programs for the entire year were worked out and mimeographed copies distributed. Until this year we have not departed from the realm of weaving for our talks, and so we decided to make the meetings more general in character and selected a variety of subjects. The plan has met with the hearty approval of the women. Four meetings during the year have been on weaving, with one of them devoted to the use of color in weaving. In November we had one of the staff from the Division of Extension of the University of Tennessee give a talk on storage and closet space in the home, a timely subject in this town where you see a new house almost every time you look out of the window. We broke all precedents in January by inviting the men folks. Gatlinburg is to have a curb market next summer, and we used our wide-awake and representative weaving group to sponsor the project and push it through. Miss Williams, the curb market specialist from the university, who is helping to organize the market, came up to this meeting and presented the plans. The school class in agriculture had worked out a vegetable garden plan for this locality which we mimeographed and gave out by the dozens hoping in this way to encourage syslematic planting. The February meeting was our finest yet. We had our first exhibit of weaving to show our women whose knowl THE MAY ARROW 449 edge of weaving had been confined to the work done in our own section. We had weaving from Sweden, a hand-woven smock from Russia, pieces from Mexico, a Navajo rug, an old jacquard coverlet, weaving from sister schools in the mountains, but best of all, Miss Clementine Douglass of the Spinning Wheel, who told us about her interesting journeys among weavers in Egypt, Greece, and Italy. She brought weaving from all those countries, too, tricky little looms, and even a three thousand year old piece of handwoven mummy cloth. How eyes popped out and ears wagged to catch every word! A terrific blizzard didn't keep the women home that day, not even the farthest ones. That was a never-to-be-forgotten weaving meeting, and every woman carried away a new inspiration and pride in her work. In March our agriculture teacher gave a talk on gardening to follow our garden plans that were given out in January. Now we are looking forward to two meetings on weaving, with the women selecting the subjects. In April the eighth-grade girls will exhibit the weaving they have done in class and have a style show of their handwovendresses. June will be our finale with a picnic lunch and Miss Margaret Ambrose, division supervisor of home demonstration agents, to give an inspirational talk to the women, as she did last year. Oh, yes, the women take turns serving refreshments too. Sometimes they play games when days are long and the women can stay until three o'clock and still get home before dark. Are our meetings worthwhile and do they fill a need in our community . We think so. The Weavers Guild and the P.T.A. are the only organized groups in our village, which is growing by leaps and bounds. Civic improvement will be a big issue locally in the next few years, and here are two groups of women beginning to realize they can do things. They are ready to undertake local problems beyond their weaving and school and have discovered that there is power in organization. Who knows where our weaving meetings will end? It is only through the interest and cooperation of the women that our meetings have been made so successful. Our outlook is bright, our faith in the future is unlimited, and our courage undaunted. OUR FOUNDERS (Continued from page 432) Fanny Whitenack Libbey was born in Berwick, Illinois, in 1848. When she was sixteen, her parents moved to Monmouth so that she could attend college and still be at home. While in college she was well known because of being one of the twelve girls who first wore the Golden Arrow of H B (I) . She was married in 1872 to Mr. Howard Libbey, she says "one of the best men ever." Their first home, for two years, was in Kansas, then in Red Wing, Minnesota, until Mr. Libbey's death in 1908. Since then, she and her youngest daughter have made their home in either Yakima or Seattle, Washington. This daughter has recently passed on and Mrs. Libbey has moved to Lake City, Minnesota. She is and has ever been keenly interested in the church and in the comfort and welfare of her family and in the happiness of others. She dearly loves H B and appreciates all it has done for her. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



