<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr4130401_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Geare , Dorothy Smallwood</name></author>
                        <author><name>Dewell, Barbara</name></author>
                        <author><name>Taylor, Harmo</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>March 1925</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr4130401_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">March 1925</date>, News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Geare , Dorothy Smallwood</name></author>
                        <author><name>Dewell, Barbara</name></author>
                        <author><name>Taylor, Harmo</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 401-407</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">37</note>
                        <note type="Folder">6</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 41, Number 3 (March 1925), Pages 401-407.</note>
			<note type="document">arr4130401_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Extracts From the Diary of Samuella Pepyless, a Novice at the Settlement School; A Visit to Gatlinburg</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Founding of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1909-1927</item>
                                <item>Teachers</item>
                                <item>Facilities</item>
                                <item>Living conditions</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr4130401_0001" seq="01" n="400-401  "/>
       <p>400 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI E. R. NICHOLS husband of Elsie Stubbs Nichols, Indiana A, brother of Mabel Nichols, Indiana A, is a professor of debating in the university at Redlands, California. He was the organizer of the first debating fraternity in the United States and is a past grand president of it. F. W. BLACKM.AR father of Dorothy Blackmar, Kansas A, is a professor of Sociology at the University of Kansas of which institution he is a graduate. Mr. Blackmar has written several texts of Sociology and is a member of Phi Kappa Psi. DR. JEANETTE THROCKMORTON cousin of Mora Throckmorton, Iowa B, is noted for her lectures. NOTICE TO ALL PI BETA PHIS Whenever you change your address for THE ARROW please fill out the following form and send it at once to the Circulation Manager, Mrs. C. E. Temple (Florence Clum), 231 N. Mary St., Lancaster, Penn. Please PRINT or TYPEWRITE Present date Chapter Date of initiation Maiden Name Married Name FORMER ADDRESS Name Street and Number City and State PRESENT ADDRESS for ARROW. Is this permanent or temporary? Name Street and No City and State .............................................. Signed. When sending announcement of marriage please add date of wedding, husband's name, Alma Mater, class and business. A change of address must reach the Circulation Manager ten days before the next issue is scheduled to appear in order to be effective. NEws FROM LITTLE PIGEON 401 NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON Edited by DOROTHY SMALLWOOD GEARE (Mrs. R. W.), Columbia A (Note. In response to an S. O. S. when the regular copy for this department failed to arrive, the teachers at the School came to the rescues The Editor.) EXTRACTS FROM THE DIARY OF SAMUELLA. PEPYLESS, A NOVICE AT THE SETTLEMENT SCHOOL MONDAY, AUGUST 18, FIRST DAY OF SCHOOL Talked for half the class period on the importance of cooking and sewing, then asked a pupil to tell in her own words the most out-standing points. Received the answer, "I don't know." Asked her if she paid attention and she said, "I reckon not." TUESDAY, AUGUST 19. Labored several hours over the lesson plans on the care of the house. Intended to teach use and care of washing machines, electric irons, etc. Imagine how I felt when I found people all washed their clothes in the river, and ironed them, if they were ironed, with flat irons heated in the fireplace. Threw away all the lesson plans I had made. TUESDAY, SEPTEMBER 25 Have not had a chance to write in this book for weeks. The Gatlinburg Community Fair has kept us simply "scratching gravel" as these people might say. We all have been working a "sight on earth." Besides helping arrange for the whole Economics exhibit for our own Fair, have been bumping over Tennessee rocky roads to other fairs in order to judge the cooking and sewing exhibits. At Pine Grove School Fair one woman followed me everywhere with her hands full of canned goods talking a blue streak; tried to explain to me why her things were so superior to all other ladies and incidentally why she should get all the ribbons. What I thought I had better not put in print. THURSDAY, AUGUST 21 Decided to have scalloped corn for lunch. My high school cooking class prepares the noon-day meal for teachers and dormitory girls. The corn was not done and the biscuits were soggy. From the amount of food left the meal must have been a huge success. We really do </p>
      <pb ref="arr4130401_0002" seq="02" n="402-403  "/>
       <p>402 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI have good meals, though. I don't want you to think my girls can't do things, for they really can cook. They can cook roast chicken with dressing, and make biscuits that melt in your mouth. They have learned all about vitamins and calories and can plan a meal fit for even the Committee to sit before. Cooking isn't the only thing they can do either. They sew like a streak. They have made bloomers and aprons, curtains for the cooking laboratory, and are ready to begin on a summer dress. WEDNESDAY, JANUARY 14 Just home from first cooking class in Sugarlands. Supper over when I got here and it was dark. But oh, what an experience! Twelve miles horseback, through slippery mud, to teach a class to make corn-starch pudding. But the pudding was good, both cooking and sewing classes enjoyed it and will be able to make it at home because they have the ingredients necessary. BARBARA. THURSDAY, OCTOBER 9 "Have you fixed your pack?" "My soul, what do I know about fixing a blanket pack." "Well, you have to get it done tonight, for Jack is going to take them to the Cherokee Orchard in the morning. And then we will get them tomorrow afternoon before we start up LaConte." FRIDAY, OCTOBER 10 My blanket is rolled with potatoes, coffee and potted meat in it. I know I never will be able to climb under its weight. As soon as school is out we start the five mile walk to the Cherokee Orchard. FRIDAY NIGHT, 12 O'cLoex We started off in high spirits, mine began to grow limp on the way to the Orchard. Apples there revived me, then we left all civilization behind and plunged on up LaConte. Our party consisted of all the new teachers and Mae, Matte, Jack, Jim, Rellie and Fred, They all encouraged inc so by saying how great I was. Dark descended on our party and hand in hand we stumbled up the horribly dark path with pines towering above. Two of the boys went on ahead to start the camp fire. After, falling down several times we finally reached camp. While the boys cooked supper we dragged in pine boughs to make the earth seem less hard and cruel as a couch of rest. We had no more than finished supper than we heard a mountain wind. Frankly, I was simply scared to death. The boys held a conference and then came back to the camp fire with pine torches and said we would have to descend the mountain. We almost cried and said we didn't care if a dead tree did fall on us. I was so tired I knew it wouldn't hurt NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 403 me, but Jack was firm so down the mountain we went. The boys have built another fire in an open field and here we sit all huddled up together. Nobody can sleep. We can see the camp fire of some of the school boys who are going to climb LaConte, too. SATURDAY, LATER IN THE DAY I don't know what time it is, what day or anything. Every bone in my body aches and I just want my little cot and a hot bath. We left the open field at three in the morning, when the mountain wind died down. We got back to our first camp up the mountain, where we had left our supplies, and had breakfast. As soon as the first rays of light filtered through the woods we started on up the mountain. The Falls were lovely but the path so muddy that climbing was most difficult. After we left the falls I just couldn't keep up with the others-Maggie and I trudged on with Jim and Rellie fairly pulling us up. We had to rest after every half dozen steps. About ten thirty we got so hungry that the boys finally had mercy on us, let us rest awhile and eat hunks of bread cut with a pocket knife and potted meat that they called "spotted dog." Nothing could have made me stop eating those for I was too tired and hungry to care. Jim dragged me the last steep lap of the trail and ended all my chances of ever saying I climbed La Conte. The lean-to looked like heaven. We ate lunch and then took the steepest of all trails to the top. I am up here now and it is lovely. We can see into North Carolina, see Gatlinburg and our little white church shining out from the green background. We are going down to the camp for supper and then come up to enjoy the moonlight. OCTOBER 12, SUNDAY MORNING I will have to spend the rest of my life here. I didn't sleep a wink all night and had to walk up and down in front of the fire to try to limber up. Pain-I never knew such agony. I would rather have ten operations than have to place one foot in front of the other. I simply can't walk all the way home. OCTOBER 12, SUNDAY AFTERNOON Miss Evelyn had the truck meet us near the orchard, God bless her. I've had a' hot bath and am in bed ready for sleep after being awake for sixty hours. HARMO, WEDNESDAY, DECEMBER 3 Nobody ever tells me what I am supposed to do. Most of the time that pleases me but it did come as somewhat of a surprise to me today </p>
      <pb ref="arr4130401_0003" seq="03" n="404-405  "/>
       <p>404 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI when someone asked me if I had completed my plans for the Christmas entertainment. I looked blank for a minute but finally managed to say "not quite." Something simply has to be done about it. FRIDAY, DECEMBER 5 I am more in the dark than ever about that Christmas affair. Everybody is worried to death but nothing has been done. Maybe if I let it wait over until Monday I will have an inspiration. The cow bell is ringing for a basketball game and the players will be waiting impatiently for our arrival so they can begin the game. FRIDAY, DECEMBER 12 My poor diary has been sadly neglected but at least we have made a start. Mrs. Duffield came to the rescue by suggesting a musical pro-gram for the older children, and what is still better, has offered to train them. We are also planning some beautiful tableaux. Everything is settled and life seems worth while. SATURDAY, DECEMBER 13 Spent all morning making costumes for the angels to wear in one of the tableaux. The wings were a complete failure so I became discouraged and stopped to go down to Eli McCarter's blacksmith shop to see about some fire dogs .he is making for me. They were finished but the problem of getting them home confronted me next. He settled it by promising to make a box and pack them for an extra charge of fifteen cents! TUESDAY, DECEMBER 16 School has been pushed into the background since a stage is being erected in my room and every available moment has to be used for practice. The tableau of the Three Wise Men promises to be a great success. THURSDAY, DECEMBER 18 This whole thing is going to be a complete failure and I don't care. I never worked so hard over anything nor had so many things go wrong. Everyone blames me for everything. I couldn't avoid being absent from class this morning. Just as I started over to school I was called back to see about sending my trunk. Of course I had to show the men where it was. It was a terribly muddy day and since they were thoughtful enough to offer to remove their shoes in order not to get the house dirty I thought I should not complain about having to wait. Then when I did go they told me the Wise Men had refused to perform. I just sat down and cried. What was I to do? Frankly I never had anything to do with Wise Men before but my training up here has taught me to rise to any situation. NEWS Fnom LITTLE PIGEON 405 FRIDAY, THE NINETEENTH The Wise Men did perform. Everyone was kind enough to say the program was a huge success, which made me feel good, even if I did realize its defects. Jack is ready to take us to Sevierville, so goodbye and Merry Christmas. MAGGIE. FRIDAY, P. M. Dear Diary: Final exams, have descended upon us. The girls in the chapter at home, would I know, feel themselves drawn closer to the Settlement School if they realized that the same affliction that is torturing them is also visiting us. Being buried in mud and examinations at the same time is almost too much for a person with only ordinary*self control. Speaking of being buried it was only less than ia: year ago that I announced my intention of applying for a position at the Settlement School. My roommate met the announcement with this very dampening reply :"My soul, you are not going to bury yourself in that mud hole for a year, are you?" Buried, did she say? Well, in spite of what I said about mud and examinations a minute ago I am as far from being buried as I ever expect to be. How could I feel buried with such answers as I have been receiving, coming in on examination papers. Here are some good ones: never appear greedy at the table. Sherman was a generul he marched to the see. do not raise up out of your chair to reach food ask for it. An exclamatory sentence is one that tells you to hurry home. SATURDAY, A. M. Planned to rest Plans frustrated by telegram announcing that whoever it is that is supposed to send in the Settlement School news to the ARROW has departed' to without remembering to perform her functions. So we have all dropped everything to gather together some news. Among other things you have been confiscated, Dear Diary. Well, another year I guess I will have a lapse of memory, too. Goodbye Dear Diary. SAMUELLA PEPYLESS, alias, BARBARA DEWELL, HARMO TAYLOR, MAGGIE WHITE, HELEN BARRETT. HELEN. </p>
      <pb ref="arr4130401_0004" seq="04" n="406-407  "/>
       <p>406 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI The New Barn at the Settlement School A VISIT TO GATLINBURG Extracts from a letter written to the Chattanooga, Tenn., alumnae club by Mrs. Noel Cardwell (Mary Louise Beckham, Tennessee A) : We drove one afternoon up to our Settlement School at Gatlinburg. I think perhaps the alumnie and active girls might be interested in our impressions and in these kodak pictures which Noel took. Dr. Bishop, President of Murphy Collegiate Institute, where we were housed at Sevierville, is the father ,of Miss Evelyn Bishop, Read Resident ,of our School. When he discovered that I was a PI Phi, he said I must go up to the. School and of icourse I was glad to know I could go, so Friday afternoon we drove-up. I say "up," advisedly. We passed through beautiful mountain scenery, going over ,a narrow road with ever so many turns. On one side is a high wall of rock--on the other side one looks way down to see water trickling over rocks. We passed an ,old water-wheel seemingly not in use. Again, we wondered how in the world the farmer cared for a crop of corn or wheat perched right on top of 'a steep hill. Occasionally we passed a typical mountain home. I have to hold myself in restraint, as I tend to wax "poetic," for it is a lovely drive. Just as I start to soar up, however, I remember a bump and come back to earth. Gatlinburg is made up of a few scattered houses two ,stores, a hotel where town folks come for summer vacations and the Settlement School. At least that is all we saw. NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 407 We found Miss Bishop at the Teachers' Cottage and she very kindly showed us around. We have just cause for feeling proud of our School. I was surprised at the modern conveniences everywhere. The buildings are frame painted tan with dark 'brown 'trimmings. They looked fresh, as though they had just received a coat of paint. We have 'about one hundred acres and what is not used for buildings is farmed by the boys. The girls do some of the cooking ,and housework under stipervision. Everyone was very proud of the barn. It is a beautiful barn, modern in every way. Downstairs there are stalls for the horses, store-rooms and other barn necessities and conveniences. I'm not .sure of barn terminology but this is a "grand" barn. The loft or upstairs, has been converted into an assembly room. There is a moving picture machine and screen up there and a large radio outfit, this last be-longing to one of the teachers. The loft is also used for an indoor basketball court. We were there the week before School opened so preparations were going on. The basements of the 'dormitories were being stocked with winter supplies. In the bathroom were all modern conveniences but I do not know how the water is handled for that as we drank from a well. In the office which is in the Teachers' Cottage, we saw some of the work of the girls: rugs, basketry, cloth which they had woven. There were woolen threads dyed lovely colors by means of juices from tree barks. In the hospital we were introduced 'to Miss Higginbotham, the nurse, who wore a white uniform. The 'atmosphere is very professional in the hospital. There is a rather complete operating room, baby scales, and other equipment which show that the needs of the community are being taken care of. The boys' dormitory or rather the cottage used for that purpose is not with the others but nearby. It is a green cottage owned by Miss Bishop and located on the hill above the hotel. The boys go to the main plant for meals. They need dormitories. The pictures tell the rest better than I can. The trip was very inspiring. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



