<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr4730331_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Curtis, Blanche Charlton</name></author>
                        <author><name>Smith, Don</name></author>
                        <author><name>Allen, LaDelle</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>February 1931</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr4730331_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">February 1931</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Curtis, Blanche Charlton</name></author>
                        <author><name>Smith, Don</name></author>
                        <author><name>Allen, LaDelle</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 330-334</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">38</note>
                        <note type="Folder">6</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 47, Number 3 (February 1931), Pages 330-334.</note>
			<note type="document">arr4730331_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">The Men at the Settlement School; Mattie Huff Pledged</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Agriculture</item>
                                <item>Weaving</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr4730331_0001" seq="01" n="330-331  "/>
       <p>'EAWAIvRAlv,ravP,avAlvnif,M11*,EW''WN %g4''Icit.''It491ciagotc4.91c4914'.9k49it'491cokii K 11 51 !,I)J AY W IEdited by Blanche Charlton Curtis Men at the Settlement School IT IS difficult, if not im-[e, to discuss the men and .nd their work at the Settle--School without including the masculine contingent as a You see in this most unusual 1together pleasant situation, our point of view, where the .(e so obviously in the minor-d hence very clannish, an aroncerning them and their must be very comprehensive elusive. nine boys who live at the :ory work on the farm out-F school hours under the di-of Ambrose Ogle, a former t in the early days of the and who is retained the year to attend to the immediate ision of the general farm These bus have the responof caring for the livestock nary, and the chores that are ary in farm work, keeping ildings and campus in order,. 11.g roads, walks, fences, etc., short are taught to do in the q'ficient manner those things ley will find necessary when .cquire farms of their own. Dys are allowed .fifteen cents ^ur for their work. This is :d to their expense account. of the boys more than earn way through school in this r. he all-day agriculture classes the twenty-six boys are given every opportunity to learn the best farming practices as' carried out on the Pi Phi farm. Every one of our two hundred apple trees are being pruned and sprayed by the boys in these classes. Hotbeds for the starting of early vegetables have been constructed, gates have been made and hung and a small shed for protecting our bee hives has been made. The classes have helped slaughter the hogs for our meat and have had charge of "curing" and packing the meat. Ingredients for feed rations for the dairy cows on the place have also been weighed out and mixed by the boys. In fact every opportunity is taken to teach the boys improved managerial and operative jobs on the farm. We have had many calls from the parents of these boys to prune and spray their fruit trees. Very often a neighbor has a sick cow, or horse or hog and asks us to come around and help him and "bring your class along." All this adds materially to their learning and experience. Then, too, we have the Pi Beta Phi chapter of the Future Farmers of Tennessee. This is an organiza tion of the boys who are enrolled in vocational agriculture classes. This F.F.T. is a part of the national organization, Future Farmers of America. There are more than a hundred chapters with a The February ARROW 331 AT WORK total of three thousand members in the high schools of Tennessee. The annual state convention meets each, April at the state capitol building in Nashville. Our chapter was represented last year by Paul Johnson and Muncie Houser. It is to be represented again this year by two delegates to be elected from the chapter at large. The outstanding thing done by the Pi Beta Phi chapter this year is the loving cup which they have offered to the best-all-around high school girl. The factors of scholarship, character, activities, deportment and attitude are taken into consideration in the selection of the winner which is to be made by a committee from the faculty. The cup will be awarded annually and the name of the winner engraved on it. This is the first award of merit ever offered at the school and the Pi Beta Phi chapter is the first in the state to offer such an award. Last year classes in poultry raising were conducted at Laurel Lick and Wears Valley schools. More than thirty boys were enrolled in these classes. About half of thisnumber now have small flocks of pure bred Barred Rock chickens hatched from eggs of our school flock. One of these classes is being conducted at Laurel Lick again this year. Work with small shop tools is being carried on and the boys have made and painted small articles such as bird houses. Just now they are painting the interior of a spare room in the school building that is to be used for weekly classes in home economics. A farmers' class is beng held weekly in Wears Valley on the production of burley tobacco. The class has a membership of about twenty-five adult farmers. Last October' and November the mountain farmers in the immediate vicinity of Gatlinburg, under the direction of the agriculture department, bought cooperatively twelve tons of wheat bran and cotton seed meal for cattle feed at a material saving. We are now considering the cooperative buying of commercial fertilizer this spring. It is hoped that this will grow into a farmers' club with a permanent organization. </p>
      <pb ref="arr4730331_0002" seq="02" n="332-333  "/>
       <p>The February ARROW new principal, Mr. King, has le confidence of his faculty quiet and efficient manner oh he goes about his work. ee afternoons a week, after hours, you will find him tun-his Wine and Blue basketichine for a week-end game. an has been very successful and the Pi Beta Phi teams own for their spirit of fair d high type of sportsman ou have not heard of Mr. and his fine work at the for the past eight years you a good Pi Phi. His latest r, as you probably know, is roduction of mountain fur-in our native woods, walnut, and maple. He works five ,,ularly in his shop and has in drawing and furniture on Saturday morning. The other two men of our "family" are Arlie Watson, who tends the furnaces in winter and supervises the gardens in summer, and Ernest (Shot) Reagan, the trouble shooter, without whom we would have been minus water, heat and lights many a time. Just now, beside the other activities already mentioned, we are getting in readiness to give our faculty play which will be presented to a critical public in the near future. Then, too, Mr. Mattil is busy several nights a week with his neighborhood basketball team. What next? No one knows, but you may be assured that something new and interesting is just around the corner when you are a man at the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School. DON SMITH Vocational Agricultural Teacher Del!e Allen who is in charge of the Arrowcraft shop, can be of great help ou in anything from interior decorating to planning your next season's ward-. Write Miss Allen about the stunning woven suitings and coats for summer not see duplicates anywhere.-EDIToR. T IMES have changed have homespuns. We often rselves feeling sorry for our :others because they had to Lomespuns. I wonder if our hildren will feel sorry for us they learn that some of us hornespuns. . I think not if they see the homespuns wore. II of Scotland you will find r, sheerer wools than those or weaving the dress ma-at the Arrow Craft Shop. In uch of the yarn used is imnot by us, but by the firm which we buy. The heavier ils adapt themselves well to Ind suits, while the lighter s are used for dresses. With the spring fashion forecast showing suits and coats, "for town and country," made of the imported tweeds, we thought that every Pi Phi should be told of the lovely fabrics made at the school suitable for the current fashions. These materials are "all wool and a yard wide" and come in browns, tans, blues, grays, greens, and most any other color you might care for. Since the dyers of the yarns used first dyed yarns to mend valuable old tapestries, one would naturally expect only the richest and deepest tones, and shades in the colors. The material may be woven with or without borders for trimmings. Where no borders are wanted for the outside tiny ones are made to The February ARROW 333 LA DELLE ALLEN trim the inside of the coat which adds a very charming effect. For those who spend their summers at the seashore or in the mountains nothing could be more practical or lovely than the soft afghan material in the pastel col-ors (and darker ones too) for sports dresses, skirts, and suits. A jacket made of all-over pattern material, woven with many colors, is an addition to any wardrobe. It can be worn with so many different dresses. These materials are all woven to order. The dress patterns with big borders for trimming, average about five yards or more in length, and are $25. The all-over pattern material for coats and jackets .is $5.00 a yard: the plain dress material $3.50 .a yard. If only very narrow borders are wanted for a bit of trimming, they may be had for a small additional cost. Small samples will be sent on request. LA DELLE ALLEN Mattie Huff Pledged MATTIE HUFF of Little Pigeon is pledged to Iowa P of Pi Beta Phi at Ames, Iowa. A graduate of our own Settlement School at Gatlinburg, is soon to wear the arrow. To those who know the school as it is today, this fact may not seem so unusual. But to those Pi Phi pioneers who searched out the darkest spot on the educational map of the United States, and who some twenty-one years ago, traveled those muddy, almost impassable roads in search of a location for a center of learning, to those pioneers and to many others the pledging of Mattie Huff to Pi Beta Phi, will bring a real thrill. Mattie was pledged not because she is one of our graduates but because she is charming, capable, and especially desirable as a fraternity member. She was rushed by other national organizations on the campus, but chose to wear the arrow. From the very beginning of the Settlement School, two of its staunchest friends have been Mat-tie's parents, Mr. and Mrs. A. J. Huff. It was Mr. Huff who begged our first investigators to locate in Gatlinburg, in order that his children and his neighbors' children might have educational advantages. It was Mrs. Huff, who with poise and graciousness, assisted the </p>
      <pb ref="arr4730331_0003" seq="03" n="3334-335  "/>
       <p>334 The February ARROW MATTIE HUFF Iowa I' Pledge school staff at the "opening" of the Jennie Nichol Memorial Hospital, and who has helped the school in every way that her frail health would permit. With extensive timbering interests and as owner of the Mountain View Hotel at Gatlinburg, Andrew Huff has always been influential in the community. He has always stood for the highest type of citizen-ship .and has been a most worthy and loyal supporter of our school. His devotion to his family is paramount. And although he and his wife personally supervised the running of the hotel, they maintained a cottage home in a sheltered"holler" where they might be alone with their family whenever possible. Each year the Huff interests have thrived, until today the Mountain View Hotel is the largest and best-equipped resort of its kind for miles around. And it is furnished with as many things as could be obtained from our Arrow Craft Shop. In the early days of the Settlement School, attendance was greatly effected because the children had to stop out to grub briars or to help put in the crop and also, because many of the mountaineers were still suspicious of our intentions. It was then that we needed all the moral support possible. Andrew Huff saw the need, and used to carry his small four year old daughter, Mattie, to school each day in order to swell the numbers. And there in the big school room, with a Pi Beta Phi pennant on the wall above her head, Mattie learned to read and write. She was always a good student and progressed rapidly. Upon reaching the higher grades, she became editor of the Wine and Blue department of the Gatlinburg News. After graduation from the school, she finished her high school work in one year at Virginia Interrnont, at Bristol ; and later, completed two years at Maryville College. Then came the decision to enter the Iowa State College at Ames. Pi Beta Phi is proud to welcome Mattie Huff . In Me oria ANITA ALLEGRA WELCH Indiana r After graduating from the high school of Lawrence, Michigan, and attending a preparatory school in Terre Haute, Indiana, for a year, Anita Welch entered Butler University at Indianapolis in September, 1917. She was pledged at once to Pi Beta Phi and initiated October 5, 1918. She was active in campus affairs and her vivacious, sunny disposition endeared her to a host of friends. Her home was a rendevouz where Pi Phis always found a welcome. Illness forcing her to leave college before graduation, she spent a year in California and recovered sufficiently to accept a position in the Ball State Teachers College at Muncie, Indiana. At the end of a year, however, she was obliged to give up her work permanently, and the succeeding years were filled with continued but unavailing efforts to regain her health. The details of her funeral were planned according to her written instructions. She was buried at Muncie, beside her mother and her sister, Nympha Welch Stauf (Indiana r), whose deaths preceded hers by a short time. To the surviving father, sister, and brother, Pi Phi extends deep sympathy. For nearly ten years Anita's friends have watched with amazement her fortitude in the face of ever-increasing difficulties. There are those of us who will meet our future troubles with head held higher, remembering her coural will smile through our son membering her smile; w' never forget her loyalty ideals and thus be truer own. She has left a rich : of memories to those who lo MARIE KOEPKE Illinois H Marie Koepke, Wilmette, member of Illinois H the James Millikin University, I Illinois, was instantly kille ary 24. Her horse became ened and dashed madly into of a fast train. Services were held in di ter house. Although only a sophomoi chapter, Marie showed tru( loyalty and spirit. Her l will be truly missed. Sym: expressed to her bereaved and friends. ELLA DEWS OLIVER Oregon A Mrs. A. H. Oliver pass( January 1 at Tacoma, Was after an illness of twelve d lowing a major operation. Mrs. Oliver entered the sity of Oregon in 1915 a graduated in 1919 during time she was very active campus, serving as vice pre: the associated student be leading many women's ath tivities. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



