<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr4430631_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Curtis, Blanche Charlton</name></author>
                        <author><name>Bishop, Evelyn</name></author>
                        <author><name>Stoolman, Lois F.</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>February 1928</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr4430631_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">February 1928</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Curtis, Blanche Charlton</name></author>
                        <author><name>Bishop, Evelyn</name></author>
                        <author><name>Stoolman, Lois F.</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 631-640</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">37</note>
                        <note type="Folder">12</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 44, Number 3 (February 1928), Pages 631-640.</note>
			<note type="document">arr4430631_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Christmas at Little Pigeon; The New Building; Prof. James M. White; How to Make Money for the Settlement School</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Staff</item>
                                <item>Holidays</item>
                                <item>Funding</item>
                                <item>Facilities</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr4430631_0001" seq="01" n="630-631  "/>
       <p>30 THE ARROW of PI BETA PHI "The SorOrity Handbook," Tenth Edition, by Ida Shaw Mar-in, 5 Cobden St., Boston, Mass., has just come from the press. n the brief period between editions, two hundred thirty-six char grants have been made by women's fraternities. This hand-'ook contains statistics pertaining. to 210,000 Greek letter women a 44 organizations, of which 26 are academic and 18 professional. ,isted in the Index we find chapters devoted to "The Higher Ed-.cation of Women;'' "The Evolution of the Sorority System ;" The Mission of the Sorority ;" "Academic Sororities ;" "Profesional Sororities ;" "Necrology of Chapters ;" "Honorary Societs ;" "The American Association of University Women ;", "The '.,arnegie Foundation ;" "Statistical Data ;" "Men's Academic 1-a.ternities;" "Monthly Study Topics :" "The Greek Alphabet ;" nd the "Addenda." .. + + + "Discarding from Strength" in the December 24, 1927, issue f the Saturday Evening Post is from the pen of Mary Badger Vilson, New York B and District of Columbia A. It is a very n.tertaining story written in Miss Wilson's usual original and fasinating style. + + + "The Moon's Birthday," by Dorothy Rowe is expected soon mm the press of Macmillan and Co. + + + It is interesting to note that Paul Schofield, husband of aura Graves Schofield, Oklahoma A, was the scenario editor of Beau Geste," judged the best motion picture during the past tar. . + + + "The Lure of the Smoky Mountains" by Mason is an excelnt . book on the Southern Mountaineers. .-.:_ . . . . :.:+ + + . "Flooded Waters,.. a new novel by ,1/largaret Weymouth .ckson, Michigan A, began with the January, 1928, issue of , win Life. .: ..:.. : ..,i + T Florence S. Page (Mrs. Jacques), Illinois H, is. the author "The Jolly Juniors," a Christmas Ballad which appeared in December issue of Woman's Home Companion,. NEWS FROM. P..IIGI.:ON 631 NEWS FROM-L1TTLE PIGEON 1,11.. Edited by BLANCHE CHARLTON CURTIS (MRS. PERCE H.) 'ills.' 2525 Hillside Drive. Burlingame. Calif. ,, ,111, C11R.ISTMAS AT LITTLE PIGEON VER since Dell Gillette first told the story of Christmas to the children of Gatlinburg, the holiday season has been the most wonderful part of the year to the teachers and pupils of the Pi Phi School. For weeks before the day there is the excitement of the preparation in which everyone from the littlest kindergartner to the head resident joins with a will. To quote from Miss Bishop's last letter. It may seem a little odd to a good many to have all this preparation for an entertainment that is staged at nine o'clock, or earlier, in the morning, and a lighted Christmas tree that is never seen except by day. If you could be here, however, you would be much more reconciled. People come from such a distance and bring the little folks, usually in much rain and mud, and it is easier to contend with all this in the daylight than, by night. With this I am including a copy of our program but it gives little idea of the excitement, .the singing. the wonderful costumes concocted for kings, queens, soldiers, shepherds and wise Men. In the cantata the high school boys and girls did some part singing, which thrilled me, for until last year we have not been able to do much along that line. The children have lots of musical ability but no training except what little rote singing we do in assembly each morning. So when the boys boomed out on the bass and the girls chimed in with the alto, I was delighted. The singing was better than usual, due in no small measure to Alice Kiewit, who has drilled them whenever she could steal any time from her and their full schedule. I would like to give the list of those clubs and individuals sending Christmas boxes and checks but know that many prefer their names not mentioned. It was a lovely Christmas for all, the gifts </p>
      <pb ref="arr4430631_0002" seq="02" n="632-633  "/>
       <p>632 TEE, ARROW OF PI BETA PHI N FR.om I.,rrTI.P: PIGF.",ON ()33 were lovely, the checks ample to cover the expense of the treat for both Sugarlands and Gatlinburg School and to give candy and oranges to most of the young people in the audience. A big box containing 160 boxes of candy from the Kenilworth Sunday School in Chicago was much appreciated and what we have saved because of that I hope can go into a fund for a radio in the Sugarlands. Besides things, sent for the boys and girls there were gifts for the house and the teachers that were just lovely. An electric corn popper does look like a wonderful luxury up here and it is, but we use it all the time and that is true of some of our other luxuries that are sent us at Christmas time. And our Christmas greetings ! no matter that there is a great big pile, everyone has been looked over and read several times. This letter is really about the School Christmas, but Mrs. Dowell thinks that you would like to know about our own, so I am going to try to tell you. We always have our own tree in our cottage. As the church was going to have service in the morning we decided we would have more time to open our packages Christmas Eve, so we had a waffle supper in the living room and then began untieing ribbons and strings. Our family consisted of mother, Mrs. Dowell, Aunt Lizzie, Eva Hathaway, Miss Howard and a friend of hers, Lillie Reagan, Ernest Reagan and myself. I might explain that Lillie and "Shot" live here and are our right hand helpers all the time so we insisted on having them come down. I almost forgot to mention that Miss Cook had to be away that night but came in Christmas morning from Knoxville and our house is still bright with the lovely flowers she brought with her. After we had looked at our gifts and listened to the radio for a much longer time than we usually do, some of the family got sleepy, but Mrs. Dow-ell, Eva and stayed up for the Christmas service from a Washington cathedral, so it was morning sure enough when we turned out our lights. It was a great satisfaction to us to have a church service on Sun-day morning. One of our local men, Pinkney Ownby, gave us a good sermon and the young people sang Christmas hymns. At the close of the service an offering of canned fruit and of money was given for the Baptist Orphanage of this state. THE NEW BUILDING ROM the time she became a member of the settlement School Committee, Nita Hill Stark, saw the great need of a build ing that would provide an adequate auditorium, additional classrooms, and rooms for the vocational subjects. With k e e n breadth of vision she worked untiringly towards obtaining t h i s Luilding. Showing motion pictures wherever she went, talking of the splendid work at Gatlinburg, and doing everything possible to arouse interest in the School, she convinced alumni and co-workers of the absolute necessity for such a structure. It was her dream while she was chairman of the Committee and to her a great deal of the credit for the splendid new building should go. Without her enthusiasm and earnestness of purpose, this building might now be only a visionary plan instead of an almost completed structure capable of meeting the acute needs at Little Pigeon. In; writing of the new building "Miss Evelyn" says : If I were to try to tell the whole story of the Pi Beta Phi Industrial Building it would mean going back several years to when Miss Kate Miller was chairman and felt so strongly the need of room for the industrial work and of an auditorium and of the plans drawn up for her by Miss Aida Wilson. Then of dropping all talk of a new building for quite a time as things did not seem to be ready for it then. </p>
      <pb ref="arr4430631_0003" seq="03" n="634-635  "/>
       <p>634 THE ARROW OF PI BETA Plil A short time after that plans were made for a girls' dormitory, thinking that that would relieve some of the congestion, but again it did not seem wise to go ahead. When Mrs. Stark was appointed chairman the question of adequate room for the industrial departments came up again and I might add, with force! The Arrowcraft department was developing by leaps and bounds and there was no place to handle the business, or store the products, the little old schoolhouse down by the road had been outgrown by the agriculture and shop class-es, the weaving room had had its day of being in the log cabin and had been moved into a grocery store room. The boys were playing basketball in the new barn, the movies were in t h barn and the class rooms, not suitable for the various entertainments and speakings. Surely this explains to those who have feared we might be following the modern program of expensive school buildings that we have stayed away from a building program just as long as possible. I might add that when we have completed this building it will have been at a cost much less than a town building could have been built. Through Mr. and Mrs. Stark, Prof. James M. White of the University of Illinois drew plans for the building, not only with-out cost to us but at a great deal of time and expense to himself. The first ones were beautiful but alas, when we began getting estimates we found they would call for a building costing three times the amount we could think of spending. These plans were taken to Mr. Turner, a Knoxville builder and also a relative of Agnes Miller Turner, who was then on the Committee. As Mr. Turner says, "Agnes just would get wound up about that School and talk and talk and the first thing I knew she had me interested, too." Mr. Turner sat up the night through more than once trying to figure changes that would cut the cost of construction and he even drew up some new plans for us. Finally, Mr. White drew a plan for a much simpler building and one more in keeping with our other buildings and the country. Mr, Mattil then took them to Mr. Turner and once again they went to' work getting estimates. I don't see how we ever could have gotten the building even now without the help Mr. Mattil and Mr. Turner have giv NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 635 en. Mr. Mattil has been here practically all the years we have talked building and knows so well the needs, as well as the local labor and what supplieS are available around here. He. and Mr. Turner worked together and separately, making slight. changes here and there, getting estimates on materials here and in Knoxville and Sevierville. They have put more work into it all than I could begin to tell. When Mrs. Freeman and Miss Ellis came for their fall visit to the School everything was as nearly ready for them to act on as possible. Before they left the building had been staked off, Mr. Turner had said he would build the building, bringing eight of his carpenters out from Knoxville, and Mr. Mattil had arranged with some of our local men to do the rock work. The foundation was started the very next week. Wonderful fall weather has been the greatest help. All fall scarcely a day has been 'lost and now the building is up and Weaving Room Home EI(bonornics Amlitorilml (''lass 1toonts )Nice Manual Training Agriculture </p>
      <pb ref="arr4430631_0004" seq="04" n="636-637  "/>
       <p>636' THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI covered, part of the wall board is already up, all windows hung, most of the doors hung, the rock work completed to the window sills and the carpenters think that they will be through by the first of February, This does not mean that the building will be completed we cannot hope for that for some time. I do think, however, that the auditorium will soon be ready for the boys to play basketball there, the shop work can be arranged for and possibly we will move the agriculture and general science work into its new room. The other rooms probably will not be finished before summer. With no heat we cannot hope to use the building much this winter. The drawing gives so clearly the use each room will be put to that I do not need to enlarge on that at all. The financial part is always an important one and therefore I am going to repeat what I wrote in my Club letter in November, knowing many who do not see the Club letters do read the ARROW. When building was discussed three years ago it was voted then to put $2,000 yearly from the general budget into the Building Fund. To this was added any, smaller sums that were at any time available. When work was started in September, 1927, the fund showed the following on hand: Sale of Mrs. Coolidge's Portrait $1,I72.97 Gift from Mrs. Lutcher Stark 1,000.00 Gift from Mrs. W. H. Stark 1,000.00 Sale of Electric Light Stock 1,550.34 Appropriations from the budget 6,000.00 Interest 2,432.84 $13,150.15 To this sum smaller sums have been added that bring the total to just about $14,000. Grand Council gave permission to the Committee to borrow as much as $10,000 if necessary but both Council and Committee hope very much that will not have to be done. They also felt that $20,000 was all that should be put into the building, exclusive of light, heat and plumbing. NE.ws FR()':\i 1..,1111.,E P'lGliON 637 While it is not the idea of any to launch a campaign to raise money for the building I do think there are those not connected with alum= clubs who would be glad to have a part in this and already I have written those on the list of "Isolated Pi Phis" who are taking the Gatlinburg News. There have been quite a good many responses and I hope more will come after the holidays. The clubs will be doing the best of service in keeping their annual contribution up to a high mark. There will be some help from the local people, especially when we finish the auditorium. Already Mr. L. S. Hall has furnished the lumber at a very low figure and in addition has given 5,000 feet. This is the biggest undertaking in a long time, in fact, I think the biggest that has been undertaken but I believe it can be accomplished, as the others have, by each one helping. EVELYN BISHOP. PROF. JAMES M. WHITE ANY have none their bit to make our Settlement School fill the needs of the section' of the country in which it is located and Prof. White of the University of Illinois through his interest in this wonderful work, aroused by Mr. and Mrs. Dutcher Stark, has more than done his. He studied our location, our community, our needs and our means and then designed an industrial school building which will be a credit to us and a real help to the people of that community. It is my privilege to tell you something of Prof. White and how he came to be interested in our work. "Who's Who" gives us the following statistical information : </p>
      <pb ref="arr4430631_0005" seq="05" n="638-639  "/>
       <p>638 THE ..\...RKONN (a: ..PI BETA .PH1 White, James McLaren, architect; born, Chicago, October 16, 1867; son of Samuel Holmes and Jennie (McLaren) White; B.S. in architecture, U. of I., 1890; studied in Paris, Franc e, a n d Poly. High School, Munich, Germany, 1894-95; one daughter, Adelaide, Louise. Connected with the U. of I., 1890; supervising architect a a d prof. architectural engineering, 1907, and superintendent of business operations, 1922; was dean College of Engineering, 1905-07. Mein. A.I.A., Soc. Promotion Engineering. Edn., Tau Beta Pi, Sigma Xi, Phi Gamma Delta, Gov. 41st dist. of Rotary International 1923-24. H o m e: Champaign, Ill. The Alumnae Quarterly of the University of Illinois, gives a more personal equation but it does not half tell the tale of what he means to us at the University of Illinois: Whenever at the University of Illinois a new building is to be planned, built, repaired, or an old one demolished; whenever a steam pipe cracks, or a telephone loses its voice or has too many voices; when the junior prom superintendent pleads for a pot of palms; when a costly tract of land is to be bought or when the grass needs mowing on a stretch we already have then and many another then does James M. White, '90, wave an authoritative hand. As supervising architect of the university he and his annexes design, maintain, and operate the physical plant. Speaking with compression this is made up of seventy buildings, 1240 acres of land, and 17 million things to whiten the hair. Prof. White for he is also professor of architectural engineering did not as a youth boil with building ambitions. Farming took his fancy. While a high school student in Peoria he tilled his father's idle lots, ran a raspberry route. and in general cut quite a trail into agriculture before he fell in with architecture. His father, having bought a sheep ranch in Iowa, James went there to help put up the needed buildings. He found a new thrill in fitting joists and tenons, stiffening struts, and lapping joints; but the joy of driving nails was what really won him over. Where would he go to study? To the University of Illinois, which then had the only school of architecture in the west. Besides, to his PROF. JAMES WHITE FROM LITTLE PIGEON 639 father's house had often come Regent Peabody, Dr. Burrill and other animate notices of this thriving seat of knowledge. The decision of James was undoubtedly hastened by the obliging Dr. Peabody, who on one of his visits showed the boy how to mount a butterfly specimen. At his graduation in 1890 the university recognized his merits and appointed him assistant in architecture. He advanced soon to professor, and in 19043 became dean of the college of engineering. His present title of supervising architect dates from 1907. In 1894 and 1895. he studied in Paris and Munich. His Marriage to Edith Shat-tuck, '90, took place in 1899. They have one daughter, Adelaide Louise, born in 1903. Prof. White and his office staff now design many and supervise the construction of all the new university buildings, although he formerly shared responsibilities with the state architect. With the cooperation of Prof. Ricker, '72, Prof, White designed the library. The woman's residence hall, ceramics building, vivarium, and various agricultural buildings he laid out in conjunction with his office force. The school of music and school of education buildings come under this head also. His work outside the University some of which he has collaborated in with other architects, includes Illinois state buildings for the Lewis and Clark exposition and the Pan-American exposition, the Douglas county soldiers' and sailors' monument, the University club, and numerous private homes. In length of service to the University he holds second place, Prof. Forbes being the only man who has been here longer. Prof. White is the brother of Prof. Alfred White of the University of Michigan whose wife and daughter, Mary, are both Pi Beta Phis. As consulting architect on the campus development at the University of Texas he became acquainted with Mr. Lutcher Stark and to know Mr. and Mrs. Stark is to know the Settlement School. Through their enthusiasm he became interested and has designed our building without any expense to us, as his contribution in our great work. LOIS F. STOOLMAN. </p>
      <pb ref="arr4430631_0006" seq="06" n="640-641  "/>
       <p>640 THE ARROW OF .Pl BETA PHI HOW TO MAKE MONEY FOR THE SETTLEMENT SCHOOL EARL Leedy, Indiana l', is a saleswoman for the Chevrolet Au tomobile Co., and has made arrangements with the Settlement School Committee to pay a commission of 4% on every Chevrolet purchased through .her. As you know, Chevrolet, has an open territory plan and any dealer can sell anywhere. All cars will be delivered direct to the door of the purchaser at the regular f.o.b. price. Each sale must he a straight cash sale, and with-out the trade-in of an old car. After 100 cars are sold, the commission will be raised to 5% and after 250 ears are sold there will to a cash bonus of $2450 given to the Settlement School. According to the Settlement School Committee, if our chapters and alumnoe clubs averaged three sales apiece in the next year, the new schdolhouse can be paid for. Orders should be sent to: Pearl Leedy. Maplewood Court, Indianapolis, Ind. THE NEW CHEVROLET The year 1927 gave to Chevrolet first place as to number of stales, choice of position at the national automobile shows and a host of loyal Chevrolet owners. With the new year General Motors offers a wonderful new Chevrolet. The motor is completely inclosed like the six cylinder Buick motor. The car has a longer wheelbase, larger tires, larger valves, four wheel brakes, snubber spring plates and a number of new features. General Motors has planned to advertise this new car in a bigger way than ever before. We will be interested to watch for these ads which will appear in thousands of papers over the United States. This should mean an opportunity for Pi Phi to make even more than we had hoped for the Settlement School building fund. Perhaps not many students can buy but we all have friends who will be in the market for cars. If we can interest business firms that buy several cars at one time salesmen's cars or trucks it will be most profitable. Now is the time for planning. Notice the ads and keep eyes and ears open for prospects. ALUMNA: DEPARTMENT 641 intiitriti~trrtutlrtrientirrutrrtritiitnttittittittitlttrltrttnttttrtiPlttttlltllllllllltdlitiitl11th!! Iltiftlitlltlltilalillllllel It 7'. : ALUMNAE DEPARTMENT Edited by AGNES MILLER TURNER, (MRS. J. R.), Oregon A 458 Rodney Ave., Portland, Oregon 7 "" Ann Arbor, Mich. Saturday, March 24, 12:30 P. M. Luncheon and election of officers. Hostess: Mrs. Alfred White, 514 For-rest. April 27-28 Founders' Day and Michigan Beta's fortieth anniversary. Chairman, Mrs. Palmer Christian. Saturday, May 5, 2 P. M. Business meeting. Hostess, Mrs. Gordon Ibbotson, Washtenaw Hills Estates. Friday, June 1, 3 to 6 P. M. Bridge tea for seniors. Hostess, Mrs, H. E. Riggs Barton Hills. Berkeley, Calif. February Rummage sale. Alumnae, Mothers' Club and Active Girls. March Evening meeting for girls engaged during day. April Founders' Day luncheon. Boston, Mass. February 26 Settlement Sf.hool meeting, 5 P. M., and Initation banquet at 7 P. M. Copley Plaza Hotel, Boston. Amy Burnham Onken will be present. April 28 Founders' Day luncheon Women's Republican Club, 46 Beacon Street, Boston. Burlington, Iowa. The club meets the third Thursday of each month. Dinner at 6 P. M., followed by bus'ness meeting and social hour. February 16 Settlement School. Perle Haydon, Leila Pen-rose, hostesses_ Burlington, Vt. February Joint meeting with active chapter in initiation. Party for actives after social time together. March History of Pi Beta Phi, examination questions, in form of quiz. April Founders' Day, celebrated with actives, and Middlebury Chapter. May Health meeting. June Joint meeting with Mothers' Club and Seniors. July Summer picnic, Mothers, Alumnae and Actives. Cheyenne, Wyo. February 6 Hostesses, Mrs. Forbes and Mrs. Taylor. March 5 Hostesses, Mrs. Lewis and Miss Nimmo. April 2 Hostesses, Mrs. Bon and Miss Hoetzel. Founders' Day. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



