<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr4420283_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Convention Chronicle</title>

                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>November 1927</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr4420283_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">November 1927</date>, Convention Chronicle</title>

                        <extent>Pages 282-284</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">37</note>
                        <note type="Folder">11</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 44, Number 2 (November 1927), Pages 282-284.</note>
			<note type="document">arr4420283_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Settlement School Program</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Founding of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1909-1927</item>
                                <item>Music</item>
                                <item>Handicraft</item>
                                <item>Programs</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr4420283_0001" seq="01" n="282-283  "/>
       <p>282 THE ARROW Ora Pi BETA PHI Few characters, fewer actions, and no words at all, except for the Reader, probably contributed to the success of this pantomime. The reader, engulfed with tears, gave to the audience the tragic story of a beautiful black-eyed daughter and her hand-some highwayman suitor, who, betrayed by a jealous lover, ended their tragic lives with shotguns and died nobly for their love. They later appeared before the audience despite the fatal wounds. Following this stunt, Gail DeWolf, Zeta Province President, gave a very clever talk on Scholarship, assuring her audience that "The Road to Success Is Well Graded." Inez Webster, Illinois A, who had recently returned from the Near East, told of her interesting work at the orphanages where she had charge of 6,000 orphans in Armenia, and also told of her work in Syria. The audience sat spellbound while she related incidents of the terrible earthquake and of the bravery of the small motherless children. It was a delight to have Miss Webster at Convention. Settlement School Program At nine o'clock, the Settlement School program began in the Lodge dining room with Nita Hill Stark, Chairman of the S.S. Committee, in charge. This was the culmination of five years of very excellent work by Mrs. Stark whose foresight, sense of humor, remarkable executive ability and interest have CONVENTION CHRONICLE 283 contributed largely to the School's progress during that time. So much of her time and of herself as chairman has she given to the work on Little Pigeon mat she has endeared herself to the School staff and to all of the mountain people, and whenever her name is mentioned before chapters or alumna; clubs it is at once associated with our big altruistic work. Her husband, Lutcher Stark, Jr., has also aided her in this work in many ways and has been of much assistance to the School. Pi Beta Phi is most fortunate in retaining Nita Stark as a Province Vice President, now that her term of office on the Settlement School Committee has expired, as her enthusiasm and loyalty are needed in national work. During the Settlement School program, mimeographed copies of mountain ballads were distributed through the audience and everyone was invited to assist in singing these quaint verses to the accompaniment of a guitar and piano. Miss Evelyn Bishop, Head Resident of the School, whose splendid work has brought the mountain people and the School so close together, sang one of the ballads of the mountain folk and followed it with the en-core, "The Lord of the Northern Sea." This ballad included one murder, one hanging and one burning at the stake, but was very much enjoyed by the audience. Mrs. Stark then presented seven other members who were on the Committee or who had served as Committee members, including Mrs. Richardson, Melinda Stuart, Frances Curtis, L o i s Stoolm.an, Agnes Turner, Gertrude Freeman and Ethel Curryer. A style show in charge of the Treasurer of the Settlement School gave the audience an opportunity to see how beautifully the splendid weaving done on the looms at Little Pigeon, can be made into dresses. A lovely sport model of green, a white wool outfit, an attractive wool knitted dress in Harding blue, and other designs worn by Pi Phi models added zest to the evening. Mrs. Stark told of the new industrial building being erected at the School and suggested that we acquire the habit of sending the School a greeting card with check at Thanksgiving and Christmas. . With her usual witty remarks, she explained the various scenes at Gatlinburg which were portrayed by three reels of niov</p>
      <pb ref="arr4420283_0002" seq="02" n="284-285  "/>
       <p>:84 THE ARROW O' Pl BETA PHI ng pictures taken by Mr. Stark and enlarged for club work. The :orner stone of the new teacher's. cottage at the Sugarlands, a eneral panorama of the valley, the Blue Ridge Mountains, Miss hew and her school hoard, the school buildings at Gatlinburg, iational visitors, members of the school staff all became reali-:ies as they moved before the eves of the spectators. Attention was called to the very splendid Arrowcraft shop display on the second floor of the Lodge where baskets, woolens, furniture, and other lovely bits of handicraft had been artistically arranged and supervised by Lois Rogers and Miss Evelyn. A sand model of the Settlement School in this exhibit was also noteworthy. At the conclusion of the program, Mrs. Stark extended an invitation to Pi Beta Phi to hold the next Convention at Gatlin-burg, assuring everyone that ample accommodations would be provided for their comfort. "The History of the Settlement School," written by Pearl Cashell Jackson at the request of Mrs. Stark was then placed on sale at 50c a copy, and within its blue and wine covers offered to all fraternity members a source of very valuable information on this our great altruistic work. This publication was significant of the thoroughness with which Mrs. Stark conducted her work on the Settlement School Committee. One of the features of the Settlement School meeting. was the reading of a letter from Anne Stuart, former Grand Treasurer. This letter was sent in response to a telegram sent from Convention which stated about twenty times "We want, Anne !" Your wants are many, Your words are few, But this is my problem, What on earth can I do? Here's a house with cares-Birdies galore A Parrott-one dog Sometimes there are more! Two hours of organ, A garden and flowers-Ali these consume Every cne of my hours. CONVENTION CHRONICLZ 28f Could I pack all my cares In a little old trunk I'd come to Convention And this is no bunk! But since I can't do it, I'll be with you by proxy. Now for heaven's sake, girls, Don't get reckless or foxy! Go tc bed early! Don't act like a dunce, Cut out the late eats And crazy old stunts. With my best to your Founders, To your Council-my love, And a greeting to all Not included above. May your meetings be peppy As I know they can. Hcw I long to be with you! Very lovingly, ANNE. Informal Spreads Thnners Beach Parties Many informal gatherings took place between and after sessions with spreads, beach parties and parades predominating. Immediately following the opening session of Convention, Eta Province delegates and visitors met for a spread in the big Breezy Point Lodge dining room. Each delegate told something of interest about her chapter, and the visiting actives and alumn2 introduced themselves. Florence Chapman Paetzold, Nebraska B, graciously responded to a unanimous request for a song; and Colorado A sang two numbers composed and used by the chap-ter. Monday night Indiana A entertained the Founders and Grand Council at dinner, honoring Mrs. Goodell, the Convention Initiate. Artistic place cards and favors added to the pleasure whilc much merriment resulted from the fortune telling by a hot e: guest. Monday evening after the evening session, Beta Proving met in the Lodge dining room for a spread, with twenty-fiv, present. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



