<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr4120179_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Geare , Dorothy Smallwood</name></author>
                        <author><name>Chew, Helen</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>December 1924</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr4120179_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">December 1924</date>, News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Geare , Dorothy Smallwood</name></author>
                        <author><name>Chew, Helen</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 178-189</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">37</note>
                        <note type="Folder">5</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 41, Number 2 (December 1924), Pages 178-189.</note>
			<note type="document">arr4120179_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">The Sugarlands Extension of Little Pigeon; Gatlinburg Growing; Sun Up</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Founding of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1909-1927</item>
                                <item>Planning</item>
                                <item>Facilities</item>
                                <item>Living conditions</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr4120179_0001" seq="01" n="178-179  "/>
       <p>I7S TIIE ...AjIROW OF PI BETA PHI NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON Edited by DOROTHY SMALLWOOD GEARE (Mrs. R. W.), Columbia A 0 0 When the Settlement School Committee. held its annual meeting at Gatlinburg last spring, one of the most important questions under consideration was that of the Sugarlands Exten SETTLEMENT SCHOOL COMMITTEE sion. This extension work had for a long time been the dream of Emma Harper Turner, Columbia A, who had suggested the idea to the Committee. After careful consideration and with the approval of the Grand Council, the Settlement School Committee decided to establish a Center in the Sugarlands to be known as the Emma Harper Turner Center. Before the final plans were adopted the Committee made a tour of inspection to that locality and came back to Gatlinburg thoroughly convinced of the great need of our entering that field. The trip to the Sugarlands was made in two Fords most of the way although some of the members of the Committee la NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 179 traversed part of the road on foot. The reason for traveling a-foot can well be imagined after a careful study of the snapshot on page 180.. The cover for this issue of the Arrow and most of the photo-graphs used in this department were furnished by Melinda B. Stuart, Nebraska B. "THE SUGARLANDS EXTENSION" OF LITTLE PIGEON. By HELEN CHEW To many Pi Phis this is an unknown land. To a fortunate few who have visited the school, it is a country of higher mountains, rockier streams, and rougher fords, a valley of delight to the hiker. To those who have lived within the shadow of these hills it is a home of poorer and less enlightened people, whose lives are bounded by the sky line of Bull Head, Balsam Top and the Great Smokies. For many years the roots of Pi Phi's influence have grown deep into the life of Gatlinburg. Unconsciously they have spread until they have touched the lives of many existing on the edge of this fuller life. Barren as their lives are, with so little comfort and beauty, they reach out for something which they call "larnin," the Sesame of life. For several years the problem of moving into the Sugarlands and establishing a center, has confronted those who have felt the needs of these people. During the summer months last year preceeding the opening of our own school, we held a little free school for all who wanted to come. Thirty children came. When the six weeks were over, the parents asked us to stay and continue the work during the year. Various reasons prevented then. But the following spring in April a meeting was called in the Sugarlands school at which the following plan was outlined to be submitted to the Pi Beta Phi school committee. Two acres of land were to be purchased by the people, ad-joining the county school land, on which the school house now stands. After four years of continued work by us, this land definitely becomes our property. With the co-operation of the people, we hope to erect a cottage to serve as a home for workers, and </p>
      <pb ref="arr4120179_0002" seq="02" n="180-181  "/>
       <p>IsO THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI social center for t h e community. The county will give a modern rural school. This is our plan for the next year, a co-operation of county, community and Pi Phi. At present we are using the old one-room school and an old mountain house for living. It will be known to all Pi Phis as "The Emma Harper Turner Center." Though only five miles from the "Burg many of o u r friends have never visited this settlement. The roads are very difficult to travel except by horse or on foot. Because it is so little known, except through its liquor, it has a very bad reputation for worse, let me say, . than the truth. The seed of many a Gatlin-burg family tree w a s planted in its soil. Of course the most progressive blood has moved to the plain country leaving the more inert to struggle with the rocky hill-sides. In spite of this emigration, the spirit of co-operation and desire for the best for their children is very strong. ROAD TO SUGARLANDS NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 181 SUGARLANDS SCHOOLHOUSE Phyllis Higgenbotham, Nurse, and Assistant in foreground "What are you going to do there ?" we were asked at the Mountain Workers' Conference last spring. "What chance have you to develop leadership? Will it be worth your money and effort?" These are questions that only the future can answer. No intelligence test can do it for you. But you are all wanting to know the more tangible things of this new undertaking of ours. First of all comes the school house, first, for in it eighty some pupils con their lessons, as in the Legend of Sleepy Hollow, all in one room, and not a very large one at that. With a curtain stretched down the center, Cora and I try to get into their dear unenlightened minds, that Tennessee is not all of the United States and North Carolina is not a foreign country. We are learning to read, spell and figure fairly well, but oh, geography and history! Nothing to tie to makes these subjects so difficult. The redeeming feature is their desire to learn. The pupils want it and their parents want it for them, that in-tangible something called "larnin" with which they can succeed in this world and prepare for the next. A few are quite bright, others learn with difficulty. When I say the Sugarlands is a country of poorer homes you may wonder how poor that means. Possibly if I tell you about a home in which Cora and I took dinner a few Sundays ago, you </p>
      <pb ref="arr4120179_0003" seq="03" n="182-183  "/>
       <p>182 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI will understand better. We left the road about a mile above our house and started .up through a field. It must have been that we climbed a mile up an uncomfortable slant, through cornfields and brier patches, until finally, after climbing a fence, we arrived at this two-room house over which was a small loft. A family of nine lived there. We ate our dinner from tin lids from lard buckets. The sweet potatoes were served on a lard can lid. Three broken dishes held the other food to be served. Four of us sat on the only chairs, while the boys stood up around the table. Chickens picked up the crumbs about our feet as we ate. The walls of the kitchen, where we were, were smoked black as coal. In the "other room" large bright blue paper bows were fastened here and there on the walls, a touch the two girls had given to brighten up a cheerless existence. Outside, late summer flowers grew in great abundance, a most striking contrast to the inside. Of course, this is in a way an exception, but I can go to more homes in which there are just as few comforts and which are not nearly so clean. I wish I could tell you about some individual cases of courageous struggling to live, usually women. One with a tubercular husband, who for five years now has planted and gathered and prepared every bite of food her family of five has eaten; who, with the help of her fourteen year old daughter, saws down the trees from which she chops her winter fire wood. The only money they have had for months she received from us for potatoes, a chicken now and then, and carded wool. Barter has been the means of their securing shoes from the store. Again I suppose this is an extreme case, but she comes to our house every week and her fight is so brave it seems worthy of telling. Yesterday one of the most affecting situations occurred that I have ever known. From the last house up the river, the par ents brought down their little six months old baby to be buried in the little graveyard on a hill not far beyond the school house. The crowd had gathered and I could see them waiting. Presently a' committee of two boys came for me to conduct the funeral services, there was no one else. Our week-end preachers were in the lumber camp during the week. What could I do? Helpless as I was I had to go. When I reached the spot they were standing about in a large circle. Within, beside the deep hole, stood this girl, scarcely seventeen, alone with a little wooden box covered with white muslin, over the top of which she had laid a piece of NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 183 embroidery work evidently taken from the fire board of her cabin. No one within ten feet of her to comfort her or to support her in this first great sorrow of her life. I asked where the father was and a rough looking creature with a cigarette was pointed out, a fellow arrested the day before for making liquor. The revenue officers had entered his house just as the baby was dying the day before and had given him permission to stay until afterthe funeral. She surely had more than her baby's death to cause tears. When our little service was over the man who stepped forward to lower the little white muslin covered box into the ground was an-other of the same liquor crowd, but because he could pay his fine was free to do his community and friend this service. With a cigarette in his mouth he did the last service for the little mountain baby. After all was over the mother went home across the hill, her husband down the river to work out his fine. Life seems so much uglier sometimes when contrasted with our gorgeous hill-sides this time of year. Cora and I went to discover the cause of a fifteen year old girl's not coming to school. In two rooms so filthy you sat on the very edge of your chair to avoid any contact, were living nine children and the parents. Five deep they stood behind their mother's chair while she told us Beulah was there all right, but no use sending her to school, she was too dumb; never could learn. For ten years she had carried babies on her right hip until she was almost deformed. Little eyes, pimply skin, scraggly hair, protruding stomach, huge bare. feet, she certainly did look impossible to teach. But how did they know, she had never had a chance, so busy minding babies for two lazy parents. Every night after school she comes to our cottage, thrilled to death that she has something else to do and think about. She thinks she is learning, but it will be a terrible struggle. In ten days she knows maybe five words, can't count to five and make a B, the first letter in her name. It will not be the facts she will learn but her life will be the brighter for having something to think about. I could go on telling you these tales, how a thirty-three year old mother of seven children put up sixty gallons of knout to feed them through the winter, how I met an old woman last week hobbling down the road in the pouring rain taking the last look of the Sugarlands, the mortgage had taken her farm and she had to leave. Life is full of these tragic things everywhere. </p>
      <pb ref="arr4120179_0004" seq="04" n="184-185  "/>
       <p>184 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI PART OF MR. OGLE'S FAMILY, SUGARLANDS But something a little brighter. In every rural community there are those boys who had no schooling in their boyhood and now in their manhood are too ashamed to show how little they know or to go to school with the little children. After much per-, suasion one started to school on Saturdays. Man size, he did not even know his letters when he saw them and of course never formed one. We began with the Moonlight School Material by following the outline of the letters in blotting paper until the accurate shape was in his mind. In this way he does not struggle over ill shaped letters impossible to read. In two Saturdays he knew his letters by sight and could write them. It will be a long hard pull for he is not above the average. Our number on Saturdays has increased to seven but I doubt if they will all stick. It takes a great deal of courage and ambition to begin at the very bottom after reaching man's estate. The girls are not so easily reached but it is not all their fault. In the eyes of their fathers girls need no education to bear children, it only fills their heads with nonsense. The older women are interested in our little house as well as the school. The first time we invited them here we had eleven, the next time, seventeen. It was interesting and surprising how some of them accepted their first cup of tea with confidence and NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON dignity and then slipped around afterward to ask Cora what it was made of. To see how many could write I asked them to put their names in a little guest book we have. Only four of the twenty-two different women who have been here could not do so. We told them about the hook worm which had been found to be so common up here, the highest infected region examined by Mr. Wile this summer. Last Saturday fifteen women tacked comforters for us and such a good time they had. Ten were here for dinner which they thought was so fine. Indeed it was most ordinary, but the dishes were all alike and the silver ware still had its first shine and the table cloth was white. They are still talking about it. It was amusing to see them slip out after dinner to use a little snuff. All the women up here use it. You would all be interested in the little old house which we remodelled to live in. New floors, the walls covered with orange colored building paper and a few more windows, for one room had none, we were able to feel clean at least. A man of the settlement made all our furniture from the heart of hickory', which is a lovely light brown. The school girls at the "Burg" wove the curtains, hand woven coverlets cover the couch, hand made rag rugs on the floor. With flowered draperies, rather curtains, at all windows and inside doorways to add an atmosphere of warmth and coziness, we look quite homey. The spring was four hundred feet away, too far to carry water comfortably. We now have it at our very door. Cora carried sand and stones to make a spring box for our butter and milk. Already the cold winds have blown down the river bringing the thought of wood for our fire place. It is almost impossible to get wood if you are a lone woman. Everybody gets his own. All over our. hillsides it lies but no way to get it to us. Either the river is in the way or the road too rough to haul over. Every time we see any men we beseech them to get us wood. So long as the weather remains as perfect as these October days are giving us, we can continue to burn our old shingles which require one of us to stoke the fire while the other cooks, they go like paper. The church has its problem. There is very little church spirit. The people are divided into two factions religiously, those up the </p>
      <pb ref="arr4120179_0005" seq="05" n="186-187  "/>
       <p>186 THE ARRow OF PI BETA PHI river and those down. Preaching once a month cannot hold them together. But that is another long story. This is the end of our first two months in the Sugarlands. The people have received us splendidly and made us feel perfectly at home. We have much to be thankful for. Only it is hard to be patient and await results. You learn from the people to plant and wait for your seed to grow. Time to them is day and night, it becomes to you one generation to another. Sometimes It seems almost hopeless to change the minds of children five and six generations held in such limited environment. You have to think in terms of more. than years. All this seems an-added responsibility to a burden already as heavy as we can carry. But as a young mother of seven children said to me the other day. "You wouldn't take nothin' for any of them and wouldn't care for another." GATLINBURG GROWING. Writing in Montgomery's Vindicator, the newspaper of Sevierville, Tennessee, the editor of that publication said in July: YE EDITOR VISITS GATLINBURG FRIDAY. Ye editor spent a very enjoyable day at Gatlinburg Friday, July 4. This Summer resort which has recently become very popular, was alive with humanity assembled from every direction and all seemed to be enjoying life and to be in an good humor. The hotels fed more than a hundred each while many were entertained in homes of the community. The lot sale conducted by Paine-Waters Auction company was a -success and attests the confidence people have in the future prosperity )f this popular resort. Last summer the Y. W. C. A. of Knoxville as well as the '. M. C. A. had a summer camp on the opposite shore of the -,ittle Pigeon from the Settlement School. The meals for nearly one hundred were successfully planned Lnd managed by Allie Reagan, a graduate of the Pi Beta Phi Setlement School, who is at present our weaving teacher. NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 187 SUN UP. Writing in the Pittsburgh Post of September 10, the editor of that daily says in part : OUR SOUTHERN MOUNTAINEERS. Arrangements made by the local Pi Beta Phi fraternity for a benefit performance of "Sun Up," now in its second week at the Pitt Theater, in the interest of education among our Southern mountaineers draw attention to a subject upon which Americans should know much more than they do. It follows that as they come to know of the conditions among this neglected element of the American people their sense of responsibility will be aroused as their hearts are touched. It is well that We make generous contributions to the cause of education in foreign lands, but it is only rea sonable that while doing so we should be careful not to neglect any of our own. The Pi Beta Phi fraternity maintains a mountain school at Gatlinburg, Servier county, Tennessee. Thus every dollar it receives through the benefit performance to be given Friday evening at the Pitt can be applied immediately in a practical way to its intended purpose. "Sun Up," depicting these mountaineers, is rated one of the truly great American plays produced in this decade. As it shows the ignorance prevailing in the section, it at the same time exhibits the aarairable traits of character that are there to develop. From the standpoint of the play itself, it is one that you should see one of those that stir the emotions greatly, bringing laughter at one time and tears at another. Miss Lucille LaVerne, who has the star part in the performance, is a native of Tennessee and has first-hand knowledge of the subject as well as that she has acquired by study of literature on it. In her declaration that the conditions are not overdrawn in the least in the play she has abundant support. In the Pittsburg Press of September 9, appeared an interview with Lucille LaVerne, star of "SUN UP" which closed with the following : Yesterday, Miss LaVerne, in the Congress of Women's Clubs, spoke before the Pi Beta Phi, Pittsburgh chapter, of the national organization, which is maintaining a school for the mountaineers near Gatlinburg, Tennessee. Friday night the Pitt theater will be given over as a benefit to the organization. Women of 25 who never have owned a book, men of 30 who are learning to read in the primer, children who cheerfully trudge miles over mountain trails for the privilege of learning "two times two equal </p>
      <pb ref="arr4120179_0006" seq="06" n="188-189  "/>
       <p>18S THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI LLOYD G. BALFOUR, x PRESIDENT OF THE L. G. BALFOUR CO. Sole Official Jeweler to Pi Beta Phi OUR OFFICIAL JEWELER 1ST four"---these are the people who are being helped through this propa ganda. The Pi Beta Phi fraternity is the one to which Mrs. Calvix Coolidge belongs. Marie McSwigan, Pennsylvania A, writes that her chapter would like to co-operate with other Pi Beta Phi clubs in putting on this benefit performance, and says : While our financial returns were much less than those of the New York Alumnae Club,. we worked on the benefit less than a weep and feel that we could have sold the entire house had we been giver time to work up the sale. Miss Emily A. Lane, 1205 House Building Smithfield Street, Pittsburgh, will be glad to assist other clubs in thh locality. The writer suggests that "The Shame woman," also by Luh Volmer, would do equally well for a benefit performance. We feel deepl3 indebted to Lucille La Verne for her whole hearted support of our cause and would like to acknowledge it through The Arrow. OUR OFFICIAL JEWELER-L. G. BALFOUR Lloyd G. Balfour, Sigma Chi, President of the L. G. Balfoui Co., and the head of the largest emblem manufacturing busines! in. the world, is the sole official jeweler of Pi Beta Phi. The Balfour Cup, which is presented each year to the P Beta Phi chapter which in the judgment of the Grand Counci most nearly meets its obligations to its college and its fraternity was given by Mr. Balfour to Pi Beta Phi in memory of his wife Ruth De Hass Balfour, Indiana r. To quote froM the Sigma Chi quarterly "Although Mr. Balfour wears a Sigma Chi pin over hi heart, he is responsible for nine out of every ten badges to be sees on any college campus in America. Either of his two factories a Attleboro, Mass., is at least three times as large as any other fac tory devoted exclusively to college fraternity jewelry. "Indeed a remarkable accomplishment for a man who defiei that age-old superstition about Friday the Thirteenth. . "Mr. Balfour, or `Bally' as he is known throughtht the en tire fraternity world, started the L. G. Balfour Co. in a 30-foc </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



