<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr4230561_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Turner, Agnes Miller</name></author>
                        <author><name>Barrett, Helen</name></author>
                        <author><name>Ownby, Annalee</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>March 1926</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr4230561_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">March 1926</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Turner, Agnes Miller</name></author>
                        <author><name>Barrett, Helen</name></author>
                        <author><name>Ownby, Annalee</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 560-574</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">37</note>
                        <note type="Folder">8</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 42, Number 3 (March 1926), Pages 560-574.</note>
			<note type="document">arr4230561_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">The Pet Show; A Letter from the Second Grade; Better Homes Campaign; Home Economics Evening School at Gatlinburg; A Chance to Help; Dr. E. A. Bishop </note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Founding of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1909-1927</item>
                                <item>Extracurricular activities</item>
                                <item>Facilities</item>
                                <item>Living conditions</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr4230561_0001" seq="01" n="560-561  "/>
       <p>560 THE ARROW Or PI BETA PHI ENTRANTS AT THE PET SHOW AND THEIR PETS NEws FROM I_,I'~"]CI,E PIGEON 561 Iliiitiulll II111111111IIIIIIilillilllllllllllilllllllll11111d111111111111111111~I1IIIIIIIIIIIilil111911IIII1111111111111IIIII11111111111111I11111 wr 2 NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON Edited by AGNES MILLER TURNER (Mrs. J. R.), 458 Rodney Ave., Portland, Ore. : 111111111111/IIIIIIIUIIIIIIIIIIIIII[IIKIIIII[III111I11111111111IIIIIIIIIIIIIIMillllllllllllllllllllllllll IIII1111IIIIIII1111111111111111111111 THE PET SHOW ometimes we fear that because of the splendid new things that are happening in Gatlinburg, such as the Better Homes Campaign, development of the weaving and other departments, and the improvement in athletics, etc., that the three "Rs" will be entirely overlooked. But nevertheless we are doling them out daily to 140 or more members of our student body. In the primary room are collected 40 or so young mountaineers, the number varying with the weather. As is the case anywhere, you will find among these small people that gather in from the hills and hollers each morning some who do not like to go to school. More than once two little knee-high primer pupils have had to be severely reprimanded for spending a school day rabbit hunting with their tiny hound puppies ! Furthermore the cooperation with the parents is not all that in some cases one and his "poke" of cats. would desire. One morning at 11 :30 an eight-year old appeared at the door and said : "I'm late because my mother wanted me to mind the baby and she told me to tell you that I was sick." In stimulating the childrens' interest in school, so that the number of school-time rabbit hunts, etc., may be minimized, interesting ,projects help a great deal. The accompanying pictures and the theme written by a little second grade girl will describe to you one of our Primary Room Projects. BRUCE WHALEY </p>
      <pb ref="arr4230561_0002" seq="02" n="562-563  "/>
       <p>562, THE ARROW Or PI BETA PHI The Pet Show was of such interest to the whole school, especially when Bruce arrived with his "poke" or sack full of cats, that affairs were very nearly disrupted for the morning. HELEN BARRETT A LETTER FROM THE SECOND GRADE We are haveing a petshow today. Charley broght to pigeons. Ernest Brought a little dog Orvle Brought to kittens. Milton Brought a little puppy dog to the petshow. Bruce Brought a poke of cats and had his picture tick. it was so cold that we had to Bring Miltons little puppy in and wrap it up and sit it by the radiator. it was so cold that we hadto sit the pets in the sun. ANNALEE OWNBY BETTER HOMES CAMPAIGN The Better Homes in America Campaign in Gatlinburg, Tennessee community was in many ways a marked success. The work of the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School in the community for a number of years had done much to prepare the people for such a campaign and the Smith-Hughes Agricultural and Home Economics Departments were a great help. Publicity was given through the school, at public entertainments by personal visits thruout the community, thru the Gatlin Ntws I' ROM LITTLE PIGEON 563 burg News and talks by different ones at the Arbor Day program held by the school on the play grounds at the school. It was impossible to have a Demonstration Home as no house was available and there was no money for such work, but by ad-vice and much talk here and there many have been persuaded to improve their homes inside and out. There are no plastered walls in the mountain homes. Most of them are celled ,,with rough boards covered with old newspapers, magazines and patent medicine advertisements. In the past year a number have secured a good grade of building paper and have put it on with narrow molding-home made-which is a great improvement in keeping the house clean. Cupboards, tables, chairs and other furniture have been made. Running water has been brought to the houses and several have put in kitchen sinks. Many have added porches and several have added rooms as well as porches and not a few have done splendid work with brush and paint. Many trees and native shrubbery have been planted around the premises which, in a few years, will very much add to the attractiveness of the homes in the community. The new homes built this spring and those being built have many conveniences, unheard of a few years ago and until recently seemed an impossibility in the community. Every one of the new homes has a bath room and while the fixtures cannot be put in at present on account of the disposal of sewage, it will not be long until even that will be provided for. Nine of the homes in Gatlinburg have sanitary cesspools and all the house conveniences found in most small cities. One of the summer hotels has five cottages and a new addition to the hotel equipped with bath and hot and cold water. Both hotels have beep, painted and the grounds improved by planting trees and shrubs. Most of the people own their own homes and a number have taken advantage of the Smith-Hughes workers help in planning house and grounds. Government bulletins have been most helpful. The School has provided playground equipment for the community and every day many children use the giant-strides, swings. see-saws, turning bars, etc. They also have an athletic field and every Saturday afternoon the field is filled with spectators rooting for the contesting baseball teams. In the fall and winter the foot-ball and basketball games are just as popular and we find the morale of the community vastly improved all the year round. Every Saturday night the School motion picture machine is in use and occasionally a social is held on the athletic field. The. grounds are lighted by electricity, which, until last year was furnished by the school's Delco plant. We now have a community plant which furnishes light and power to all desiring such. As these new things have been added every member of the family has been anxious to do something to fix up the home in some way and they have been </p>
      <pb ref="arr4230561_0003" seq="03" n="564-565  "/>
       <p>564 THE ARROW 01^ PI BETA PHI EAST TENNESSEE HOMES Oldest type log cabin Old Log House, never more than two rooms Common Type of Old House NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 565 astonished that the use of a small amount of paint or stain could make such an improvement. The School took over an old cabin in the Sugarlands, six miles farther up in the mountains, last year and by laying new floors, papering the walls with building paper, putting in ,some windows, screening the back porch and doors, enlarging the 'front porch, piping water from a spring 400 feet up the river to the house, pruning the fruit trees, making flower beds, placing home spun curtains at the windoWs with cretonne hangings at windows, and inside door-ways and spraying the house with a dark green stain, we have demonstrated to the people in the community what can be done by labor with a small outlay of money. Splendid vegetable and flower gardens are the rule among the mountain people. Many of the house-wives have weaving looms and their homes are made very attractive by hangings, cushions, coverlets, dresser covers, towels and rugs. They love music and sing the old mountain ballads and are becoming interested in, good reading, especially in the Agricultural magazines. We have been able to put many things across for the betterment of the homes through the Gatlinburg News, put out each month by the school and the result has been surprising. The people,' as a rule, very slow to take up anything new, have been willing to try the suggestions offered in farming, gardening and cooking and seem anxious for more. It is a great step forward that they are even willing to try new ways of doing things and shows they are interested in making plans for further advancement. The health of the community is improved and much credit must be given to the untiring e,:forts of the community nurse who for five years has worked among these people. She has given them instructions in keeping clean, in cleaning up the premises and most of all in "swatting the flies." She has used the lantern slides which give one a clearer idea of just what the fly does to the health of the community. A recent visitor, who was connected with the School ten years ago, was astonished when she saw the improvements in the way the homes were kept, in the dress of the people, their manners and their ways of living. She thought they had come a long way in the ten years from the small unkept cabin lighted with candles to the comfortable home lighted with electricity, she visited during her visit this spring. MRS. ANNA DowELL, Chairman Better Homes In America Campaign, Gatlinburg, Tenn. A copy of this report is on file with the Better Homes Dept. in Washington, D. C. </p>
      <pb ref="arr4230561_0004" seq="04" n="566-567  "/>
       <p>566 THE ARROW Or PI BETA PHI BETTER HOMES Box House, following log cabin Gatlinburg House recently remodeled New House well planned, plenty of windows. Attractive. NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 567 HOME ECONOMICS EVENING SCHOOL AT GATLINBURG Last spring I was sent to. Gatlinburg to teach home economics in the school for one month as the home economics teacher was away, then to teach a Smith Hughes home economics Evening School during the summer. The only thing I knew about an evening school was that it was for women and girls over sixteen years of age. The schedule at Gatlinburg was different from that of the ordinary school. The foods classes prepared a dinner for five members of the faculty and the dormitory girls five days of the week in the home economics room, then on Saturday the home economics teacher and the dormitory girls got Saturday dinner, and as much as possible of the Sunday dinner. We teachers took turns helping the girls get supper. The home economics teacher helped to see to the food 'supplies for the dormitory. Two afternoon's a week I was to go to Sugarlands. I had hardly learned what I was supposed to do and gotten started with my work till it was time to get ready to stop, so I did not get very interested in my first month's work. The Evening School work was something new to me and I was anxious to get started at it. The first week I went to Sugarlands and stayed two days. I canvassed a part of Sugarlands and told them of my plans for the summer and asked the women to meet at the Teacher's Cottage the next Thursday. I went to one home and found the women in the field burning briars. They had a seven months old baby lying on the ground wrapped up well and the mother's hat in front of it to keep the sun out o,f its face. I asked about the baby and they told me it had not been well lately for they had to feed it and its food didn't seem to agree with it. I asked what they fed it. She said "Nothing but Irish potatoes." I told her to come to my classes and we would study about feeding babies. She said "I know more now about babies than I want to." After school closed I had one class for the women and one for the little girls at Gatlinburg, at Sugarlands and at Cartertown. Evening School work is not necessarily taught in the evening, but at the time of day most convenient for the women, so I had one MRS. DAVE OGLE, Sugarlands She tends store, helps make crop, has a big family to do for and is now learning to read and write. </p>
      <pb ref="arr4230561_0005" seq="05" n="568-569  "/>
       <p>568 THE ARROW Or PI BETA PHI class each afternoon except Saturday and one class Friday morning. The women's classes are supposed to be from one and one-third to one and one-half hours, but I knew it would be difficult to get any-one to come very far for only that much time, so I told them to stay as late as they pleased. I always got home just at "dusky dark." At Cartertown I taught in a combination church and school house. We would lift the blackboards, made oif painted planks, and put them across the backs of the benches for a table. Miss Evelyn sent up a sewing machine so we had a very good laboratory for sewing. The only drawback was that it had to be torn up each week so the room would look well for Sunday School. The children at Sugarlands were mostly small ones so they made doll clothes. The children at Gatlinburg and Cartertown made combination suits. One woman asked me if I wanted the women to do their work in class like the children. I told her I wanted her to do whatever would be the most help to her, but to be sure she didn't run out of work. Well, she never did get out of work. She missed only twice and more than made up for that by working over-time. I never knew what we were going to sew until the women came, then one woman would ask me to help her cut a baby dress, another wanted to cut a little boy's suit, and sometimes another would want to make a suit of underclothes for her husband. They were more interested in getting help in cutting out clothes than in anything else. The Gatlinburg women always worked well. I didn't have many at a time, but when someone would get a new dress she would come and cut it out and get it about half finished in an afternoon. Cartertown is a small community so the attendance was necessarily low. Sometimes two women would take turns coming to class to keep me from being discouraged. Sometimes I would ride up to Cartertown and hitch my horse and go inside and read my Home Economics Journal or lie down on the bench to sleep until someone would come. If I decided no one was coming I would go SUGARLANDS CHILDREN NEws PROM LITTLE PIGEON 569 to one of the homes and ask them to let me help them do some-thing, for I was determined not to have an absence against me after making the trip. The few Cartertown children were good workers. My largest class was the Sugarlands children. There were seventeen enrolled and most of them came well. The women at Sugar-lands came because the little girls wanted a dress cut by pattern or because they wanted somewhere to go. If I got too busy cooking to talk to them they would sometimes leave me in the middle of a demonstration. The Sugarlands women did not like to spend money for they had very little to use so the last few weeks I bought cloth and paid them one dollar to make a plain one-piece dress, then sold the dresses for them. .1 told one woman I would be glad to have her come to our classes and she said: "I think that is nice for us mountain women don't know nothing but to work, work, work." When I asked one of the Sugarlands women why the women didn't come better, she said, "Well, we all know how to sew, it don't look so well, but it holds, and so far as the cooking, you could learn them how to cook sooner than you could learn them how to eat it." Most of the mountain people had never used a commercial pat-tern_ Many of them used no pattern at all, but cut their dresses free hand. One girl told me her father would not let her wear a dress that did not have two "brenths" in it. The same girl asked me how to make a cake frosting. When I began to talk to her about it I learned that she had always just beaten an egg white and put it on the cake without even adding sugar or browning it. They fry almost everything. It is not uncommon to see fried eggs on the table with almost enough ,tat to cover them. Now these things I have told you are just some of the worst ones, so do not get the idea that some of the people have who visit Gatlinburg. Some of the visitors come expecting to find the people living in trees yet, and they are disappointed to find that the funny things they have heard are not true of all the people. I spent my mornings visiting the homes and helping the women do their canning, sewing or anything they would let me do. One time I helped to clean an oil stove and I often helped cut dresses. I would stay until our conversation began to flag, then I would leave. That made some of my visits so' short that I was able to make nearly three hundred visits during the summer. I almost always walked when visiting. My longest walk was about seven miles. Everywhere I went they told me what Miss Evelyn and the Pi Phis had done for them. One day Mrs. Curtis came to visit the school, she asked me if I wanted anything for my department. I told her I thought it </p>
      <pb ref="arr4230561_0006" seq="06" n="570-571  "/>
       <p>570 THE ARROW Or PI BETA PHI A FEW OF THE PRIMER CLASS, FALL OF 1925 NEws FROM LITTLE: PIGEON 571 would be nice to have the home economics room celled and two more windows put in. Miss Evelyn soon had it remodeled. While Miss Evelyn was in Canada I got enough light grey paint from Mrs. Dowell (at a bargain) to paint the walls of the room, for part of it was brick and part wood. I thought that I, as an East Tennessee-an, owed that much to the Pi Phi school. I painted the walls and bought cheesecloth and wrapped the steam pipes through the room. Miss Evelyn had already bought another sewing machine. She got several books for the home economics library and gave us a screen that was not in use so the room can be screened off into a nice little dining room, sewing room and kitchen. The home economics laboratory has enough equipment now to meet the state requirements for first class high schools. Miss White, the State Home Economics Supervisor, and Miss Evelyn decided to continue my work until Christmas. When school began I stopped my visits and taught two eighty minute home economics classes to the high school children every morning and served milk or something to the first and second grade children at noon. In the afternoon I had two classes for the Gatlinburg women and two for the Sugarlands women ,and one class for the Sugarlands children each week. The Sugarlands children made a combination suit in the fall. The high school girls followed the state home economics course, as a cook had been employed for the dormitory. At Sugar-lands we cooked a few lessons, then we went back to sewing. At Gatlinburg I gave demonstrations in cooking the first part of the afternoon, then had sewing the last part, or gave the whole after-noon to sewing if I thought that was what they wanted. The Gatlinburg women decided that they, would like to spend the last six weeks in cooking. They wanted to do the cooking themselves. They paid a small ;fee and we organized a foods class. The class was conducted like the high school work. E'er several lessons we prepared foods suitable for a breakfast, then we served a breakfast. The rest of the time we cooked what different ones asked for. These women went home and tried the things there that they had made in class. During the nine months I enrolled eighty-seven women, but I had an average attendance of only 4 plus during the summer with one lesson a week and visiting and helping them in their home, and 5 plus during the fall without visiting and lessons twice a week. The three Revival meetings and the bad weather caused the attendance to be some lower in the fall than it would have been. Miss Evelyn decided early in the fall that the classes should be continued thru the school year and when the State Supervisor came, just before the Christmas holidays, she promised State Aid for the Evening School JEAN STEEL. work. </p>
      <pb ref="arr4230561_0007" seq="07" n="572-573  "/>
       <p>572 THE' ARROW Or PI BETA PHI A CHANCE TO HELP Jim Huskey has lived his thirty-two years like all other mountain boys of his generation, with practically nothing upon which to build a life of worthwhile activity. The last school which he attended was in the little log cabin four miles from his home, the last school this side of North Carolina. During those three months he tried to read from the third reader. That is the ,extent of his education. The lumber camps are practically the only possibility for the illiterate here and in them Jim spent his youth. He was naturally quick with his fingers and carpentering and cabinet making became almost a trade. "Still", he said, "there was al ways a dissatisfaction. I felt down deep in my heart there was some thing more than we people could see and feel." He was' no better than the average boy of this coun try on the surface, until one da3 at a protracted meeting. as you can only find in this country, he found his religion. It formed the fertile soil in which the seeds of his war experience took root. Jim enlisted and was detailed to Camp Pike as an orderly in the Government hospital. There he spent two years-among people with at least professional education if not cultural. He learned in those contacts that life held much to strive for, and just as much to !fight as in the mountain country. After the war he returned to the old life with nothing in the future but lumber camps and whiskey. But the vision which his religion had given him intensified by the fortunate contacts of his war experience, made these impossible. At least one man came out of the war with an ideal. The Bible was almost a closed book to him, but with the light of his miserable third grade equipment, scarcely better than none, he began his struggle to discover its truths, that lie might unfold them to his people. In his halting, illiterate way he has been carrying on this attempt to preach in the little school and church houses of this section, yet never ceasing to realize the need of an enlightened mind and long for an education. JIM HUSKEY NEws FROM LITTLE PIGEON 573 Now at his very door has come the chance, in the establishing of an extension School of the Pi Phis in the Sugarlands. Almost too late many think, for at thirty-two he has a wife and four children for whom he must provide. He owns his little piece ()if land on which is a three room log house, but the garden and field do not raise enough food and corn for the entire year. It is necessary to buy, for which he must work. This leaves no time for study. "How long will it take me to get an education," he asks. How little we can answer that will not discourage. "But I'll get it if it takes twenty years," he said. An intense desire to learn, as Jim has, is rare among the adult mountain folk. Our work for twelve years has touched the intellectual life of the children. Now we have our first chance to broaden that service, to include some of those who lost that opportunity in childhood. We cannot afford to lose the chance. HELEN CHEW DR. E. A. BISHOP Many Pi Phis from all parts of the country will learn with deep sorrow and regret of the passing of Miss Evelyn's father-Dr. E. A. Bishop at the Methodist Episcopal hospital in Brooklyn on Monday, December 21-for practically every visitor to the School spent the night, or at least partook of one meal in his home in Sevierville, on completing the first lap of her journey from Knoxville to Gatlinburg, in the days when it was not so easy to make the trip, and when Dr. Bishop's home was jokingly named the Pi Phi hotel. It was invariably Dr. Bishop-who, busy as he was-always had time to welcome visitors, see that they had a way of getting to their destination or to entertain them while in Sevierville. Many a trip North in the interest of Murphy College was also in the interest of the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, for he often included meetings with Pi Phis, or spoke at alumnae clubs of the School at Gatlinburg. Dr. Elwell Alexander Bishop was born in Wrightstown, N. J., in 1852, receiving his early education in county schools, and teaching for several years aftei in order to put himself through college. He attended Wesleyan University of Connecticut graduating in 1878. He was married the same year to Clara Irene Brown of Pointville, N. J., her death occurring in 1908. In 1911 he married Carrie A. Miller of Hartford, Conn. Mt. Union College honored him with the degree o,f D. D. in 1895, while he was similarly honored in 1910 by his own university. The greater part of his life was spent in educational work for which he had unusual ability in handling people and problems, </p>
      <pb ref="arr4230561_0008" seq="08" n="574-575  "/>
       <p>574 THE ARROW Or Pi BETA PHI bringing to the task in hand unusual vision and understanding. He resigned the principalship of Montpelier Seminary in 1912 to take charge ofMurphy Collegiate Institute. The school property which then consisted of five and one-half acres, and valued at $30,000, now covers sixty-three and one-half acres on which three new buildings erected at a cost of $400,000 stand; the first .of a total plan of seven;-A Boys' Dormitory, Administration Building, and Girls' Dormitory; three buildings in three years, showing the indefatigable work of a marl who had already spent many busy years and won for himself a name in the field oif education. But after all, the buildings ar"e a small part of his work:-there are the boys and girls at Murphy (a large majority of them from the mountains), who owe their chance of an education to him; the men and women in the business world who owed their start in life to him, and to whom he turned often when in need of funds to carry on the present big undertaking-and above all there is the untold influnce for good of "the man who has done more for Sevier County than any other man." It was while on his annual trip North to raise money for the school that Dr. Bishop sgrered a relapse, following an attack of colitis in'-the fall, and while at first it was hopedthat his illness would not' prove serious, later his son Harold who lives in New York wired for the rest of the family,-Mrs. Bishop, Ethel .(Mrs. Queto of Cincinnati) and Evelyn of Gatlinburg. We all miss him, for there was no more loyal Pi Phi in spirit, nor a man more greatly and widely beloved than Dr. Bishop. PHYLIS HIGINBOTHAM. EDITORIALS 575 111111111111111111113111113111,11111111111113)11111111111111113111111d111111111111111I11101,1211111101111111r111111,II1111131111111111111111111111111 ei ... EDITORIALS IIIIII111113,I1Il~lifi,311111111131131111,I111111111l111lII11113I131[1111111111111111111113111II1111I1111111~11131111111,1~13111I111111E1111,,; The cover of this issue of THE ARROW is a picture of the memorial sundial erected by the faculty and students of Eastern High School, Washington, D. C., in recognition of Our Cover the splendid work for girls done by A. Margaret Merrill, Columbia A. The sundial is a bronze with the inscription. Memoriam-Anne Margaret Merrill---Eastern, High School, 1909-1920 "Time flies, Love Stays" A splendid picture of A. Margaret Merrill in her Camp .Fire garb was used in THE ARROW of December 1924. * * * Our Settlement School has lost a staunch friend in the death of Dr. E. O. Bishop of Sevierville, Tenn. Even before his daughter, Evelyn became head of our staff at Gatlinburg, A Great Loss Dr. Bishop was vitally interested in our work and its development. I know that all those who were identified with the early life of the School recall, as I do, his genuine interest, wise advice and encouragement. I shall always remember with pleasure the hours spent in his hospitable home and the eagerness with which he discussed mountain work and its problems. He went to Tennessee and assumed his du-ties in Sevierville after long educational experience in the North and I suppose no one will ever realize' how much Murphy College and kindred interests owe to his training, experience, fine tact and genuine interest in the problems he faced. I have heard it stated that the Methodist Episcopal Church has no more promising work under its supervision than the work Dr. Bishop was doing. He was always glad to bring, visitors to Gatlinburg and the community always welcomed him and he was equally ready and willing to speak to groups of Pi Phis and their friend's about our School when he was on his own lecture trips. Many of our f raternities have heard him with enthusiasm and I know all will sympathize with his splendid family in their sorrow. SARAH POMEROY R.UGG </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



