<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr4930315_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Frost, Mary Cooper</name></author>
                        <author><name>Bishop, Evelyn</name></author>
                        <author><name>Collins, Katherine</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>February 1933</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr4930315_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">February 1933</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Frost, Mary Cooper</name></author>
                        <author><name>Bishop, Evelyn</name></author>
                        <author><name>Collins, Katherine</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 314-320</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">38</note>
                        <note type="Folder">10</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 49, Number 3 (February 1933), Pages 314-320.</note>
			<note type="document">arr4930315_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">There Is a Santa Claus; To the Fair; Mollie Moore; Farm Management Studies; A Letter to Pi Beta Phi; Requirements for Teachers in Tennesse</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Holidays</item>
                                <item>Teachers</item>
                                <item>Fairs</item>
                                <item>Agriculture</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr4930315_0001" seq="01" n="314-315  "/>
       <p>NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON Edited by MARY COOPER FROST 11,111111131.111swIt.1121m.m.t...11111111111111.1.111111.11111.11AIII.11:111111011011110.1111.1101.2111.1110.111111.111111.11^11111.101111IIIIIIII1.111.1111 THE E IS A SANTA CLAUS By EVELYN BISHOP THERE really is a Santa Claus; and if you ever begin to doubt the Good Saint, just spend a Christmas at Gatlin-burg and your faith will be renewed. Christmas is not just a day or a week here; it lasts a full month. Thanksgiving is no more than over when preparations begin for the Christmas entertainment. This comes the morning school closes, and for many the sixteenth of December meant more than did the twenty-fifth. For two weeks each teacher is pretty sure it is a mistake to put so much time into practice, but by the time the eventful day arrives all are as excited as the children. This year the youngest pupils gave a short operetta; the third, fourth, fifth, and sixth grades gave a play and a pageant; and the seventh grade gave a play. I feared it would all be about the length of Strange Interlude and re-quire intermission and perhaps dinner too; but when the time came, even the little folks managed to listen pretty quietly, and all was over by noon. It was a blessing we did close so early, for the children scarcely had time to get home before the snow began to pour down. In spite of an attic full of improvised costumes of various kinds there are many new ones to make each year. Again this year the P.T.A. ladies helped with the sewing and saved the teachers many a night of hard work. The best part is that the women are willing and take much interest. We have so many pupils in school that Mr. King was sure there would be no place for thevisitors ; but by the time all the chairs and benches had been brought in, and even some bleachers, there were seats for nearly everyone. Since the beginnings of the school, it has been the custom to give each child a Christmas gift. For the past three or four years we have wondered if the time had come when we should discontinue the custom. We would decide to, and then the lovely boxes would come with gifts enough for all, and we would be sure it was all right to have a toy or doll for each one. I can see some of you smiling as you read this and remember the discussions we have had, how firm we have tried to be up to the last minute, and then with what joy we have weakened and wrapped up those presents. This year it was all decided for us we knew it was out of the question to try to give to all the pupils in school. To those clubs which wrote asking about Christmas I suggested their sending money to help get the fruit and candy. How-ever, a number sent their boxes as usual. We talked with the women at P.T.A. and Weaving meetings, and all agreed that the best way to do would be to appoint three or four women to pack baskets for some of the families that surely would have no other Christmas and then have a sale the day after school closed. We also talked with two . merchants to see if that plan would in any way hurt their business. Both agreed it was perfectly all right to carry out the plans. As it snowed all the afternoon and THE FEBRUARY ARROW 315 night of the sixteenth, I did not think that many could get out the next day; but in the morning several women came to help arrange and tag the things. The home economics room looked like a Christmas toy shop. There were dolls of all sizes and styles of dress, toys that fascinated us all, and practical things such as baby gowns and blankets, many pairs of stockings, and one table of used clothing that could be sold very cheap. In fact, all prices were low enough to make it possible for almost anyone to buy a toy or a doll. Opening these Christmas boxes has always been the biggest excitement of the year for us, and I realized this year that it had been almost a shame to deprive the people of the fun. They just reveled in the things. I am sure, too, that it encouraged several people to have a family tree Christmas Eve. My heart nearly failed me the day before school closed when one little girl asked me whether it were true that there would be no gifts on the Christmas tree. When I told her, "Yes," she said in a pitiful voice, "Well, I don't guess it will seem much like Christmas." No doubt I would still be worrying about that child if I had not seen the mother, the girl, and the little brother looking at every doll and every toy over and over again. The few nickels that were tied up in an old handkerchief were spent with the greatest joy in the world, even though the mother and the little girl did not agree in their tastes. The mother kept urging the child to decide in favor of a doll with hair ; she said she always did like a doll with "haar," but the youngster was firm for a bald-headed baby, and that was the one she carried home with her. All afternoon people came; and as a result nearly $30 was added to the noon lunch fund, and I am sure as many children were made happy as when the gifts were distributed from the tree. We are convinced it was a most successful venture, and I believeyou all would have been satisfied ,had you been here to see how it worked out. Fruit, candy, and toys were saved to put into the baskets the women packed the next day; and all during the vacation we gave to children who we knew would be without Christmas at home. Wednesday before Christmas had been set as the night to carol and then play games in the school gym, but the ice and snow as well as much flu in the neighborhood caused the caroling to be postponed. We had the games how-ever. On Sunday night the weather was milder, and Miss Whaling suggested caroling instead of the B.Y.P.U. service. Our own family Christmas is always just grand. We have Christmas Eve just for ourselves. Of course that includes a few in the Burg who have al-ways had Christmas with us. It would never seem right without our precious Aunt Lizzie. We open our packages and read our cards, drink coffee, and eat our fruit cake, and wouldn't be any-where else for anything in the world. However, Gatlinburg was not the only place where Santa Claus called. He may have the reputation of traveling only on snow, but I can testify he makes his rounds through mud too. The roads into Laurel Lick were a sorry looking sight, but Christmas was there just the same. I could tell a tale on myself of how I started in the morning of the twenty-third and would drive until I saw some still worse looking road, then tell my passengers they would have to walk the rest of the way, have a change of heart, and drive on a little farther. We finally reached the school just in time for the program which I wouldn't have missed for any-thing. Pauline Whaling had been over there three days helping with costumes and practice, and there were brownies, fairies, bees, good little boys and girls and Santa Claus just as though there had been snow and reindeer. All the time I was enjoying the play and the </p>
      <pb ref="arr4930315_0002" seq="02" n="316-317  "/>
       <p>316 THE FEBRUARY ARROW songs I found myself wondering how all those people could get into that schoolroom with so little mud. Eva explained afterward when she told us that some of their pupils even washed their shoes at the pump before they went in. And speaking of shoes re-minds me that several boys and girls are in school now who wouldn't be but for a pair of new shoes or a sweater. The Christmas checks for Laurel Lick allowed enough for some most necessary clothing, and in return the children are helping in various ways. Already a few potatoes have paid for a pencil or a tablet, and two cords of wood have bought shoes and overalls. Giving in a way that will help is no small problem but one that we all try to work at. Again this year the friend in Chicago that our family call the Christmas Candy Man sent us a generous box of candy, and that with the checks that came provided candy and oranges for all the boys and the girls in the Gatlin-burg and the Laurel Lick schools. Even though we did not use the contents of the lovely boxes in the usual way, I believe just as many people were made happy and more good was done. I only wish you all could have seen what a lovely Christmas we had. Many thanks for all you did and lots of good wishes for 1933 ! TO THE FAIR By KATHERINE COLLINS, Colorado Alpha "So deck yourselves out in your finest array and heigh-ho! Come to the Fair !" And we went, the eight dormitory girls, a truckload of boys, Jessie Branham, the home economics teacher ; Don Smith, the agriculture teacher, and I to the East Tennessee Fair in Knoxville. For weeks the girls had been getting ready for the momentous trip. And with the help of Mrs. McDonald, matron of the girls' dormitory, each girl had a new fall hat cocked on one side of her head. The boys literally shone .one could have seen himself reflected in either their slicked-down hair or polished shoes. At the fairgrounds the boys and Mr. Smith left us. As our ostensible purpose in coming to the Fair had been to see what great and wonderful things the farms of Tennessee could do, we did manage to glance at the exhibits. And then we "took in the sights." Half of the girls had never been to a city be-fore, and none of them (or I, for that matter) had ever been to a big fair. So there was lots for us to see. We began with the ferris wheel. At first, Miss Branham and I had to coax some of the more faint-hearted to get on, but before it was over we were begging them to get off; and we were trying to find excuses for not accompanying them on some of the wilder rides that the Fair offered. We met the boys and Mr. Smith for a picnic supper. After supper we watched trapeze-performers and tightrope-walkers while standing on a hill that had at least a 90 per cent grade. We stood an hour of this, then we gently suggested to some of the boys and girls that it would be nice to go get good seats to watch the fireworks. They refused to budge until the last flip-flop was turned. We rushed to the edge of the lake to see the fireworks on the other side. If anyone could have seen the shining eyes that watched the last skyrocket burst into the Stars and Stripes, I'm sure he would have felt the same thrill that we experienced. THE FEBRUARY ARROW MOLLIE MOO E By LADELLE ALLEN 317 The word "cooperation" and Mollie Moore are synonymous. Meetings are Mollie's particular joy; for no matter what the nature of the meeting, be it a rummage sale, weaving meeting, curb market meeting, old harp singing, or a Southern Handicrafters Guild meeting, Mollie is on the front row taking every-thing in. She comes early and brings her lunch but usually has to leave early to be home before dark. She lives al-most at the head of Baskins Creek and trudges a rough mountain road which crosses the creek seventeen times there are foot logs between school and her home. The road is too rough for any wagon; and all food supplies bought at the village store are taken up on a wooden sled, still a popular and necessary means of transportation in the mountains. In the seven years that Mollie has been weaving for the school she has woven Pi Phi towels, all-over pattern towels, monks' belt finger towels, knitting bags, and last but by no means least Washington diamond ring runners. In the past nine months Mollie has woven, with some help from her two daughters, 771 of these runners, a full share of the 6767 yards woven by the forty-six women who weave for the school. The more intricate the pattern, and the Washington diamond ring is an intricate one, the better Mollie likes it. Shesays she "would a `sight on earth' rather weave a pattern than just plain weaving, it's more interesting." During the fall rush there nobody works harder or more faithfully than Mollie. When she promises to bring MOLLIE MOORE in weaving, you know she will ,be here regardless of the weather. The Washington diamond ring runners which Mollie weaves are 14 inches by 12 inches, fringed, all-over pattern, in almost any desired color, priced at 75 cents. May we send you one? FA M M NAGEMENT STUDIES By DON SMITH To the boys now studying farming at the Settlement School, the subject of farm management as a new field of agriculture has presented quite a few new problems and has brought up more than one old problem in a new light. Heretofore, the whole business of farming has been attacked from the student angle chiefly with the one question, "How ?" How can I grow better corn, better potatoes, more corn, make hens lay more eggs, or cows give more </p>
      <pb ref="arr4930315_0003" seq="03" n="318-319  "/>
       <p>318 THE FEBRUARY ARROW milk? It is now becoming more and more a recognized fact that "How ?" is no longer the chief consideration, but that the queries "What ?" and "How much ?" and "Why ?" are demanding attention from every student of agriculture in high school, or even for that matter, in college. We would like to add, with perhaps the characteristic freshness of the relatively inexperienced youngster, that a serious facing of the above questions would have a strong tendency to help de-fossilize more than one Ph.D. who occupies a chair in our agricultural colleges. Enough of that! You are, no doubt, wondering what all this discourse has to do with the things our boys do here at the school. This year we have been studying the farm, more as a business and not as a place to learn how to grow more corn or potatoes. The following are some of the abilities which we are seeking to develop in the boys: 1. To select and economically secure a farm on which one can make a better and happier living. 2. To arrange fields, pastures, wood lands so that they will produce the better living and be economically cared for over a period of years. 3. To locate properly new buildings and fences, or arrange old ones on the farm. 4. To plan and provide more convenient, comfortable, attractive and economical buildings and fences. 5. To make the outside of buildings, home grounds and surroundings more sanitary and at-tractive. 6. To save and economically use food and feed products that are produced on the farm. 7. To determine the economic returns from the different enterprises on the farm. If we fully develop any of these abilities, either in ourselves or our students, we shall be busy a long, long time but we have been, and still are, plugging along. One of the things with which the boys have had most fun is taking a farm of limited area, sketching it on paper and showing locations of fields,pastures and wood lands and making out a plan by which one animal unit per 5 acres can be kept, and providing for feed for the amount of livestock the year around to be produced on the farm. Early last fall the boys planned, and ordered seed to sow 5 acres of a mixture of barley, winter oats, Austrian peas, wheat, rye, and rape for winter pasture for the cows on the school farm. These pastures have caused quite a bit of favorable comment from our neighbors, as well as increased milk production from the cows. The boys are keeping records of the number of cow-hours grazing which the pastures are returning. Then, too, we have attacked the alternative of a young man renting or buying a farm, with the assumption, of course, that he has very limited capital. The problem of land taxes, interest on investments and borrowed capital, labor income, and net profit or loss, have been rehashed and discussed. Each boy has been required to write a rental con-tract for a farm of 15'0 acres or more in legal form, covering all the possibilities of the situation, both from the standpoint of the renter and the land owner. Yesterday we took our Bostrom level and surveyed a pipe line from a spring across the hill to carry water to Jim Reagan's new house. We found he would have to install a hydraulic ram. He thinks he will do this. Our next job is to make a complete plan for this year's gardens on the school farm. We must raise more vegetables on the same ground this summer, if possible, for there are rumors of a curb market in Gatlinburg to take care of the summer tourists' demands. We wish ourselves luck. THE FEBRUARY ARROW 319 LETTEI \ TO PI ETA PHI Harrison McCarter, the basket maker whose picture appeared in the February, 1932, ARROW, makes the square markets, wall pockets, garden baskets and magazine baskets When asked if he would write a short article on what the school had meant to the community, he said he would be pleased to do the best he could, though he knew he could not begin to say what he wanted to. The article was brought to the Arrow Craft in two installments, the first just a very few days after he had said he would write it. He said that the folks all went to church and he just ''datyed at him" and wrote a bit. About a week later he brought in the P.S., saying he had to get up in the night and give one of the children a dose of castor oil and so just stayed up and wrote a bit more. Harrison was rather apologetic when he brought it in because he did not feel he had done justice to the subject, but I am sure we will all agree that he has said a great deal. LADELLE ALLEN It is regrettable that ARROW readers cannot see the letter as Mr. McCarter wrote it, but a reprint follows: Nov 30 1932 Star Route In regard to the Phi Beta Pi Settlement School: I want to express my thought in regard to what the Phi Beta Pi School has been worth to this community and other joining communities it has been worth lots to the people I cant begin to tell what it has been worth to me it has give people a job in many ways and give people a chance to school their children clost home and give them a chance to pay their way through schooland it is helpful in many other ways it has give many a person a job which had not been for this School probley they would have not got any job which many has got well I cant express my thoughts and sympathy I have for the Phi Beta Pi School just the way I would like to it has been worth a fortune to lots of us people but there is lots of us do not Presinate what the School has done for us. so I will close Truly yurs [Signed] Harrison McCarter P.S. a flew more words to the school I have worked for the school last 15 years and I find it honest and helpful in many ways it has been helpful to lots of communities in sickness and in health and has learned lots of the young people many things about carpenter work and lots of the young girls to cook and sew which maybe if it had not ben for the school they would not tuck interest in so we cant say how much we presinate what they have done for us thanking them very much. REQUI EMENTS F0 R TEACHERS IN TENNESSEE In order that members of the fraternity wishing to teach at Gatlin-burg may know the requirements for teaching certificates in Tennessee, the Settlement School Committee is publishing below information from the State Department of Education in Nashville. Quoted from requirements for Tennessee Certificates. Senior High School Teacher: Standard four-year college degree; 27 quarter hours of educational credit. No applicant will be licensed to teach a subject of which he or she has less than 18 quarter hours of credit. To qualify for Home Economics the applicant must offer 12 quarter hours of foods and nutrition 12 quarter hours of clothing and textiles and 12 quarter hours of home management, house furnishings, child care and home nursing. Elementary and Two-Year High School Teacher: Two-year high school teacher (4-year certificate) Six quarters (72 weeks) of standard college work ; 90 quarter hours of credit including 18 quarter hours of education. Elementary teacher (Permanent certificate) ---Two-year curriculum for elementary teachers of an accredited college or normal school consisting of not less than 90 quarter hours of credit including 18 quarter hours of education. Elementary teacher (4-year certificate) Three quarters (36 weeks) of standard college or normal school work consisting of not less than 45 quarter hours of credit including 9 quarter hours of elementary school methods and management. In his letter of January 4, 1933, Mr. P. M. Harned, Supervisor of Certification, wrote: </p>
      <pb ref="arr4930315_0004" seq="04" n="320-321  "/>
       <p>320 THE FEBRUARY ARROW The Educational courses required for permanent elementary certificates have not been pre-scribed. We expect those who are undertaking to meet the requirements for elementary certificates to confine their Educational courses to the elementary field, and those who are applicants for high school certificates to confine their courses to the secondary field. We do not count as professional Education courses in Religious Education, and if Psychology credit is offered as professional Education, the ap-plicant is limited to two semester hours of General and four semester hours of Educational Psychology. Actives who think they would like to teach at the Settlement School at some future time are advised to study these requirements. "I AM STILL RICH' p We have passed through a panic, suffered from a crash on the stock market, and are now more than half way through the depression, and I am still rich. It may be true that I have much less to live on than I had a year ago, but it is certainly true that I have just as much as ever to live for. The real values of life are unshaken and solid. . . The depression has not lowered the value of a single friendship. Neighbors still greet us in the same old cordial way, business associates believe in us, and our sons hold us in high respect. The wife's welcome at the close of the day has not depreciated in the least, and our daughters continue to lavish their affection upon us with the same old extravagance. My faith in the goodness of the universe is unimpaired. By that faith I am emboldened as I face defeat and despair. The prayers my mother taught me and the faith in God instilled in me by a devout father remain as price-less treasures no depression can touch. No nation becomes great by becoming rich. Neither does a man find en-during satisfaction in life by owning something only by becoming some-thing. The most degrading poverty is that which results from killing thespirit that the body may be served. This depression is a challenge, not a catastrophe. A generation that has conquered the air and sent giant planes circling the globe, which has plunged into the deeps and disported on the ocean's floor, which has climbed above the clouds and lived in the stratosphere, is now faced with the challenge to rise above its dependence on mere things and seek an emancipation of the spirit of man. The last six months have been for many men a thrilling spiritual adventure through which they have discovered their real wealth. Bereft of dividends and profits, they are discovering the sustaining powers of a strong religious faith, the abiding values of courage, heroism, honor, charity, and trustworthiness. A financial crisis can wipe out profits and bring business to a standstill, but character is beyond its reach. It can rob us of all we have, but it cannot affect what we are. The deepest satisfactions of life those which come from sharing and serving remain secure. I am still rich because I am independently rich none of my wealth depends upon the business conditions or market reports. Financial Advertisers Bulletin, via Laurel of II K F OM PI PHI PENS Edited by ANNA HOLM DE MONSEIGLE (MRS. EDMOND F.) rrlllttrltllrlaalrllartttltltlaarrrtartaarwtraawrritatttllwarrallrrrlrtrttarrrtiaralatltAtirraaltarttltanarrrleltatllwtlttAtlltlarrrlwtlaAAtlrAaltwaAtrrtarllatwtlltltr Your editor wishes it were possible to share with all ARROW readers the many gracious letters which come to her desk. These all reflect the charming personality of their authors and help make the work of this department a joy. One envelope postmarked Dead-wood, South Dakota, was found to contain a letter bearing an even more intriguing heading: Tinton, Black Hills, South Dakota. Yes, you've no doubt guessed that this reply came from Ethel Powelson Hueston, Iowa A, who has just made another contribution to fiction. ARROW readers are referred to the February, 1931, issue for a story and photograph of Mrs. Hueston. The jacket of Good Times hails the book as "a cure for chronic and acute gloom," and further describes it as "a peripatetic comedy, light, sure and diverting." The leading characters are destitute young people, victims of depression, 1932 style, who decide to "hitch-hike" to the West. In passing, the wayfarers make converts who share their astonishing, often near-tragic, but always breath-taking adventures. How-ever, it is in depicting the life of these young folks after they settle down on a ranch in the Black Hills that Mrs. Hueston excells. She has succeeded in transferring to the printed page her love for the country she calls home. We recommend the book to lovers of youth, adventure, and romance. The latest of the children's books by Lois Donaldson, Florida A, is Greta in 7eatheriand. This is styled a Swedish" picture book and again the pictures are by Maj Lindeman one of the favorite children's artists in Sweden. The story relates the happy experience of a little girl who was whisked away from a rainy night down on earth to the joyous realm of Weatherland, where she meets the makers of sunshine LOIS DONALDSON and happy smiles. From the cave where the little old men forge the sunbeams, she follows the golden path along the West until she meets the golden Princess and the little girls dressed all in yellow. The book contains enough light and happiness to dispel all gloom and brighten even the darkest day. Once more we note the grace with which Miss Donaldson handles her words and the skill with which she creates the atmosphere of fancy and imagination all with that light and delicate touch which children love. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



