<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr4030594_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>On Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Miller, Katie B.</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>March 1924</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr4030594_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">March 1924</date>, On Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Miller, Katie B.</name></author>
                        <extent>Page 594</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">37</note>
                        <note type="Folder">4</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 40, Number 3 (March 1924), Page 594.</note>
			<note type="document">arr4030594_0000</note>


	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Founding of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1909-1927</item>
                                <item>Teachers</item>
                                <item>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</item>
                                <item>Funding</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr4030594_0001" seq="01" n="594-595  "/>
       <p>594 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PM (Courtesy of Washington Alumna, Club) ON LITTLE PIGEON We, Pi Phi sisters here, they, hillfolk sisters there, eve, in the midst of all things lovely and true, They, for whom the whole world seems askew, Shall we, the women on whom God's light Shines, not by reason of our right, Refuse to share with our sisters there? -KATE B. MILLER. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



