<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr4840603_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Frost, Mary Cooper</name></author>
                        <author><name>Wyer, Eva Armstrong</name></author>
                        <author><name>Armstrong, Mary Rachel</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>May 1932</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr4840603_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">May 1932</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Frost, Mary Cooper</name></author>
                        <author><name>Wyer, Eva Armstrong</name></author>
                        <author><name>Armstrong, Mary Rachel</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 603-606</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">38</note>
                        <note type="Folder">8</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 48, Number 4 (May 1932), Pages 603-606.</note>
			<note type="document">arr4840603_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Evelyn Bishop; The New Nurse; Gatlinburg Home Economics Project; The Glee Club; Boys' Basketball Team of Pi Beta Phi School, 1932; Elsie Barbero Conser; A typical day at the Arrowcraft Shop-</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Nurses</item>
                                <item>Home economics</item>
                                <item>Sports</item>
                                <item>Music</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr4840603_0001" seq="01" n="602-603  "/>
       <p>The May ARROW judgment, and sportsmanship, combined with a rare sense of humor, makes her services in great demand with Los Angeles folk. Twenty-one years old, and a college instructor this is the unusual distinction of Sarah Farnham Payne, who be-came the youngest member of the faculty of Southern Methodist University this year. Sarah was graduated with honors from the University of Texas in 1930. While in college she was a member of (t) B K, Cal) and Gown, Ashbel Literary Society. In ,June, 1931, she received her Master's degree in psychology from Columbia University. In all, she has attended five universities, for she has also done summer work at University of Colorado, University of Alabama, and University of Southern California. The "Pi Beta Phi Quartet" of Oklahoma composed of (left to right) Mattie Mae Lowry, Maxine McDonald, Jerry Bruin, and Barbara Waggoner, is in demand on the campus of Oklahoma A. and M. College for programs at college functions. Its latest appearance was at the. P.E.O. Convention, held at Enid, Oklahoma, April 12-14. SARAH PAYNE ').c*491t4'.2tt'*'ple.4swicii.91c4',ac'4ac4xv,49itiatzow I*k' fl{I)J 11 II W ~ n , E ti x 1 l~`~ edited by Mary Cooper Frost Evelyn Bishop MISS EVELYN and devotion to the Settlement School! Again the two have proved themselves synonymous. Miss Bishop was to have had leave of absence beginning October 1 last, but events conspired to keep her on at the school. The first delay came when, at the last moment, the weaving teacher could not return to Gatlinburg. Very fortunately for the school Winnogene Redding, the former weaving teacher, consented to fill in for the year. It should be said here that the work has progressed well under her direction. Miss Redding was hardly established when Frances Moore, the nurse, received offer of such a good positionelsewhere that she could not refuse it. So it was that Miss Evelyn did not get away until January 1, and then went only so far as Sevierville where she was with her mother. Each week until her return to active duty the latter part of February she went back to the school to take care of correspondence and confer with the staff, all members of which rose nobly to meet the emergency created by her absence. The close of the school year 1931-1932 finds Miss Evelyn again doing, as only she can do them, the countless things that fall to the director of the Settlement School. It also finds the whole fraternity in her debt more deeply than ever. The New Nurse . By Eva Armstrong Wyer, Kansas Beta ANOTHER Miss Moore, but Virginia not Frances, started her work as nurse at the Settlement School on March 15. It had been hoped that she would be released in time to come March 1, but the doctor in charge of the health unit at Bristol, Tennessee, where Miss Moore was substituting for the head. nurse was doing a special piece of work that he was unable to finish then. Quite naturally he did not want to start a new person. During the summer Miss Moore substituted in Sevierville for the county nurse and was very much liked by the community. Since August she has been doing substitute work for the State De-partment of Health in Sullivan County. Her period of substitution was to end in January, but the county health officer asked to keep her for two months. Had funds been available, the county would have kept her permanently. The director of child hygiene in the state spoke very highly of her work. Miss Moore had her hospital training at Wesley Memorial Hospital in Atlanta, Georgia, and received her diploma in 1928. From 1928 to 1930 she did private duty nursing in Atlanta. She took her public health training in Vanderbilt University, receiving her certificate in 1931. Miss Moore's home is in Cedartown, Georgia. </p>
      <pb ref="arr4840603_0002" seq="02" n="604-605  "/>
       <p>)4 The May ARROW Gatlinburg Home Economics Projects By Mary Rachel Armstrong HERETOFORE, home eco )mics has been mainly cooking and ;wing, but recently our attention has turned to a more inclusive pro-ram of all homemaking activities, ich woman trying to make everything )unt for comfort and beauty, sanitaon and health in home, school, and ammunity. Instead of sending all of ur handicraft work away for others ) enjoy, we are making our own homes right and cheerful with handwoven rticles and handfinished furniture. Sacks have found numerous uses in iatlinburg communities. With a little ye and much work sugar, flour, and ran sacks are being made into curains, rugs, bedspreads, runners, chair overs, and pillows. Our woodboxes have put on legs and .re standing on a higher level. We no onger have to bend to the floor each ime we put a stick in the stove. We have also learned that the only way to keep the children's clothes out of the middle of the floor is to give them a place to put them. Mrs. Clabo had her house remodeled this past summer. When I came back this fall she asked me to visit her and help her plan curtains for her home. Before I left she said, "I must show you my ward-robes. That's what you harped on so much." Our biggest problem is nutrition. A course in Red Cross nutrition, for which the women will get credit from the national Red Cross, is planned for this spring. We hope to correct the undernourished condition of so many and to learn how to teach the children to eat new foods and to like to be well and healthy. In such a short article you have only a sample of our homemaking program. I hope that in time you may all visit the mountain homes and see for your-selves. SENIOR CLASS Back row, left to right: Beryl Reagan, Retta Trentham, Evelyn Ogle, Alda Clabo, Paul Lawson, [arold Reagan. Second row: Everett Kirkland, Josie Ogle, Eula Watson, Blanche Carr, Carl Ogle. Front row: Ethel King, Della Clabo, Edith McCarter, Frank McMahan, Robert Merriel, Herert Clabo, Merle Karns not in picture. The May ARROW 605 The Glee Club By Vivian Blair, Oregon Alpha UPON my advent into the Pi Phi School three years ago, I asked the boys and girls if they would care to organize a glee club..The suggestion appealed to them, for soon the membership grew to fifty, with many of the younger ones clamoring for admittance! Their enthusiasm is apparent when you consider that they would be overjoyed to have glee club every night if it were possible. Their repertoire of songs is growing rapidly they can easily learn a new song in one evening, including the partharmony. They sing ballads, negro spirituals, religious songs, regular glee club songs, and hest of all do they sing words of their own interpretation set to Pi Phi music. The boys and girls have a true appreciation of music, which is expressed in the fine spirit of their songs. If anyone wants to please the glee club, just ask it to function at the community gatherings. They refuse to say "no" and "stage-fright" is not included in their vocabulary Boys' Basketball Team of Pi Beta Phi School, 1932 By William King, Principal THE boys' basketball team of Pi Beta Phi school has just concluded one of the most successful seasons in the history of the school. Their schedule consisted of fifteen games with the strongest teams from the largest high schools in this section of the state. Of this number of games they .won tenand lost five, making a total of 345 points to 298 for their opponents. They lost only one game on their home court, and that by the slim margin of one point. This record, considering the fact that there are only fifteen boys in high school and only a two year high school, is quite remarkable. Names left to right: Harold Reagan, Robert Merriel, Robert Pickle, Carl Ogle, Rellie Dodgen, Paul Lawson, Herbert Clabo, Lavater Cotter, and William King, Coach. </p>
      <pb ref="arr4840603_0003" seq="03" n="606-607  "/>
       <p>606 The May ARROW Elsie Barbero Conser As A volunteer worker Elsie Barbero Conser, Iowa B, went to the Settlement School last August from her home in Pasadena. Mrs. Conser not only taught classes in music but also gave private lessons to some of the older children. She encouraged and helped Mary Rachel Armstrong and Vivian Blair in their work with theglee club. The altitude affected her health from the beginning and before Christmas forced her to leave Gatlin-burg. When she left, the school sustained a very real loss, not only because of Mrs. Conser's ability as a teacher but because of her splendid and helpful spirit. Correction In the last ARROW, announcement was made that "The Story of Gatlin-burg" was written by Dean Greve of the University of Tennessee. How-ever, authorship should be credited to Mrs. Jeanette Greve, a resident of Gatlinhurg and the mother of Dean Greve. The book is on sale at the Arrow Craft Shop. As the ARROW goes to press, news has been received that Mrs. Greve has passed away. The school has lost a wonder ful friend and the community a real neighbor. A typical day at the Arrowcraft Shop in the Mountain View Hotel gives one a composite picture of the American tourist. The very early visitors are the athletic ones, who will appear with aching muscles and sunburnt noses the next day. Then the lazier hotel guests drift in and go carefully through the stock. Most of them are really anxious to see exactly the quality and prices of the Pi Phi work, so they can plan what they wish to buy. During the middle of the day the transients come. The questions fly. Is II B .4, a religious sect? Where is a mountaineer? Do we (the two girls in charge) du all the weaving? The classic question was that of the woman who asked if Mr. Stephen's lovely pastel of a mountain cabin was woven or hooked. We answer carefully and send them to see the school. Most of them are sincerely appreciative and admiring. There is a hurried visit from a group of Knoxville society people having cottages in the vicinity, and then come a Pi Phi and her husband who want to see just what she has been helping to do. They are always charming and intensely interested, and are the best of all our visitors. Helen Hi/am, Texas A </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



