<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr4910039_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Settlement School Reports</title>
                        <author><name>Bishop, Evelyn</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>September 1932</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr4910039_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">September 1932</date>, Settlement School Reports</title>
                        <author><name>Bishop, Evelyn</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 38-54</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">38</note>
                        <note type="Folder">9</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 49, Number 1 (September 1932), Pages 38-54.</note>
			<note type="document">arr4910039_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Director of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School; Pi Beta Phi School Report; Arrow Craft Shop Report; Treasurer of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School Committee</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Curriculum</item>
                                <item>Health care</item>
                                <item>Facilities</item>
                                <item>Funding</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr4910039_0001" seq="01" n="38-39  "/>
       <p>38 1:\ DI THE SEPTEMBER ARROW ECT0OF PI I* ETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL TWENTY years ago Gatlinburg was an isolated mountain community, with two small stores, a church and a one room schoolhouse. The people lived on little hillside farms that followed the three creeks that come into Little Pigeon River at Gatlinburg. Little cash changed hands in those days and eggs and chickens were brought to the store to be exchanged for the most necessary household supplies. The school term was short and the local teachers were equipped with little education for their chosen profession, the only one aside from lumbering, that paid cash. With this short and not too inspiring school year there was naturally an indifference to daily attendance and a strong feeling that any outdoor work was of more importance than a day in school, no matter what the age of the child might be. Yet there was an honest, intelligent, and worthwhile people living here, only needing an understanding of how they could help themselves toward a more satisfying life. It is easy to understand why efforts the first few years were practically all in the grade school. The teachers found it a task to keep pupils in school regularly and to maintain anything like a graded school. Not least of their own problems, was that of learning to keep house away from the supplies and conveniences they had been used to. The school problem never could have been solved but by the friendly visiting done in the homes. The pity is that the time ever comes when we try to understand pupils without a knowledge of the home life and background. For six years the grade teaching and community work were all that could be attempted. However, plans were being laid for other work. The first to take form was the health program. Home economics, agriculture, and crafts fol-lowed. Adding a new department a year, as was done for a time, may have been going too fast, but all seemed worthwhile and money did come in to finance them. A report of the development of any one of these departments would make interesting reading. Finally it seemed necessary to take a few boarding students. With this had to come student labor and the supervising of it, which was and continues to be no small responsibility. With better grade schools through the mountain sections it is not necessary to take pupils with less than seventh or eighth grade start. There is but one free high school in this large county. With limited dormitory quarters we cannot take more than twenty to twenty-five boarding pupils. These are chosen from the applicants who live in this county, from 5 to 25 miles from Gatlinburg, who do not live within reasonable distance of a high school, who are not on an improved road, and whose parents are not able to give them help. We do not take any town boys and girls. Providing work and a home for these pupils brings more care and expense than any other department, but the largest results. Little by little, year after year, less thought and money have been expended on the routine school work and more on the vocational, industrial, health, and community work. The county has improved its schools steadily, the school term has been lengthened, local teachers are better prepared, and the county now pays the grade teachers in our school. I feel we should turn over to the county the first seven grades, giving them time to make their plans and build a consolidated school in Gatlinburg. With the development of the National Park there are bound to come many changes. The present, while people are moving, would seem the THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 39 time to reorganize the county schools of this district. The mission of any philanthropic institution should be to carry work that cannot be done by the county system. Our grades can be carried by the county; our other work is of a different character and important, and it surely would be a sufficiently large program to carry. School Contrary to usual, attendance in-creased each month during the year. Final reports showed 200 pupils registered, the largest number in the history of the school. Not a small part of this increase was in the upper grades. While the attendance officer was very slow in getting to work in the fall and home visiting failed to bring results in every case, we still had a better daily attendance than in other years. Mr. King continually worked for this, in hopes that the daily attendance could be increased enough to allow us another teacher. We missed this by a very few pupils. Three teachers, Eleanor Brabson, Miriam Swann, and Barbara Horton had the primer and six grades; the enrollment was 130. We expect this coming year to add one more grade teacher and put the seventh grade in this building. The P.T.A. women again furnished the noon lunch for the primary and underweight children in this building. They also raised enough money to have a young married lady come for an hour and a half each morning to prepare for the lunch. The teachers helped during the noon hour and the high school girls took turns in helping with the hand-washing and general cleaning up. Mrs. Conser, who was here during the fall, was of great help in both this and the high school building. The help she gave both teachers and pupils in music meant more than we can tell. Seventh, eighth, ninth, and tenth grades were taught by Mr. King and Miss Blair. For study we had the largeroom that had been the agriculture classroom. The farm shop had been moved into a little shop building near. In addition to teaching and acting as principal of the school Mr. King coached basketball. Although all the teams our boys play are from four year high schools our boys make a good showing. Vivian Blair and Mary Rachel Arm-strong added to their regular work glee club for the older boys and girls and an athletic program for the high school girls. The girls keep in better health without competitive athletics, as they have not had the systematic training to build them up for basketball and they also carry a heavy work schedule out of school hours. Athletics, jn addition to the regular labor program, is hard on the boys too, but they are bet-ter able to hold up to it. We do not make the use of the library that we should. The past year each teacher has kept a selection of books in her room and that seems the best way to manage unless we find we have some person on the staff who can give a little time regularly to the library. Sugarlands and Fork-of-the-River will not have schools the coming year. They are in the Park area and comparatively few families are left there. As they have moved out, the cabins have been torn down. The few children left in these places will be brought to Gatlinburg school. There will be a truck from Cherokee Orchard, too, we think. These children will fill our grade building, but the extra teacher the county will allow us can take care of the increase. Dormitory While the dormitory is one of the places where some of the finest training can be given, I have not felt that we have accomplished what we may reasonably expect in the work with the girls. Our aim has always been toward a model home life and a place </p>
      <pb ref="arr4910039_0002" seq="02" n="40-41  "/>
       <p>40 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW where we can give the girls careful training in home making. The cottage has become too crowded; there is no place for quiet reading or study or for a girl to have a few minutes to herself. The evening study hour is held in the dining room. In this cottage forty-five take their meals, and the housemother, one or two cooks, and fifteen girls live. In trying to solve the problem I have come to the conclusion that it would be better to limit the number of girls living there to ten. Mrs. Rorex, the housemother, feels that she has too much responsibility. She plans the meals, looks after the girls' work in both kitchen and dining room, and has all the care of the dormitory girls except during study hour. This is a trying position and scarcely ever does anyone feel she can take it for more than two years. If it were possible to have a housekeeper who could care for the dormitory girls, supervise some of their out-of-school work, look after the linens and give a little much needed attention to the laundry work, it would be a great help. All the girls need more training in housework than can be given them under the present conditions. If there could be a solution here, I am sure all would be happier. The boys' dormitory is much more satisfactorily arranged and the boys' work during the year proved this. Miss Glover, the housemother, also gave time in the high school study room. During the school year the boys were able to do nearly enough work to keep up with their expenses, so during the summer we had but one boy working on the place. This kept the number of boarders .down and it was better to hire what added labor was necessary. The coming year we will again limit the number of dormitory boys to ten. Home Economics The same program was carried in this department as has been the custom. The mornings were given to high school work. The afternoons were used for visiting, community home economics classes and work in connection with P.T.A., Better Homes, etc. The afternoon classes were in Gatlinburg, two in McCookville, about five miles from here, and one in Banner, three miles away. This is a field where much can be done and I would be sorry to see the evening school classes discontinued but we may find a cut will have to be made in this department. It has been possible only be-cause of the generous allowance the State Department gives for the Evening School work, which they offer us again for next year. I hope we can add two new communities to our list of evening school classes. Agriculture A University of Tennessee professor told us not long ago that Smith-Hughes Agriculture in Gatlinburg was some-thing very different from the usual high school work. No doubt he was right, for it does combine many different kinds of work and carries more than the usual amount of responsibility. The mornings are devoted to the Agriculture classes for seventh, eighth, ninth,and tenth grades. These thirty-three boys have the usual classroom work and in addition practical lessons here on the farm. In addition each boy carries a home project that must be checked on often. We are proud of the stock judging teams the past year. The dairy team represented Sevier County at the East Tennessee Division contest, which means that they scored over several four-year high schools' teams. The II B '(1, chapter of the Future Farmers of Tennessee had 21 members. Two meetings were held each month, one given over to a trip to some good farm or to the Agricultural College. Again three of the boys represented the chapter at the state conference in Nashville. Afternoons are given over to evening THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 41 school classes in other communities and various calls. Advice is given on spraying orchards, pruning, care of stock, farm crops, and of course there are numerous calls to see sick cows or horses. A very satisfactory program was carried in a community fourteen miles from here where the men had asked for some special help. Mr. Smith held ten meetings during the winter and the men were really interested in the course, which was "Planning the Farm Program for 1932." Twenty-six farmers were enrolled, but the attendance was not limited to these men. Last year the farm shop work was more satisfactory than in other years, due in large measure to a shop outside the school building. In addition to the carpenter work, there was simple forge work taught, which the boys enjoyed. The general care and planning for the farm is carried by the Smith-Hughes teacher. While we have a local farmer who is very good in supervising the work of the boys on the place, a great deal of responsibility has to be carried by Mr. Smith. The farm work helps the boys earn their expenses and gives them practical instruction in farm work and care of stock, especially adapted to the boys of this section. Health In October Frances Moore, who had been the nurse for three years, took another position and from then until Virginia Moore came, the middle of March, we were .without a nurse. As Miss Moore had been with the Sevier County Health Unit last summer she did not feel she was taking up new work in a new field. It is possible to do more public health work these days than some years ago. One of the first things each year is to visit the thirteen schools of this district. The county health physician usually makes the examinations and the children are all weighed and measured. Follow-up work comes and many throats, eyes, and teeth are looked after. Chest, thyroid, and baby clinics are held at the Health Center with experienced doctors in charge, and here again the nurse has plenty of follow-up work. Summer is the busiest time for various inoculations, although there is a good deal all the year. Clinics are held in all the nearby communities and it is a surprise to go into a little place where you see only a few houses set down between the hills and find eighty people waiting for the nurse. During the school year a home nursing class is taught in connection with the high school home economics. This past year a new venture was made. Some of the children who were much under weight or had serious physical handicaps were given a half hour rest period twice a day. Five cots were put in the library room and one of the dormitory girls looked after the children. At first they rebelled, saying they didn't come to school to go to bed, they weren't tired, etc., but they soon became reconciled and in every case the child showed improvement. The dentist continues to come to the Health Center one Saturday a month and although many people can go to town to a dentist there still seems to be plenty for the dentist to do here. During the year we have received from the Friends of the Mountain Children $200. Half of this is to be used for special eye and dental work, the other half goes for work with children, especially along the line of nutrition. While many organizations and individuals contribute to this fund, it is of interest to know that the (D T Sorority gave $1200 last year and hope to make an annual contribution of that much. They feel it is better to assist centers already established and work organized, rather than to carry small individual work. Again we give our sincere thanks to Lillie Reagan,. She is always defendable </p>
      <pb ref="arr4910039_0003" seq="03" n="42-43  "/>
       <p>42 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW and whether we have a nurse or not, keeps things going wonderfully well at the Health Center. Her knowledge of the local conditions is a great help, especially to a new nurse. Arrow Craft Judging from reports from other schools and shops, a cheerful report from Arrow Craft would seem to be impossible. However, to the joy of all, the shop can report about the usual amount of business. This seems nothing short of remarkable and means that both here and abroad more than usual effort has been made. The past year Miss Allen sent more letters to the clubs and chapters than ever before and each issue of THE ARROW had articles and cuts telling of the various things for sale. All this brought results. The usual number of weavers have been retained, even though there are so many other shops in Gatlinburg. Every effort has been made to plan at-tractive and inexpensive articles and I have but to tell you that in the year 2577 finger towels and 3226 hot mats were sold to convince you that small things have been in demand. The win-ter has been spent in planning as many things as possible that the clubs can sell at a low price. During the winter Mrs. Duffield, who lives at the Mountain View Hotel, has had charge of the shop there, with very good results. Miss Allen is urging all clubs and chapters to have an exhibit of Arrow Craft things when they have their fall Settlement School meeting. The exhibit can be small and, even if nothing is sold, there is sure to be an added interest in the school. Weaving Arrow Craft and weaving could really be under the same heading, as one is so dependent on the other. When we found, late in the fall, that Miss Strand could not come back toher work, r immediately sent word to our former teacher, Miss Redding, and within a few days she was here and ready for work. Knowing the women, the business, and the fall rush so well she was able to accomplish in a few weeks what a new person never could have done. Alice McCarter again helped with the weaving class for seventh and eighth grade girls. There is no doubt that good work is done by these girls in their weaving, and there is not time for it after the girls are in high school. More than forty weavers are coming for supplies, making new warps, getting instruction, or bringing in finished products all the time. We have been de-lighted that we could keep so many busy during the year. A great deal of thought has been given to the buying of supplies so that we could avail ourselves of every bit of discount and save on carrying charges. The monthly weaving meeting is something anyone would enjoy. At each meeting some definite problem is discussed, such as; laundering linen and wool, making a warp, color combinations. Then time is given for singing, visiting, and of course simple refreshments. From twenty-five to thirty-five attend and it is a social as well as educational meeting. Because of these meetings and the work done with the women in their homes, the State department allows us $600 each year toward the salary of the weaving teacher. O Bice Each year more work is carried in this office but each year there can be more system. Many things that were new and just being tried out a few yea'rs ago have become routine work. The two big pieces of work carried by the office are the Arrow Craft and student labor accounts, which take much time on account of detail work. Not least of Miss Cooke's work is to see that we keep expenditures down as low as pos THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 43 sible and to watch that we do not go over that budget allowance that has had to be sliced year after year. No one could be more conscientious nor have the interest of the school more at heart. Being the financial watch dog isn't al-ways the easiest place to fill. Extension The extension in Sugarlands was again carried by Eva Hathaway, Emily Burton, and Mrs. Belle Hathaway. Eva and. Emily taught the eight grades and Mrs. Hathaway was the housemother. For the past two years people have been moving out of the Sugarlands, as that is the National Park area. There was even a question of whether the school could continue through the entire year. The few children still living in Sugar-lands will be brought by truck to the Gatlinburg school next year, so the County Superintendent tells us. It has been impossible to carry a satisfactory community program, for no new interest could be taken when all knew they would move within a short time. Eventually our cottage will be sold to the Park. For some years the people of Laurel Lick, a community about fourteen miles from here, have been anxious for n B teachers. This past spring fifty-six people signed a paper asking Miss Hathaway to go there to teach and the County School Board approved her appointment. Mattie Huff will teach the lower grades, as Emily Burton does not return this year. The people are fixing a one-room cabin for the girls this fall and say they will build them a cottage in the winter. Laurel Lick offers a splendid field for work and the people are anxious to cooperate in every way possible. Last year Mr. Smith had a night class for farmers and each week, no matter what the weather, there was a good attendance. Not only did the men enter into the discussions but they made an effort to put into practice many of the things advised, Extension allowance had to be left entirely off the budget for the coming year. This does not mean that there was not a thoroughly sympathetic feeling for ex-tension, but that it was necessary to cut in every possible way until times were better and more money should come in. The county pays the two teachers and we shall help them in every way we can. Eventually I believe that we can put the extension work back on our program. Mattie and Eva deserve a great deal of credit for going in this fall and carrying the work. At least they know we are behind them in spirit if not financially. While it is a regret that any work has to be discontinued or hampered because of lack of funds, it is wonderful that we are able to continue this well. All are so thankful that it is possible to keep on with so much of the work during these hard times. Community It seems that each year brings more changes to our community. I wonder many times that the people here have been able to keep the balance they have with the rapid changes that have been thrust upon them. It is remarkable that they have been able to cling to so many of their worthwhile things and let so many worthless ones slip by. The past year little shops have sprung up on all sides, two dance halls have been opened, dozens of cottages have been built. There are more tourists coming in than ever before and many more week-end pleasure seekers. A splendid piece of community work could be done by a young man coming here in the summer and devoting his time to the young people, especially on Saturdays and Sundays. This year we no doubt could have secured such a man through the Friends' Service Association which is training men and women for various kinds of social service. Had our plans been more settled, I should have urged this. Our little church is doing just as well as it can. There has been talk of a resi</p>
      <pb ref="arr4910039_0004" seq="04" n="44-45  "/>
       <p>44 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW dent pastor with services each Sunday and this will come before long but just now the people are fearful about obligating themselves to that extent. We have church services twice a month and Sunday School and Young People's meetings each Sunday. One need only go to the Sunday night meeting and see a church full of young people to realize there is a rich field waiting. During the winter Mr. Mattil coached a young men's basketball team. The men were really interested and Mr. Mattil was instrumental in providing some-thing stimulating for these men to do three evenings each week. The P. T. A. women had a rummage sale and bazaar in the fall to raise money for the noon lunch in the grade building. Later in the year they gave a play which was a success both financially and socially. From both P. T. A. and weaving meetings has grown an interest in many outside things and a willingness on the part of the women to carry any work. Our hopes for civic improvement are surely through these two groups. Better exhibits, better babies, better crops, better spirit. "Bigger and better than ever" is the Fair slogan. It is hard to estimate the number of people at-tending, but there are not less than 600 school pupils in the parade and older people and babies are not lacking. It is a tremendous piece of work but all feel it has been worthwhile. Old Timers' Day continues to be one of the most, interesting days of the year. We hoped in the beginning we could have one day for the older people when they could get together for visiting and good times and could keep alive some of the old customs. It has really grown beyond our biggest hopes and to be absent from Old Timers' Day is to miss a real treat. The morning is given over to speaking, story telling, singing and business session. In the afternoon there are contests in weaving, spinning, carding, board splitting, corn shucking, hog calling, rifle shooting, and almost any-thing that belonged to the old days. The church had a homecoming and decoration the last Sunday in May. At least five hundred people were served dinner under the trees on our school grounds. The dinner was good, the order was splendid, and all had a good time. We opened the new school building be-cause of drinking fountains and toilet rooms and when I tell you that on Monday morning the building and grounds were as neat as before the homecoming you will agree with me that no 100 per cent examination paper could ever stand for as much as that. In the winter I asked for a local school committee to be appointed. The P. T. A. named two women and the church two men, a splendid committee. In talking over the school matters not long ago, I found that they had missed very much the "Gatlinburg News" and felt that it might be possible to work out a plan forfinancing it and having it pay for itself. No one has yet approached us about the Sugarlands Cottage but before long it will be bought for the National Park, as it is in the Park area. I am hoping that until the Park needs it we can retain a lease and use it for a rest cottage for the staff. Such privileges are being granted. Our whole country is urging a "Live at Home Program." The need of practical education is being emphasized in all sections of the country. The value of student labor and ways of providing for it is common talk among educators. In our small way we are trying to work along these lines. We must see that this Live-at-Home program brings much more into the lives of our people than merely an improved economic condition. They are entitled to as full and satisfactory a life as the town can give and they must have it if they remain happy and take an interest in helping to develop a fuller rural life. This year we have had several visitors who are spending much time working and studying over the mountain problem. One told me that, to her sur THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 45 prise, her success in the field the past year had been due to no small extent to the fact that their staff and community people had worked out together a six-year plan for their various activities. They may never carry them to completion, may never want to, but the stimulus and faith in a growing work cannot be overestimated. Another well known educator urged us to concentrate on the fine piece of industrial and community development we had started, letting go the things that could go on without us. To use her words: "Why continue to do a piece of average grade work the county could now relieve you of and does pay for when you could accomplish so much more along the industrial and vocational lines of education if you were not trying to spread yourselves so very thin ?" We must continue on a program of rigid economy. Were times normal, I would not urge large expenditures. The thing I do plead for is a thorough study of this particular community as it is today, a large vision of what development we can hope to see within the next ten years. The past twenty years have brought changes as we would want them to. We are willing to face them. Are we as ready and willing to face the new issue? EVELYN BISHOP PI BETA PHI SCHOOL REPORT July 1, 2931, through June 15, 1932 Money on hand July 1, `ea` ".".". ".".".".' " .' " .".".".". Receipts Community Service "."w 10.05 acay School 796.96 Farm 237.07 Fuel ''''''''''''''' '''''''''''' 27.50 Furnishings 2.00 Hospital 363.34 Labor ... 166.40 Living 1,734.30 Miscellaneous 110.67 Permanent Improvement (Teachers' Cottage) 106.00 Publicity 6.05 Repair and Upkeep 21.89 School ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' '' '' '' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' 17.96 719.00 S. S. Treasurer Home Economics ~~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~ ~ ~~ ~ ~~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ 6,253.33 Student Labor (Arrow Craft) " ." .' " .' ' . . ' 40o5 Sugarlands ' ' ".".". "."."..'..'..' 1.22 $11,999.56 Disbursements Administration ' .. '. ' ". 'w 65.58 214.80 Office 28.70 Teachers' Permanent 28.70 Permanent Improvement: Teachers' Cottag~ Bull Pen 321.41 Implement ~~~. ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~ ~ ~ ~ ~ 234.17 Hog Shed 11.40 688.53 ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' '' '' ' ' ' ' '''''' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' 109.90 Repair and Upkeep 1,083.23 School .. . 264.93 Smith-Hughes Agric 264.85 Sugarlands Telephone and Telegram ~~~~~..-^.^..'.".'."." 173.36 $10,82 5.43 m 1.131^61 </p>
      <pb ref="arr4910039_0005" seq="05" n="46-47  "/>
       <p>46 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW ARROW CRAFT SHOP REPORT July 1, 1931, through June 15, 1932 Money on hand July 1, 1931 $ 2,364.41 Receipts $12,977.05 Cash from Accounts Receivable Cash from State 300.00 Cash from loans on Warrants 385.50 Arrow Craft Cash Sales 4,737.90 $18,400.45 $20,764.86 Posted but not deposited 30.44 Deposited $20,734.42 Arrow Craft Cash Sales Baskets $ 176.75 Weaving 2,831.89 Finished furniture 192.65 Chairs, stools, and wood baskets 40.00 Miscellaneous 313.78 Hooked and Tufted goods, quilts 798.63 Transportation 10.51 Postal claims collected 10.50 Weaving supplies 388.07 $ 4,762.78 Less commission paid from cash 24.88 Disbursements $ 4,737.90 Baskets $ 714.73 Weaving 4,553.28 Finished, Furniture 890.75 Chairs, stools, and wood baskets 201.75 Miscellaneous 627.82 Hooked and tufted goods, quilts 2,493.63 Industrial expenses and supplies 447.32 Salaries 2,955.50 Lights 23.46 Living 637.50 Weaving supplies 3,408.19 Publicity 103.23 Transportation 531.60 Equipment .... . 47.08 Commission on sales at hotel 196.18 Warrants bought of teachers 482.00 Telephone and Telegram 10.88 Office 89.32 Permanent improvement 60.49 Repair and upkeep 204.26 Refund on customer's account 3.70 Southern Mountain Guild fee 10.00 General labor 6.40 Student labor 40.05 Fuel 25.50 $18,764.62 Cash balance June 15, 1932 $ 1,969.80 TREASU OF PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT f''' E SCHOOL COMMITTEE MRS. LOIS FRANKLIN STOOLMAN, CHAIRMAN NATIONAL BOARD OF TRUSTEE FUNDS, Pi Beta Phi Fraternity In accordance with the request of Miss Grace Post, who is the Treasurer of your Settlement School, I have audited her books and records for the year ended on June 30, 1932 ; I have also inspected the audit report of Messrs. Homer K. Jones and Company covering the operations of your School, for the same period, as reflected by the books which are kept at Gatlinburg, Tennessee. From these sources I have prepared a Balance Sheet as of June 30, 1932, showing a Net Worth for your School of $120,754.51, and an Income and Expense Statement for the year ended on that date, showing an excess of Expenses over Income of $2,473.10. My report to your officers and the Members of the Settlement School Committee contains a lengthy discussion of the various items contained in the Balance Sheet and Profit and Loss Statement, which are omitted at this time for the purpose of brevity. Respectfully submitted, ELIAs J. AYE Certified Public Accountant Gatlinburg Balance Account Balance July 1, 1931 $ 19,062.95 Loss for Year ended June 30, 1932 Schedule D 1,731.95 $ 17,331.00 Deduct Permanent Improvements and Equipment purchased, transferred to Treasurer's Books Exhibit B-3 107.57 $ 17,223.43 REPORT OF HOMER K. JONES AND COMPANY, KNOXVILLE, TENNESSEE June 30, 1932 MISS GRACE POST, TREASURER, Pi Beta Phi Settlement School. At your request we have made an examination of the books and records of the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School and the ARROW Craft Shop of Gatlinburg, Tennessee, for the fiscal year ending June 30, 1932. Attached hereto, we are submitting our report which shows in detail the results of operations for the period under review, the scope of our examination and the balance sheets of the School and ARROW Craft Shop as reflectedby the books at Gatlinburg at the close of business June 30, 1932. A few minor clerical errors were located and corrected during the course of our examination and except for the trade discount feature discussed in the foregoing paragraphs, your books were in excellent condition. Respectfully submitted, HOMER K. JONES AND COMPANY By H. CLAY JONES Certified Public Accountant Knoxville, Tennessee, July 28, 1932. PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL BALANCE SHEET June 30, 1932 Assets Cash on Deposit Bankof Sevierville Exhibit A-1 $ 1,766.62 Petty Cash Fund 10.00 $ 1,776.62 Liabilities Gatlinburg Balance Account Balance July 1, 1931 $ 1,141.61 Receipts in Excess of Disbursements Schedule C 635.01 SCHEDULE A ARROW CRAFT SHOP BALANCE SHEET June 30, 1932 Assets Cash On Deposit Bank of Sevierville Exhibit B-1 $ 2,232.65 Petty Cash Fund 25.00 Change Fund Mountain View Hotel 10.00 Accounts Receivable Exhibit B-2 Consignment Accounts $ 3,089.36 Customers Accounts 1,416.97 $ 4,506.33 Deduct Trade Discounts Allowable 874.45 3,631.88 96.50 Liabilities SCHEDULE B STATEMENT OF INCOME AND DISBURSEMENTS July 1, 1931, to June 30, 1932 SETTLEMENT SCHOOL Receipts: County School $ 796.96 Pi Beta Phi Settlement School Treasurer 6,253.33 Smith-Hughes Agriculture Receipts $ 1,406.50 Disbursements 264.85 1,141.65 Smith-Hughes Home Economics Receipts $ 183.38 Disbursements 106.13 77.25 Hospital Receipts $ 367.34 Disbursements 262.01 105.33 $ 1,776.62 Loans to Teachers on Warrants Inventories Merchandise $ 9,357.23 Weaving Supplies 1,870.17 11,227.40 $ 17,223.43 </p>
      <pb ref="arr4910039_0006" seq="06" n="48-49  "/>
       <p>.. . .. . . . . . . . . . . . . . .. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Farm D~~~~~~ 1,819.87 1,576.86 Miscellaneous Exhibit u-1 "..".' ` 165.72 $ 6,963.38 Disbursements: Administration ' " .' ' ' ' ' ' ' '4 65.58 '''''''' ' ''''''' '''''''''''''''''' 219.81 Boys Dormitory Community Service 29.45 Fuel 990.48 Furnishings and Home Supplies 348.65 Labor 284.07 Lights 794.02 Living Expense 827.64 Office Expense 34.05 Permanent Improvements Exhibit ~~. ~~~~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~~ ~~~ ~~ ~ ~~ ~ ~~ 582.53 Publicity 103.85 Repairs and Upkeep 1,091.22 School Expense 246.97 Sugarlands Expense -~~G Telephone and Telegraph Miscellaneous Exhibit ~~' 162.63 6,328.37 * See Schedule of Permanent Improvements. ** Includes Gasoline Engine Purchased $30.00. SCHEDULE C STATEMENT OF INCOME AND EXPENSE Year Ended June 30, 1932 ARROW CRAFT SHOP Income Baskets " "."."$ $ $ 1,488.10 $ Less Cost of Sales- ~~~~~ ~~~~.."."."~ ~..~..~.. 1,093.56 730.88 1,824.44 Deduct Inventory 6*0-32 ' ' ' ' ' ' " . ' " . ' ' ' ' 739.05. 1,085.39' Gross Profit on Baskets Sold ' . .' ' 402.71 Weaving Sales '.".". $ 12a13/7 Less Cost of Sales-$ 6,403.93 l~~-~.~~ ~ 4,696.33 $ 14,015z7 Deduct Inventory 6*0-32 5,579.15 8,436.52 Gross Profit on Weaving Sold 3,877.45 Finished Furniture Sales .. $ 1,270.75 Less Cost of Sales Inventory 7-1-31 w 1,857.95 Purchases 890.75 $ 2,748.70 Deduct Inventory 6-30-32 1,147.50. _1,601.20, z=" on Finished Furniture Sold 330.45 Chairs, Stools and Wood Baskets Sales * 505/0 Less Cost of Sales- Purchases 7-1-31 ~.~~.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~` 680.25 205.25 $ 885.50 Deduct Inventory 6-30-32 601.00, _284.50` Gross Profits on Chairs, Stools and Wood Baskets Sold 220.90 Hooked and Tufted Goods, Quilts, $ 4,202.18 Sales Inventory 7-1-31 $ 720.30 Purchases 2,531.48 $ 3,251.78 Deduct Inventory 6*0-32 896.4, _~~~3 Gross Profit on Hooked and Tufted Goods, Quilts, ~= 1,8*6.8 Miscellaneous Item~_ "."."."."."."."." $ 989.83 Sales- Inventory 7-1-31 $ 606.28 Purchases ".".".".".".".".".".-'640.72, $ 1,247.00 Deduct Inventory e-30-32 394.0~. _8~~~ Gross Profit on Miscellaneous Items 136.91 Total of Above ~".".". " .".".".".".".".~6~~~" $ 6,154.37 Trade Discount Allowable on Unpaid Deduct Trade ~~~~~ ~ ~ ~ ~~ ~~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ' ~ '. '. ' ' ' ' " .' ' ~"874.45 Transportation Cost ~ ~~~~. . Less Amount Charged Customers . ' " 484.30 80.19 2 74.53 Gross Profit on Sales '....'..$ 3,179.84 Selling and Administrative Expenses Industrial Publicity ". ".".".' ".".".".".".".'x Industrial Expense Commission on Sales Exhibit D-1 ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' '' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' '' ' ' ' '' Industrial Salaries Living Expense Office Expense Lights .................................. . ........ Miscellaneous Exhibit 5,211.79 Loss from Operations $ 2,031.95 Income State of Tennessee Weaving 300.00 SCHEDULE D STATEMENT OF PERMANENT IMPROVEMENTS AND EQUIPMENT TRANSFERRED TO TREASURER'S BOOKS Year Ending June 30, 1932 ARROW CRAFT SHOP Industrial Equipment Purchased Stove, "."."."."."."."."."."."."."."."."."."."."w 13.35 Electric Iron Lamp.Shade ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 6.23 Warping Reel ' ' " . " . " ." . ' ' ' ' ' ' " . ' ' ' " . ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " .' ' ' " . ' ' " ' '. . '. . .. 15.00 Spool Rack ...".'."."."."."."."...' "." " 8.50 Total Industrial Equipment Purchased $ 47.08 Improvements Shutters for Shop Building 60.49 EXHIBIT B-3 STATEMENT OF PERMANENT IMPROVEMENTS Year Ending June 30, 1932 SETTLEMENT SCHOOL Teachers' Cottage $ 15.55 B Tull ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~'~~~ Hog Shed 11.40 EXHIBIT C-2 STATEMENT OF CONDITION June 30, 1932 Assets Current Assets: Petty Cash and Change Funds * 45.00 Cash on Hand Magazines ^ 58.67 Cash on Deposit: First National Bank of Pasadena 6,822.12 Bank of Sevierville, Tenn. School Account 1,766.62 Bank of Sevierville, Tenn. Arrow Craft 2,232.65 Accounts Receivable: Consignments 3,089.36 Customers' Accounts '''-'''''' ''''''''''''''''''''' 1,416.97 Total Less Trade ~~~~~~~~~~~ ' 3,631.88 Loans to Teachers on Warrants 96.50 </p>
      <pb ref="arr4910039_0007" seq="07" n="50-51  "/>
       <p>Inventories: Merchandise 9,357.23 Weaving Supplies 1,870.17 11,227.40 Total Current Assets $ 25,880.84 School Endowment Fund: Investments 16,518.78 Amount due Endowment Fund, as per last Report 14,844.79 Less amount restored this year 1,500.00. 13,344.79. Total General Endowment Fund ... . 29,863.57 Certificate of Deposit No. 11179 Pasadena Trust and Savings Bank Hazel Todd Meaden Fund 50.00 Total Endowment Fund ^ ........ Assets: Buildings, Equipment and Live Stock 86,841.04 Deferred Charges: Prepaid Insurance 1,663.85 Total Assets $144,299.30 LIABILITIES AND NET WORTH Liabilities: Accrued Interest Payable on Mortgage $ 200.00 Mortgage Payable 10,000.00 Due School Endowment Fund 13,344.79 Total Liabilities ^ .....$ 23,544.79 Net Worth: Reserve for School Endowment Fund 29,863.57 Reserve for Hazel Todd Meadon Fund $ 1,291.86 Less Invested in Sugarlands Cottage 1,241.86 50.00 Donation by Mr. Voorheis 7,882.87 General Surplus June 30, 1931 87,514.54 Less: Charged back by returned check $ 200.00 Three-fourths Active Chapters Contributions for the year, carried to Reserve 1,883.37 Excess Expenses over Incomes for year ended 6-30-32, as per Exhibit "B" 2,473.10 4,556.47 Total General Surplus 82,958.07 Total Net Worth 120,754.51 Total liabilities and net worth $144,299.30 CASH AND BONDS IN ENDOWMENT FUND June 30, 1932 Face Value Book Value Cash Bonds Bonds Cash with Grand Treasurer June 30, 1931: Harris Investment Co $ 198.67 School Treasurer's Check # 392 2,860.62 School Treasurer's Check #393 1,728.62 To which was added June 30, 1932 Three-fourths Active Chapters Contributions 1,883.37 Cash repaid to Endowment Fund by vote of Committee 1,500.00 Total Cash $ From which the following bonds were purchased during the year: Commonwealth Edison 1st Coll. "C" 41/2's Crane Co. 10 Yr S/F Note 5's Southern Bell Tel. and Tel. 30 Yr 1st S/F 5's Southern California Edison Gen. 30 Yr. 5's Total Bonds purchased this year Bonds in Endowment Fund 6-30-31: Aluminum Co. of America S.F. Deb. 5's $ 2,000.00 $ 2,067.50 Ashland Corp. 1st Leasehold S.F. 6's 1,000.00 1,000.00 Cumberland County Power and Light Co. 1st 41/2's 1,000.00 955.00 O. B. and Mary E. B. Farnham 1st R.E. 5 's * 300.00 30550:0000 Minnesota Power and Light Co. 1st Ref. 5's 1,000.00 1,025.00 Missouri River, Sioux City Bridge Co. 1st S.F. 6's 1,000.00 1,000.00 Oklahoma Gas and Electric Co. 1st "A" 5's 1,000.00 1,000.00 Vicksburg Bridge and Terminal Co. 1st S.F. 6's 1,000.00 1,000.00 Total Bonds in Fund 6/30/31 8,300.00' 8,347.50 Total Cash and Bonds June 30, 1932 $ 3,546.28 $ 12,800.00 12,972.50 , 29,913.57 8,171.28 $ 500.00 $ 476.25 2,000.00 2,025.00 1,000.00 1,065.00 1,000.00 1,058.75 4,625.00.. 4,500.00". 4,625.00 Cash in Fund ' $ 3,546.28 Book value of ~~~..~~.~~~. ~~~.~. Savings Bank ".".".".".".".' ' 12,972.50 SCHEDULE OF FIXED ASSETS Pine 30, 1932 Real Estate " .' ' " " .'$ 7,90 0.00 Fences and Walks .. . .~ 998.48 Water System 633.07 Chicken Houses .. ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 734.59 .. ... .... . . . . .. . . .. .. . New Barn 3,336.16 Hospital Arrow Craft Shop 2,000.00 2,400.00 Mary Pollard Cottage . .. . ` 4,317.73 Industrial Building 25 006.57 Electric Light Plant ` 662.09 114.91 School House .. . 6,743.85 Stuart Cottage 2,011.02 Sugarland Cottage 3,772.71 Teachers Cottage Woodcraft Shop 7,882.87 Agricultural Shop 331.09 Bull Pens and Shed Hog .. . 332.81 Tool Shed 234.17 Automobile 905.10 Equipment ` 3,347.78 Equipment '' ''' ' ' ' ' ' '' '' 2,500.00 Equipment 2,083.03 Equipment and Fixtures Mary Pollard Cottage 1,000.00 Equipment 500.00 Equipment and Fixtures Evelyn Bishop House 500.00 Equipment and Fixtures Hospital .~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ Equipment and Fixtures New Barn _650.00 Equipment and Fixtures Chicken House 250.00 Total Less Reserve for ~~~~~~~ ~. .~. .~. .~ ~.~. . .~ ~ 3,782.30 77,481.04 Total Fixed Live Stock Inventory 1,460.00 STATEMENT ,OF INCOME AND EXPENSE Year Ended June 30, 1932 School Treasnrer's Books Books Total Income: $ $ 796.96 Smith Hughes Agriculture ' 1,406.50 1,406.50 Smith Hughes Home Economics 183.38 183.38 Hospital Farm .~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 367.34 243.01 367.34 243.01 Contributions Active Chapters 2,451.17 2,451.17 Contributions Alumnm Clubs . . ' 16,768.35 16,768.35 Contributions Individuals 576.50 576.50 Magazine Agency Interest Earned .~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 1,698.89 547.98 1,698.89 547.98 Miscellaneous 165.72, 165.72 Total Income $: 3,162.91 , $22,042.89 25,205.80 Expense: o 264.85 $ 2,074.96 $ 2,339.81 Smith Hughes Home Economics 106.13 1,250.00 1,356.13 262x01 2,146.11 2,408.12 Administration . .. 65.58 366.99 432.57 Auto Expense ` 219.81 219.81 Boys Dormitory ''''''''''' ''''' '''' 180.00 Community aervice 29.45 29.45 Fuel . ' 990.48 990.48 Furnishings and Home Supplies 348.65 348.65 Labor 284.07 284.07 Lights 794.02 794.02 Living Expense 827.64 827.64 Office Expense 34.05 180.00 214.05 ~~o 129.08 232.93 R~=~' and Upkeep 1,091.22 1o91.22 School Expense 246.97 246.97 </p>
      <pb ref="arr4910039_0008" seq="08" n="52-53  "/>
       <p> 276.92 580.14 857.06 90.50 Miscellaneous 162.63 326.77 489.40 Insurance 958.99 958.99 Salaries 5,159.13 5,159.13 ................................................. 1,265.86 1,265.86 Travel Expense 450.00 450.00 2,510.22 2,510.22 Total Expense $ 8,198.70 $ 17,748.25 $ 25,946.95 Excess School Expense over Income 741.15 Operations See School Audit Report ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " . ' ' ' ' ' ' ' . ' ' ' ' ' . . . 1,731/5 Excess Expenses over Income for the year ' ' .. . . ' . ' '. . ' .' . .' . . . ' . . ' .. . .' $ 2,473.10 * Salary $600.00, less gain in Live Stock Inventory $250.00 $350.00 DETAILS OF CHAPTER CONTRIBUTIONS FOR YEAR ENDED JUNE 30, 1932, AND MAGAZINE EARNINGS BY CHAPTERS FOR PART OF THE YEAR ACTIVE CHAPTERS Magazine Magazine Contributions Agency Profits Contributions Agency Profits Alpha Alpha ALUMNIE CLUBS Boston, Mass. ".".'w 204.75 $ Buffalo, N.Y 84.00 Burlington, Vt. ''''''' 10.75 Connecticut 150.00 N.Y New York, N.Y. 318.94 .150.00 Syracuse, N.Y 100o0 Canada 210.00 3.708.70 Ontario Alpha ".'$ -$ - 6.15 Maine Alpha 15.00 .20 14.35 Vermont Alpha 73.60 24.65 Vermont Beta ' .80 75.70 ". 4.65 9.60 New York Alpha - .o New York Gamma 20.00 1.45 New York Delta "." 50.00 - Beta Akron, Ohio ...o 40.00 Athens, ... ~~~l Valley, Pa. Pennsylvania ~~~ Cincinnati, Ohio 125.00 8.85 Clarksburg, W.Va 5.00 2.75 Cleveland Ohio 1,266.00 7.25 Columbus, Ohio 160.00 13.40 Delaware, Ohio 7.00 1.15 Harrisburg-Lancaster, Pa 200.00 .45 Mahoning Valley, Ohio 56.00 2.80 Miami Valley, Ohio 50.00 3.25 Morgantown, W.Va. . 10.00 .90 Northern New Jersey 350.00 18.00 Ohio Gamma __ _ Philadelphia, Pa 339.71 17.80 Pittsburgh, Pa 108.03 7.20 So. New Jersey 45.58 23.25 South Hills, Pa. "..' 45.00 3.05 Toledo, e` 100.00 $ 124.60 Gamma $ 158.60 $ 7.11 Beta Pennsylvania Alpha ".'$ 92.00 $ 9.10 Pennsylvania Beta Pennsylvania ~~~~~.~ 40.00 64.94 3.556 Ohio Alpha 150.00 5.15 Ohio Beta Ohio Delta ~" . " . " .' ~~G z~m $ 421.94 $ 39.25 Baltimore, Md o 124.00 $ 15.70 Maryland Alpha o 50.00 $ 4.01 North Carolina 50.00 Dist. of Columbia Alpha 50.00 3.40 Richmond, Va. ." 70.00 11.60 Virginia Alpha 45.00 .80 Washington, D.C. "." 959.70 44o5 Virginia Gamma 50.00 .50 ----' --- No. Carolina Alpha 25.00 - v1,20s.7m $ 71.35 a=Carolina Alpha 8.00 - Delta Bloomfield Hills, Mich. 50.00 Bloomington, Ind 31.00 Fort Wayne, Ind 10.00 Grand Rapids, Mich. . . . 30.00 Indianapolis, Ind 286.92 Southwestern Ind _ $ 228.00 $ 8.71 D w' 23.75 $ 20.75 $ - 14.4n Michigan Beta 62.75 2.90 Indiana Alpha 10.00 1.80 81.50 Indiana Beta 25.00 3.85 Indiana Gamma 25.00 4.80 Indiana Delta " 58.00 7.10 12.65 $ 201.50 4.45 $ 971.16 $ 152.50 Epsilon Carrollton, Mo $ _ Chattanooga, Tenn. 5.00 Columbia, Mo 133.74 Falls Cities Louisville, Ky 33.28 Joplin, Mo - Kansas City, Mo 750.00 Memphis, Tenn 16.00 Nashville, Tenn 5.00 St. Louis, Mo 707.00 Springfield, Mo 75.00 ALUMNAE CLUBS Magazine Contributions Agency Profits ACTIVE CHAPTERS Magazine Contributions Agency Profits Epsilon _ Missouri Alpha $ 25.00 $ 2.40 Missouri Beta 50.00 L90 7.50 Missouri Gamma 15.00 Kentucky Alpha 35.00 6.15 2.95 Tennessee Alpha 25.00 .90 66.60 $ 150.00 $ 8.95 2.00 68.65 13.45 $1,725.02 Zeta Atlanta, Ga $ 100.00 Birmingham, Ala 10.00 DeLand, Fla 75.00 Jacksonville, Fla 30.00 Lakeland, Fla 5.00 Miami, Fla 25.00 Orlando, Fla 85.00 Palm Beach, Fla 8.00 St. Petersburg, Fla Eta Avon, Libbie Brook Gaddis $ 16.00 Beloit, Wis 15.00 Carthage, Ill 15.00 Champaign-Urbana, Ill 100.00 Chicago, Ill. North 500.00 Chicago, Ill. South 300.00 Chicago West Suburban 120.00 Decatur, Ill 185.00 Elgin, Ill 27.50 Galesburg, Ill.. 75.00 Glenhurston, Ill 15.00 Madison, Wis 100.00 Milwaukee, Wis 175.00 Monmouth, Ill 30.00 North Shore, Ill 500.00 Oak Park and River Forest, 25.00 Peoria, Ill Rockford, Ill 25.00 Springfield, Ill 40.00 Theta Ames, Iowa $ 125.00 Burlington, Iowa 7.00 Cedar Rapids, Iowa 60.00 Des Moines, Iowa 188.22 Duluth, Minn 50.00 Grand Forks, N.D 20.00 Indianola, Iowa 25.00 Iowa City, Iowa 40.00 Minneapolis, Minn. . 150.00 Mt. Pleasant, Iowa 15.00 St. Paul, Minn 50.00 Sioux City, Iowa .. 25.00 Winnipeg, Man., Canada 10.00 1.15 1.00 $ 3.85 7.35 2.75 1.00 12.55 .85 3.55 2.80 .35 5.20 6.65 4.50 4.40 $ .70 15.75 7.60 2.30 3.20 1.85 11.45 15.95 11.15 8.70 .50 .25 $ 338.00 $ 24.60 22.00 .90 3.65 13.65 $2,263.50 $ 96.00 Zeta Alabama Alpha $ 25.00 $ Florida Alpha 50.00 Florida Beta 50.00 Florida Gamma 51.52 $ 176.52 $ Eta Wisconsin Alpha $ 50.00 $ .75 Wisconsin Beta 25.00 1.00 Illinois Alpha 25.20 Illinois Beta-Delta 25.00 Illinois Epsilon 25.00 Illinois Zeta 100.00 Illinois Eta 50.00 $ 300.20 $ 1.75 Theta Manitoba Alpha $ 10.00 No. Dakota Alpha 2.50 1.10 Minnesota Alpha 12.50 Iowa Alpha 20.00 3.00 Iowa Beta 5.00 .40 Iowa Gamma 5.00 _ Iowa Zeta $ $ 55.00 $ 4.50 $ 765.22 $ 79.40 Iota Boulder, Colo $ 50.00 Casper, Wyo 50.00 Cheyenne, Wyo 5.00 Denver, Colo 352.50 Lawrence, Kan 47.00 Lincoln, Neb 50.00 Manhattan, Kan 100.00 Omaha, Neb Poudre Valley 20.00 Pueblo, Colo 35.00 Topeka, Kan 22.00 Wichita, Kan 75.00 Laramie, Wyo 50.00 Iota $ 3.20 South Dakota Alpha $ 21.41 $ _ 9.55 Nebraska Beta 2.50 5.55 Kansas Alpha 47.75 Kansas Beta 75.00 1.15 13.05 Colorado Alpha 100.00 2.70 14.85 Colorado Beta 100.00 1.00 29.35 Wyoming Alpha 9.90 5.40 2.05 57.55 22.35 $ 296.41 $ 7.35 $ 856.50 $ 220.55 </p>
      <pb ref="arr4910039_0009" seq="09" n="54-55  "/>
       <p>ALUMNIE CLUBS Magazine Contributions Agency Profits Kappa rdmore, Okla $ 11.00 $ ustin, Tex 210.00 ryan, Tex 13.68 1.05 ,alias, Tex 200.00 5.60 ayetteville, Ark 15.00 ort Smith, Ark 15.00 4.50 ouston, Tex 250.00 24.87 ittle Rock, Ark 35.00 3.55 fuskogee, Okla 15.00 2.95 few Orleans, La 69.25 _ Forman, Okla _ _ klahoma City, Okla 25.00 16.40 krnulgee, Okla 20.00 3.00 abine District 317.34 12.60 hreveport, La 50.00 tillwater, Okla 10.00 ulsa, Okla 50.00 71.60 Claco, Tex 25.00 Lambda poise, Idaho $ 50.00 $ ;orvallis, Ore 7.50 10.05 ;ugene, Ore 50.00 19.50 ortland, Ore 450.00 31.85 alem, Ore 10.00 1.90 Battle, Wash 159.79 6.60 pokane, Wash 100.00 . acoma, Wash 100.00 Venatchee, Wash 10.00 f'akima, Wash 25.00 ACTIVE CHAPTERS Magazine Contributions Agency Profits Kappa Oklahoma Alpha $ 10.00 $ .50 Oklahoma Beta 25.00 Arkansas Alpha 5.00 1.65 Texas Alpha 100.00 Texas Beta 15.00 Louisiana Alpha 50.00 $ 205.00 $ 2.15 Lambda $ Alberta Alpha $ Montana Alpha 38.00 Idaho Alpha 5.00 1.50 Washington Alpha Washington Beta 10.00 10.30 Oregon Alpha 1.50 Oregon Beta 15.00 1.35 $ 68.00 $ 14.65 $1,331.27 $ 146.12 $ 69.90 Mu $ California Alpha $ 50.00 $ ....... California Beta 22.40 1.40 California Gamma 75.00 _ California Delta 75.00 28.80 Nevada Alpha _ Arizona Alpha 50.00 Utah Alpha 1.30 6.00 $ 250.00 1.30 1.70 5.50 7.40 6.00 _ 1.50 6.25 9.05 $2,392.23 96.00 RECAPITULATION $ 962.29 Mu Albuquerque, N. M $ lerkeley, Calif 500.00 77lendale, Calif 105.00 .ong Beach, Calif 75.00 -os Angeles, Calif 1,000.00 vlonterey Bay, Calif 14.00 ,Tevada Alumni 25.00 'alo Alto, Calif 65.00 'asadena, Calif 115.00 'hoenix, Calif 31.00 an Diego, Calif 100.00 an Francisco, Calif 142.23 an Jose, Calif 20.00 Tanta Monica, Calif. . 50.00 Eucson, Ariz Jtah Alumnae 75.00 -Ia.waii 75.00 ALUMNIE CLUBS Magazine Contributions Agency Profits tlpha $1,052.14 $ 139.40 seta 2,907.32 124.60 3amma 1,203.70 71.35 )elta 971.16 152.50 ipsilon 1,725.02 163.55 eta 338.00 24.60 ta 2,263.50 96.00 Cheta 765.22 79.40 ota 856.50 220.55 lappa 1,331.27 146.12 .ambda 962.29 69.90 v1u 2,392.23 96.00 Total $16,768.35 $1,383.97 Details on Magazine Earnings cover a part of the year only. ACTIVE CHAPTERS Magazine Contributions Agency Profits Alpha $ 158.60 $ 7.10 Beta 421.94 39.25 Gamma 228.00 8.71 Delta 201.50 4.70 Epsilon 150.00 8.95 Zeta 176.52 Eta 300.20 1.75 Theta 55.00 4.50 Iota 296.41 7.35 Kappa 205.00 2.15 Lambda 68.00 14.65 Mu 250.00 1.30 Total upon which 3 /4ths computed $2,511.17 $ 100.41. NOTE: Penn Beta for Eva Cailor $10.00 Ohio Alpha for Hazel Todd Meaden Fund 50.00 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW MAGAZINE AGENCY 55 IT IS a pleasant and cheerful task to make the report of the National Magazine Agency for the year 1931-32, as the total in commissions is the largest of which the National Agent has any record. $1500 was sent to the Settlement School after the expenses of running the agency were deducted. This shows that magazine work is growing in power, and that commissions from it may soon be counted on as a potent factor in the support of the school. More alumnae clubs are patronizing the agency, and the active chapters have made a beginning in the work. Many clubs earned larger commissions than in previous years, due to the fact that more stress was placed on the securing of subscriptions, and that clubs are beginning to realize that a nice pro-portion of their Settlement School donations may be earned by this easy method. The detailed report of the commissions of clubs and chapters by provinces is given in connection with the report of the Settlement School Treasurer elsewhere in THE ARROW, so that each group may see at a glance their total of gifts to the school. This year, in ranking clubs for magazine earnings, two methods have been used: (1) total commission, (2) commission per member. Cards were sent out to club secretaries asking them to send to the National Magazine Agent the number of paid members in their club. Some clubs did not respond to this request, therefore their commission per member could not be calculated. Many clubs with medium or small membership have come to the front in this second method of rating, while some of the larger clubs still hold their place among the first. The following clubs have earned the largest total commissions: 1. Detroit, $81.50 Mrs. F. E. Ehlert, Agent 2. New York, $75.70 Mrs. D. D. Fredrick-son, Agent 3. Tulsa, $71.60 Mrs. W. P. Beeve, Agent 4. St. Louis, $68.65 Mrs. W. R. Gentry, Jr., Agent 5. Kansas City, $66.60 Mrs. H. E. Scurlock, Agent 6. Wichita, $57.55 Mrs. E. S. Stephenson, Agent 7. Denver, $47.75 Mrs. Arnim Thebus, Agent 8. Washington, D.C., $44.05 Mrs. D. D. Drain, Agent These clubs have earned the highest commission per paid member: 1. Tulsa, $1.32 per member Mrs. W. P. Beeve, Agent 2. Athens, $1.31 per member Mrs. F. B. Gullum, Agent 3. Detroit, $1.29 per member Mrs. F. E. Ehlert, Agent 4. Manhattan, $1.04 per member Mrs. C. C. Brewer, Agent 5. Mt. Pleasant, $1.01 per member Mrs. C. F. Hayes, Agent 6. Ann Arbor, .989 per member Miss Jessica Brown, Agent 7. Atlanta, .984 per member Miss Martha Pratt, Agent 8.. New York, .97 per member Mrs. D. D. Fredrickson, Agent In both methods of rating, many clubs followed closely after these eight, and it is a matter of regret that space does not permit them to be mentioned. It would be interesting to figure what the results would have been if all clubs had done as well as the aforementioned eight in each group. Without much mathematics, it can be seen that the grand total would have increased many thousands of dollars. The National Magazine Agent wishes to ex-press her appreciation of the steady, dependable work of the agents of all alumnae clubs, as upon their constant efforts depended the success of the agency. Each subscription, no matter how small a commission it gives, adds just that much to our total. Each one is valuable, in that it gives a renewal for the following year, and if club agents keep their renewals coming in and secure some new business each year, the commissions mount up amaz</p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



