<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr4530221_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Curtis, Blanche Charlton</name></author>
                        <author><name>Pollard, Mary O.</name></author>
                        <author><name>Watson, Katherine</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>February 1929</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr4530221_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">February 1929</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Curtis, Blanche Charlton</name></author>
                        <author><name>Pollard, Mary O.</name></author>
                        <author><name>Watson, Katherine</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 221-231</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">38</note>
                        <note type="Folder">1</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 45, Number 2 (February 1929), Pages 221-231.</note>
			<note type="document">arr4530221_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Twelve Years After; The Little Cottage; Evening School Classes</note>
                        <note type="Additional Information">if numbered correctly, this should be issue 3</note>
	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Development</item>
                                <item>Living conditions</item>
                                <item>Facilities</item>
                                <item>Home economics</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr4530221_0001" seq="01" n="220-221  "/>
       <p>THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI M. FosTER father of Fran-r Buckmaster, Ohio A, is ssioner of the Court of Jashington, D.C. He was a )ngressman from Ohio. Mr. a graduate of Ohio Uniid a member of Phi Delta .ET GRIFFIN daughter of Bancroft Griffin, New York a class of 17j in Jamaica, -k, in June 1928, and de--Le valedictory address. She ved the medal for highest in Greek and Latin and :.teen years of age. ALBERT PIERCE brother of rce Cunningham, Colorado me received the doctor of 7 degree in chemistry from Johns Hopkins University. Dr. Pierce has been totally deaf since he was eleven years old so all of his work has been done through the medium of lip reading which he studies at the Clark School for the Deaf in Northampton, Massachusetts. Dr. Pierce received his bachelor of arts and graduate in pharmacy degrees from the University of Iowa and his master of science degree from the University of Denver. In 1915 Dr. Pierce married Lita Towner, member of Kappa Kappa Gamma and daughter of Horace Mann Towner, governor of Porto Rico. She died in IgI8 leaving a small son and in 1g26 Dr. Pierce married again. He firmly believes a deaf person can do anything anyone else can if he tries and has written several articles showing the bright side of his affliction. S ME CODY )ROAD ,0a..R16XSS ,,r, C.---ourtcsy of the Northern Pacific Ry. THRILLING CODY ROAD Yellowstone Park rwelve rears after By MARY O. POLLARD V\7 HEN I STARTED for the first time to Gatlinburg in Sep tember, 1913, my courage was high, and I looked forward with much zest to a year of pleasure and service. By the time I had transferred across Knoxville in the early morning hours of the following day, and found myself seated in the dirty coach of the "Knoxville Slow and Easy," my courage was waning. By the time the train had begun its slow crawl up the grade toward Sevierville and I had examined my fellow passengers, I wondered why I had ever agreed to come. When two hours later was stooping under the edge of the coach at' Sevierville to allow the circus-going crowd to surge into the train before I could make my way to the station platform, my heart had sunk very low. When I had walked past the smallpox sign on a shanty on the river bank, had smelled the pig pens by the bridge, and had eaten a belated breakfast at the Snapp House, I 'would gladly have backed out from my bar-gain if I could have done so withany plausible excuse except cowardice. Three school years after, when I took my leave of the burg on the first of April, 1916, it was with as much regret as my arrival had caused me trepidation; and at the station when I had watched the circus crowd boarding the train and had wished I dared go back with them, three years later I sat on a pile of lumber with Mrs. Bishop and Miss Evelyn and wept bitter tears at departing. I had found at Gatlinburg some, of the dearest friends of my life; I had learned to know the heart of the people, and I admired and respected and loved my neighbors and my friends. The Transformation Last spring, when Miss Evelyn insisted that there was a welcome for me at the Cottage, I arrived with almost as much hesitation and fear as I had on my previous coming. As the train wound among the mountains between the Kentucky line and Knoxville, I tried to picture what it would all look </p>
      <pb ref="arr4530221_0002" seq="02" n="222-223  "/>
       <p>222 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI like now with the new roads and the new hotels and the new school buildings and most of all with the new personnel at the Cottage. When 'I was hurried from the rail-road station to the bus station in Knoxville, and found myself speeding around the curves and rushing along the "pike" between Knoxville and Sevierville where we used to make a full day's journey, I felt as if I were in a dream. Again at Sevierville, at a new hotel, as gladly as I would have turned back, before, I would have turned back this time, had it not been for the cordial welcome of Mrs. Bishop. The next morning Mrs. Bishop and I started to the Burg, to be ready for Old Settlers' Day. It all did not seem possible. Seated in an auto-mobile we flew over the road where on my first trip we had forded the Little Pigeon six times between the bridge just outside Sevierville and our arrival at the Burg. This journey which, in good weather used to take us at least three hours, and in which we scarcely dared go faster than a walk for fear of upsetting in the holes and tipping on the huge rocks, was being accomplished in less tha'n three-quarters of an hour. Nothing along the way seemed natural. As we crossed the bridge at Banner, I still could not adjust myself. When we neared the Burg, there still was no familiar land-mark. The old mill where we used to fish was a tea room, on the right hand side where formerlyonly bushes were, were now an antique shop, a gift shop, a garage, a lunchroom. Could this be the same Gatlinburg? At the curve where we used to get our first glimpse of the settlement the view was entirely changed. The old Methodist Church was gone; the hotel was in front of me; a new store occupied the site of Miss Nancy's house; and even the trees had grown so that the white walls of the old school house barely peeped through the branches. Past the new post office, and Squire Maples' house with its stone wall and its new paint, between the attractive stone gate posts we turned into the lane where formerly we used to wade through the mud. In front of us was a row of buildings where had stood our one little cot tag e, with its shed and barn at the foot of the hill. In an instant I found myself in the cottage where I had spent three busy, anxious, happy years. Except for the front porch there was nothing that looked at all the same. The added story at the rear, the dining room, the stairway, the dormitory above, the stepping stones from the door everything was different. And this entirely aside from the electric lights and the Frigida.ire and the running water, and the telephone. Those things fitted into these new sun rouridings; they would have been out of place in our house with its fireplaces, and its well in the yard, and its kerosene lamps and lanterns. Mary O. Pollard, Vermont Alpha, one of the pioneer workers in the Settlement School project and head resident during the days of the three-room cottage, went back to visit Gatlinburg this past summer. While it was very difficult for her to grasp the remarkable changes that had taken place in the Burg, no one appreciates them more than Miss Pollard. She was so delighted with everything that she purchased a beautiful site for a mountain cottage in the shadow of the sentinel of the Great Smokies, Mount Le Conte. NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON So far I had not sensed the new buildings. I merely sensed people. All about me were people. Where formerly visitors had been such a rarity that we talked of their coming for weeks and of their departure for more weeks, there seemed to be a busy swarm of people all of whom seemed to belong. Instead of our old family of five or at the most six, the tables seemed endless; and when one person got up, another reset the table and took the place. I felt as if I were in a moving picture. When I saw Miss Onken, I realized that the Settlement School Committee was having its meeting at the School, and that not all these people really were permanent residents. Yet it took several days for me to know the work of each one the bookkeeper the two girls at the shop; the domestic science teacher who sometimes stopped in on her way between visits to Banner and Laurel Lick and other out-lying stations, the nurse, the nurse's assistant oh, yes, I recognized Lillie; but all this was a change from our little group who ate and cooked and worked together sharing in common all the duties. Old Friends In a few minutes after my arrival the Settlement Committee and I made our way to the new building. The crowd had gathered in the gymnasium for the forenoon program of Old Settlers' Day, and I stood in hesitation at the rear of the room trying to make some-thing or somebody look natural to me. Then Miss Evelyn insisted that I go to the platform. In a daze I tried to make out faces that I knew. One by one I saw theold friends Lewis Cla and Sherman; Lawson an( Reagen, Amos Trentham Whaley yes the grown pc gan to look familiar, but tIl folks never appeared fan me. Arlena clerking in t office; Blanche Huff ready third year of high school clerking in the hotel office Maples Ogle with half-gro dren about her, Elder al Mae settled in their ow with their three children Maples in college I could just myself to them, they 17 strangers to me. As the weeks passed, 1 things began to take fore mind. The most obvious were, of course, the exter: the new roads, the new h Steve Whaley's old corn fie Roaring Fork and on where Doctor Montgomery used to be alone, the nevc building; the paint on the and the walls about the ya flowers in every dooryard tomobiles which honked p hours of day and night. ence of the guests at t: was obvious, for some were people who came to week in the country and I get the amenities of thei: home and assumed the d: the swagger that, in thei went with a summer vac the country. These, : seemed the exception rat] the rule, and their present served to emphasize the fi tesy and the interest that jority of the village gu in the welfare of the co] There was nothing, I am caused me any greater cl </p>
      <pb ref="arr4530221_0003" seq="03" n="224-225  "/>
       <p>THE ARROW OF P1 BETA PHI change than the constant Ind coming of girls and in bathing suits. I try to the scene had one of the iris or one of the Pi Phi in my day gone along the treet of the Burg in a suit of today. Yet their passing caused not a of comment, apparently, the loafers on the store from their external immt, one of the noticeable is in the living conditions eople. One item alone will fy this. In scarcely a place isited did I not find screens doors and the windows. I think who had screens lived there, and I could f only three or four famiow the poorest families feel i of them. With this change ment has gone, of course, changes. A good many lave piped water into kitch-.d there is an occasional m installed. The grade of incomparable with that in y. Every field has good very house has good hens; Ian has good pigs. In no t the influence of the school vn more conclusively than :hange in the grade of farm 'pt All For the Best people themselves? It is t they are better dressed, and do not show any perceptible difference in clothes from those of the visitor. at the hotel. It is rather that they obviously have money in their pockets. One may say what he will about money not being necessary for happiness and for self respect. I know from looking at these friends of mine this summer that the coming of the industrial work into their lives has made of the women and the children a different people from what I knew, twelve years ago. They have learned that they have some-thing that people are willing to spend money for. They therefore feel their own industrial importance; they look anyone in the eye with whom they talk; they are self-respecting, productive citizens, and in this consciousness they carry themselves with an added dignity and an innate pride that commands the respect of the visitors. Gatlinburg is not the village that I went to twelve years ago. I confess that I missed some of the things, that I wished them back. Yet when I began to think what I would have back, I decided that the changes that have come are the ones that we were working for, and I do not believe that Gatlinburg will lose its self-respect because it gains prosperity and becomes an intimate part of the great world outside, and the progress that has been made is a credit to themselves as well as to the fraternity. NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON The Jttle Cottage By KATHERINE WATSON 225 P ERHAPS IT WOULD BE WELL to begin with the idea and then tell of its development into reality for so it was with our Little Cottage. It was November and I'd begun to wonder how a unit of "House Planning and Management" could best be taught. We had an avail-able cottage in our orchard and I had thought of letting the girls plan remodeling it and furnishing it but only on paper! Then one day a friend came and suggested a Demonstration House to be entered in the April Contest. Immediately vague imaginings began to take form and color. I could almost see the shabby little frame cottage preen -itself and take on an air of self respect and happiness. And as suddenly bushes of laurel and rhododendron seemed to hop from the mountain behind to the front of the cottage to nestle there and help make a home. 'Twas on Friday that the vision came and by Monday I was fairly bursting with excitement. Before I could tell the glad news to the girls I had to consult the Higher Powers and have the plan approved. This was a matter of but few moments. Everyone seemed in favor of such a project. When the girls finally knew they were almost as fascinated as I to think of actually furnishing a cottage as part of their work and so it began. Plans About three two-hour class periods were spent in plans for re-modeling the house so as to include a bathroom. This was done, of course, after a visit to the cottage. Each girl had a very definite view on the matter and they weren't all alike! After much discussion a plan was accepted where-by only one partition had to be built. There were also many and intense objections to having the kitchen in the front of the house. These were not entirely over-ridden until the attractive kitchen was an actuality. Then came the measuring for lumber, and securing it. If you have not lived way back up in the mountains you have no idea of what such seemingly trifling things are. But after a few weeks work did begin. I am not so sure the boys of the manual training classes were thrilled at the beginning. They could see no point in "so many kitchen shelves." Why, "Only a house keeper could possibly need them." In my opinion they deserve even more credit than the girls. They could see no vision and yet did their very best. The road from the school to the cottage (about one and one-half miles) was rough and muddy as December bad days came. Often it was too cold to work. So it was not until sometime in February that each shelf was securely nailed in place, the beaver boarding done, and the bathroom partition a reality. Again it was the girls' time three lessons were spent in trans</p>
      <pb ref="arr4530221_0004" seq="04" n="226-227  "/>
       <p>. .y :. :~ gym :~+ ~ w _,s ` t } . BEFORE AND AFTER The model cottage at Gatlinburg which received $100 as second prize in the National Better Homes Project. NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON planting shrubs. Unless you've very carefully dug up rhododendron and carried it down an al-most perpendicular mountain side without shaking too much dirt from its roots, then as carefully set it in its laboriously prepared home, I'm afraid you can't appreciate the work my girls success-fully accomplished. "If Winter Comes " It took spring a long, long time to come this year and there were so many days when no work could be done. With home-made candy as a gentle persuasion I finally got my brothers (twelve and sixteen years) to harrow the yard so as to level the bumps. Then we sowed grass, which in due time came up and was lovely. I must tell of the house painting. We used a creosote shingle stain moss green in color. One Saturday morning we started spraying it on with a hand pump. One of my brothers was to pump while the other sprayed. We all stood around watching breathlessly to see the transformation of the first rough boards. The pump worked but, alas, with a reverse action and it was a boy instead of a board that was trans-formed. He was the most sickening green I ever be-held. The pump was finally fixed and we got half of the house sprayed that day and the rest another Saturday. We are all very proud of the job, though to the professional paint-er I'm sure it would appear teurish. And now for the inside. kitchen would be a good pl start. Just inside and to the of the door leading from the room into the kitchen is ow net. "Our," for ours it certa and it is a pride and joy the $1.40. We started with a splintery, bow-legged affair. boys built three shelves or and the girls, not satisfied, a back for those same s: Then we used zinc for the the table, tacking it on se, Next the legs were scrape( glass and sandpapered. Twc of gray enamel were applie the whole thing. Then the faced with Japanese red h Next came the equipment. marshmallow tins, when dre; gray lacquer with red trim made excellent boxes for bre sugar. Each has its name stenciled on the top. Sal hi bottles make the very nic spice jars when their to] painted red and lettered. T1 problem of meal and flour easy to solve. First a boar, enough and long enough to two big lard cans. Then bi lers screwec the bottom. an upright ' Then the lar Again sonic and red and you're t The Trim Proceed i the stove w1l baby range of cast irc four big e3 Memorial Gift A very beautiful and fit ting tribute to the memory of a beloved sister was made in November when Mrs. Charles Carroll Folmer of Grand Rapids, Michigan, sent the Settlement School a gift of fifty dollars as a me morial to her sister, Kather ine Rogers (Mrs. Lewis B. Cutcheon) of Michigan Beta '98. </p>
      <pb ref="arr4530221_0005" seq="05" n="228-229  "/>
       <p>8 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI vo little ones ones, a warming ven, an oven large enough for a )ast pan (moderate size), and all Jr $37.50. Oh, yes, and a place )r a water back. Now directly opposite the range ou'll find shelves six of them Dr kitchen utensils. These are at le right hand side of the sink and aese have blue and white gingham urtains cross stitched in red, that lip easily on wires, to keep out ust and look pretty. These are lso found on our cabinet. We have two drain boards which /ere made in the school shop. Lineed oil was rubbed into the wood a prevent the absorption of water. )ur sink is high enough to keep ou from breaking your back daily t dish washing. It is in front f a window so here is light and it also a view of the mountains nd a nasturtium bed. Just to the left, and where it aay be seen from the living room a built-in corner cupboard with :hinese-red trimmings and lovely lue china, willow ware. There are wo doors at the bottom which, /hen open, disclose big things like n ice-cream freezer. Then a table for two or four ut no more, under the front win-ow. It was horrid black kind of lission stuff but now it is a pretty ray and red. The linoleum, though not a fine 'mole, is very pretty with its touch f red. We waxed it at once and y keeping it waxed hope to make last longer. I almost forgot the :itchen stool, which you will find a front of the cabinet. The living room and library eren't hard at least not so very ! )ne day the women in the evening chool class spent the day and crubbed. They dissolved soap and a little lye in hot water. This they threw with main force onto the ceiling and walls, using a stew pan with a handle for the purpose. Then they brushed it all down and scrubbed the floor. That same day the girls washed windows. We simply took them out of the frames and into the yard because it was easier than using ladders. The pictures show better than I can ever tell how these rooms looked after the -furniture was placed. I believe they fail to show, however, the table in the library which is either dressing table or desk. It is like the one to the right of the living room fire but has a mirror hanging over it. The mirror is shaped like the one over the chest of drawers. Next the tiny hallway. We could get no picture of it or the bath-room because they were too small. Let us enter the hall from the living room. To our right is a clothes closet with a shelf for hats and a rod for hangers and a shoe bag on the door. The bag was made by the women in evening school class. To your left against the living room wall are three deep shelves for linen and bedding. Curtains of print sliding on wires serve as doors. Like the ones in the kitchen, they may. be pinched back with clothes pins which are lacquored red. Under these shelves is a most noble clothes basket made by "Broom-Tying Richard Ogle." He takes pride in all his work and was especially proud of this big basket. It is made of white oak splits and has a "kiver," (cover). I must add that Richard was among the first to visit our house on Sunday of our opening nor did he leave until the last visitor had gone. Richard had counted them all NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON with great satisfaction. He beamed with pride when they admired his basket. The bathroom is almost a sight unseen in our mountains. First we gave the walls three coats of cream paint. Then laid and waxed a blue and cream linoleum. For weeks it seemed that there would be nothing but a towel rack to indicate the purpose of this cheerful room. Finally it was the Saturday before the opening and yet no sign of tub. I went down to our store and told the man I would stay until he sent me and the tub, etc., home. He evidently didn't like the idea for soon we, tub and I, were in a truck. Of course the fixtures could only be placed that afternoon., But they had to be scrubbed vigorously and the out-side of the tub enameled. Final Touches Finally we come to our rose and green bedroom. Here one door was changed, another sealed up and a fireplace unsealed. Next rough boards were nailed to the studding, then the beaver board put on with pine strips. The windows and doors were faced and the baseboards put on. After the boys had done all this a man was hired to do the rock work and we were wellpleased with the result. The beav board was, soiled so a coat of al bastine was applied. The stri were given a coat of clear varni.5 We left all of the floors witho any finish except scrubbing course, because there was neith time nor money for anything eh I will not describe the bedroom b cause. the pictures show it so Ilea ly. I think we love it most. It so simple and clean and the sup shine pours in from morning um night. The screen porch adjoining bo kitchen and living room is tI nicest summer dining room ima inable. It has a table and foi comfortable split bottom chair There is a drop leaf table in tl living room that may be used rainy weather. So there is plen of dining space. If you now have the picture an unpretentious but charming comfortable mountain home your mind's eye, my aim in writii this has been reached. We of t] Gatlinburg community feel th this Better Homes Project h been of far-reaching benefit. meant long and hard work, but think I express the feeling of ea girl and boy and woman when say our efforts have been mo than repaid. evening eSchool Classes By KATHERINE WATSON EVENING SCHOOL CLASSES are those held either in the afternoon or evening for women and girls over sixteen years of age. The class must have sixwomen who attend regularly, a preferably ten. The purpose these classes is to give home e( nomics education to adults by de ing with problems which t1</p>
      <pb ref="arr4530221_0006" seq="06" n="230-231  "/>
       <p>THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI elves bring up, and when posgiving short courses in varilases of the work. ning School work is inform. t will have to be informal our rural women become accustomed to the idea of ion and that will be many To give an idea of the a brief outline of a week's KATHERINE WATSON as they are held during the nwill probably serve best. s Monday at twelve-thirty mble into a taxi laden with as, scissors, tapes, magazines, t is a distance of some seven ht miles to Pigeon Forge a clothing class is held in hool building. Pigeon Forge mall community right on the ay. Its people might well be bed as "proud" but kindly. must be handled with care hey already know much! There are both women and girls in this class. Usually each comes with her own problem a child's dress to be made from one of her own, a house dress, a nightgown, curtains to be planned, a new way to make pretty cushions. All these problems must be handled so as to benefit each member of the class if possible. The greatest difficulty is that each woman is so absorbed with her own problem that it is hard for her to wait for some other's to be explained. The order of first come, first served is absolutely necessary here. There is very little time for theory but between problems and in connection with them I try to squeeze in a little color and line and their whys and wherefores. Fashion books are a source of delight. I was able to secure some large ones with colored pictures. These and current magazines serve to occupy those women who come with nothing to do. At the end of the two hours at Pigeon Forge we have usually cut three or four garments and perhaps fitted them. The actual sewing is done largely at home. Tuesday afternoon at Banner is very interesting. I call it my class of nine women and ninety children! The "ninety" is perhaps exaggerated but they are such lively youngsters that by the end of the class it seems as if there were actually that many. The women must bring the youngest three if they come and I am always glad to have them. These women seem most interested in foods. I am glad because some of the children show the need of proper diet. At each class I NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON 231 try to prepare some simple every-day food in. pleasing way and so that it may, without any risk, be given to the three or four year* old child. Baked custards, simple breads, eggs in various ways. To them any method of cooking an egg, with the exception of frying, is new. Often I prepare two or three simple foods that may be used together. The women bring the materials, except when they forget! In such cases, if I don't have the article myself, we have to change plans and do the best we can. While the food is cooking we cut a child's dress or rompers, or a house dress or whatever has been brought along. When the food is done each has a taste, including the ninety babies. Then the girls wash dishes different girls each time. Banner is just beginning to take an interest in evening-school work and there is much to be done. Tuesday night at Gatlinburg is a class in foods. Gatlinburg has had this work for some three years so more formal instruction can be given. The class is composed of girls and women. The children are left at home. The attendance here varies from six to sixteen. Meal planning and serving is a source of much interest here. The women themselves actually planned the meals and two would bring the food and cook and serve the meal. Each is a gala occasion, besides serving to give the women self-confidence and valuable information. At Sugarlands Wednesday after-noon, we find a class of girls ranging from fifteen to twenty years, with perhaps one or two older women. Foods work here seems to hOld their interest better thanclothing. They bring pencil and paper and take down the recipe which is for the simple preparation of an everyday food again. Some-times I demonstrate and again they do the work. One day a very simple meal was prepared with a menu of escalloped potatoes, slaw, hot muffins and butter. Laurel Lick is, a long way and a tiresome trip. At 6:30 A.M. I take a taxi at the Burg. .At 7:00 I'm at Pigeon Forge where I hunt until I secure a horse, or rather a nag. It may be the peddler's noble "Charlie-Dan" or a farmer's faithful Maud. You would laugh to see Charlie-Dan's heavy black mustache, his bridle with blinds and his chic strap of pink gingham, his saddle blanket of a feed sack. To' urge him out of a walk is agony to the rider. So for an hour we amble around the hills, which are really lovely, to a small white schoolhouse perched in the sunshine on top of one. The class here is of girls, a small class but faithful. There would be more, I am sure, but visiting is next to impossible because of the length of time required for going and coming. Foods here again is the chief interest. Sometimes a cake is made by request, sometimes soup, sometimes potatoes prepared in different ways, also by request. Friday closes the week with a clothing class at the Burg. It is a class of women and babies. I keep a big packing box properly lined to deposit the baby in, give him a ball to play with while his mother cuts her dress. This is a class of construction and the women always have almost more than we can accomplish. The time always flies The week is gone! </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



