<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr4740459_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Curtis, Blanche Charlton</name></author>
                        <author><name>Bishop, Evelyn</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>May 1931</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr4740459_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">May 1931</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Curtis, Blanche Charlton</name></author>
                        <author><name>Bishop, Evelyn</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 458-464</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">38</note>
                        <note type="Folder">6</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 47, Number 4 (May 1931), Pages 458-464.</note>
			<note type="document">arr4740459_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Aunt Lizzie Reagan; Aunt Sabria King; The Southern Mountains Handicraft Guild; A Needed Gift; Gatlinburg Notes</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Southern Appalachian culture</item>
                                <item>Handicraft</item>
                                <item>Food</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr4740459_0001" seq="01" n="458-459  "/>
       <p>FAST.A.AvMvP,,AvirAvPWAlvA,AwANRANORMI'MVAM. ?i.c4oic''42itoAtc4'vic,oleolcoic'49R.4'91c'49icoicami ,O *All N. !{I)J II Id IN II MPII,JC ti edited by Blanche Charlton Curtis tunt Lizz o fleaan ONE of the greatest )rivileges of belonging to the "good Ad days" of our school was that )f knowing some of the older )eople of the mountains. The past en years have taken a heavy toll ind there are now few left who )elong to those days. Many Pi Phis who have been in Jatlinburg have hear=d Aunt Lizzie ay "I came one day and she came he next" and that was the way it vas. From the first day I was at the chool Aunt Lizzie was there and that a staunch friend she has been AUNT LIZZIE REAGANto the school and to each of us individually. And what a strong link she has been to join the past with the present. Aunt Lizzie came to take care of the little Prickett baby while his mother and father were in the schoolroom teaching, but-before the first year was over she had taken on her shoulders many household cares in our little family. She said she soon found that if we were to have light bread all the time she must learn to make it, for I was sure to be away just the time the bread should be mixed and with pride she found she could bake a better loaf than I could. Cooking was not nearly all Aunt Lizzie looked after. The second year we bought our first cow' and Aunt Lizzie was the proud caretaker of it, not trusting the milking to any male resident of Gatlinburg. That same year she was the sole care-taker of my little pet pig and brought it from a wee thing to the II (t. market. The first chickens were Aunt Lizzie's care. In fact, as our farm animals grew in number it was hard for the men to persuade Aunt Lizzie that the chickens were going to have to be put in the new chicken houses and yards, farther from the convenient kitchen door. And it was with many a misgiving and much reluctance that the milking was finally turned over to the The May ARROW dormitory boys and the man who had come to the school as a farmer. The flowers continued to be hers, though, as long as she stayed. How could Phyllis Higinbotham ever have done her first years of nursing here without Aunt Lizzie's help? She knew every family for miles around and their family history. Few long trips were taken without first consulting Aunt Lizzie about direction, roads, and family, for Phyllis saw early in the game who she could trust, which speaks for her wisdom as well as Aunt Lizzie's. But changes had to come. Our little family that used to number four or five during the winter and one or two in summer and that included all who lived on the place kept growing until there were about forty-five to live with. Even the summer that used to be so quiet never found us with less than twelve or fifteen in the family. The home life had changed, there was a hurry and bustle that Aunt Lizzie didn't enjoy, and the work was too hard. She bought a little place on Mill Creek and the house is at the Lrow of the hill. She can look down into the valley and says she hears our dinner bell and some days watches us go to dinner. Now and then we have supper on her porch and on those too rare occasions we always say we soon will go back for another good visit. Aunt Lizzie is versatile. Giving up her work at the school didn't mean that she gave up all interests, any more than bringing up five children and under especially hard conditions meant that she had given up caring for children. Far from it. Six grandchildren in one family and that many and more in anotherone mean that every night some them stay with her. With their he she puts in a small crop and has garden anyone may well be prat of. She has her pet cow that sl says she can tell anywhere and th she uses as an excuse for alwa. going home before dark each nie All this would keep most fol: busy but the past two years anoth occupation has been take up and only wish I could begin to tell yc of the joy that has come with Some years ago we bought the b old-fashioned loom that used to b long to Aunt Lydia. It couldn't set up, as the weaving room th, was under a porch and the spa, too small for such a big thin When the new building was cot pleted and they moved into the b weaving room, there was a love corner just right for the Au Lydia loom. Of course Aunt Liz2 was the one they turned to he set up the old residenter. Mi Strand, the weaving teacher, su gested that Aunt Lizzie put on warp and thread it for the old jea patterns. After thirty-five yea Aunt Lizzie set up the loo: threaded it and wove. Not a sins thing had she forgotten in all th time. In fact she knew many a litl "turn" that Miss Strand had nev heard of and that Aunt Lizzie tc her of with great pride. In she Aunt Lizzie is queen of the wea ing room. All winter she has wov because she said the room w warm, I know she will continue tl spring and will have an equa: good excuse but the great reas is that she just loves it. Besid weaving she winds bobbins for se eral women living near who wea for the school. She not only c manage the old loom better th </p>
      <pb ref="arr4740459_0002" seq="02" n="460-461  "/>
       <p>The May ARROW le else but can manage the ing wheel the bobbins are d on. ere is no finer example of the mountain person, with splen-,ative ability and intelligence, .nt THE household of Aunt a of King's Branch is a miniakingdom and its subjects are aembers of her family whom ules with a firm hand. Nobody notices Aunt Sabria's husband she is present, for she simply 1es,, him aside as if he were a in her way. A quiet old man a patriarchal white beard, by e of which Victoria Strand, weaving teacher, has named minor prophet," he sits all day e porch or by the fireside. Ap-Itly he never ventures to speak rd in regard to affairs of the AUNT SABRIA KINGinnate dignity, and courtesy and strong character. No one is dearer to me as a friend and no one more loyal to our school. EVELYN BISHOP family. The daughters, Emmaline and Katherine, are equally meek in submitting to their mother's autocratic management. They are weavers for the school, but Aunt Sabria is really mistress of ceremonies. In years gone by she was an expert weaver but now she leaves the actual work to others and assumes the role of critic and director. Not infrequently she undertakes to dictate to Miss Strand her opinions about prices and de-signs. Aunt Sabria considers herself an authority on most domestic subjects. Although the need for hand-made cloth has passed, on King's Branch, as in other mountain communities, her hands have not for-gotten their skill in the old arts of carding and spinning. At the first Old Timers' Day program she won the prizes for these accomplishments. Certainly she is a thrifty housewife and a gracious hostess. Not only does she watch over the looms of Emmaline and Katherine but she directs the cultivation of the farm. Her garden and fine flock of chickens are her chief pride. The three-room house, its walls papered with seed catalogs and newspapers, is always immaculate and the little dooryard is swept as clean as a floor. Not a weed or blade of grass mars its smooth surface, only the rose bushes and other shrubs tidily arranged about the fence. The May ARROW 461 Sometimes on hot summer days Aunt Sabria and the two daughters will stop work to sit in a solemn row on the porch. Few families live above them on the branch, so a chance passer-by is always noted with interest. "Come in and set awhile out of the sun," Aunt Sabria will call, "Gain' up to Mollie's?" When I tell her that I'm going to see Mollie's daughter and the new baby she will say, "Well, the baby's pert enough, but that girl don't know a thing about raisin' a young un. I've been telling them . . ." and on she will go with a lecture on the rearing of babies. Aunt Sabria is a midwife and has a vast store of pseudo-medical knowledge that she has gathered from various sources. She is reputed to be the best "granny-woman" for miles about and many a patient would rather have her services than those of the best physician in the country. With her neat calico dress and white apron, and her trim little midwife kit, she really is a figure worthy of respect. Scores of babies she has welcomed into the world. She boasts proudly that she has dressed five pairs of twins. Not only is she kind to her patients and scrupulously clean in caring for them, but she has very good judgment and is most unwilling for them to incur any risk at her hands. Though she privately considers herself a remarkably clever midwife, she never hesitates one moment to call for a physician's assistance if she feels at all doubtful about the case. One of the doctors said, "If Aunt Sabria sends for me, I know I'd better get there." She is a mighty influence in her own little community, setting a fine example of homemaking and neighborliness. In every home along the creek one finds evidence of her teaching. Everywhere the people say, "Well, Aunt Sabria told me." By these tokens Aunt Sabria represents the finest stock of the mountains. She is a real pioneer who faces life with courage and dignity. FRANCES Mooan The Southern Mountains Handicraft Guild ON MARCH 27, 1931, the third annual meeting of the Handicraft Guild of the Southern Mountains was held at the Mountain View Hotel in Gatlinburg, with more than forty members and friends of the guild in attendance. If we can judge the future by the interest of the present we can be sure that a big, really worth-while thing will evolve from this small beginning. The reason for establishing the guild is no doubt apparent to all. There is the desire to preserve the handicrafts of the mountains, to en-courage the home industries with their individuality and their beauty of color and design, to improve in every possible way the crafts, and to make a very definite study in regard to the marketing of these products. There are more than thirty producing centers and individuals in the guild membership, as well as several people who have joined as interested friends. Quite the ma</p>
      <pb ref="arr4740459_0003" seq="03" n="462-463  "/>
       <p>462 The May ARROW jority of the centers are schools more or less like ours and located in the mountains of Virginia, West Virginia, North Carolina, Kentucky, Georgia and Tennessee. The crafts include weaving, basketry, furniture making, pottery, toy making, wood carving, broom making, quilting and no doubt others that I am less familiar with. had passed the one hundred mark. In the near future there will probably be one central place where samples from various centers can be seen and also where the standardizing of prices can be worked out. In the main the schools have a pretty uniform price but some vary a good deal, as many II cD clubs have found out, and there has TREASURES AT THE HANDICRAFT DISPLAY At the annual Mountain Workers' Conference held in Knoxville a year ago this spring there was a most beautiful exhibit of the handicrafts, each exhibiting center or individual sending not more . than three of their products. It brought only the most beautiful and choice things and was a great inspiration to all who saw it. This year there was an exhibit but of only old things. Many coverlits, counter-panes and old pieces of furniturebeen much distress among some clubs because of this variance. The United States has been slow in recognizing the work done through its crafts. Several European countries have guilds of long standing maintained by their crovernments: Canada has a most splendid organization. New England is now working along this line and we are proud to belong to the Southern Mountains Handicraft Guild and to be a charter member. The May ARROW A Needed Gift WHERE is -the Pi Phi School ?" How many times this question has been asked and how useless it is to say "Look for the stone wall." There are stone walls and stone walls in Gatlinburg nowas well as painted building painted buildings. The questi( really been answered in a m( tractive way, as the accompt picture shows. Last spring Mr. and Mrs. Gibson (Mary E. Wallahan, rado B) of Cleveland were h, a visit and were impressed the need of something to tc visitor or the passerby whi where we were. In the wii beautiful bronze plate 20" b was sent and is now placed entrance to the grounds. Age have a IT cl) husband to that a generous gift to the school. we say we just couldn't get without these II (I) husband: have helped us in so many, ways. Gatlinbnrg Notes ONLY a Dickens could do it justice ! Picture them filing in-to the home economics room, where they are met at the door by the primary teacher with a bottle of cod liver oil and a big spoon, a dose which they gulp down bravely, and then proceed to the sink. There one of the older girls pours a little liquid soap into their outstretched hands. They briskly rub it in, rinse it off under the faucet, and then pass on to the table, where they sit quietly until grace is said. This is the routine of the primary children. The food is provided by the women of the community, and the home economics teacher starts the fire and gets things going during a free period, while the other teach-ers and the older girls help w serving and clearing up. On' dish is supplied each day, th, dren bringing the rest of lunch from home, and not th valuable part of the program fact that they have to sit and eat slowly. New dishes are viewed wii picion by children in Gatlinb elsewhere, and it takes ingen. think of ways to make the ne, appealing. Cocoa was not esp enjoyed until someone called ice cream" now it is a real And boiled custard, which th never seen, was promptly tened "sweet gravy" by the cl themselves, and still goes b name. </p>
      <pb ref="arr4740459_0004" seq="04" n="464-465  "/>
       <p>The May ARROW iture Farmers of Tennessee is :nusual organization, of which 2 is a flourishing 11 B 4) chap-at the school, was only char--I in November, 1927, yet it tidy has over a hundred chap-with a total of over three sand members in the high ols of Tennessee. :sere are three grades of memhip: the lowest, the "Green-1," the next, the "Tennessee ner," and the highest, the "Tenee Planter." To progress from grade to the next requires a ate achievement of money from tice work and certain invest-Ls in farming or stock. These stments total a very imposing over a hundred thousand dol-[n farming and nearly twenty-thousand in banks in the first of its existence. le emblem of the Future Farm-)f Tennessee is an owl (wisperched upon the beam of a (labor), with a rising sun in )ackground, representing hope opportunity. The Greenhand .s the insignia developed in ze, the Farmer, in silver and Planter, in gold. The Planter have competed with other ters and his degree is con-:d by the governor of the state appropriate ceremonies. To at-his degree he must have had years organized instruction in tional agriculture, with out-ling supervized farm practice :, at least $200.00 earned from ing either in the bank or provely invested, a general high )l average of 85, and in addihe must have outstanding ties of leadership ! ere is a convention each year e state capitol and the incor porators include the governor, the state commissioner of education and the commissioners of agriculture and of vocational agriculture. A Case from Laurel Lick Not long ago the nurse discovered a fifteen-year-old girl in Laurel Lick (a community about fifteen miles from Gatlinburg and most difficult to reach) suffering from pellagra, a bad leg ulcer, and in a miserable physical condition generally. Her parents were dead and she was living with a married brother under what seemed utterly hopeless home conditions. Failing to get the girl into a Knoxville hospital, the nurse brought her to the school hospital for two weeks, where she received treatment. But not only did the girl receive physical help but she learned to write her name! It was hard, too, for a fifteen-year-old with absolutely no mental training, but she persevered, and then she even learned to read a little from the primer that the girls at the school brought her. And she was given her first doll, and she made some clothes for it, as well as an outing flannel gown for herself. In two weeks there was such a marked improvement, both physical and mental, that it stimulated the brother and sister-in-law so that to everyone's delight, they are now doing their very best to carry out the nurse's instruction at home and the girl has a chance to recover completely, The II P nurse is helping in every way she can even taking her the canned salmon that is so good for pellagra. This is just one of many cases that should make every II . feel that her effort is bringing very real results. N1,WV,34FANEMPAvPAW,PAWRAWAVEMP,10,FM actoiwoltolcoic,oleolcolc4ac'49,tc,49itoleatli ti(I)tJ '3 I Li XIkL''''f "M edited by Esther Fuller Janss HIDDEN behind a couple of initials, "H.C." is the anonymity of one of our most specialized and commendable IT .1c) writers, Helen Comstock, California B. More than a year ago she wrote in answer to an inquiry from this department of the ARROW that she was "just an associate editor" of International Studio. Now this hap-pens to the finest art treasures the world over. Paintings to pewter, bronzes to tapestry ... such subjects are described and picturized in a beautiful manner. At last an article which is attributed directly to the pen of Miss Comstock has appeared in the magazine, but it was only through a revelation in the Reader's Digest, that handy guide which helps track down many an elusive II (I) writer, that the identity of this II EI) writer was discovered. The article in the magazine was signed simply, "H.C." but the Reader's Digest showed that the initials stood for Helen Comstock. "Buddhist and Shinto Shrines at Nara and Nikko" is the title of the article. Photographs of some of the rarest and most exquisite of Japanese shrines are reproduced. The very adjectives used in the description show Miss Comstock to be one of the earth's persons who loves beauty, fine detail, and pains-taking artistry. The two towns are described asbeing in the "center of a crescent formed by the islands of Japan." Nara was the first capital of Japan, according to Miss Comstock, and some of the buildings were erected in 1624 and are still standing, "Buildings resplendent with lacquer and gold and color, and the same kind of artistry has gone into the making of their exteriors as might be lavished on a jewel box or casket designed for inviolable seclusion . ." so goes her account of these temples. A consideration of International Studio as a magazine makes one wonder at the widespread delicately technical knowledge of art that must be possessed by the editors in order to maintain their position as authorities of the widely varied subjects contained within its pages. A connoisseur par excellence . that must be Miss Comstock's rating, for she has been on the staff for several years. One sure-fire source of material for this department is Margaret Weymouth Jackson, Michigan A. A check back through the ARROW files for the time since it came under my direction shows that Mrs. Jack-son's name, like Abou Ben Adhem's "leads all the rest" in frequency of mention. But there's a reason a very good one. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



