<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr5010023_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Settlement School Reports</title>
                        <author><name>Hill, Frankie C. </name></author>
                        <author><name>Bishop, Evelyn</name></author>
                        <author><name>Post, Grace</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>September 1933</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr5010023_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">September 1933</date>, Settlement School Reports</title>
                        <author><name>Hill, Frankie C. </name></author>
                        <author><name>Bishop, Evelyn</name></author>
                        <author><name>Post, Grace</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 22-42</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">38</note>
                        <note type="Folder">11</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 50, Number 1 (September 1933), Pages 22-42.</note>
			<note type="document">arr5010023_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Settlement School Committee Chairman; Director of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School; Treasurer of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Funding</item>
                                <item>Curriculum</item>
                                <item>Facilities</item>
                                <item>Teachers</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr5010023_0001" seq="01" n="22-23  "/>
       <p>22 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW fore again asks that any Pi Beta Phis who have pictures, letters, or bits of news of historical interest, send them to her. In this manner, you will be doing a great service to the Fraternity. The Historian wishes to thank allthose who have made contributions to this phase of the work of the Fraternity, and she takes this opportunity to send greetings to the Pi Beta Phis every-where! GRACE FILLER SETTLEMENT SCHOOL COMMITTEE CHAI MAN IT IS MOST gratifying to know that the steady forward progress of the work at the Settlement School has continued during this year. Miss Bishop has writ-ten, "In many ways this is the best year the School has ever had." The enrollment is larger than it has ever been. This is due to the fact that many of the mountaineers have had to leave their homes, crude huts though they be, since the Government has taken over their land for the Great Smoky National Park, and they have moved to Gatlin-burg and along the nearby creeks. Gatlinburg has grown into a small village, and one who had to ride on horse back over the mountains twenty years ago would scarcely recognize the thriving little old burg, built on the main high-way to the Park. A trip into some of the neighboring coves makes one realize by contrast the great influence our School has played in the development of the community surrounding it. The leadership of our School was never more needed than it is in these changing years. Material prosperity does not necessarily induce higher ideals, and the mountain people need the School to help them keep the ideals which are a heritage from the forefathers who came and settled in homes far up in the mountains. Guidance is essential and the School supplies their need. Last summer the Committee had to face the fact that the income for the coming year would be less than the preceding one, but little did they think that our country would be in the throes of a great economic and financial crisis. Serious situations have had to be faced, but happily, the work of the School has notbeen slackened. Curtailments did have to be made in expenditures, and all workers were given cuts in their salaries. It was most inspiring to know that the remunerative part of the work is not their uppermost thought, and that they have labored as loyally this year as ever before. They love the people; they know their needs, and they give their best to them from early morn till far into the night. The six grades of grammar school were taught by four teachers Miriam Swann, Eleanor Brabson, Katherine Collins (Colorado A), and Stella Huff and each teacher had a crowded room. It was not feasible to add an-other teacher, although the congested conditions made the work more difficult. For next year perhaps there can be another teacher in the grade school. High school teachers were William King, principal; Pauline Whaling (Illinois A) ; Don Smith, agriculture and manual training; Jessie Branham, home economics; and Gene Redding, weaving. The dormitories were under the supervision of Mrs. McDonald and Mrs. Hathaway. There were eleven girls and eight boys housed in them, and they paid for their living in the housekeeping and in work on the farm. As a measure of economy, the Committee thinks it wise to close the dormitories for the coming year. When the financial strain is relieved, they will be used again to help keep the boys and girls who can not otherwise get their schooling. Aside from being a mother to the girls in the dormitory, Mrs. McDonald has supervised the meals for the THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 23 "family," which includes all the workers and the boys and girls. During the summer she busies herself in carming the vegetables from our garden, thereby making a great saving during the win-ter months. The farm has been supervised by Mr. Don Smith, the Smith-Hughes worker, and it has produced a satisfactory yield. There are enough cows and chickens to furnish milk, butter, and eggs for the school use, and any surplus has been sold in the community. There were two men who worked on the farm, and they were assisted by dormitory boys. Mr. Smith has conducted classes for men and boys in nearby communities and this work in helping the men has endeared him to all the mountain people. Virginia Moore, R.C.N., is in charge of the Health Department, and many interesting things could be told of her work. On one of her visits up Caney Creek, she found a family of mother, father, and seven children living in a one room hut, its only furnishing consisting of four beds, a sewing machine, a stove, and a few boxes which were used for chairs. Lillie Reagan, a former pupil in the school, is her assistant, and she spends her time in the Jennie Nichol Memorial Health Center. Virginia goes night and day ministering to the sick and those in need of medical care. Her work is recognized by the whole community, and she is loved by all to whom she has brought relief and comfort in their suffering. The popular name for the new baby girls in the community is "Virginia" and how better could the mothers show their gratitude for her service? The Arrow Craft Shop continues its thriving business, and to La Delle Allen, its manager, and to Gene Redding, the weaving teacher and designer of this fascinating handiwork of the loom, goes the credit for its success. No other shop has suffered so little during the financial crisis as has our shop. Its suc-cess is evidence of the deep interest anc loyalty of all Pi Phis. As these lovely articles are sold, the money is going in-to the building up of the lives and th( bettering of the homes of the mountaineers who have handed down the ari of weaving and basketry from generation to generation. It is most fascinatinE to spend some hours in the shop, feasting the eye on the beauties of then lovely linens, coverlets, furniture, baskets, and so forth, and also to see the joy and pride on the faces of the workers as they come in the shop, with the articles they have made, and the eagerness of others coming to get the linen and wool and cotton yarn to start an-other piece. Two former pupils of th( school, Veatress Parton and Alice Mc-Carter, are the assistants in the shop, and are giving half a day each. The shop in the Mountain View Hotel with Mrs. Duffield as manager continues tc have a good business. Mr. Huff, th( owner of the hotel, is the father of Pi Phi and a Pi Phi daughter-in-law, and he has been one of the most loyal friends the school has had in its twenty years of service. The activities directed by the Schoo: still give pleasure to the community Old Timers' Day in the summer anc the Fair in the fall are directed by Mr Smith and Mr. Mattil, and are enjoyes by old and young. The Parent Teachers Association has done a fine piece of work, and the Weavers' Guild has meeting each month. Our School continues to occupy its place among mown, tain schools, and its workers contribut( their share in helping solve the moun, tain school problems. We have repre sentatives from our School at confer ences of Mountain Workers, the South. ern Handicraft Guild, the State an. County Teachers' meetings, health con ferences, and the Future Farmers of Tennessee. Our school's chapter (2, F.F.T.'s is known as the II B (1) Chap ter. The extension work which </p>
      <pb ref="arr5010023_0002" seq="02" n="24-25  "/>
       <p>24 THE SEPTEMBER ARR)W started at the Sugarlands was discontinued this year. The people had moved out as the Government had taken this section as a part of the Park. The School and Shop received a severe shock during January. On account of the failure of the Bank of Eastern Tennessee in Knoxville, the Bank of Sevierville, which is a subsidiary, had to close its doors. It is probable that the money will be recovered, in time. The Arrow Craft Shop has forged ahead and is succeeding in buying materials and in paying the weavers, in order to keep its stock built up. A real loss has come in the resignation of Evelyn Bishop as Director. She has been the guiding spirit in the building of the School, and its growth is the harvest of her years of untiring work. The Committee has accepted her resignation with regret and appreciation of her great service to the Fraternity. She will be greatly missed, but inspired by her, the School will continue to grow and to hold its place of responsibility and leadership in the community. Though the Extension Work in Sugarlands was discontinued, there was one Pi Phi who had taught there for several years and had seen the need for service among the mountain people and was filled with a spirit of helpfulness. This was Eva Hathaway, and during the past year, she taught the school at Laurel Lick and lived in a one room cabin. It was our privilege to let Eva use in this school some of the equipment from the Sugarlands. The committee members have served faithfully, and the chairman wishes to express to the fraternity the joy we have had in serving in this phase of its work. Mary Frost of Denver has given most interesting glimpses of the school lifein "News from Little Pigeon." Grace Post is our treasurer, and we are most fortunate in having some one who understands the financing of the School. Our income has not been so large this year as formerly, but, due to her knowledge of, and ability to handle the funds, we have had a balance each month. The Alumnle and Actives have been most loyal in their support during these months of stress and strain, and we sincerely appreciate the support which has been given the School. Helen Tottle has cared for the requests for slides of the School, and Mary Gibson has supplied the material for programs for Settlement School meetings of the Alumni Clubs. As a measure of economy, the Committee has not sent out the usual folders of information about the School. The Chairman has derived much pleasure from this first year of work on the committee. She wishes to express her appreciation of the cooperation of the members serving with her, and also of the great assistance which has been given by our Grand President and other members of Grand Council. There have been difficulties for us to face and we have tried to consider every situation very seriously. It seems as though every organization has had similar problems. Ours is one of those institutions which are dependent on voluntary contributions, and many of which consequently have had to suffer heavily in their operations. All the greater is our gratitude for the loyal support of every Alumnae Club and Active Chapter, and the members of the Committee want to give sincerest words of gratitude and praise to them for the donations to the School and for the work which they have entailed. FRANKIE C. HILL DIRECTO IRS OF PI ETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL TO BE ABLE to give anything like a cheerful report of 1932-1933 would seem almost an impossibility. However, I do believe the blessings out-numberthe burdens and that we should be more full of thanks than complaints. Surely I know of no school of this kind that weathered the past year as well. THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 25 There were times in the spring when the committee felt the wise thing to do would be to stop the school work; but we were able to complete the school year and all the departments were continued through. This could not have been done without the cooperation of each one in economizing in every possible way. When you consider, that, for the first time since so many departments have been carried, scarcely a dollar of state or county money came in until the very end of the fiscal year, that teachers did not receive salary so could not keep up their payments to the school for their board, and that contributions were much less, you wonder how it was possible to carry on. Added to this were bank failures here and everywhere. A Sevierville bank closed with quite a sum of Arrow Craft money and some school funds and while there is every indication that it will reopen this summer it is certain that the funds will be tied up for some time yet. To be able to pay bills promptly every month under all these conditions was nothing short of wonderful. I know of no other school maintained to such an extent on voluntary contributions that fared as well. I do know of more than one that carried on from day to day last winter not knowing where the next meal was coming from and sometimes not much of a meal did come. Surely it was proved to us day after day that we had much, much to be thankful for. It is true that in many respects the people of this section have not felt the depression as much as in some other places but there have been hardships and still are. Many people who had gone to towns or cities have come back to the hills since work has been scarce; every little cabin is again occupied and steep hillsides are growing something of a crop. Difficult times for many started several years ago when sawmills and logging camps ceased to operate, and many men who knew no other way of getting cash found themselves with-out work. Men who had known nothing but this type of work for twenty-five years could not easily turn to other trades, nor were there many trades to turn to. It was necessary for the younger members of the families to take over the financial burden as they had, in many cases, a training that more nearly fitted them for the present time. I could tell of many families where the girls or the women, with their weaving, are bringing in all the cash the families have. The saving thing in the situation is that practically all are used to living as much as possible off a little garden, a cow, and some chickens. School The opening of school, August 1, was a hectic time, and we were unable to settle into anything like routine work for several weeks. Into our already crowded three grade rooms came fifty children from the Park area where three grade schools had been closed. The county provided transportation to Gatlinburg. While the county also allowed an extra teacher she could not be appointed until school opened and the enrollment proved her necessary, and we could not engage a teacher even though we knew she would be needed, because we could not assume the responsibility of even a month of salary. To complicate matters still more, one school bus brought all these children from Cherokee Orchard, Elkmont Mountain, and Sugarlands. That meant that one load had to come an hour be-fore school opened at 7:50 each morning, and another load had to wait an hour after school closed in the after-noon. This added very much to the teachers' work and responsibility. Katherine Collins, Colorado A, came two weeks after school opened and the work then was divided between the four girls. The division had to be made ac-cording to numbers rather than grades, and resulted in Eleanor Brabson taking the primer class, Miriam Swann, the first and second grades, Katherine Col</p>
      <pb ref="arr5010023_0003" seq="03" n="26-27  "/>
       <p>26 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW Ens, the third and fifth grades, and Stella Huff, the fourth and sixth grades. There never was a time when the rooms with two grades were not too crowded, and I feel sure the condition will be the same the coming year. With the county having difficulty paying the present number and in fact reducing salaries and teachers too we can not hope for another grade teacher from the county. We had the extra room in the grade building and the expense to us would have been very little. The teachers carried on splendidly but it was impossible to accomplish all they really wanted to under these conditions. With increased numbers the noon lunch was double the work and expense. The P.T.A. women and the teachers made a call for canned vegeables and fruit and all fall and early winter children came to school with cans for the noon lunch. The people surely responded well. The P.T.A. bore all expense of this. During the year they raised money by a rummage sale and by a play. In the summer vacation they will paint and freshen up the basement room and have it ready for the new school term. The Junior High school had its problems too. Pauline Whaling, Illinois A, could not come until the first of September. We were fortunate in being able to get Mrs. Roy Marshall, an experienced high school teacher from Sevierville, for the first month of school. When Pauline got here the work was well organized but it never is easy for a new teacher at once to take up the work. The fortunate thing was that Mr. King, the principal, was beginning his third year and so was entirely familiar with the work. It takes a much firmer hand on school affairs than it did some years ago; and the principal finds that with full time teaching and the many other things to do he has his hands full. Mr. King also coached the basketball team and our young two-year-high boys won a good per cent of the games eventhough all were played with four-year-high teams. In addition to Pauline's regular teaching she had a gymnasium class for the girls. She also continued the glee club work. Vivian Blair Reagan, who had taught here for three years, helped with the glee club; and the operetta in the spring was proof of the good work done by Pauline and Vivian and the pupils too. Our chapter of F.F.T. reported a good year with twenty-one members. Three delegates attended the State Convention at Nashville in April. Twelve pupils completed the eighth grade and nine, second-year high school. No doubt most of these pupils will continue their high-school work this fall. Of the class of 1932, sixteen entered other schools last fall and all but two or three completed the year. If our school can provide training through the first two years not only in classes but in various kinds of labor the young folks can usually find it possible to continue, even though it means in most cases making their entire way. Home Economics Jessie Branham, University of Tennessee, came to us in August as teacher of Home Economics. Both firstand second-year high school girls have Home Economics classes each morning and although they follow the course prescribed by the State there are many times when that course has to be adapted to the needs as well as purses of the girls here. When school opened Fair was not far off so canning was an important thing. In the spring, the second-year girls were especially interested in clothes. I believe all new spring dresses for first-and second-year dormitory girls were made in the Home Economics classes and of course the graduation dresses were. I am sure that a new Home Economics teacher in Gatlinburg is mighty THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 27 glad of the formal classes when she first comes. The Evening School work must seem vague and indefinite until it is really started. To decide in which communities to have classes, get acquainted with the grade teacher in that place and find if she is interested in having the work, and to plan out work that will be interesting and practical are some of the things that must be considered first. The past year there were classes in four different places: Laurel Lick, Banner, Glades, and McCookeville. In all but Laurel Lick the work was done in the same room where classes were going on, and with no equipment. In the Glades the problem of how to have a cooking class for the girls was solved by taking the girls to the home of one of our weaving women who lives near the school. In the spring there was an afternoon class for Gatlinburg women. The State reimburses for the Evening School work. In addition to the morning and afternoon teaching the Home Economics teacher needs to be actively interested in the noon lunch, the P.T.A. organization, the Fair, and any social activities of school or community. Agriculture Student Labor Farm In reading the reports from the various departments which I wish all could read one is more and more impressed with the fact that school and community can not be considered as separate interests but are closely inter-woven. The realization of this helps in building up a practical program. In these past months almost any farmer would think he had a sufficiently difficult problem to make his farm any-where nearly break even. A Smith-Hughes Agriculture teacher might think that a full time job, but in Gatlinburg we combine these two and then add more. There were enrolled in the school classes 20 high-school boys and 12eighth-grade boys, the largest number ever enrolled in these classes. In addition to their regular school course each boy carried a supervised home project. These included care of 310 laying hens, 8 milk cows, 2 hogs, 8 acres of corn, 6 acres winter pasture, 2 acres pespedeza, 3 acres truck garden, 2 acres tobacco, 1/2 acre potatoes, 1/8 acre small fruit. The total net profit from these projects was $615.85. Afternoon classes were held in Banner, McCookeville, and Caney. One afternoon a week was given to each of these three schools. Only the oldest boys were enrolled. Because of lack of equipment and limited space these groups had to be small and the work had to be of an interesting and practical nature. The past winter and spring the farm has been of more interest to the community than ever before and as year by year it grows toward self-support and we believe this year it will nearly come to that it becomes more of a practical demonstration for the men to observe. To quote Mr. Smith, "Reducing the cost of production without impairing the efficiency of the farm has been our chief aim with regard to this type of work. . . The farm is always of great value as a practical laboratory for the boarding students. . . . Farm, living, and dormitory boys have been inseparably linked." It would be hard to know whether to tell about the dormitory boys and the farm or the farm and the dormitory boys. The past year we had from 9 to 12 boys living at the school and they were a fine group. Ambrose Ogle, our farmer, supervises the boys' work and deserves much credit for the satisfactory development of the boys and the improved condition of the place. Girls' Cottage Seldom if ever have I been able to give a more satisfactory report of the Girls' Cottage. Reducing the number </p>
      <pb ref="arr5010023_0004" seq="04" n="28-29  "/>
       <p>28 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW of girls in the cottage from 18 to 11 proved a wise move as the girls had been too crowded the year before. Mrs. McDonald had the care of these girls as well as entire responsibility of the meals for about forty of us. She has a fine understanding of young people and a keen interest and enjoyment in them. Coupled with this was an ability to manage economically and well, and that difficult and incessant work went on smoothly and happily. During the summer the work was still heavy for the family had to be looked after, canning done and the summer people who came to the kitchen each day for milk, cheese, and butter took much time. Mrs. McDonald never lost an opportunity to turn the farm and kitchen products into cash. To my mind we cannot overestimate the fine training given the boys and girls who live here, or the care taken of them by both Mrs. Hathaway who was house mother for the boys and Mrs. McDonald in the girls' cottage. The boys and girls are busy from morning to night and that keeps them happy and out of mischief too. While student labor, well organized and supervised, may not pay back in dollars and cents it surely does pay big dividends in the development of young people. Arrow Craft and Weaving The past year has been a difficult one for Arrow Craft and the weaving department. However there are so many things to be thankful for it would be wrong to dwell much on troubles. The year started with the usual rush of summer tourists and clubs orders, coupled with putting into effect the changes that seemed advisable as to new business methods. The clubs gave wonderful cooperation again this past year. Ninety clubs handled Arrow Craft products. The methods of ordering and settling accounts never have been bet-ter. We know there must have been areal effort on the part of the clubs to sell things and all the year we were the envy of other centers belonging to the Southern Mountain Handicraft Guild because Of our fine market. In the fall there were more women weaving than ever before and that meant many families were being sup-plied with the necessities through this weaving. Miss Allen and Miss Redding had made every effort to plan small and inexpensive articles that would be attractive. No one can realize the immense amount of work that comes with building up a trade of small handmade things, but these are what kept the business going. After Christmas troubles began to come with the closing of banks. From then on the usual winter and spring planning was modified. That is the time when new patterns are worked out and stock replenished for the summer and fall business. Instead of many women weaving there were times when there were only four or five. Gradually things began to pick up, enough money came in each month to pay salaries and anything left over was put into materials and labor. We believe the fall will find Arrow Craft carrying on just as heretofore. In order to economize, the two girls, Veatress Parton and Alice McCarter, were put on half time in the shop and during the summer only one girl was in the shop with Miss Allen. The eighth-grade girls in the school are given a double period of weaving each day and the work done this past year by these girls has been unusually fine. Miss Redding plans and super-vises the course but Alice McCarter does the greater part of the teaching, and does it splendidly. In the fall the women organized as the Gatlinburg Weavers Guild, having meetings once each month. Attendance was good no matter what the weather was, programs were interesting and "a good time was always had by all." Dur THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 29 ing the winter and early spring the women were especially interested in planning for their gardens and the Wayside Market which they sponsored, and which has started off quite success-fully. In fact this group and the P.T.A. can be depended on for anything they may be called upon to do. During the entire year every effort has been made, not only in Arrow Craft but in each department of the school, to run as economically as possible. No small amount of credit should be given Miss Cooke for the careful watch she has kept of the expenditures and her willingness to plan with each department. She and all other members of the staff have had the interest of the school at heart and have been untiring in their efforts. Extension Extension work in Sugarlands closed with the end of the County school term in the spring of 1932. The 25 boys and girls still living in that section of the Park were brought to the Gatlin-burg school by County school bus. For some years a community about 14 miles from here has been asking that II B .1) have extension work in their community. When_ these people knew that Eva Hathaway would not be in Sugarlands another year they asked the County School Board to have her appointed to teach in their school. The people offered to put up a little house but it did not seem wise at first and I do not see how they could have financed it last year. There was a little one-room store building, 12 feet by 24 feet, and into this one room Eva moved. She took a little furniture from the Teachers' Cottage in Sugarlands but only the most necessary things. Mattie Huff had planned to teach with her but that was impossible so a young teacher from Sevierville took the primary room and lived with Eva. It was surprising how attractive the little house was and certainly it was a shining example ofwhat could be done with little. The greatest difficulty was that water had to be carried a quarter of a mile and all winter the road was slippery clay mud. The school year was very satisfactory, everything considered, but Eva was disappointed that more community work was not done. With house work and teaching, the girls were busy from five o'clock in the morning until after dark and distances to the homes were too great for anything but Saturday visiting. Living in such close quarters and 5 miles from the nearest store made me feel that the best thing for the girls was to get out every week-end possible and I usually went to the school for them Friday afternoons. When roads were too bad I stopped 2 miles this side and they walked out to the car. While it was impossible to allow anything from the budget for this work several Pi Phis, and interested husbands, contributed and anyone would be amazed at the things accomplished with the $150 of cash. Eva said many times that she did not think she could have gone through the year without this help for there were scarcely any school books, little or no school equipment, and some household things were necessary too. The few pencils and tablets the children had Eva bought for them and they brought eggs, pine kindling, or potatoes in return. Barter in these parts started long before the present depression and has continued. This is real pioneer work and, unless one loves the back country and people and can be content away from the bright lights, he had better not tackle the job. In fact, I have had no applications for it. We are hoping that an-other year the County can pay salaries more promptly and that will help a lot even though the already small salaries will again be cut. Health This is another one of the departments where the year never begins and </p>
      <pb ref="arr5010023_0005" seq="05" n="30-31  "/>
       <p>30 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW never ends, but the work goes on for-ever. No doubt more and better babies are responsible for this as the depression crop of babies has been a wonderful one this past year but more and healthier preschool and school children play a big part in the program too. During the summer, clinics are held not only in Gatlinburg but up various hills and hollows. Inoculations numbered the past year 896 and the report shows that this community had only one case of typhoid, and no diphtheria or smallpox. We were exceptionally free from communicable diseases the past year eight cases of scarlet fever being about all. Pupils in several schools were weighed and examined by the nurse and County health physician, and of the 397 on record about one-third were found below normal in weight. Many defects listed were corrected and much follow-up work done. Four schools participated in the State Blue Ribbon Health Contest and 87 ribbons were awarded. This is a program of certain health habits carried out by the school children. Caney and McCookeville schools were tuberculin tested by health physician. Out of 10 positives, 8 were taken to chest clinics. The nurse gave a course in Home Hygiene and Care of the Sick to the first-year high school girls. I wish I could stop to tell of several young women who this past year took really splendid care of patients in their homes. One very ill mother told me she needed no better nurse than her daughter and that she had learned right here in school, in years past, so many things she was now putting into practice in caring for her. During the year we had only one emergency case in the Health Center. One of the dormitory boys was operated on for ruptured appendix. With good roads, telephone, and even an am-bulance in Sevierville, there is usually a way to get operative cases to a Knox ville hospital. In the late winter a doctor moved to Gatlinburg and the people appreciate having a doctor at hand and the nurse is relieved of many cases she might otherwise have to look after. During the year we had the $200 from the Friends of the Mountain Chil dren to use as we thought best. Perhaps you would like to know some of the things done: Nine tonsil operations patients taken to Maryville where specialists op erated and charged only for the 24-hour care in the infirmary. Several children were taken to a Knoxville specialist for eye correction examinations were given and only glasses were charged for. A number of children from this section and Laurel Lick had dental work done by the Knoxville dentist who continues to come here one Saturday each month. Yeast, medicine, and medical care were gotten for a pellagra patient living some miles from here. Cod liver oil was got for babies and underweight children. Milk was got for under-weight school children during the first two or three months of school. There will be another tonsil clinic before school opens again. The com mittee that administers this fund says we may have another $100 this coming fall. While cold figures never begin to tell the tale this partial list will help a little to give some idea of the work and of how closely the school and com munity are linked: School children weighed and examined 397 Dressings at Health Center 966 Prenatal and postnatal visits 182 Infancy and preschool visits 419 Inoculations and vaccinations 896 Homes visited 655 Tuberculosis field visits 29 In balancing the State budget this past winter the Health appropriation was cut in half. This will seriously affect the Health Unit. The Sevier Coun THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 31 ty Unit has been ranking fourth in the list of State Units and we are sorry to have its efficiency curtailed. We fear that the County Health Physician and our nurse will be the sole survivors left to carry on. It al-ways seems in every place that health and education are the first places where cuts are made surely it is proving that way this year. Practically all the Tennessee land for the Smoky Mountain National Park has been purchased and a considerable amount of work in the Park has been going on all the past year. It has been the aim of the Park officials to give employment to as many local men as possible and the men working on the roads and trails are usually employed for three weeks or a month, then that crew is laid off and another group of men given work. When the Reforestation Camps opened about 900 boys were put into this section of Tennessee and North Carolina. With the moving of the people from the Park lands, other little settlements around here have become more thickly settled. This is the time when the various schools in this district should be carefully looked over and changes made, but county funds are too low to allow anything for a building program. It was impossible for the county to build agrade school in Gatlinburg this year but they will be glad to do so as soon as times are a little better. With the coming of good roads, many tourists, building of little cabins all over the burg, cheap dances and little law enforcement, there is much that should be done for the protection of our little town and of our young people. There is a fine group of women in the P.T.A. and in the Weavers' Guild; also the people are interested in the church and community affairs. I wish that there could be as good an organization of men interested in civic improvements and I believe that this is bound to come before long as the people are already seeing the need of it. There never was a time when the school was more needed as a stabilizing force. While the type of community work may have changed there is more need than ever and we can not be blind to it. I do not see how the staff, each with a full time program, can do more community work but at least we can be interested and sympathetic to it all and help in every possible way. Now and then I am asked if our work in Gatlinburg is about done. It is done only when we lose our interest and vision of what there is to be done. The field was never whiter to the harvest. EVELYN BISHOP TREASUREI* OF PI ETA PHI ~iiti SETTLEMENT SCHOOL MISS GRACE POST, TREASURER, Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee. DEAR MISS POST: We have completed our examination of the books and records of the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School and the Arrow Craft Shop of Gatlinburg, Tennessee, for the fiscal year ended June 30, 1933. Herewith we submit our report showing in detail the scope of our examination, the financial condition of the School and Arrow Craft Shop at June 30,1933 and the results of operations for the year under review. Balance Sheet, Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Schedule A Balance Sheet, Arrow Craft Shop, Schedule B The current assets consisting of cash ac-counts, accounts receivable and inventories of the School and Shop are carried on the books at Gatlinburg and are shown on balance sheets Schedules A and B. All other </p>
      <pb ref="arr5010023_0006" seq="06" n="32-33  "/>
       <p>32 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW assets and liabilities are carried on the Treasurer's books. The checking accounts with your depositories have been thoroughly audited for the year and reconciled with statements furnished by the banks. Your current account is with the Sevier County Bank, Sc;ierville, Tennessee, the Bank of Sevierville having been closed during January, 1933, and no transactions through this bank are reflected on your books since the date of closing. The balances in the Bank of Sevierville at the date of closing are as follows: Checking Account Pi Beta Phi Settlement School $ 297.02 Checking Account Arrow Craft Shop 1,637.39 Savings Account Arrow Craft Shop 2,000.00 Total $3,934.41 We have been informed that efforts were being made to re-open the Bank of Sevierville about August 1, 1933, but at this date we have no authoritative information to this effect. The small petty cash funds have been included herein as reflected by the books with-out further verification. Accounts receivable due the Arrow Craft Shop have been listed from your records but we have not verified the balances by corresponding with the debtors. The charges are now being handled on a net basis and no trade discounts are allowable on the balances shown as due. Inventories of the Arrow Craft Shop are included as submitted to us by the manager of the Shop. Income and Disbursements, School, Schedule C This statement we believe to be self-explanatory with the exception of the item of permanent improvements amounting to $21.86 which should be set up on the Treasurer's books with the fixed assets. A list of the items composing this amount is included as Exhibit C-2. Income and Expense, Arrow Craft Shop, Schedule D The results of operations of the Arrow Craft Shop for the year under review are shown in detail on Schedule D. During the current year, the procedure of handling trade discounts, referred to in our last report, has been eliminated so that the sales and corresponding charges are entered net. A summary of the principal classifications of income and expense for the period under review is shown below in comparison with the corresponding figures for the previous year. Capital Expenditures During the year several small capital expenditures were made, details of which will be found on Exhibits B-4 and C-2. These items have been closed off of the School and Shop books and should be capitalized on the books of the Treasurer. Scope of Examination and General Remarks The transactions through the checking ac-counts with your depositories were thoroughly examined and the accounts reconciled with statements furnished by the banks. In examining the cancelled checks, several were found that had not been endorsed by the payees. A list of these checks is included herein for your information. Two checks (numbers 2079 and 2092) were not signed by your accountant, however both had been paid by the bank and otherwise appeared in order. The books of original entry were thoroughly examined, the additions verified, the postings to general ledger checked and a trial balance taken showing same to be in balance after correcting the clerical errors found during our examination. Respectfully submitted, HOMER K. JONES AND COMPANY By H. CLAY JONES Certified Public Accountant Knoxville, Tennessee, July 14, 1933. PRINCIPAL' CLASSIFICATIONS OF INCOME AND EXPENSE Year ending 6/30/33 Year ending 6/30/32 Amount Ratio To Amount Ratio To Net Sales Net Sales Net Sales $13,344.53 100.00% $17,795.70 100.00% Cost of Goods Sold 10,230.27 76.66% 14,615.86 82.13% Gross Profit 3,114.26 23.34% 3,179.84 17.87% Expenses 4,143.34 31.05% 5,211.79 29.29% Loss from Operations 1,029.08 7.71% 2,031.95 11.42% Other income 300.00 2.25% 300.00 1.69% Net Loss for Year 729.08 5.46% 1,731.95 9.73% THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 3 SCHEDULE A PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL GATLINBURG, TENNESSEE BALANCE SHEET June 30, 1933 Assets Cash on Deposit Sevier County Bank Exhibit A-1 ". ' ". " . ' '$ 137.13 Petty Cash Fund ".' "."."." .' " . ' " . '. `n.ou Deposits in Closed Banks 444.1 Liabilities Gatlinburg Balance Account " .' ' ' " . " $1,776.62 Disbursements in Excess of Receipts Schedule C 1.;2.47 444.1 SCHEDULE B ARROW CRAFT SHOP GATLINBURG, TENNESSEE BALANCE SHEET June 30, 1933 Assess Cash On Deposit Sevier County Bank Exhibit B-z $ 982.30 Petty Cash Fund ~~~'~~i"."."."."."."."."."."."~. 25.00 Change Fund Mountain 10.00 $ 1,017.3 Accounts Receivable Exhibit B-2 " . 3,468.E Inventories $ 399.21 Arrow Craft Shop Weaving Supplies 1,891.44 8,313.5 Deposits in Closed Banks B"nk of Sevierville Checking Account Exhibit B-3 $ 1,637.39 Liabilities Gatlinburg Balance Account $16,494.35 Deduct Permanent Improvements and Equipment Purchased Transferred to SCHEDULE C STATEMENT OF INCOME AND DISBURSEMENTS July 1, 1932, mJune 30, 1933 PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL Receipts: Pi Beta Phi Settlement School Treasurer o2.725.37 Smith-Hughes Agriculture $ 57.72 Disbursements . . ' ' .' . ' ' 220.42 162.70 Home Economics Receipts Smith-Hughes ' m 220.02 Hospital $ 70.77 Disbursements ' ' ' ' ' " . ' ' ' ' ' " . ' " . ' " . ' ' ' ' ' " . ' ' ' " . 306.72 235.95 Farm ' ' ' " . " . ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " . ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' '~~~~~ / /u Disbursements Miscellaneous Exhibit c-z '. .".' 70.37 $2,661. Disbursements: Administration " . ' " . ' " . $ 17.00 Auto Expense ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ''' '' ' '' '' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' 244.05 Boys' Dormitory Community ~~~~ "."."."."~.~~~~~.~~.~..... 156.8Fuel </p>
      <pb ref="arr5010023_0007" seq="07" n="34-35  "/>
       <p>34 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW Labor 174.06 Lights 672.76 Living 1,163.54 Office 39.59 Permanent Improvements Exhibit C-2 21.86 Publicity 17.43 Repairs and Upkeep 641.89 School Expense 255.83 Telephone and Telegraph 65.75 Miscellaneous Exhibit C-.l 102.57 3,993.99 Disbursements in Excess of Receipts $1,332.47 SCHEDULE D STATEMENT OF INCOME AND EXPENSE Year Ended June 30, 1933 ARROW CRAFT SHOP Income Ba,rkets Sales .. . $ 548.12 Less Cost of Sales- Inventory 7-1-32 $ 718,08 Purchases 101.33 $ 819.41 Deduct Inventory 6-30-33 475.01 344.40 Gross Profit on Baskets Sold $ 203.72 Weaving Sales $7,834.10 Less Cost of Sales- Inventory 7-1-32 $5,193.69 Supplies Used 1,788.75 $9,307.28 Labor 2,324.84 Deduct Inventory 6-30-33 3,655.15 5,652.13 Gross Profit on Weaving Sold 2,181.97 Finished Furniture Sales $ 525.67 Less Cost of Sales- Inventory 7-1-32 $1,109.50 Purchases 131.40 $1,240.90 Deduct Inventory 6-30-33 745.90 495.00 Gross Profit on Finished Furniture Sold 30.67 Chairs, Stools, and Wood Baskets Sales $ 223.00 Less Cost of Sales- Inventory 7-1-32 $ 601.00 Purchases 80.80 $ 681.80 Deduct Inventory 6-30-33 398.00 283.80 Loss on Chairs, Stools, and Wood Baskets Sold 60.80 Hooked and Tufted Goods, Quilts, etc. Sales $1,539.94 Less Cost of Sales Inventory 7-1-32 $ 793.95 Purchases 1,052.73 $1,846.68 Deduct Inventory 6-30-33 523.55 1,323.13 Gross Profit on Hooked and Tufted Goods and Quilts, etc., Sold 216.81 Miscellaneous Items Sales $ 618.24 Less Cost of Sales Inventory 7-1-32 $ 379.76 Purchases 341.66 $ 721.42 Deduct Inventory 6-30-33 225.32 496.10 Gross Profit on Miscellaneous Items Sold 122.14 Gross Profit on Above Sales $2,694.51 Mountain View Hotel Shop Sales $2,436.09 Less Commissions on Sales 380.63 $2,055.46 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 35 Less Cost of Sales- Inventory 7-1-32 $ 561.25 Merchandise from Arrow Craft Shop 1,229.22 $1,790.47 Deduct Inventory 6-30-33 399.21 1,391.26 Gross Profit-Hotel Shop $ 664.20 Deduct Rent 180.00 Net Income from Hotel Shop 484.20 $3,178.71 Deduct Transportation Cost $ 386.18 Less Amount Charged to Customers 321.73 64.45 Gross Profit on Sales $3,114.26 Selling and Administrative Expenses Industrial Publicity $ 37.81 Industrial Expense and Supplies 205.49 Industrial Salaries 2,832.03 Industrial Miscellaneous-Exhibit D-1 143.97 Living Expense 701.58 Fuel 43.25 Light N18. Rr.eefeapifison aend ar'Upyee?egi; Telegraph 15.40 Knitting 19.71 Bad Debts 31.09 4,143.34 Loss from Operations $I,029.08 Other Income State of Tennessee-Weaving 300.00 Net Loss for Year $ 729.08 NATIONAL BOARD OF TRUSTEE FUNDS, Pi Beta Phi Fraternity, MRS. LOIS FRANKLIN STOOLMAN, CHAIR-MAN, 1001 South Third Street, Champaign, Illinois. LADIES: Pursuant to my engagement, I have audited the books and records of the Treasurer of your Settlement School for the year ended June 30, 1933. I have also received and examined the audit report of Messrs. Homer K. Jones and Company, of Knoxville, Tennessee, who made an audit of the school books kept at the school. By combining the results shown on the Jones report with the results of operations shown on your Treasurer's books, I have prepared a Balance Sheet as of June 30, 1933, and an Income and Expense Statement for the year ended on that date. I also received a statement from your Magazine Agency and have included their cash on hand and their receipts and disbursements for the same period. Balance Sheet The Balance Sheet of June 30, 1933, contains practically the same items as the one submitted for June 30, 1932, with the exception that the later Balance Sheet shows $3,934.41 which is tied up in the Bank of Sevierville, , which institution has been closed. You have paid $1,500.00 on the mortgage during the year, but the amount duethe School Endowment Fund remains un. changed. The schedule of Fixed Assets contains two small additions, both of which are shown on the Jones report. With these two exceptions and the additions to the Reserve for Depreciation, the Fixed Assets remain as they were at the close of the preceding year. Statement of Income and Expense The school expenses for the year exceed the income by $3,460.55, as shown by Exhibit "B." These expenses, however, include $2,478.54, which is a charge for the estimated depreciation on the fixed assets and was not paid out in cash. Arrow Craft Shop There is included in this report a statement of Income and Expense for the Arrow Craft Shop. The figures shown on this statement were assembled from the report of Homer K. Jones and Company and you will find the same information, in greater detail, on that report. The information is included here for your convenience in having all of the data assembled in one report. In conclusion, it seems to me that you are to be congratulated upon going through the year just past without suffering more serious losses than you have been called upon to do. Respectfully submitted, ELIAS J. AYE Certified Public Accountant </p>
      <pb ref="arr5010023_0008" seq="08" n="36-37  "/>
       <p>36 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW . EXHIBIT "A" PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL BALANCE SHEET June 30, 1933 Assets Current Assets: Petty Cash and Change Funds $ 45.00 Cash on Hand Magazine 16.52 Funds on Deposit: First National Bank of Pasadena, Calif. Schedule A-1 3,951.90 Sevier County Bank, Sevierville, Tenn. School Account 137.13 Sevier County Bank, Sevierville, Tenn. Arrow Craft 982.30 Accounts Receivable Arrow Craft 3,468.83 Accounts Receivable Magazine 2.00 Inventories: Hotel Shop $ 399.21 Arrow Craft Shop 6,022.93 Weaving Supplies 1,891.44 8,313.58 Total Current Assets $ 16,917.26 School Endowment Fund: Investments Schedule A-II 18,076.80 Amount Due Endowment Fund 13,344.79 Certificate of Deposit No. 11179 Pasadena Trust and Savings Bank Hazel Todd Meaden Fund 50.00 Total Endowment Fund 31,471.59 Fixed Assets: Buildings, Equipment and Live Stock Net Book Value Schedule .A-III 84,441.61 Deferred Charges: Prepaid Insurance 1,844.80 Deposits in Closed Bank: Bank of Sevierville School Account 297.02 Bank of Sevierville Arrow Craft Checking Account 1,637.39 Bank of Sevierville Savings Account 2,000.00 3,934.41 138,609.67 Liabilities and Net Worth Liabilities: Accrued Interest on Mortgage January 1 to June 30, 1933 $ 200.00 Mortgage rlacteo(plaianbloew.,;I.eiii 13,344.79 Total Liabilities $ 22,044.79 Net Worth: Reserve for School Endowment Fund as per Statement June 30, 1932 $ 29,863.57 Add: Three-fourths Active Chapter Contributions 1,558.02 31,421.59 Reserve for Hazel Todd Meaden Fund 1,291.86 Less: Invested in Sugarlands Cottage 1,241.86 50.00 Donation by Mr. Voorheis 7,882.87 General Surplus June 30, 1932 82,958.07 Less: Three-fourths Active Chapter Contributions to Sinking Fund Reserve $1,558.02 Excess Expenses over Income for School See Ex hibit "B" 3,460.55 Loss from Arrow Craft Operations See Ex hibit "C" 729.08 5,747.65 Total General Surplus 77,210.42 Total Net Worth 116,564.88 Total Liabilities and Net Worth $138,609.67 Total Deposits in Closed Bank Total Assets THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 37 EXHIBIT "B" STATEMENT OF INCOME AND EXPENSE Year Ended June 30, 1933 School Treasurer's Books Books Total Income: _ 57,72 Smith-Hughes Home Economics 220.02 Hospital Farm . ~~~~~~~~~~~ 1,8070.77 0.38 Miscellaneous "."..". m.3r Contributions Active Chapters Contributions Alumnx Clubs Contributions Individuals Magazine Agency-Alum= Clubs Magazine Agency Active Chapters Magazine Agency Individuals Magazine Agency Bonus from Publisher ~~~t Earned First National Earned Sinking Fund Expense: _ 220.42 Smith-Hughes-Home Economics 48.13 Hospital and Health Unit 306.72 1,707.84 Administration 17.00 ' '' ' ' ' ' '' ' 244.05 Boys' Dormitory 191.25 Community Service 1.77 Fuel 156.84 Furnishings and Home Supplies 227.80 Labor ` 174.06 Lights 672.76 Living 1,163.54 Office 39.59 Publicity 17.43 Repairs and Upkeep School Expense Telephone and Telegraph ... . ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ -~~S 102.57 Magazine Agency Loss a/c Bank ~~~ ~ Magazine Agency Expenses Insurance Salaries Travel Expense Depreciation on Fixed Interest Paid Tax on Bank Checks Total Expense ` . . . ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' 'w6,255.24 Excess Expense Over Income Carried to Balance Sheet Exhibit EXHIBIT "C" ARROW CRAFT SHOP-STATEMENT OF INCOME AND EXPENSE For Year Ended June 30, 1933 220.02 70.77 1,800.38 70.37 2,077.34 2,077.34 11,040.45 11,040.45 79.92 79.92 1,425.74 1,425.74 104.42 104.42 58.07 58.07 337.96 337.96 668.76 668.76 28.36 28.36 15,821.02 $18,040.28 ~ $ 2,199.96 $ 2,420.38 849.96 898.09 2,226.26 2,532.98 540.00 2,247.84 267.60 284.60 244.05 191.25 1.77 156.84 227.80 174.06 672.76 1,163.54 174.96 214.55 17.43 641.89 255.83 65.75 166.86 269.43 542.71 542.71 23.63 23,63 1,147.60 1,147.60 3,719.25 3,719.25 504.90 504.90 400.00 400.00 2,478.54 2,478.54 3.36 3.36 $ 15,245.59 $ 21,500.83 $ 575.43 $ 3,460.5S Sales Baskets .. " .' ". ". " . ". ' " . " . " . 'w 548.12 7 , 8 3 4 . 1 0 Finished Furniture 525.67 Chairs, Stools, and Wood Baskets 223.00 Hooked and Tufted Goods, Quilts, etc 1,539.94 Miscellaneous Items Mountain View Hotel ~~~.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~. ~~ 2,055.46 618.24 Totals ' ' ' ' ' ' Expenses: Transportation Costs Industrial Publicity Industrial Expense and Supplies Industrial Salaries Industrial Miscellaneous Living Expense Fuel Lights ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ Office Expense Cost of Gross Sales Profit $ 344.40 $ 203.72 5,652.13 2,181.97 495.00 30.67 283.80 60.80 1,323.13 216.81 496.10 122.14 1,571.26 484.20 $ 10,165.82 3,178.71 $ 64.45 37.81 205.49 2,832.03 143.97 701.58 43.25 24.21 76.3 </p>
      <pb ref="arr5010023_0009" seq="09" n="38-39  "/>
       <p>38 THE SEPTEMBER ARRO Repairs and Upkeep " 15.40 Telephone and Telegraph 12.42 19.71 ~~~Y~~~'~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 31.09 Total Expenses 4,207.79 Loss Before Inco"~~~~~~~~"~Other Income ~~~~~~~~~'.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ ` $1 , 0 2 9 . 0 8 300.00 Net Loss for Year Carried to Balance Sheet Exhibit "A" .... $ 729.08 NOTE: The figures shown on this Statement of Income and Expense are taken from the report of Messrs. Homer K. Jones and Company. For further details please refer to their report. SCHEDULE A-II ENDOWMENT FUND June 30, 1933 Face Book Value Value Bonds as per Report of June 30, 1932: Commonwealth Edison 1st Coll. "C" ".".".".".".".' v 500.00 $ 476.25 Crane Co. 10 Yrs. S/F Note 5's 2,000.00 2,025.00 Southern Bell Tel. and Tel. 30 Yr. 1st S/F 5's 1,000.00 Southern California Edison Co. Gen. 30 Yr. 5's 1,000.00 Aluminum Co. of America S/F Deb. 5's 2,000.00 2,067.50 Ashland Corp. 1st Leasehold S/F 6's 1,000.00 1,000.00 Cumberland Co. Power and Light 1st 4 's 1,000.00 Geo. O. B. and Mary E. B. R.E. 51/2's 300.00 955.00 Minnesota Power and Light 1st Pref. 5's Missouri River, Sioux City Bridge 1st ~~~~.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 1,000.00 1,000.00 1,000.00 _ Oklahoma Gas and Electric 1st "A" 5's V~~~~~~~~~~~~ Co. ~~~~~~.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 1,000.00 1,000.00 1,000.00 Total as per Last Report w12,8o0.o m12,972.50 Bonds purchased during year: U. S. of America 4th Liberty Loan 41/4's 3,500.00 Total Bonds Cash on Hand June 30, 1932, as per Report $ 3,546.28 Cash remitted by School Treasurer 1,558.02 Total Cash 5,104.30 NoTE: The total par value of the above bonds has been verified by a. statement from the Harris Trust and Savings Bank, but the price paid for the Liberty Bonds purchased during the year and the amount of cash in the hands of the Committee on June 30, 1933, is unknown to me. SCHEDULE A-Ill FIXED ASSETS June 30, 1933 Real Estate "."."."."."."."..' $ 7,900.00 Fences and Walks ".".".".".".".".".' m 34 Water System 633.07 Incubator -Roost --- 734.59 Barn, 3,336.16 Hospital 2,000.00 Arrow Craft Shop 2,400.00 Mary Pollard Cottage 4,317.73 Industrial Building 25,006.57 Electric Light Plant 662.09 Log Cabin ''''''''''''''''''''''''''''' 114.91 School House 6,743.85 Stuart Cottage 2,011.02 Sugarlands 3,772.71 Teachers Cottage 6,715.31 Wood Craft Shop 7,882.87 Agricultural Shop 331.09 Small Buildings 566.98 Auto Equipment 905-10 Equipment and 3,405.03 Equipment and Fixtures School House 2,500.00 Equipment and Fixtures Teachers Cottage 2,083.03 Equipment Cottage 1,000.00 Equipment and Fixtures Stuart Cottage 500.00 Equipment and Fixtures Boys Dormitory 500.00 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 39 Equipment and Fixtures-New Barn 650.00 Equipment and Fixtures-Incubator and Roost House 250.00 Total $81,342.45 Less Reserve for Depreciation 6,260.84 75,081.61 Total Fixed Assets $82,981.61 Live Stock Inventory 1,460.00 Total Fixed Assets and Live Stock Inventory $84,441.61 PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL DETAILS OF CHAPTER CONTRIBUTIONS AND MAGAZINE EARNINGS For Year Ended June 30, 1933 ALUMNiE CLUBS ACTIVE CHAPTERS Contributions Agency Magazine Magazine Profits Contributions Agency Profits Alpha Alpha Boston, Mass $ 180.43 $ 18.65 Ontario Alpha $ 20.50 $ Buffalo, N.Y 60.00 12.45 Maine Alpha Burlington, Vt 15.00 12.90 Vermont Alpha 26.44 2.00 Hartford, Conn 47.09 30.80 Vermont Beta New York, N.Y 284.83 89.30 Massachusetts Alpha 2.10 Rochester, N.Y 100.00 4.50 New York Alpha 10.00 4.80 iyracuse, N.Y 100.00 1.25 New York Gamma 10.80 Toronto, Canada 52.00 _ New York Delta 25.00 W. Mass. Alum 23.28 $ 92.74 $ 8.90 New Haven, Conn 35.00 Portland, Me 44.17 $ 941.80 $ 169.85 Beta 48.38 $ Beta 6.70 Akron, Ohio $ Pennsylvania Alpha $ 100.00 Athens, Ohio 22.00 7.05 Pennsylvania Beta 50.00 .90 Central Pennsylvania 2.00 Pennsylvania Gamma . _ _ Cincinnati, Ohio 100.00 20.30 Ohio Alpha 50.00 3.15 Clarksburg, W.Va. 5.00 Ohio Beta 98.56 4.37 Cleveland, Ohio 130.00 13.85 Ohio Delta 40.00 11.75 Columbus, Ohio 22.60 West Virginia Alpha 20.00 ...... Dayton, Ohio 35.00 $ 358.56 Delaware, Ohio 5.00 3.90 $ 26.87 Harrisburg-Lancaster, Pa. 125.00 Mahoning Valley, Ohio 26.00 Morgantown, W.Va 40.00 2.40 Northern New Jersey . 300.00 25.70 Ohio Valley 200.00 15.00 Philadelphia, Pa Pittsburgh, Pa 70.00 7.70 Southern New jersey 15.00 35.75 South Hills, Pa _ 8.15 Toledo, Ohio 85.00 9.55 $1,208.38 $ 171.95 Gactn Ina $ 19.25 Gamma $ Baltimore, Md $ 35.00 Maryland Alpha $ 35.00 North Carolina 50.00 _ Dist. of Columbia Alpha 25.00 Richmond, Va 55.00 6.50 Virginia Alpha 30.00 Washington, D.C 407.00 52.55 Virginia Gamma 25.00 North Carolina Alpha 25.00 2.50 $ 547.00 78.30 North Carolina Beta _ South Carolina Alpha 10.00 $ 150.00 $ 2.50 Delta 133.00 $ 18.50 Delta $ 1.00 Ann Arbor, Mich $ Michigan Alpha $ 10.00 Bloomfield Hills, Mich 14.00 5.10 Michigan Beta 122.50 Bloomington, Ind 25.00 4.00 Indiana Alpha 23.90 3.25 Detroit, Mich 85.00 50.78 Indiana Beta 26.40 Fort Wayne, Ind 20.00 12.11 Indiana Gamma 38.89 Franklin, Ind 50.00 _ Indiana Delta 27.90 1.90 Grand Rapids, Mich 1.00 9.55 Hillsdale, Mich 25.00 _ $ 249.59 6.15 Indianapolis, Ind 165.68 16.45 Lafayette, Ind 55.00 9.30 Southwestern, Ind 55.00 1.70 S 628.68 $ 127.49 </p>
      <pb ref="arr5010023_0010" seq="10" n="40-41  "/>
       <p>40 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW Magazine Contributions Agency Profits Epsilon 12.00 $ 7.45 Chattanooga, Tenn $ Columbia, Mo 61.03 8.00 Kansas City, Mo 500.00 57.90 Louisville, Ky 30.00 2.75 Memphis, Tenn 62.00 2.65 Nashville, Tenn 9.00 3.60 St. Joseph, Mo 2.50 St. Louis, Mo 570.16 102.21 Springfield, Mo 25.00 6.40 $1,271.69 $ 190.96 $ 13.50 Zeta 100.00 Atlanta, Ga $ Birmingham, Ala 35.00 9.60 De Land, Fla Jacksonville, Fla 15.00 Lakeland, Fla 5.00 Miami, Fla 20.00 Orlando, Fla 25.00 2.05 Palm Beach, Fla 10.00 .75 St. Petersburg, Fla Tampa, Fla 10.00 $ 220.00 $ 25.90 Eta $ 1.25 Avon (Libbie Brook Gad10.05 dis) $ Beloit, Wis 15.00 3.75 Carthage, Ill 10.00 3.28 Champaign-Urbana, 110.00 5.75 Chicago, Ill. North 500.00 .95 Chicago, Ill, South . 300.00 1.00 Chicago Business Women 76.00 Chicago West Suburban 75.00 4.45 Decatur, Ill 107.00 42.25 Elgin, Ill 18.45 Galesburg, Ill 70.00 2.00 Glenhurston, Ill 15.00 1.65 Madison, Wis 76.00 8.55 Milwaukee, Wis 200.00 23.35 Monmouth, Ill 7.00 1.00 North Shore, Ill 300.00 30.25 Oak Park and River Forest 25.00 Ill Peoria, Ill 116.25 Rockford, Ill 32.75 1.55 Springfield, Ill 35.00 6.35 $2,098.50 $ 137.38 Theta $ 18.60 Ames, Iowa $ 54.80 19.25 4.80 2.50 3.70 1.00 13.80 15.10 7.15 11.35 1.25 Burlington, Iowa 10.00 Cedar Rapids, Iowa . 40.00 Des Moines, Iowa 60.00 Duluth, Minnesota Grand Forks, N.D Indianola, Iowa Iowa City, Iowa 50.00 Minneapolis, Minn Mt. Pleasant, Iowa St. Paul, Minn Sioux City, Iowa 25.00 Winnipeg, Canada $ 239.80 $ 98.50 Iota Boulder, Colo $ 25.00 $ .50 Casper, Wyo 50.00 8.70 Cheyenne, Wyo 20.00 10.50 Denver, Colo 350.00 29.15 Laramie, Wyo 40.00 13.45 Lawrence, Kan 38.00 14.10 Lincoln, Neb 50.00 21.10 Manhattan, Kan 100.00 42.44 Omaha-Council Bluffs . 100.00 1.50 Poudre Valley 3.15 Pueblo, Colo 35.00 3.10 Topeka, Kan 28.75 2.10 Wichita, Kan 50.00 66.92 $ 886.75 $ 216.71 ALuMNIE CLUBS 1.65 5.15 1.00 1.85 4.85 $ 4.85 8.50 2.30 $ 276.15 2.50 Epsilon Missouri Alpha $ 25.00 Missouri Beta 10.00 Missouri Gamma 7.50 Kentucky Alpha 35.00 Tennessee Alpha 20.00 ACTIVE CHAPTERS Magazine Contributions Agency Profits Zeta Alabama Alpha $ Florida Alpha Florida Beta Florida Gamma $ 85.00 . 'tic Wisconsin Alpha 50.00 Wisconsin Beta 8.00 Illinois Alpha Illinois Beta-Delta 40.00 Illinois Epsilon 65.00 Illinois Zeta 100.00 Illinois Eta 20.00 283.00 Theta Manitoba Alpha $ 10.00 North Dakota Alpha Minnesota Alpha 20.00 Iowa Alpha 5.00 Iowa Beta Iowa Gamma Iowa Zeta 10.00 $ 45.00 Iota South Dakota Alpha $ Nebraska Beta Kansas Alpha 25.00 Kansas Beta 50.00 Colorado Alpha 116.50 Colorado Beta 64.50 Wyoming Alpha 11.65 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 41 ALUMN.E CLUBS Magazine Contributions Agency Profits Kappa Ardmore, Okla $ 10.00 Austin, Texas 75.00 Bryan, Texas 16.00 Dallas, Texas 200.00 Fayetteville, Ark 15.00 Fort Smith, Ark 12.00 4.50 Houston, Texas 129.75 8.70 Little Rock, Ark 50 Muskogee, Okla 15.18 New Orleans, La 60 Norman, Okla 25.00 3.90 Oklahoma City, Okla 25.00 7.65 Okmulgee, Okla. 15.00 1.40 Sabine District 50.00 28.10 Shreveport, La 50.00 Stillwater, Okla Tulsa, Okla 50.00 32.75 Waco, Texas $ 687.93 $ 90.50 Lambda Boise, Idaho 50.00 Calgary, Canada 5.00 Corvallis, Oregon Edmonton, Canada 5.06 Eugene, Oregon 25.00 Portland, Oregon 200.00 Salem, Oregon 10.00 Seattle, Washington 150.75 1pokane, Washington 75.00 Tacoma, Washington 75.00 Wenatchee, Washington Yakima, Washington 10.00 605.81 42.85 Mu Albuquerque, N.M $ $ 10.65 Berkeley, Calif 100.00 21.10 El Paso, Texas _ Glendale, Calif 75.00 Hawaii 75.00 Long Beach, Calif Los Angeles, Calif. 1,000.00 Monterey Bay 10.50 Nevada Alumnae 6.17 Palo Alto, Calif 40.00 Pasadena, Calif 105.00 Phoenix, Ariz_ 20.00 San Diego, Calif 70.16 San Francisco, Calif. 50.00 San Jose, Calif 50.00 Santa Monica, Calif 57.50 Tucson, Ariz 8.25 Utah Alumnae 36.53 $1,704.11 $ 75.35 COMMISSIONS CREDITED TO INDIVIDUALS Miss Onken $30 65 Miss Reisinger 5 50 Clark (Oskaloosa, Iowa) 85 Graham (Abilene, Kan.) 50 Rushville, Ill 25 Irvin (Oxford, Ohio) 2 00 Mexico 2 10 Lough (Calif.) 93 Johnson (Mass.) 1 50 Nicholson (Chicago, Ill.) 98 Bishop (Tenn.) 68 Filler (Pa.) 3 43 Centerville, Iowa 4 40 Parks (Pa.) 1 25 Sherwood (N.Y.) 1 25 Worcester, Mass 1 00 Rock Valley, Iowa 80 $58 07ACTIVE CHAPTERS Magazine Contributions Agency Profits Kappa Oklahoma Alpha $ 15.00 Oklahoma Beta 20.00 Arkansas Alpha 7.50 Texas Alpha 50.00 Texas Beta 25.00 Louisiana Alpha 25.00 $ 142.50 Lambda Alberta Alpha $ 10.00 $ Montana Alpha 25.00 Idaho Alpha 12.00 Washington Alpha 5.00 Washington Beta 5.00 3.50 Oregon Alpha 15.00 2.05 Oregon Beta 15.30 1.40 $ 87.30 $ 6.95 Mu California Alpha $ California Beta California Gamma 75.00 California Delta 80.00 Nevada Alpha Arizona Alpha Utah Alpha 50.00 $ 210.00 $ 20.90 The following contributions were received from Theta Province too late to be embodied in the above report: ALU MN/E CLUBS Mt. Pleasant, Iowa $ 45.00 Duluth, Minn 125.00 Ames, Iowa 42.00 Des Moines, Iowa 70.00 St Paul, Minn 100.00 Indianola, Minn 15.00 Minneapolis, Minn 75.00 Cedar Rapids, Iowa 22.00 $494.00 INDIVIDUALS Abbie Langmaid $ 10.00 ACTIVE CHAPTERS Iowa Gamma $ 8.00 Iowa Beta 3.00 $ 11.00 .65 1.75 8.25 10.50 14.85 5.05 4.20 18.00 3.65 2.00 3.10 4.85 6.20 5.80 .60 3.00 3.60 5.00 3.00 4.40 6.75 6.75 </p>
      <pb ref="arr5010023_0011" seq="11" n="42-43  "/>
       <p>42 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW RECAPITULATION ALUMNX CLUBS Magazine Contributions Agency Profits Alpha $ 941.80 $ 169.85 Beta 1,208.38 171.95 Gamma 547.00 78.30 Delta 628.68 127.49 Epsilon 1,271.69 190.96 Zeta 220.00 25.90 Eta 2,098.50 137.38 Theta 239.80 98.50 Iota 886.75 216.71 Kappa 687.93 90.50 Lambda 605.81 42.85 Mu 1,704.11 75.35 Total $11,040.45 $ 1,425.74 Individuals 58.07 ACTIVE CHAPTERS Magazine Contributions Agency Profits Alpha $ 92.74 $ 8.90 Beta 358.56 26.87 Gamma 150.00 2.50 Delta 249.59 6.15 Epsilon 97.50 9.65 Zeta 85.00 _ Eta 283.00 11.75 Theta 45.00 4.85 Iota 276.15 2.30 Kappa 142.50 3.60 Lambda 87.30 6.95 Mu 210.00 20.90 Total $ 2,077.34 104.42 DI ECTO OF THE MAGAZINE AGENCY ANOTHER YEAR of work for II B (I) is over, and in spite of depressions, bank failures, and things of that nature, The Director of the National Magazine Agency is proud to say that the magazine subscription business has held its own. Pi Phis everywhere have taken an interest in the work. As will be seen in the financial statement, a total of $1,400 was sent to the Settlement School, and $560 is tied up in a defunct bank in St. Louis. Thus, with very little mental arithmetic, one can see that nearly $2,000 was earned by the Agency. What a year we would have had, if banks had not come tumbling down around our eats! This merely means that more Pi Phis are awakening to the fact that there is money and more money to be made in magazine subscriptions. In explanation of the aforementioned bank failure, it should be stated here that it has always been the policy of the Director of the Agency to keep in any bank as small a balance as is consistently possible. The balance in the bank, at the time of its closing, was negligible, but checks, which had not been cleared, caused the amount lost to be $560. According to information recently received, there will besomething realized in the pay-off. At least twenty-five cents on the dollar is hoped for. Possibly some ARROW readers will wonder at the item on the financial statement marked "Special Bonus from Publishers." For the first time in the regime of this Director, she has dealt directly with the publishers of thirteen of the most popular magazines. While this method of handling means in-creased labor, still it was well worth it in increased commissions on these periodicals, and monthly bonuses on the volume of orders. This system has been responsible for approximately $338, without counting the larger commissions credited directly to clubs and chapters. In grading the Alumni Clubs ac-cording to commissions earned, two methods have been used (1) total commission and (2) commission per paid member in the club. To many small clubs of ten or twelve members, it is as great an achievement to earn from one to two dollars per member, as it is for a large club of one hundred members to earn fifty or sixty dollars. The following is the list of the eight highest clubs, according to the two methods of rating: THE SEPTEMBER ARRow 43 TOTAL COMMISSION I, St. Louis, $102.21 Mrs. Frank C. Ball, Agent 2. New York, $89.30 Mrs. D. D. Fredrickson, Agent 3. Wichita, $66.92 Mrs. E. S. Stephenson, Agent 4. Kansas City, $57.90 Mrs. H. E. Seurlock, Agent 5. Washington, D.C., $52.55 Mrs. D. D. Drain, Agent 6. Detroit, $50,78 Mrs. F. E. Ehlert, Agent 7. Manhattan, $42.44 Mrs, C. C. Brewer, Agent 8. Decatur, Ill., $42.25 Betty Starr, Agent COMMISSION PER PAID MEMBER 1. Southern New Jersey, $2.38 per member Mrs. N. R. Jones, Agent 2. Wichita, $1.67 per member Mrs. E. S. Stephenson, Agent 3. Hartford, $1.62 per member Erminie Pollard, Agent 4. Cincinnati, $1.45 per member Stella Koons, Agent 5. Manhattan, $1.41 per member Mrs. C. C. Brewer, Agent 6. New York, $1.37 per member Mrs. D. D. Fredrickson, Agent 7. Iowa City, $1.25 per member Mrs. Franklyn Roberts, Agent 8. Laramie, $1.22 per member Mrs. J. C. Jensen, Agent Many others follow closely on the heels of these eight clubs in each list, but time and space does not permit mentioning all of them. Each total, no matter how small, is greatly appreciated, and the untiring efforts of some of the club agents is inspiring to the Director. The Chapters' work on magazines has remained about the same. Thirty-one chapters sent in orders this year, as against thirty-three last year. Ohio Zi leads the list of total commissions, with Nevada A, Utah A, and Pennsylvania A next in line. In closing, the Director of the National Magazine Agency wishes to thank Miss Onken, who yearly constitutes herself a committee of one to se-cure subscriptions from family and friends. Her enthusiasm and belief in the Agency is always an inspiration. The Director wishes to thank all clubs and chapters for their efforts, and to beg for continued cooperation in this work. As can be seen from the financial report this year, there is an ever in-creasing amount of money to be made in the sale of magazine subscriptions. All clubs and chapters have money-raising schemes, which must be abandoned from year to year, as their use-fulness . depends upon a short period of enthusiasm. But in magazine work, where a steady market always exists, many thousands of dollars could be earned if each Pi Phi would induce her own family and friends to subscribe through the n B 41) Agency. DOROTHY J. MILLER FINANCIAL STATEMENT OF THE MAGAZINE AGENCY Balance on hand June 1, 1932 $ 58.67 Receipts Commissions credited Alum nae Clubs $1,425.74 Commissions credited Ac tive Chapters 104.42 Commissions credited In dividuals 58.07 Special Bonus from Pub lishers 337.96 1,926.19 $1,984.86 enditures Sent to Settlement School .$1,400.00 Money impounded in Bank Failure 542.71 Expense incurred in Bank Failure (Protest Fees) 18.00 1,960.71 Operating expenses 5.63 $1,966.34 Balance on hand June 1, 1933 16.52 Unpaid subscription 2.00 18.52 1,984.86 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



