<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr5820133_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Thirty Years on Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Spring, Agnes Wright</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>December 1941</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr5820133_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">December 1941</date>, Thirty Years on Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Spring, Agnes Wright</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 133-157</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">39</note>
                        <note type="Folder">10</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 58, Number 2 (December 1941), Pages 133-157.</note>
			<note type="document">arr5820133_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Introduction, and photo credits to Dorothy J. MacLean; Pi Beta Phi's Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Land</item>
                                <item>Education</item>
                                <item>Southern Appalachian culture</item>
                                <item>Health care</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr5820133_0001" seq="01" n="132-133  "/>
       <p>132 It eth THE DECEMBER ARROW rainard Le Roy, Massachusetts Alpha, Member of the Settlement School Committee If you ever want to know just what list of qualifications would rate ace high for a nember of the Settlement School Committee just hunt up Beth Brainard Le Roy's. She's :ops in them all! Her natural bent, her experiences and her :arefully studied philosophy of life give her rare equipment for her present position in )ur National family. She was born with that inner grace that shines through the windows )f the soul and she has nurtured it and cul-:ivated it that she might the better serve her Fellow man. All good causes hold a direct Ind moving appeal for her. Immediately upon her marriage she co-)perated with her husband in the management of the George Junior Republic, a ;elf-governed colony for boys, and she ;tudied every phase of the work, finding (or manufacturing) time to write a book about :t. Later her husband headed the "Boys' 2lub of Boston," a huge organization, and 'gain Beth cooperated and kept close to the work. Her interest in youth was not all out-;ide the home for she devoted the best in aer to her own seven children. Soon after her husband's death she was :hosen out of all greater Boston as the one woman to mother English refugee children and to supervise their placing in American homes. Her rare gift for fitting round pegs into round holes preempted success in this venture. For three successive summers she has directed a camp for boys in a forward looking Youth Movement. There is a courage called forth by emergencies that makes our heroes and heroines ; and there is a courage called for every day in certain lives, a courage displayed by men and women apart from any incentive of worldly glory. Endowed with this courage Beth has constantly developed it, that she might solve her own readjustments bravely and learn how to help others to solve theirs. Service has been her theme song throughout life for church, charity, community, and individual, and she has consciously lived and so ordered her days that together God and man might be served. Does this sound as if she really wasn't human ? Well, she is very much so! She loves fun loves her friends, and they all love her and have grand times with her. ANNA ROBINSON NICKERSON Massachusetts A New Members of Settlement School Committee Grand Council announces that two new nembers of the Settlement School Commit-tee have been appointed: Agnes Wright 3pring, Charter member of Wyoming A, dormer ARROW Editor and former National Historian, author of the History of Pi Beta Phi, becomes editor of the News From Little Pigeon of the ARROW ; and Lolita Snell Prouty, Colorado A, of Denver. -. Plan for your trip to Convention, New Ocean House, Swampscott, Mass., June 21-27, 1942. HE FOLLOWING PAGES are devoted to the Settlement School to bring to Pi Phis everywhere a new realization of the work that is being done at Gatlinburg, especially from the point of view of human interest, a new estimate of the measure of good that has come to the Gatlinburg community and the surrounding mountain region through the work of the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School. The past years unroll in Mrs. Spring's article like a great record of selfless effort, of devotion to the School and to the Fraternity which has so long maintained it as a Memorial to its Founders. Photographs by Dorothy J. MacLean, Gatlinburg, Tenn. First Rights Reserved </p>
      <pb ref="arr5820133_0002" seq="02" n="134-135  "/>
       <p>rovn tIeie Iwme~ in the oh.. Thirty Years on Little Pi eon ,a) P eta Phi's Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee By AGNES WRIGHT SPRING, Wyoming A IN EASTERN Tennessee land of dogwood and mountain laurel in the shadow of the Great Smoky Mountains lies the town of Gatlinburg, clinging to the banks of the Little Pigeon River, in a romantically beautiful valley. More than 1,250,000 tourists this season (1941) rolled through this gate-way to the Great Smoky Mountains National Park, in streamlined cars over a smooth, broad highway that skirts the front of the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School. Most of the visitors accepted as a matter of course the $100,000 hotels, the modern up-to-the-minute tourist camps, the hand-craft shops, the neon signs and the attractive stores, with little realization that most of them are owned and operated by the men and women and their sons and daughters who only thirty-one years ago were isolated from the rest of the world by mud, religion, and the effects of the Civil War. In 1910 when Pi Beta Phi questioned the Commissioner of Education in Washington, D.C., concerning a place in which to locate a settlement school, he unhesitatingly named Eastern Tennessee as being the most needy one from the standpoint of education of any area in the entire United States. Gatlinburg then was just a community along the road, comprising about six houses, three general stores, and one church house, but it had an educational need that extended for five miles up and down the creeks and "hollers" in every direction. Because the hills were so steep the more than 200 families living along the various creeks that flowed into Little Pigeon River, used Gatlinburg as a hub for visiting and trading (when any trading was done) . This community, 17 miles from Sevierville, was at that time without school facilities and without any prospect of obtaining any. It was then customary in the mountain districts to run the school terms, when any were held, only about five months in the year. Many times the teacher, who was paid $30 a month, had little more than a fifth grade education. Convinced that this was an ideal location in which to do altruistic work, Pi Beta Phi began the organization of a settlement school to give to the mountaineers of Eastern Tennessee, educational training and advantages, with particular emphasis on industrial and agricultural work, which would enrich their lives and equip them to make a satisfactory living in their own homeland. Down through the years since the establishment of the School with 14 pupils in March 1912, there has been a gradual development among both the younger and the older people, which has made it possible for them to adjust themselves to the changing conditions that have come to their valley with the establishing of the Great Smoky Mountains National Park, and has enabled them to take advantage of the amazing opportunities that are now at hand. The part that the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School has played in this development is apparent on every side. Many of the boys and girls who have attended our School have gone away to colleges and universities for higher education, but invariably they have returned to the Smokies, which they love, and have settled down to making their living there. Some are on small farms, some are running tourist camps and shops, and others are working in the hotels and summer resorts owned by relatives. More than 100 women, who have been trained in our School, are now supporting their families through their weaving. No one in Gatlinburg is on relief. Often one sees in the Burg a recognition pin on the coat lapel of a business man or woman the wings of Little Pigeon a pin worn by those who are at the Settlement School or who have at one time been on the staff. This year for the first time, the School has as its principal one of our own graduates, Ben Fleming, who holds an A.B. degree from Tusculum College and is working for his Master's Degree at the University of Tennessee. Through his background and training acquired in Gatlinburg, Mr. Fleming has a fine understanding of the mountain people and their needs. These mountain folk have a fine heritage. Thirty years ago many of them were "un 135 </p>
      <pb ref="arr5820133_0003" seq="03" n="136-137  "/>
       <p>THE DECEMBER ARROW 137 educated" in book learning but they were highly "cultured." Their English and Scottish ancestors came into the Gatlinburg area some time between 1801 and 1820. They came over the Indian Gap Trail on horse-back and on foot from North and South Carolina. There were Huskies and Whaleys, Reagans, Ogles, Claibos, and many others. The corner stone of the present Baptist Church in Gatlinburg bears the date: "June 1837." The little settlement was first called "The White Oak Flats," but the postoffice name was Gatlinburg in honor of Radford Gatlin, who kept a store there for many years. According to tradition he was always "alawin' " and no one liked him. The settlers agreed to name the postoffice for him if he would leave the country. Gatlin left several years before the Civil War and his name remained. The Pi Beta Phi Settlement School was established in appreciation of the twelve Founders of the Fraternity, and upon the celebration of Pi Beta Phi's Fiftieth Anniversary the School was presented to them as a memorial. In accepting it, Mrs. Libbie Brook Gaddis, Spokesman for the Founders, said: This is one of the proudest moments in the lives of your Founders. We have watched with great interest the beginning and development of this great undertaking. To you, who have thought out and wrought out the problems of the Settlement School, great credit is due; and you have the heartfelt gratitude of the whole Fraternity. Now that this great work is an accomplished fact we have a right to a just pride in its success. Our hearts are stirred with deep emotion when we think of your devotion to your Founders, and we want you to know that we fully appreciate the nobility of spirit pervading the whole organization. We are overwhelmed when we think of the honor you have conferred upon us in permitting the Settlement School to stand as a memorial to your Founders. We have tried to comply with your wishes and we recognize the fact that this deed conveys to the Pi Beta Phi Fraternity the property held in trust by Mrs. Elizabeth Clarke Helmick and Miss Kate Miller for the Settlement School at Gatlinburg, Tennessee. We have received the honor of a memorial at your hands, the deed we pass over to the Grand President as the Representative of the Fraternity, with our hopes and prayers. And now as we approach the celebration of Pi Beta Phi's Seventy-Fifth or Diamond Anniversary, it is deemed fitting that we re-dedicate the School to the memory of the Founders, all of whom have now passed to the Great Beyond. May their "hopes and prayers" guide the Settlement School into future service whether it be along the Little Pigeon or in distant "hollers." To the outside world .Gatlinburg is a modern, sophisticated village to those who have been intimately connected with the School there is a deep appreciation of the fact that there is a continuing need for stabilizing forces. In reality Gatlinburg is still a "community along the main highway." It is not an incorporated town and it faces many problems pertaining to public welfare. Although uniformed bell hops carry lug-gage at the fine hotels, and neon signs light the dusk along the main street only a stone's throw away can be heard the bawling of cows, a pig squealing, or a dog chasing chickens in Squire Maple's back yard. And often the stillness of the night or early morning is broken by the baying of a fox hound just in from the chase. Every issue of the Gatlinburg News carries this warning: "Don't feed the bears!" (Referring to the bears that roam the National Park and its environs.) "HIGH HAT RESTAURANT DANCING AND BEER" reads a 'sign just out-side the Gatlinburg town limits, on the very spot where the foot trail used to branch off to Aunt Lydia Whaley's cabin on the mountainside. Aunt Lydia could quote Scripture by the hour and it was she who told me that the poor apples in the orchards of the vicinity were not the result of pests or blight but came from "a iedgment of the Lord-because some of the folks are goin' down to Knoxville and ridin"round in them a.utymobiles." That was more than 20 years ago. From her doorway amidst mountain laurel, magnolia and tulip trees, Aunt Lydia, then 81 years old, would point down to the valley floor to the exact spot in the road where her husband, a Northerner, was shot down during the Civil War while trying to rescue a sick neighbor who had been captured by the Rebels. Over that spot now stream hundreds of cars each day and night. Mint Lydia was "a savin' " of the $8 a month pension which the Government al-lowed her after her husband's death and from early dawn until dark she tended her crop, took her own corn to mill, made shoes for her children out of old ones that she ripped up, and often for the sum of $1 each, made coats by hand in order to pay the taxes on her land. </p>
      <pb ref="arr5820133_0004" seq="04" n="138-139  "/>
       <p>THE DECEMBER ARROW 139 She knew how to make "ooze" out of barks, roots, and weeds and could explain in detail each step necessary to the making of "county pins," beginning with the raising of the sheep, the shearing of them, the washing, spinning, twisting, and dyeing of wool to the making of patterns such as the "Gentleman's Fancy Little Bow Knot" and the "Rattlesnake." These patterns were made from "drafts" handed down from mother to daughter for more than 150 years. Her first question to all women visitors was: "Be ye married ?" If the answer were in the negative she would say: "Why ben't ye ? Ye be old enough." Aunt Lydia, in the peace and quiet of the valley, thought out a philosophy of her own. When asked if she found life easier than when she was bringing up her family she replied: "Well, no. It's easier to have chilurn on the toes than on the heart. Back when my chilurn was on my toes was the best of it. When they're on the toes it's easier ; when they're on the heart, it's worse. I've seen a heap of ups and down and had a world of trouble the whole world through, and I hope to get to a better land some day. But the trials of this world must be borne with patience. This world is only a stopping place." Aunt Lydia made some of the finest baskets ever made in the mountains and replicas of them are still placed on sale in the shops in Gatlinburg. A turn in the opposite direction from the path to Aunt Lydia's former home site, leads to Aunt Lizzie Reagan's home. Just beyond Aunt Lizzie's corn patch an aeroplane slithers to its many daily landings in a tiny landing field. Aunt Lizzie accepts this recent innovation with the same immobile expression that has watched the many lightning-like changes come to her valley in the hills. Aunt Lizzie first became connected with the Settlement School when she came to take care of the infant son of Mr. and Mrs. Norman Prickett of the School staff in 1918. Soon she was taking care of everyone and became the regular School housekeeper. She was a most important link between the mountain people and the School. Everyone depended upon Aunt Lizzie. She insisted on milking the cow ; she made the butter ; picked wild berries and canned them ; helped with the garden ; and kept the house in order though she did say one morning, "You uns mustn't patronize after me." Aunt Lizzie is a true mountain woman, but she admitted after living in the new model teachers' cottage at the School that living in our "tight house" had "plumb bodaciously sp'iled" her for a cabin such as numerous children and grandchildren found very comfortable. Her son, Jim, now owns some of the best tourist cabins in Gatlinburg. Aunt Lizzie knew everyone for miles around and their family histories, and after Nurse Higinbotham came to the School, few long trips were taken without first consulting Aunt Lizzie about direction, roads, and family history. For nine years she was on the School staff. As changes came, however, she did not enjoy the bustle and the work became too intricate for one of her advanced years, so she bought a little place on Mill Creek, with a house at the brow of the hill from which she can look down on the valley. She still puts in crop, takes care of her garden and pet cow, and does some of the finest weaving in the mountains. Years ago when the School bought the big old-fashioned loom that used to belong to Aunt Lydia Whaley, Aunt Lizzie Reagan was the only one who could set it up. Although she had been away from a loom 35 years, she set it up, put on a warp and threaded it. Not a single thing had she forgotten in all that time. In fact, she knew many a little turn that the weaving teacher had never heard of. In appreciation of her fine loyalty and her assistance, the Settlement School Committee presented to her a Pi Beta Phi Patroness pin. She still spends many hours at the big loom in the Arrowcraft shop and the "Aunt Lizzie" patterns are in great demand. It was Aunt Lizzie's son, Jim, who drove the little one horse buggy to take, me on the first lap of a journey to consult a doctor at Knoxville more than 20 years ago. We headed for Pigeon Forge over the old road that was torn up in many places to make way for the new road that was being built. The old road was knee-deep in mud. At one particularly narrow curve I had to get out of the buggy while Jim unhitched the horse and then held the vehicle against the mountain-side in order to let a load of tan bark pull by us. There were no bridges and we had to ford Little Pigeon River. As the water swirled into the bottom of the buggy Jim solemnly nodded to a particularly treacherous looking spot near by and said in a monotone: "Man drowned right over there last week." </p>
      <pb ref="arr5820133_0005" seq="05" n="140-141  "/>
       <p>\ \ have come tA,eie children, , . . THE DECEMBER ARROW 141 I often wondered how Jim knew I couldn't swim a stroke! In front of the motion picture theater on the main street during lull hours this summer, an usher could be seen in a smart new uniform that resembled that of a French officer. The billboards carried the announcements of the latest Hollywood productions. Only a few hundred yards to the rear of this modern concrete theater, stands our great model barn, in the loft of which the first motion pictures were shown in the Smoky Mountains. The people came from up Bas-kin', down Mill Creek, down Roaring Fork, from Holy Top and Dick's Range, over devious mountain trails and rocky, muddy mountain roads to see this marvel of invention. Most of them came afoot, carrying babies, leading little children, and lighting their uncertain way with lamps and lanterns. And they sat in amazed silence, on bales of hay and on crude benches while the shadow figures flitted across the silver screen. That was in 1923. Aunt Lizzie Reagan went both nights the first time the machine was put into operation, and reported that she saw folks there that she hadn't seen for years. Today the residents of the Burg, many of whom attended our School, take part in plays and entertainments such as were not dreamed of in the early times. Each summer for three years the members of the Weavers' Guild have produced a play in the School auditorium, entitled "Store Britches." The play, written by Mrs. Elder Ogle, a member of the Guild, affords as much pleasure and amusement to the players as to the audience. Proceeds from some of the performances have been presented to the Gatlinburg Public Library and to the Red Cross. Some of the money has been loaned to weavers to purchase glasses and to obtain necessary medical aid for their families. When the first term of our School opened in 1912 the children did not know how to play even the simple games like "Button-Button" or "Farmer in-the-Dell." The teachers reported that the little ones had such "sad faces." They knew nothing of Christmas as we celebrated it. Their first dolls, which were given to them by the School, were hung up on the walls to be looked at but not touched. They learned the stories of Christmas, many of them for the first time in 1912. And they came to believe in Santa Claus because of the visits of the younger teachers who strapped packs of toys on their backs and climbed the narrow, rocky trails up into the far away districts. Today there is a beautiful little Community Christmas tree in the small parkway, owned by the Settlement School along the main high-way, which has been planted and is being cared for by the Gatlinburg Garden Club. In the fifth year of the School, the children took part in the first dramatic production given in Gatlinburg, "The Birds' Christmas Carol." It was astonishing how well the parts were enacted and with what zest the children entered into the performance. Soon a lyceum course was held in the School every two weeks comprising in part, a radiopticon lecture; musical given by Evelyn Bishop, New York A, the teacher of music at Murphy College, and a musical entertainment by Harve Reagan, Lawson Maples, and Henry Quarrels. It was Harve, who for years led the "harp singing" in the neighborhood and who also played accompaniments on his guitar for such . ballads as "Barbara Allen," "Lord Thomas and Fair Ellender" (known also as "The Brown Girl"), and the "Turkish Lady." Today Wiley Oakley's band plays "Comin' Round the Mountain" with all the snap and zip of a modern swing band. It was less than 20 years ago that the boys of the School learned to play basketball. They had never seen a game before and were very reluctant to wear the athletic suits that were provided for them. They insisted upon wearing their overalls under their trunks. What would they have thought then if they had seen young women strolling up and down the main street of Gatlinburg as they do today in shorts! On the hillside just above Gatlinburg's miniature airport is the old burying ground, where often in the earlier days the photo-graph of a departed one was placed in a glass container on top of the grave. Bits of bright colored glass, paper flowers, toys, or trinkets of which the deceased was fond also were placed on the graves. Not so many years ago there were no undertakers in the mountains. The body of the dead was simply placed in a wooden box lined with calico, with the lid nailed down and the whole covered with black calico. If the funeral was held in the church house and the mourners, some of whom had walked from various parts of the mountains, wished to view the </p>
      <pb ref="arr5820133_0006" seq="06" n="142-143  "/>
       <p>th5 dog . THE DECEMBER ARROW 143 remains, it was necessary to tear off the lid of the box to the accompaniment of the screeching of nails. Now the Gatlinburg News carries the advertisement of funeral directors and under-takers in Sevierville, who can reach many mountain districts because of the good roads. I recall distinctly the story of one of our young teachers up at our Sugarlands school. One afternoon she saw a group of people in the little church yard. Two of the younger ones were sent to ask her to read the funeral service. She left her classes and clutching the Bible went to the burying ground. No minister was available and there was nothing else she could do but go. She read a few verses from the Bible and said a prayer while the folks stood around the grave of an infant whose grief stricken young mother stood near by. The father of the baby was at her side hand-cuffed to a "Revenooer" who was waiting to take him "down the river" to be tried for moonshining. Every visitor to Gatlinburg takes a ramble through Charley Ogle's store a many-roomed building in which you can find every-thing from a hair pin to a kitchen range and a T-bone steak. It was Charley who, when a boy, rounded up all of the firecrackers in the Burg and set them off all at once when it was learned that "them wimmin" (our Pi Phis) , were going to stay and continue to run the school in Gatlinburg. Although Pi Beta Phi entered the mountains with the avowed intention of staying and of establishing a permanent school, the local people were slow in giving the promised cooperation. They had had no experience with purely altruistic projects and many were skeptical about the religious affiliations of the Pi Phis. When the matter of providing land and a permanent location for the School dragged on and on with nothing being accomplished, Mrs. Helmick, the chairman of the Settlement School Committee, issued an ultimatum. She said that it was customary in most places for the business men to support movements such as ours, and that the people must do their part in buying land and thus assuring us that they wanted our school. If they did not do so by a certain hour the School would be moved elsewhere. The story of how Andy Huff was sent for at his lumber camp eight miles away, and of how Mrs. Huff urged him not to let the school go away is thrilling. Andy Huff and Steve Whaley headed a subscription list with $250 each, and then proceeded to collect the rest of the $1800 that was needed to purchase the Ogle property. Pi Beta Phi contributed $600. A hack had been ordered from Sevierville to come up to take the Committee and the School equipment away, if the money for the land purchase was not raised in the allotted time. Kate Miller, a member of the School committee, who waited on the porch of the teacher's cottage with Mrs. Huff and Mrs. Helmick while the groups of excited people gathered around Ogle's store at the foot of the hill, said later: "Just before noon Mr. E. E. Ogle came up to say that he had decided to sell the tract if the money could be raised, that he would give as much as anyone towards the purchase price. He would give $250. He said he would rather have the school than his land provided he could get a fair price for the land. His neighbors said that if Eph had wanted to 'sell to anyone else he could have gotten $2,000. . . . The last stage of the transaction was at hand. The hack from Sevierville now arrived and raised the excitement to fever heat. Soon after its arrival, word was sent us that we were wanted at the store. Men were crowding around the outside of the building, on the steps, in the doors and were standing inside and sitting on the counters. We found Mr. Ogle busy writing a title bond to be held by us till the deed could be made and sworn to. Almost all the money had been subscribed and Mr. Huff and Mr. Maple had agreed to make up any final deficit. When the terms were finally and satisfactorily embodied in this preliminary instrument, it was signed and given to Mrs. Helmick. The wave of relaxation that passed through that assemblage was almost audible." It was then that Charley Ogle fired off the firecrackers! From the beginning the School has grown gradually and has expanded through the loyal support of the members of the entire Fraternity and through the continued support and interest of the people of Gatlinburg and neighboring districts. The School property now comprises some 120 acres of land on which stand the Jennie Nicol Health Center, Pollard Cottage (dormitory for girls), Stuart Cottage (dormitory for boys), Teachers' Cottage, Elementary School Building, Ogle Cabin Museum, Vocational Training and High School Building, Handcraft Building, Arrowcraft Shop, barn, </p>
      <pb ref="arr5820133_0007" seq="07" n="144-145  "/>
       <p>:t THE DECEMBER ARROW 145 sheds, chicken houses, and garage. From our initial enrollment of 14 pupils in the lower grades in 1912, the School has increased to an enrollment in 1940-41 of 285 in the the elementary grades and 138 students in the high school. The main purpose of the School has been to give to the community educational training equivalent to a complete elementary and high school course, with particular emphasis on industrial and agricultural work, to pro-vide a health center, to maintain a settlement house with recreational activities, and to ex-tend to the mountain people such other help as from time to time might be needed. From the start, the teachers have done much visiting in homes ; have held regular Mothers' meetings ; have attended public meetings and services ; and have endeavored to make friends with those who were especially unfriendly towards the School. There have always been two families most outstanding in their interest and support of the School: the Huffs and the Steve Whaleys. It was Andy Huff who carried his small four-year-old daughter, Mattie, to our School each day in order to encourage attendance. And it was Mattie, now Mrs. Lawson, who later became a Pi Beta Phi at Iowa State College, Ames, Iowa. She is now putting her practical training in hotel management into practice as she and her husband are managing a large cafe and tourist camp not far from her father's Mountain View Hotel. I had a fine little chat with Andy Huff last summer. I did not find him in his spacious hotel lobby. He is seldom to be found there. I did find him outside directing traffic during an evening of especially heavy tourist trade. While cars from Ohio and Indiana and Florida and Michigan threaded their way around us to and from the huge parking place near the Mountain View, Andy Huff and I reminisced of early days of the School and talked of the changes that have come to Gatlinburg. Andy has the reputation of being the leader in every progressive movement in Gatlinburg since he moved his family into that community thirty-five years ago. Mr. Huff's first wife, who passed away several years ago, after a lingering illness, was one of the most enthusiastic supporters of the School through its pioneer period. The devotion of her entire family to her during her illness is known to everyone on Little Pigeon, and the story of how her son, jack, carried her on his back to the top of Mount Le Conte is fast becoming a saga. As her health failed, Mrs. Huff expressed a desire to see the Great Smokies from the top of the mountain, where Jack had built a shelter cabin for climbers. One day Jack, who was an experienced climber, appeared with a chair contraption strapped to his back, which he had built for his mother. Gently she was lifted into this and the boy started up the rough road. After leaving Cherokee Orchard, four miles away, they left the road for a steep trail. Climbing ravines of impressive depth, skirting cliffs of great height that rose to sky lines of jagged tree-covered peaks, crossing roaring streams on stepping stones, and pulling himself up perpendicular slopes by means of old tree roots, Jack at last reached the goal. Dense fog, however, obscured the view which Mrs. Huff had so longed to see, but her wish to be on Mount Le Conte once more was gratified. Estella Huff Cox, for a time a member of the Settlement School Staff, is now on our local Health Committee and is a leader in all progressive things concerning Gatlinburg. Last June, with her sister, Mattie, and her brother Jim's wife, she entertained at a very lovely tea in honor of our new Director at the School, Mrs. Elizabeth Peck. The members of Grand Council and the Settlement School Members were invited, as well as many of the women of the village. The home setting and the tea were as pleasing as any in any district. Both of the Huff boys, Jack and Jim, married Pi Phis from our School staff . Jack and his wife entertain guests at their mountain top lodge, while Jim and his wife have a Duncan Hines-approved tourist camp in the Burg. "Uncle Steve" Whaley and Mrs. Whaley preside over their fine Riverside Inn, assisted by one of their sons, a former student at our School. Another son operates the Greystone Hotel, an impressive hostelry built of native stone. As I approached this massive structure which stands in the center of the former Whaley pasture, with an artistic background of foliage-covered hills, it seemed only just yesterday that II B built the first modern building erected in this entire mountain region. As the story goes, the concrete foundation was poured into the frames one afternoon at sundown while a group of mountain men looked on skeptically. About sunup the next morning one of the men and </p>
      <pb ref="arr5820133_0008" seq="08" n="146-147  "/>
       <p>to be educated 4 Pi a Ph,i </p>
      <pb ref="arr5820133_0009" seq="09" n="148-149  "/>
       <p>THE DECEMBER ARROW 149 Although many efforts were made to obtain a nurse for the School, none could be found on account of the war demands. It was not until the fall of 1920 that the Committee was successful in getting one. Nurse Phyllis Higinbotham, Ontario A, a graduate of -Johns Hopkins University, who had seen overseas duty, and who later had obtained her Master's Degree at Columbia University, came to the School to begin the very necessary health work in the community. At the start there was nothing for her to work with: no office, no supplies nothing but a great need. Soon, however, the old Ogle cottage, belonging to II B was converted into a hospital and on May 8, 1922 it was dedicated with appropriate ceremonies as the Jennie Nicol Memorial Hospital, in honor of Pi Phi's pioneer doctor, Founder Jennie Nicol. Miss Higinbotham's personality as well as her ability, won the cooperation of four doctors in Sevierville and Knoxville, who agreed to keep office hours in Gatlinburg once a month. They taught her much that belonged to the sphere of a doctor because they felt that there would be emergencies to be met when they would not be able to be present. Within six years Nurse Higinbotham built up such a health center that one of the leading doctors from the State Medical University at Memphis, after looking it over thoroughly, wrote a report in detail, in which he advised the state to use this rural health center and emergency hospital as a model for any rural centers that might be created in the state! And thus a Health Center Unit was established at the School in 1926 with the County Court voting money to assist in its support. State and Federal funds were made available to match those of la B ^Ic . Free serums and toxins were provided by the State of Tennessee. The new funds made possible a sufficient income for a county nurse, county health physician, and sanitary specialist, in addition to the nurse in two schools. Our School nurse examined school children for eye, nose and throat troubles and at-tended to general health. She answered calls day and night on foot or on horseback over terrible roads, fording swollen streams, ploughing through mud, or negotiating rickety footlogs. There were no telephones in those days. The saddle bags had to carry every kind of supply and utensil that might be needed. Nurse Higinbotham trained a class of midwives or "Granny Women," as they were called, to help with the obstetrical cases in the event the doctor could not reach the patient in time. The Nurse also taught personal hygiene and the cleaning up of premises, including the swatting of flies. She assisted O. J. Mattil, the Smith-Hughes teacher, in conducting Health Meetings in the various neighboring schools. In 1926 "Miss Phyllis" resigned to accept the appointment as State Supervisor of Public Health Nurses for Tennessee. Other splendid nurses followed her on our staff. With better roads they were able to extend their services longer distances. They were called upon to minister not only to humans but also to vaccinate dogs for rabies. One nurse reported as follows: "gave vaccinations today to 229 people and 37 dogs at a three-room school." By 1931 the nurse was visiting 13 schools regularly in addition to carrying on the routine work of her office. In the winter of 1932-33 a doctor moved to Sevierville and thus relieved the nurse of many cases. Gatlinburg now has a resident physician and every effort is being made by II B (I), through a local health committee, to cooperate with him and with the health authorities of the county and state in order to make our Health Center of the greatest service to the community. Our School nurse, Marjorie Chalmers, endeavors not only to take care of the sick but to educate the people to take care of themselves and their families according to modern health standards. Especially is attention directed towards Better Babies. Mrs. Chalmers is beloved by families up and down every "holler," as well as in the Burg. Long after office hours she makes calls to the homes of those who are unable to come to the center for help. The work which she has done to obtain expert medical assistance for crippled children of the area has had splendid results. The look on the face of a little old lady "Up Baskins," who clung to "Miss Marjorie" as she was leaving her cabin after a friendly call, is one of the most vivid memories that I carried away from Tennessee last June. The building of the new highway through Gatlinburg and the influx of tourists to the Park has brought to our health center doors many accident emergency cases. These victims of speed or carelessness are given emergency treatment by our nurse and are sent to the </p>
      <pb ref="arr5820133_0010" seq="10" n="150-151  "/>
       <p>7 k ~ . ~ ~ K A . ~ / ' A~ ice( THE DECEMBER ARROW 151 local doctor or to a hospital in Sevierville. Whenever I heard the siren of the high-way patrol screeching through the valley, escorting an emergency case to the health center, I was reminded of how Miss Evelyn and Miss Phyllis crawled on their hands and knees one night to bring a little boy with a broken leg down the mountainside and across a footlog, in order that he .might have proper care at our little hospital. I was privileged to be among those who dedicated the Jennie Nicol Memorial Hospital in 1922. The road to Pigeon Forge was being built and was not passable, so we reached the mountains via the caboose on a lumber train that wound and twisted its way along the Little River from Knoxville to Elkmont. After lunch in the little eating house at Elkmont (which is still there) , we the Grand Council departed for Gatlinburg in a wheezing Ford that blew out a tire and set us afoot about four miles from our destination. The rest of the way was negotiated on foot, while our luggage, tied up in yards of cheesecloth to protect it from mud splatters, was transported in a hayrack. Anne Stuart and I fell behind the others and leisurely made our way along the road and the trails, stopping now and then to quench our thirst in various rippling streams that we crossed. Imagine how we felt upon arriving at the Settlement School, to have the Director warn us immediately not to drink any stream water, as all sewage from the "hollers" drained into the creeks! At that moment we were thankful that the little hospital was close at hand. But strangely enough we suffered no ill effects from our liquid indulgence. Folks today, however, are not so fortunate as the "ailment" seems to be rather prevalent during certain seasons of the year. Whether the water is the cause of the trouble has not yet been definitely determined. This may be one of the big problems which our School will be privileged to help solve. At the hospital dedication Mrs. Andy Huff and Mrs. Steve Whaley, as members of the local committee, welcomed us with true mountain hospitality and presided with dignity and efficiency over their various duties. When the ceremonies had been well launched someone reported to Mrs. Huff that "Johnny so-and-so" was "jiggin' on the back porch." Johnny was promptly "quieted down," as dancing was forbidden in those days. But now, as I scan the Gatlinburg News of September 25, 1941, I see an announcement of a tap dancing class to be held "every Tuesday and Friday night during the winter months," by Miss Paulene Wrinkle. Too, last summer, one of the favorite diversions of both the tourists and the mountain young folks alike, was the nightly Square Dance in the Burg. Playing cards, as well as dancing, were quite tabu two decades ago in the Burg, but the, same September 25 issue of the Gatlin-burg News tells of a bridge party given in the Burg by members of a bridge club and even describes the hats and gowns worn by the ladies. It was in 1915 that "them wimmin" at the School announced that classes would be started in manual training. The excitement and curiosity over the fact that they were going to "teach tools," equalled that of a circus coming to town and when the five benches were in place, with the tools set out, every man and boy able to come to the School did so. Apparently no one knew much about tools, except the saw, plane, and hammer. Through the years, under the guidance of various able instructors, the 'pupils and also many grownups have learned to remodel furniture and to make new pieces. Much of the pioneer work in this field was accomplished by 0. J. Mattil, who was in charge of the agricultural department. He taught classes in shop work, animal husbandry, horticulture, and poultry raising. He visited orchards, taught the art of spraying and pruning, of weed eradication, and of crop rotation. Using his Ford car as a motor he gave many demonstrations with moving pictures in many outlying school houses. L. E. Voorheis formerly of Cincinnati, Ohio, who owns an estate in the heart of the National Park area, became deeply interested in the development of the boys of the Gatlin-burg community and offered to build and to equip a wood-working shop for the School. This was the beginning of *the organized industrial work for the boys. When it was found that the shop would be too expensive for the School to manage it was leased to Mr. Mattil who put five boys to work re-finishing "antiques" and reproducing crickets, book shelves, etc., which found a ready market. After resigning from the School staff, Mr. Mattil opened a woodworking shop of his own and now divides his time between it and his duties as a government employee. </p>
      <pb ref="arr5820133_0011" seq="11" n="152-153  "/>
       <p>in rucit~~ o//2ea~th, .. . THE DECEMBER ARROW 153 Twenty years ago the "Ladies of the Committee" spent many moments discussing the problem of importing a pure bred Jersey bull for our School farm and whether we should build up a Jersey herd. One of the first problems to be disposed of by the Committee in session this year was whether to remove our Jersey cows from a pasture in front of the Mountain View Hotel, as many guests objected to them for various reasons. How the Burg has changed! Our agricultural work today is being carried on most ably by William Coe, who holds a Master's Degree from the University of Tennessee. He has done splendid work not only with our own farm and our school boys, but among the men of the community. All agricultural and vocational courses of study are based upon the needs of the community and especial effort is being made by Mr. Coe to help the farmers to increase their "low incomes." The II B (1) chapter of the Future Farmers of America, under the leadership of our agricultural teachers, has won outstanding recognition in various fields and projects at county and State Fairs. From the beginning of the Settlement School the teachers have encouraged the mountain people in reviving and preserving old crafts and customs. They urged them to sing folksongs, to perfect their work in basket making, and to revive the almost lost art of weaving. When the School was first established the Gatlinburg community was shut in by almost impassable roads and rugged mountains and there was no outlet for handicrafts. Although basket making was one of the oldest industries in the mountains, the people had no market for their products so the baskets which they made were used chiefly for household purposes such as for berry picking and for wood gathering. In the fall of 1915 the School began the sale of baskets through the Fraternity. Materials were purchased for the work and every effort was made to raise the standard of workmanship. It took much patience and perseverance to raise the standard. Often the School bought baskets that were not up to par in order to encourage the maker and to increase the output, hoping to raise the standard gradually. To the alumnae clubs of II B (1. goes the credit of creating a market for the baskets and for the other handwork and thus making it possible to revive the fireside industries in Gatlinburg. In urging this revival, Caroline McKnight Hughes, Minnesota A, the first instructor in this type of work at the School, said: "In the yesteryear this country was a community of weavers, but after the War `store cloth' was cheap so that one woman after another put the old loom aside, but many of our neighbors today know how to spin and weave though it has been a `tol'able long spell' since any of them have done such a thing. One woman not far from the school, has her old loom up and is willing to make `kivers' and these are all dear to the hearts of old-timers. Many of the women still use the big hand wheel to twist stocking yarn but the little wheel for flax has disappeared. Everyone is using Diamond dyes to color their yarn but a large per cent know how to make `ooze', out of barks, roots, weeds, etc. All the looms about here are either the one `grandpap brunged from Car'liny when he coomed in,' or are copies of these old ones, and of course, one and all are crude home-made affairs. They are clumsy and big and all the weavers are old women. `Up yander in the mo'tains' there are many looms in use, and the women have little or no use for `store cloth' but down in our Burg all are fond of it. In 1920 a weaving teacher was added to the School staff and the next year three School looms were set up. Almost at once the weavers began selling their work to tourists at the small hotels of the Burg. As quickly as possible the School arranged to buy the products from the looms in order to assist the women in making money for their families and in encouraging them in the revival of the old art. By 1923 the sales had reached $1,000 a year. In 1925 Winogene Redding, a splendid weaving teacher, who is at present in charge of the weaving department of our Arrowcraft shop was employed full time. Miles upon miles she walked through the cold winter months during those first years to instruct the women at their looms. She provided inspiration for new designs and worked out new combinations of colors. She encouraged originality in the weaving of rugs, coverlets, runners, and the like. By 1927 sales from weaving had jumped to $ 14,000. Women from every direction sought instruction from "Miss Gene." One woman walked five miles with her young daughter one cold morning and when she arrived at </p>
      <pb ref="arr5820133_0012" seq="12" n="154-155  "/>
       <p>. ~ A w3 . a _; /4 ~ fy THE DECEMBER ARROW 155 the Settlement School she said: "I've worked hard all my life, I started to hoe corn and 'taters when I was a little 'un an' I been hoein' ever since. I've had nine chillun, seven are livin' an' two are dead. I've lived in the same holler for twenty year sometimes I think I'd like a sight to change. When I heered of this weavin' I jest thought I'd quit workin' in the field an' let the young uns do hit. I'm forty-four year old an' I'm tired, so I aim to work inside now." Gene Redding has a fine understanding of human nature and has been most influential in encouraging the mountain women to work in the Parent-Teachers' Association, in Garden Club, and in the Weavers' Guild. With the creation of the Great Smoky Mountains National Park hundreds of thou-sands of visitors came to Gatlinburg for the first time, and the demand for woven products became so great that II B (I) established and now maintains two shops in the Burg: one in the Mountain View Hotel, which is run by "Miss Georgia" Duffield and the other, the Arrowcraft Shop on our own School grounds. One hundred women, weaving under the supervision of "Miss Gene" and Mrs. Ethel Snow, supervisor of the Arrowcraft Shop, are supporting their families through the sales of their work. There is no one living on Government relief in Gatlin-burg. The work of the weavers is carefully inspected. The women receive thread and yarns from the weaving department and no work is accepted unless it is up to standard. All of the work is sold through Arrowcraft and its branches. Fifty percent of the sales are made direct to customers through Arrowcraft and its branches ; the other fifty per cent is purchased from Arrowcraft and is sold by our II B (I) alumnae clubs throughout the country. It is a real inspiration to watch the stream of visitors coming into the attractive Arrow-craft Shop, day and night, and to hear their comments upon the splendid quality of our work. It is then we realize that it has paid to keep our standards high. As I observed our efficient Arrowcraft workers, Lura Ownby and Edna McCarter, graduates of our School, selling and wrapping up, exquisite ,handcraft products in attractive gift boxes in this up to ^date shop, I thought back to the days when "Miss Evelyn" and her staff often were awakened at sunup to buy the baskets and weaving from the folks who had walked miles to dispose of their products and who had no conception of "office hours." In those days the attic of the Teachers' Cottage bulged with baskets. Hundreds of packages were wrapped in the basement or in the office or in the Director's room wherever there was space to take care of the fast-growing fireside products department. Today "Miss Evelyn" is as busy as ever. She has an attractive modern Guest House on top of the hill overlooking the Burg on the site where she and "Miss Phyllis" once owned a cabin that was used for a time as a Boys' Dormitory for the School. Another former School staff member, William King, who was principal for eleven years, also is a part of Gatlinburg's business life. He owns and manages a fine tourist camp just across Little Pigeon from the Arrowcraft Shop. The School still turns to Mr. King for much advice and help. To tell in detail of all of the accomplishments of the School down through the years would require far more space than has been allotted for this article. There would be many pages alone about our extension work in Sugarlands and Little River, up Baskins and Spruce Flats, and Mill Creek, and Little Dudley. Sugarlands, as you know, was included in the National Park area, so we sold the Hazel Todd Meaden cottage and gave up our work there when most of the families moved out of the Park. One of the teachers wrote of Sugarlands when we first went in there, as follows: "It is a land of poorer homes. One family where the teachers ate Sunday dinner served the food on lard pail lids. Three broken dishes held the other food to be served. Four of us sat on the only chairs while the boys stood up. Chickens pi'cked up crumbs under foot while we ate. The walls were blackened with smoke. Large bright blue paper bows had been fastened on the walls by the little girls to brighten this cheerless existence." Many of the Sugarlands families now live up Baskins, within the Gatlinburg area, and many have spent the money paid them for their little homes in the Park area. There should be many pages written about the accomplishments of the homemaking department of the School; of the organization of classes in cooking and sewing, canning and gardening. There are dozens of stories which could be told of how the children </p>
      <pb ref="arr5820133_0013" seq="13" n="156-157  "/>
       <p>} (+~ ~~q ,~ .,' ,~r'v d+ (5,;::% r '?if.'Q i:.:~ rnt ::'J..ii::l: :.::v. r ~ ~4.,~ S R+ ~, wn ey'~am' ~ :. ~ ~~' ~1[~.n ~:k?i~+a. ..: _... ,x.'~i_~.~~'Y~'~R:,.r: ",.~ .. .._-_ } .~..`~..u:.. mss'. Ohk THE DECEMBER ARROW 157 were taught to eat new dishes such as hot chocolate and warm custards, and of how the girls have learned to cook on various types of stoves from coal to oil. There should be mention made of how we have just acquired the help of a W.P.A. music teacher who is being welcomed this year with much delight; and of the new teacher of handcrafts, John Poore, who plans to build a kiln and to teach pottery in addition to many other, useful crafts. As we look back through the years we see many failures as well as successes in our School, but we know that we have a right to claim a share in the success of many of the lives of the men and women of the Gatlinburg Community. We have become so much a part of their lives that we are accepted as a matter of course, as one member of a family accepts another. When we look upon the smooth, broad highway and see all of the modern improvements and modern businesses right at our doorway we wonder what our next work should be, and some even wonder if our work down in, the Smokies is almost over. Personally I think it is not. When we attend Old Timers Day, held on the Settlement School grounds, and sit for hours in a hot, sticky, tremendously crowded auditorium and mingle and talk with the folks from up and down the "hollers" we feel an inner gladness that there is much left for us to do. There are many folks who still look to us and need us. They are not concerned about the 1,000,000 tourists that go up and down the road. They want to know what to do when a "bar" gets a few yards out of the Park boundary and kills their pigs; what to do to make the over-worked barren hill-side produce a better crop of corn; and how to design a new "kivver." I adore Old Timers Day! I never tire of visiting with the folks who knew Aunt Lydia, or in hearing Aunt Sally Compton win first in the Hog and Husband Calling contests, or in hearing old time stories. I like to discuss with the older men the price of crops or the possibility of buying a new horse for our farm to take the place of "Lady." I like to see the youngsters compete with the oldsters in ballad singing and in the telling of tall tales. I am thrilled to watch the steady hands of the older men as they shoot with their hog rifles or shuck corn. I walked down the trail with one dear little pioneer who is "nioh on to eighty." She has won the spinning contest for five years. Although she has lived on the same small hillside farm for 78 years, her life is no longer as isolated nor as monotonous as it used to be even though she is shut in by hills and valleys. When I asked her if she had grandchildren in the training camps and what she thought of the World situation to-day, she replied: "Yes, I have two grandsons in the service. I don't know what the War is doing today as I haven't listened to my radio since mornin' !" The II B (I) Settlement School has been a stabilizing force and I believe will continue to be one for years to come. Although Gatlin-burg itself has changed tremendously through the creation ' of the National Park and the general order of things, "there are still re-mote homes lost up the valleys and hidden on the mountain sides that are very little nearer the varied life of the community than they were in 1912. In them poverty and disease still exist to be met and conquered." No matter what lines our work may follow in the future, may we continue to fulfill the "hopes and prayers" of our Founders and to do honor to them through the memorial which they so cherished through our II B (I) Settlement School on Little Pigeon in the Heart of the Great Smoky Mountains! </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



