<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr5420141_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Holton, Lillian Beck </name></author>
                        <author><name>Chalmers, R.N., Marjorie</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>November 1937</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr5420141_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">November 1937</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Holton, Lillian Beck </name></author>
                        <author><name>Chalmers, R.N., Marjorie</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 141-144</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">39</note>
                        <note type="Folder">2</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 54, Number 2 (November 1937), Pages 141-144.</note>
			<note type="document">arr5420141_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">The Settlement School Committee Meeting; Garden Club; Notes From Mrs. Weaver's Letters; The Health Center Has Made Its Place; New Pi Phis On Staff; August Sales; A Chow Sweater</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Facilities</item>
                                <item>Health care</item>
                                <item>Agriculture</item>
                                <item>Weaving</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr5420141_0001" seq="01" n="140-141  "/>
       <p>THE NovEMBER ARROW ie Settlement School; Ann Jami-.ce Vice-President; and Helen At, Province President. son, Province vice-President, at the conference, voiced her ap preciation of its immeasurable value in providing her with a knowledge of alumnae opinions and wishes and indicated that another conference before Convention convenes would be profitable. KAPPA PROVINCE CONVENTI By FRANKIE COCHRAN HILL, Texas A rr, N nio, Texas, was the rendezvous rovince Pi Phis on June 16 and D full of history and romance is o visit and with a group of en-Irnnm arranging delightful enter-Phi actives and alumnae enjoyed days. the Spanish Governor's Palace Convention. A more picturesque !1dom found. The palace itself interest, and the patio with the rers and plants lends a unique The refectory table in the dining for a centerpiece a mound of )ssoms. To add to the beauty of an Antonio Pi Phis became beaued Senoras and Senoritas. A wan-: in native costume strummed his ang as he walked in and out of d garden. )om of the Plaza Hotel was the e model pledging and initiation vhich were conducted by Gladys )pa Province President, and Nita Grand Secretary. The initiates amp Leachman, Dallas, Texas, '..ewis Maverick, San Antonio, oky-shine in true Pi Phi fashion first day's activities to a close.  for discussion at the first meet-.elationship of Advisory Boards apters, Mothers' Clubs, Rushing, Alumnae Recommendations, and )rships of Active Chapters by .e climax of the morning session was the talk by Mrs. Stark. Her subject was "How can Pi Beta Phi Maintain Her High Place in the Fraternity World ?" At the close she announced that Oklahoma A had won the Balfour Cup for 1936-37. The meeting adjourned for lunch which was held in the Origina Mexican Restaurant. The tables were most artistically decorated and a real Mexican luncheon was served. At the afternoon session of the alumnee, with Mrs. Moore presiding, the following program was given: Club Problems and Interests, 1. Ways and Means, 2. Programs, 3. The Proper Functioning of an Alumni Club, and 4. Social Affairs. The second part of the program took up a discussion of the three projects of the Fraternity, the Settlement School, the Endowment Fund, and the Loan Fund. During the same hours the actives held their conference in the Roof Garden of the Plaza Hotel with Miss Scivally presiding. All of these discussions proved most helpful to the actives as well as the alumnae. Climaxing the two days was the banquet for which there were one hundred and ten reservations. Emily Wurbach Mickler, toast-mistress, cleverly introduced each toast to a "Pi Beta Phi Round-Up." A singing cowboy interspersed the toasts with his songs of the range. The Loving Cup Song brought to a close a most delightful gathering of Pi Phis. The next Kappa province convention will be held in Houston in 1939. Scholarship to a junior (Continued from page 136) high in scholarship, leadership ity. The selection of the candi-; award is made jointly by the iniversity and a committee from :lub. Miss Ashley is the first re-club is offering the scholarship 3ject. Mrs. Charles McArthur is chairman of the scholarship committee. Othr members of the committee are: Mrs. Charles A. Haskins, Mrs. Margaret Armstrong Boster and Mrs. Paul D. Barlett. Mrs. Oliver B. Simmons will be the president ,of the club the coming year. NEWS F \ M LITTLE PIGEON 11tll lllll THE SETTLEMENT SCHOOL COMMITTEE MEET By LILLIAN BECK HOLTON, Chairman The Settlement School Committee convened for the first session of the 1937 meeting in the living room of Teachers' Cottage at 8:00 A.M. on the first day of June. The chairman, Lillian Beck Holton, presided and all other members, including Josephine Mc-Cleverty, Marie Bacon Hagee, Jeffries Green Pace, and Helen Pierce Bang were present. Reports of the Committee and the staff gave a most satisfactory resume of the year's work. The director and other staff members gave suggestions for improvements and changes, all of which were most carefully studied by the Committee. Each of the three divisions of our work in Gatlinburg has grown in size and in efficiency the past year. The school has been larger and the work of a higher grade. There were twenty-two graduates in the first class to finish the four-year high school. Arrow Craft did the largest business in its history and the health work was most effectively carried on. Plans for the coming year were decided upon. With the aid of Miss Onken, the Committee induced the state supervisors of vocational education to give our school Smith-Hughes aid for vocational agriculture, and the county board of education was induced to give us a fifth teacher in the high school. This enables the agriculture and home economics teachers to give their full time to the vocational work, with home projects for the pupils. They will also have time for adult classes. The usual tour of the buildings andgrounds was' made and various cided upon. A white and green ci was decided upon for all frame bt Pollard, Stuart and the elemer ing were to be painted this sump SKYLAND HIGHWAY After a consultation with the o officer, it was decided to make cer in the sewage disposal system. A was ordered, thus insuring sa, water for the school. The committee viewed a part ing picture film which is to be Mrs. Pace, and which will be clubs for Settlement School progr The committee members enjo its with the members of Gran.d the two meetings overlapped There was also opportunity to vis in the community and for a d mountain to see the beautiful dendrons which were in full blc GARDEN CLU An outgrowth of the Weavers' Guild, the Garden Club, was organized by Gene Red-ding last spring. Although started by the weavers, the membership includes any woman in Gatlinburg who is interested in gardening. Talks on various phases of gardening by the members, exchange of cuttings and roots of shrubs and flowers, displays of flowers andplants make up the programs of meetings. The first community the planting of native wild flow, along the banks of Little Pig the Weaving and Arrow Craft b dub has been an incentive not members but to other people the grounds around their homes </p>
      <pb ref="arr5420141_0002" seq="02" n="142-143  "/>
       <p>THE NOVEMBER ARROW NOTES F OM M S. WEAVE S LETTERS I* \ fourth week of school finds us with the elementary and 88 in the high There are ten boys and seven girls, have room for, in the dormitories. EUNICE WEAVER Illinois Z the grade building and does a fine job su-Derintending the playgrounds. Eleanor Pack is managing the sixth grade nicely. The old teachers are back and doing good work. Today I have seen some funny outfits around the school. Boys are wearing straw hats with feathers in them and are carrying milk bottles, eggs and chickens. They are being initiated into the Future Farmers of Tennessee. Mrs. Smith, our new housekeeper, is very motherly with the dormitory boys and girls. She serves good meals and is trying hard to keep within her allowance for food. The painting is all finished. Next week we will start making gravel walks and then we will do a lot of tree trimming. We are about to attempt something very interesting. The staff is going to make a quilt a very pretty one I think. Mr. King is to make the quilting frame (he says he can do a perfect job) and the rest of us will do the piecing and quilting. The pattern will be original, a dogwood flower design. It will be sold for the benefit of the P.T.A. lunch-room fund. . The money made by the Los Angeles Club on the Pi Phi cook books is to be used for special projects. The first hundred dollars King says we have a fine faculty. Mr. was used for new furniture for Mrs. Weaver's taking a keen interest in his agriculroom. The beautiful cherry bedroom set which uses. Rosalie Ellis is starting in well was purchased was made of native lumber Le economics. Mr. Price has charge of by Los Reagan. THE WEAVING ROOM THE NOVEMBER ARROW THE HEALTH CENTE HAS MA E ITS PI By MARJORIE CHALMERS, R.N. It is difficult, In the midst of the daily routine, to anticipate the reaction of an outsider to the particular phases of one's work. Statistics are boring things, and like children, we desire a story about it all. If mere figures can be inserted painlessly enough, well and good. Otherwise, like our friends in the mountains, "we jest caint take it." Bonnie had just started her first month of school, and was very happy in the fun she was having. But Bonnie developed a sore throat, and had to stay out of school. The doctor pronounced it Diphtheria, and Mother sorrowfully admitted that Bonnie had never had Antitoxin. As soon as the news was out, business at the Health Center increased. Some children, whose parents had delayed or refused preventive measures, were brought in, and twenty-seven were given the serum. School records were checked, and every child who had not had a negative Schick test for Diphtheria immunity, was immediately tested, and the positive reactions called in to be immunized. Only ninety pupils in the entire school needed the test, and but thirteen of those proved positive. We had been told the goal was to be fifty per cent immune, but the first check found us far higher than that. It is a great source of gratification, when health education has progressed to the point where seventy-five per cent of the population voluntarily present themselves and their families for preventive measures, and parents are ashamed at neglecting them. The fight is not yet over, but little by little, we are gaining ground. At our most isolated school, Big Ridge, not a single vaccination for small pox could be made the first year I was here although two or three of the children had been vaccinated. Last year, four were given, and this year, ten more have been added to the list. Calls on several families, and more confidence, have "converted" a larger group. The almost universal answer is, NEW PI PHIS ON STAFF Frances Brown, Missouri Gamma, took up Tennessee Alpha, is teachin, her work as bookkeeper the middle of May. and helping with the mu Rosalie Ellis, Kansas Beta, is the new vocaschool. tional home economics teacher. Eleanor Pack, THE PIG'S TAIL, ON INDIAN "Well-1-1, if you say hit's a won't mind." One realizes where most of when first aid dressings sin( total 853. Cuts and sores, si of the school children avc Dressings are usually small, if the dressings fairly melt of the staff have been initi~ teries of making applicators and more than once, when st have proven themselves "f The weather has been nee ly, and the mountains grow 11 ors deepen. Each day finds for the inoculations in the in full swing. Far from dr( most of the children see!' "party." At the first sound the-Chevie" pulling up th( faces appear at the window; tle hands wave a greeting, s looking. Although Geraldine has s (lets and running board, an( from sharp rocks, we are fine shape. I wish you caul some of our trips, for I an enjoy the scenery and the E you would be prouder than you are carrying on through ter fix to come with us." </p>
      <pb ref="arr5420141_0003" seq="03" n="144-145  "/>
       <p>THE NOVEMBER ARROW AUGUST SALES le tourist season in the Smokies It. This year Gatlinburg had han ever before. Many Pi Phis :hool each day. The Arrow 1 a record business, $1,185.59 s Georgie has had the ambition to reach the $1,000 mark for the hotel shop and in August she did with $1,007.33. There are many other gift and craft shops in Gatlin-burg so these sales show that people appreciate the quality and beauty of Arrow Craft products. AUNT LIZZIE, WHO SPUN THE YARN A CHOW SWEATE hen the ARROW Editor was on alifornia after Grand Council y magazine cover caught her border framed a picture of a ' dog. That sold the magazine, d on the train the Editor turned [ling in the chow beauties who s relatives. Then "About That '" said a headline, and below re of our Aunt Lizzie Reagan one time housekeeper of the .00l, now a weaver, and always .d of the school! ry, and how close it came to lo on the morning of her de-sited Aunt Lizzie in her little a hill, set in its background )llyhocks, and looking far out ntains! !ad the story how a Mr. W. Walter Lewis of Chicago, was the owner of a soft warm sweater knitted of yarn spun from the combings of a red chow rejoicing in the name of Whatapooch, of much the same pedigree as the Editor's own pet. And here the tale comes back to the Settlement School, for Mr. Brockway Crouch who had raised the dog, had saved the combings and sent them to Aunt Lizzie, who carded the wool and spun the yarn. The sweater was then given to Mr. Lewis, who vouches for its beauty. It seems this use of chow hair is not new, and was often done in England in war time when wool was scarce. When the Editor thinks of the red chow hair she has thrown away in seventeen years of chow ownership she sees the many sweaters she might have had! ....IIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIII.IIIIIIII.A..11.11111111111,111.1111111IIIIIIII1,111111118111811III.111.11011.11.1.11111124111111.1111.311011153.1111.110100611011111111111111111111111111.111111 EXCHANGES AND COLLEGE NOTE Edited by JUANITA DAY CARMAN, Minnesota A $I P IIIIIII1111111 lllllllllll The summer convention of A T SL held at Breezy Point, Minnesota, was saddened by the drowning of Robert Weinstock, the delegate from Ohio, in Pelican Lake, the first day of the convention. He was drowned when going to the aid of a friend who was knocked from a sail boat. Alpha Tau Omega has created a new office of National Vocational Director whose duties shall be to organize and promote a plan to assist the actives and alumni with their vocational and employment problems. The summer issue of the Lamp of A Z is devoted to Vocations and Avocations. Some of the intriguing articles are entitled, "Marriage, a Vocation," "Ride Your Hobby for Pay," "What? Archeology," and "What Does The Girl In New England Do ?" The leading article in the Phi Gamma Delta tells of Lutcher Stark and what he has done for Texas and the Phi Gams at Austin. Mr. Stark, the husband of Pi Phi's, Grand Secretary tore up the $30,000 mortgage which he held on the chapter house when the chapter had won first place in scholarship for the year. The Anchora devotes a section to distinguished A r husbands. Alfred M. Landon, Phil Stong, and Irving Maurer, president of Beloit College are among those so honored. Founders' Day in New York City this spring drew 572 Phi Delta Thetas, the largest number ever assembled. Congratulations to Alice Wick, Grand President of K, who became the mother of a son in June and the Editor of the Triangle puns, "Is the son of a Grand President a grand son ?" Kappa Kappa Gamma has appointed a suiting dietitian for the Fraternity. . Bales, dean of the department of home nomics at North Dakota State College, the office which so far as is known, first of its kind in the Greek letter work Alpha Delta Pi day nursery fellows: formerly available only at the Universit Chicago and the University of Texas, a be extended to a greater number of sch the Adelphean reports. Instead of design permanent fellowships, applications wi. received from various nursery schools it United States and Canada and the best plications will be chosen from those subm each year. The nursery schools are A Delta Pi's national philanthropic activit: The Aglaia of ^(I) An advertisement appeared in the Syr, Post Standard, local daily newspaper ma The ad read: "Lost lady's purse, contai Psi U, Phi Psi, and Beta Theta Pi frate pins. Valuable to owner for sentimental sons." The Fraternity Mor, Mrs. Roosevelt presented the Chi Oi National Achievement Award to Kath Cornell, the famous artist. Addresses made by Mary Love Collins, Eleanor Rc Belmont, and Alexander Woollcott, Delta Chi. PI PHI, TOO IS A "FRATERNITY" Like Kappa Alpha Theta, Alpha Ph never been a sorority. Alpha Phi's pl( are given an interesting explanation o reason why they are joining not a so: but a fraternity. They are taught tha word "fraternity" was derived not "frater," a Latin word, but from "phrl which is bona fide Greek. "Phrater" in G meant a member of a "phratra," which tribe, a group of blood relatives which be composed either of men or of we </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



