<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr5020183_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Frost, Mary Cooper</name></author>
                        <author><name>Parton, Veatress</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>November 1933</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr5020183_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">November 1933</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Frost, Mary Cooper</name></author>
                        <author><name>Parton, Veatress</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 182-185</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">38</note>
                        <note type="Folder">11</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 50, Number 2 (November 1933), Pages 182-185.</note>
			<note type="document">arr5020183_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">The Staff; Accomplishments of Settlement School Committee; For Those Who Would Teach at Gatlinburg; Settlement School Represented in Exhibit; With Our Graduates; Mrs. Huff; Arrow Crafters Offer to Help with Your Christmas Shopping</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Staff</item>
                                <item>Teachers</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>
                                <item>Weaving</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr5020183_0001" seq="01" n="182-183  "/>
       <p>NEWS F LITTLE PIGEON (Si M Edited by MARY COOPER FROST 1.111111.1111111111.111.111111.1.111111111.18011,11110..11111 111515111.11111183111.11.11180.1181.1.111111.11110111.11111611.11R.011....111.1111.1111.11111.11.111.1111I THE STAFF THE NEW DIRECTOR The Settlement School Committee takes pleasure in presenting the new director--Maryalice Chaffee, Michigan A. Miss Chaffee is a native of Grand Rapids. Here and in such widely varied places as West Lake School for Girls in Los Angeles; Penn Hall at Charn MARYALICE CHAFFEE bersburg, Pennsylvania; and in University High School, Grand Forks, North Dakota, she had her early schooling. After being graduated from Central High School in Grand Rapids, Miss Chaffee followed her family, always interested in the furniture business, by working for two years in a chain furniture store, and then going to Detroit with the J. L. Hudson Company. She helped herself through Hillsdale College working in the Home Economics Department and serving, during her last two years, as district manager for Luzier's Special Formula. Labora-tories for which she directed the activities of six or eight women. Although such a busy program prevented Miss Chaffee from holding major fraternity offices, it is interesting to note that she was chapter Settlement School Chair-man. She did her share on the campus too, being assistant editor of the college paper, vice-president of the fresh-man dormitory, and member of the advisory board of the student council. Her major subjects were business administration and home economics, and her minors were child psychology and sociology. When Miss Chaffee received her appointment to the directorship of the Settlement School, she was connected with the Family Service Association of Grand Rapids. It will be seen that college specialization and business, social service, and administrative experience were hers to draw upon when she began her work at Gatlinburg. The committee bespeaks for Miss Chaffee and the Settlement School the same loyal and interested support that the actives and alumnx of H B cl) have always given to Miss Bishop and the fraternity's enterprise in the Great Smoky Mountains. THE NEW BOOKKEEPER It's a long jump from being chapter treasurer one year to being Settlement School bookkeeper the next, but Lucy Ellen Field, Texas A, has that accomplishment to her credit. Perhaps enthusiasm for the work at Gatlinburg is in her veins, for she is the daughter of a Texas A, Nonie Mason Field (Mrs. Scott) . Lucy came to the School in July THE NOVEMBER ARROW 183 after taking her degree at Texas University in business administration last January. In vacations she had worked in a bank. During the month when she was on duty before the opening of the term she was able to familiarize herself with her new work. The foregoing accounts, brief though they are, show that the Settlement School Committee has been successful in filling vacancies on the staff with Pi Phis who are trained to do the work which their new duties impose upon them. THE TEACHERS The School is very fortunate in having most of last year's teachers back. Eleanor Brabson has the primer class, and Miriam Swann, the first graders. Stella Huff is in charge of the fifth and sixth grades. Jessie Branham has added to her home economics classes for girls one for boys at night, by request. Pauline Whaling, Illinois A, continues high school classes in English and history. Don Smith manages the farm and teaches agriculture and animal husbandry to the boys in school and to various groups of men in and near Gatlinburg. The teaching staff of the Settlement School is now headed by V. A. Hampton, a native of Tennessee. Although Mr. Hampton has had three years of experience in Kentucky and Tennessee schools, he was graduated only this past June from the University of Tennessee. As principal of the high school he is carrying out fully all state requirements. He coaches the basketball team three times a week. He and Miss Chaffee hold weekly teachers' meetings. They havearranged to have one of the teachers supervise the playgrounds during the lunch period, and the result is better discipline. All the teachers are visiting the children's homes. They intend to keep the enrollment as high as possible. From Missouri r comes jean Hand-ley to teach grades two and three. Al-though she doesn't have the same classes, Jean really is filling the vacancy made by the resignation of Katherine Collins, Colorado A. Beginning as president of the freshman class, Jean ended her very active undergraduate career as commencement speaker at Drury College last June. Martha Huff hardly needs an introduction to readers of News From Little Pigeon because her parents were among the first friends of the Settlement School and because she was enrolled there for three years herself. After two years in Maryville College in Tennessee, Mattie, as she is often called, en-rolled at Iowa State where she became a member of Iowa r. She teaches the fourth grade and helps with the music in the elementary school, where she is the sixth teacher. Last year the whole staff felt the need for a sixth teacher here, but only this fall has it been possible to have one. To keep her, the school must have in the first eight grades an average daily attendance of 175. The end of August there were 183, but an epidemic of whooping cough early in September took more than 20 children out at a time. The high school has forty pupils.* * News about other members of the staff will appear in subsequent issues of the ARROW. ACCOMPLISHMENTS OF THE SETTLEMENT SCHOOL COMMITTEE The Settlement School Committee in session July 20-27 in. Gatlinburg: 1. Studied and accepted annual reports of committee members and staff department heads; 2. Adopted, subject to the approval of Grand Council, a manual for the director and one for the bookkeeper of the Settlement School; 3. Were guests one evening of Mr. and Mrs. Steve Whaley and met at the River</p>
      <pb ref="arr5020183_0002" seq="02" n="184-185  "/>
       <p>184 THE NOVEMBER ARROW side Hotel. Mrs. Newt Clabo and Harvey Reagan who with the hostess are members of a Gatlinburg committee organized to assist with the undertakings of the Settlement School; with these discussed matters of local interest, particularly the necessity for II B to close the dormitories as the best means of curtailing expenses without impairing the service of the school to the immediate community ;* 4. Conferred with county school officials; 5. Discussed Convention plans; 6. After several conferences with officials, sold the Sugarlands cottage, situated in the Great Smoky Mountains National Park, for $3000 and a five-year lease, the $3000 to be applied on the mortgage of $8500 on the School; 7. Elected Maryalice Chaffee, Michigan * The closing of the dormitories has not affected the high school enrollment. Wear's Valley and Pigeon Forge have their own high schools this year, and the only ninth-grade children who are not now back in Gatlinburg live in one or the other of these communities. A, as director to succeed Evelyn Bishop, resigned; 8. Filled vacancies on the School staff; 9. Reduced from 5 per cent to 15 per cent all salaries of the Settlement School staff in order to meet the reduced income; 10. Through planned economies in every department cut the budget for 1933-1934 by $5188 from that of 1932-1933; 11. Authorized investigation of the water supply of the School and the chlorination of the water if necessary; 12. Called on the Receiver of the Bank of Sevierville with regard to the agreement of depositors; 13. Was conscious more than ever before of the interest of the community in the School; 14. Was deeply impressed by the continued loyalty of all members of II B to the fraternity's great altruistic project the past year when each gift represented a very real sacrifice; 15. Was gratified by the unfailing devotion of the staff in meeting the difficult prob. lems of the times, especially continued salary reductions. FO THOSE WHO WOULD TEAC AT GATLINBURG The explanation of Tennessee laws governing the certification of teachers that was published in the ARROW for February of this year has not proved as helpful as the committee had hoped. An interpretation by the Tennessee super-visor of certification will probably clear away the difficulty: "The educational courses required for permanent elementary certificates have not been prescribed. We expect those who are undertaking to meet the requirements for elementary certificates to confine their edu-cational courses to the elementary field, and those who are applicants for high school certificates to confine their courses to the secondary field." In other words, unless an applicant for a position in an elementary school in Tennessee has credits in elementary education, she will not be certificated by the State Department of Education; and if she is not certificated, she will not be paid from public school funds. Credits in secondary school education may not be substituted. SETTLEMENT SCHOOL ESENTE ID I. EP IN EXHI imp IT The exhibit of Southern Mountain Handicrafts collected and arranged by Allen Eaton of Russell Sage Foundation, and to which Arrow Craft of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School contributed a number of articles, is being circulated by the American Federation of Arts. The exhibit was shown at the Corcoran Gallery, Washington, D.C., during October. Anyone interested in obtaining this exhibit or being included in the itinerary, may write for information to Mr. Frederic A. Whiting, The American Federation of Arts, Barr Building, Farragut Square, Washington, D.C. Mr. Whiting, president of the Amer THE NOVEMBER ARROW 185 ican Federation of Arts has said that this exhibit is the finest and most outstanding one of its kind ever assembled in WITH OU \ The following letter was recently received from Veatress Parton, who assists in the Arrow Craft Shop at Gatlinburg. I have recently returned (to Gatlinburg) from spending a very enjoy-able summer in Woodstock, New York. It was indeed a novelty to me to be any length of time in New York, since I have spent the greater part of my life in Gatlinburg. It may be of interest to all Pi Phis to know that our Arrow Craft Shop, in which I have been employed for the past five years, is well represented in the shop in the Little Gallery in Wood-stock, which is owned by the artist, L. E. Jones. I was amused as well as surprised at the conception many people have of our mountaineers and their work. I spent a great deal of my time explaining about our dear Settlement School, its aims, its purposes, and its accomplishments and telling about the America. Arrow Craft has a number of beautiful things on display and is proud to be included. GRADUATES display of our hand-woven goods and other hand-made things. Many people were surprised that I had learned to weave from my grandmother and later had been taught the technical points of weaving in the Settlement School. The Pi Beta Phi School has done many wonderful things for the mountain people. In my work in the Arrow Craft Shop I continually hear expressions of appreciation from the mountain folk, as they bring in their weaving to sell. They think that the School is the best school on earth and that no other organization could do for one group of people what Pi Beta Phi is doing for us. It makes me very happy when I see that this feeling is prevalent among them, because Pi Phi, to me, means just everything that it does to them. VEATRESS PARTON rl5. duff IN THE DEATH of Mrs. Andrew Huff the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School has lost one of its most loyal friends. From the day of its be-ginning Mrs. Huff gave the School her unfailing support because of her belief in the good it would work in the community. As it justified her faith, she sent her children there. Two daughters now are on the teaching staff. For the last few years illness prevented Mrs. Huff from continuing her old-time active participation in affairs, but it never diminished her interest in the School. The end came on August 30. </p>
      <pb ref="arr5020183_0003" seq="03" n="186-187  "/>
       <p>Arrow Crafters To Help With Your Christmas Shoppin 1: Scarf, Gentleman's Fancy pattern of soft wool, 92 by 48 inches, woven in white with black border, grey with blue, tan with brown, and green with darker green, $1.75 each. 2. Doll Rugs 3 by 41/2 inches, hit or miss pattern. Attractive for small what-nots as well as for doll houses, 15c. 3. Doilies of natural linen bordered in red, orange, yellow, blue, green, and black, 7 by 7 inches for end tables or such, 25c; 7 by 12 inches also for end table, 35c; 12 by 17 inches for plate doilies, 50c. 4. Whig Rose runners 6 by 8 inches, miniature pattern. A nice bit of color for any room. In all colors with white fringe, 50c. 5. Knitting bag natural linen with a very gay Texas Frame Rose border, $2.00. 6. Baby pillow 12 by 15 inches, pink or blue linen with white lambs, $1.00. 7. Buttons--Buckles Braceletshandmade of black walnut, wild cherry, or maple. Most attractive for sports or tailored clothes, and especially so when used with an Arrow Craft belt. Buttons, small, 15c each; medium, 17 c each; large, 20c each. Buckles, small, 65c each; large, 75c each. Bracelets 50c each. 8. Lydia Runner 12 by 16 inches, a gay bit of weaving to be used either as a breakfast plate doily or for an odd table. Our Smoky Mountain version of peasant art, $1.00. 9. Wool bags woven to match the belts, zipper fastening, 7 by 10 inches, $1.75. 10. Candles and Candle Holders hand dipped bees-wax candles in natural or antique blue, green, or red. They burn with a much brighter flame and last longer than the ordinary candle. The 7-inch ones are 25c a pair; 12-inch are 50c a pair. The holders of hand turned cherry or black walnut a limited quantity for 50c each. 11. Beverage Napkins all linen, 6 by 6 inches fringed, bordered on two sides in red, blue, yellow, green, or rainbow, 4 for 75c. 12. Pewter Plates hand hammered by Penland Weavers and Potters, a mountain school in North Carolina. The pewter has a lovely texture and a nice weight. coaster size 3 inches .50 bread and butter 6 inches .75 salad 8 inches $1.50 tea 10 inches 2.50 deep plate 12 inches 4.00 medium platter, dog wood design cut in each end 5.00 13. Belts wool or cotton, woven on the Rose Path pattern with stripes. Ideal for hand knitted and sports dresses. Red, blue, green, brown, or black with contrasting stripes, $1.00. All prices subject to change without notice. Postage extra. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



