<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr5340377_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Brown, Charlotte Cropley</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>May 1937</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr5340377_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">May 1937</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Brown, Charlotte Cropley</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 377-381</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">39</note>
                        <note type="Folder">1</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 53, Number 4 (May 1937), Pages 377-381.</note>
			<note type="document">arr5340377_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Go to Gatlinburg: A Travelog from a Pi Phi Family</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Tourism</item>
                                <item>Promotion</item>
                                <item>Southern Appalachian culture</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr5340377_0001" seq="01" n="376-377  "/>
       <p>THE MAY ARROW . Somehow an alarm clock an-makes me want to stay in bed, etting me up. When I awake I :then and make myself a big cup Tong with a slice of bread and 'ce it back to bed. Everything :e and quiet and cosy then and I 0THY McCLEARY, D.C.A. Thus it was that she turned out ipt which was deemed best by dges than Martha Foley, editor gazine, Lewis Gannett, critic on ,rk Herald-Tribune and Harry E. naging Editor of Doubleday, for Heaven was also chosen by Guild for distribution among its Lo read this prize-winning novel L new writer of unusual ability. pproach and vigorous charactericertain high standard for herself did not forget when they opened ,ok Naked to Laughter. That she appointed her critical friends is )on as the first chapter had been is centered about Ruby Shreve, who was the milliner in a small town. Ruby was not the usual mousey sort, cringing be-hind protective pince-nez glasses. When an assistant was apprehended in one of her acts of kleptomania, Ruby caught her by the wrists in a grip that left red evidences of her strength. In the life that was lived in the shop and her quarters behind it this strength usually displayed itself in the directness of her character. But Ruby had her weakness, and it was a womanly desire for love. When Herman came into her life, it be-came impossible for her to keep him out of her mind. But this is no ordinary study of a woman in love, for Ruby had none of the feminine wiles. Her direct approach to the complacent blond giant Herman was her only way of projecting herself. It left her naked to the laughter of her world, until a bitterly won wisdom came to her. Thus runs the plot, but the mastery this Pi Phi author displays is revealed in her excellent characterizations. "As for `plot' in a story or novel," she says, "it appears to me so wholly a matter of character-development that I never give it a thought. Characters, if watched long enough and attentively enough, will invariably respond by creating their own plot and to me that is all that one dares ask of them. It's no fair taking your finger and moving a character like a chessman. No, fiction-writing might rather be compared to sitting in the engine of a train, stoking up for a journey over a tailless track, with a headlight which sees not more than half an inch ahead. . . . But what a lovely trip with characters whom one loves!" Miss McCleary attended George Washing-ton University, where she was initiated into D.C. A. In various ways, she accumulated the experiences so valuable to an author. She acted in a New York City stock company, wrote for a newspaper syndicate and had a job as clerk in a Brooklyn department store. Next to writing, her greatest interest is cooking. (She is the author of "A Primer of Cooking.") In her free time, she continues her study of French, Italian, and Spanish. In private life, she is Mrs. Harry M. Hamilton and has an eight-year-old boy, Charles. She is a sister of Ethel McCleary Whitmore, also D.C. A. Winnipeg are sponsoring a most interesting kindergarten in that city, and gave lent performance for it January 27. More about this project another time! NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON Edited by CHARLOTTE CROPLEY BROWN, Vermont B DRAWING WATER Go to Gatlinbur A. Travelog from a Pi Phi Family* (o) THE MOTHER SPEAKS: It is only honest to state that our objective was not Gatlinburg. For years the fact that we who live in Massachusetts had elderly parents in Arkansas had given rise to periodic conversations like this. "We really must go to Little Rock this Summer." "Yes, but even Father and Mother say it is so hot that we could not stand it. Don't you re-member Mother's letter last summer in which she quoted the temperature 98 degrees, 99 degrees, and 102 degrees day after day? And at night she had to rub ice on the sheets andwring out her night-gown in water she put it on ?" "But when can we And so the matter dangled. We wan go, but the only months when a scho ter had time were reported as too Ii endurance. There is often no apparent reason important decision except inspiration one was possibly breathed in from the bed where I was poking about for buds one sunny March morning. I su said to myself, "We shall go to Al this summer !" It was only a moment * The family contributing this article is the Earl Maltby Benson family of Wellesley, Massachusetts. Mrs is a member of Massachusetts A, Mr. Benson is a Boston schoolmaster, and Miss Barbara Benson, their da.ugl recent Mt. Holyoke graduate. </p>
      <pb ref="arr5340377_0002" seq="02" n="378-379  "/>
       <p>THE MAY ARROW ;iasm had flown to B., digging at end of the border, and he had also rld the third member of the family ira, who would' have only three :ation from the bookshopt where ioth) worked, and who might pos other plans than riding 3200 luncheon, however, Barbara was I think she was remembering the she was eighteen, when her parents enly decided they would take her to or a year after her Commencement Holyoke. She had seen this come t had helped her to realize that a rice made, preparatory events often ne and make a pattern. following weeks plans grew. The Tole was delivered ; Grandfather Imother in Little Rock wrote they ided a cool spacious sleeping porch, arranged to add black Rosalie to because she could fry chicken so er than their man Lindsay; books vith routes marked and hotels and -,gested, stuffed the mail box every Peter, the cocker spaniel, was kennel. We locked the door and ;t stop for the night was in Scars-v York. The next morning the ith whom we stopped drove our car :he Holland Tunnel, and following ons to keep to the Skyway Drive, d rapidly along above the heavy few jersey cities. most of this day we passed through ;ylvania farming country where the re startling decorations in bright "porches" for the cattle. The road red for miles with hollyhocks. All zld have them wherever possible. later the Blue Ridge Mountains around us as we climbed the new )rive above winding valleys. We lonely cabins here and there far s and villages. What kind of life, .red, do people live so far away we call civilization ? Most of these were told, will have to move out town, because the building of this s this territory a park land. "It will thing, too, because the youngsters to go to school now." Later on, in Smokies, we were to see a similar while on this trip, received her appointment In Division of the National Board of the Id is in charge of interpretation and informa-!r office in New York City. situation great mountains, a National Park, and what it meant to the people in their cabins. We recalled the lonely huts in the mountains of Scotland where the shepherd and his family have only hill and sky and sheep for company. The next morning found us on our way to Knoxville, a name which meant only one thing to us. It was the point at which one turns southeast for Gatlinburg, the town which from the beginning had loomed large in our plans. We had decided to make no detours for pleasure, however, until our visit in Little Rock was over, and thus it was with real regret that we passed through Knoxville, making a straight line across Tennessee, through Nashville to Memphis. We drove through heat that sounds unbearable, but it did not harm nor delay us. At times the thermometer registered 114 , and at the Andrew Jackson, where we stopped in Nashville, the hotel clerk had wisely mislaid his thermometer. We were seeing a new world, the world of great level stretches of cotton, with crazy black shanties of negroes scattered through the fields. Never having seen cotton growing, I thought at first that the small plants were potatoes, and once when we stopped by the road I asked a boy in a field if his potatoes were doing well. "Potatoes! That ain't potatoes, that's the finest field of cotton this side the Mississippi !" As we drove through this country we began dimly to know something of the problem of the tenant farmer and the sharecropper. But that is another story. In fact, all this preamble may seem to you "an-other story," but the Editor asked for the "How" of our journey. She also asked for the "What." After crossing the Mississippi and spending a week in Little Rock, we retraced our road to Knoxville, and here is where B. comes in to tell what we saw and did at Gatlinburg. THE FATHER SPEAKS: I have always known that one's state of mind is closely associated with environment. At three o'clock on a torrid July after-noon I was just impossible. For two long days I had been cooped up in a sun-baked Chevrolet, looking at a long straight ribbon of concrete that runs from Memphis to Knoxville. I was beginning to fuss in the most approved style and inwardly wondered if I should ever see the last of Tennessee. Mildred and Barbara would have been perfectly justi THE MAY ARROW fled in opening the door and rolling me down an embankment into a cotton field. The last whine disappeared, however, by magic, after we crossed the river at Knoxville. In the dim distance we could see the hazy outlines of the Great Smokies. Forty miles and we would be at our journey's end. It was forty miles of sheer loveliness past neat farm buildings set in the midst of level fields of grain, then into a wooded valley along a CORN PATCH curving road which followed a tumbling mountain stream. The gurgling water cooled and soothed us as we followed its winding course. As we crossed a bridge, Mildred spied a sign, LITTLE PIGEON RIVER. Then we knew that we were among friends. Little Pigeon has always meant but one thing in our family, the Settlement School. High up above us rose LeConte, wooded to the very top ; on either side of the road steep paths with rustic railings led to small cabins, and behind them row upon row of corn grew on a forty-five degree hillside. It must have been planted by fairies ! How human folk could do more than scramble up the steep incline seemed impossible. When we passed through the st( way bearing the sign, "Pi Beta Phi S, School," and drew up before the ' Cottage, it was four o'clock, but the disappeared behind the friendly m So cool and invigorating was the ail have been early morning. We were ferent world! On the porch was a women in conference, Pi Beta Phi ment School Committee. Ordinarily when one breaks in committee meeting, he is put in promptly and properly with instrt sit down and wait. Mrs. Weaver of the school, and the members of tional Committee are not ordinar however. When Mildred had introc self and family, we immediately fe belonged there, and even I, in the such an august body, lost all my sh] Any impression of the Settleme would be incomplete without a wt miration for Mrs. Weaver and her were all impressed with her enthu the end of a strenuous day she wa show us the school. After she had made reservations cabins owned and managed by a f dent, we began our tour. In the Stuart Cottage we met Mary Ellet add, who, with the help of twc mountain girls, was preparing su atmosphere of a fine old Nev, kitchen pervaded the place, and as her preparing crisp salads and si ham, I was tempted to saunter aro back door an hour later and ask if want me to work a bit on the woc I was impressed with the comp equipment. A separate building up-to-date hospital where a resid assisted by the local doctor, car health of the community. A mod building faces a broad playing f the Gatlinburg boy can learn ti game as well as his brother in th largest barn we saw in this part of is the model building belonging to Mountain boys are now learning stock, the value of rotation of crc the latest methods of agriculture are instructed in dress making a and are trained in all the ameniti making, something that was end: in the lives of the former gener In the industrial building we f material evidence of the school's are the hand looms where nat </p>
      <pb ref="arr5340377_0003" seq="03" n="380-381  "/>
       <p>0 THE MAY ARROW ave articles which would grace a Fifth enue shop window, scarves, neckties (I re two and wish I had more) , runners, cur-as, and bedspreads. Miss Redding, the efent weaving teacher, told us how the school plies the material and pays the members the weaving guild, ninety in number, when articles are completed. We saw the supply m with compartments filled with hanks of n, and looked with envious eyes at the !s of the finished Arrowcraft products. We 7 home-woven goods in several Gatlinburg Ts, but they were all inferior in quality of rkmanship and design. 'xi the Arrowcraft Shop, Mrs. Snow, the nager, had on display products of the loom I hand-made cherry chairs and tables. The res were reasonable, but our funds not sufent to satisfy our desires. upper at the New Mountain View Hotel de us yearn to stay on indefinitely in quiet valley. Good home-cooked food in ndance, served in family style, was a de-Itful change from meals in air-conditioned 1 rooms of the large cities. As I paid the at the desk, I saw a modest folder which cribed the hotel and quoted the rates, 50 per day American plan. If there is ther hostel in the East which includes i.ls and room at such a price, I have yet lear of it. n the afternoon we called on Mollie ore who lives with her mother and sister L little cabin on the side of the Sevierville d. Mollie is. a member of the Weavers' ld, and showed us how she operated her m, which was set up in the living room. tile she worked, her mother, seventy-five, us of her struggle to bring up a family six; how she planted and cultivated the side piece of corn and often fell down [le carrying the bags down the hill. Now had reached a peaceful old age and was ,arently living comfortably in her cabin the Little Pigeon. Both Mollie and her tiler declared that they did not know what r would have done if the School had not n there to help in "lightening the load." E DAUGHTER SPEAKS: ,.nd here, with mention of a lighter load, third member of the family lifts her pen. rom this present life in New York City, !rwoven with the strange confusion of tic and noise, skyscrapers and slums, I back on Gatlinburg resting there so etly in the valley by the Little Pigeon, with the same affection which I hold in my heart for the small villages in the Italian Alps. Is it possible that we were there little over twenty-four hours? Long enough at any rate to sense the friendliness, the strength, and the permanency of this small community. What do I remember ? First, the cool afternoon shadows cast by the sheltering mountain sides, the sound of the clear water of Little Pigeon bubbling over the rocks, patch-work quilts, homespun, baskets and furniture displayed so attractively in the Settlement School shop, looms worn and shiny resting on cabin porches, two of the most beautiful girls I have ever seen, and a friendly speech sounding quite strange to my New England ears trained to the "R" of Yankee origin. I remember also the pleasant sensation I experienced when told about the Weavers' Guild. It was almost as if I were tasting history again. My knowledge of dates is scant, but all the same, mention of this Weavers' Guild took me back somewhere around page 270 of my history schoolbook, back to the time when the crafts were dignified, when a member of the craft guild was an artist and a person of influence in his community. And here in the year 1936, in the mountains of Tennessee, we came upon a weavers' guild! The accomplishments of this group which has approximately 100 members are many. Not only does the Guild produce fabrics, but drama as well. A play bill or two, and enthusiastic rumors, were responsible for our staying over in Gatlinburg to see "Lightening the Load," a play written and produced by the Guild members in the assembly hall at the Settlement School. The day had been hot, not even the chill waters of Little Pigeon could change the burning noon-day. I thought with compassion of the farmers working in their cotton fields along the Tennessee highway and was grateful for the wooded glades of Gatlinburg. Shortly after four o'clock the air began to change. The sun dropped behind the mountains. The birds began to sing, and a fresh breeze stirred the trees. There was an air of festivity in the village all that day, and after supper we started down the road, joining others along the way. We wandered peacefully along the path, through the pasture under the placid gaze of the Settlement School cows, and waited with others for the doors to open. The hall was filled that evening. Children took the front row seats. Fathers and mothers sat behind them. With a certain sense of guilt, THE MAY ARROW I must admit that we three sat among the children, watching and listening with all the enthusiasm of the youngest among them. What is the theater without music in the pit? The Gatlinburg Theater measured up in this respect, too. Four young men took their place before the curtain. They plucked mountain tunes from their strings and sang songs which set feet to tapping and hands to clapping. The hall became dark and the curtain rolled up on Gatlinburg in its early days. Here was the interior of a cabin, with women gathered together for a sewing bee. There was the ever-present loom, a pot of dye over the fire, a spinning wheel, a girl carding wool by the fireplace, another rocking a baby in a cradle. All of them were chatting about their work, the hardships and monotony of their life, recipes, and children. "Why, I brought up twelve children under one pair of blankets," one old lady said into the gossip-laden air. There on the stage at Gatlinburg was en-acted the story of the village's past years. The rumor of a school being opened, the hint of superstition at people invading the valley. Finally, we saw the village in and witnessed the work the S had done in lightening the 1( It is an injustice that I sr play so inadequately. I wou lines and quote characters. A is to tell of the charm anc sincerity of the weavers who this play, and to tell of ho flected the attitude of the p lase toward the Pi Phi Settle The trip from Massachus and back was all too brief, cities, towns and people, I remained in my memory as burg. To my mind the scho the thorough way in which part of the village without su side theories upon it. To the an ideal rural project. To ( native industries it is a sol artistic work. To one who a friendly village. Need I this, that whether you are Phi or just a husband or a Phi, do visit this Settlement burg on Little Pigeon. IN THE MOUNTAIN FASTNESS </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



