<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr5510079_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Settlement School Reports </title>
                        <author><name>Holton, Lillian Beck </name></author>
                        <author><name>Holton, Edwin L.</name></author>
                        <author><name>Stark, H. J. L. </name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>September 1938</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr5510079_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">September 1938</date>, Settlement School Reports </title>
                        <author><name>Holton, Lillian Beck </name></author>
                        <author><name>Holton, Edwin L.</name></author>
                        <author><name>Stark, H. J. L. </name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 78-100</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">39</note>
                        <note type="Folder">4</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 55, Number 1 (September 1938), Pages 78-100.</note>
			<note type="document">arr5510079_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Chairman of the Settlement School Committee; Report of Dr. Holton on the Settlement School; Report of Mr. Lutcher Stark on the Settlement School; Pi Beta Phi Settlement School- Report on Audit of Treasurer's Accounts Year Ended June 30, 1938; Report of the Vocational Agriculture Teacher, 1937-38; Arrow Craft Report, 1937-38; Report of the Home Economics Department 1937-38; Elementary School Report, 1937-38; Jennie Nicol Memorial Health Center, May 1937-April 1938; Dormitory Report, 1937-38</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Funding</item>
                                <item>Staff</item>
                                <item>Facilities</item>
                                <item>Health care</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr5510079_0001" seq="01" n="78-79  "/>
       <p>THE SEPTEMBER ARROW Settlement School Reports L.N. OF THE SETTLEMENT SCHOOL COMMITTEE has placed the affairs of the cool in the hands of a committee by the Grand Council and an-n and to the Fraternity. Three asked to become a member of [ accepted and worked for one ficient direction of Frankie Cochcial place on the Committee that Df the News from Little Pigeon. at year, which was immediately er Beach Convention, I took over of the Settlement School Comguest of Grand Council. During it have elapsed since I took this lave to the best of my ability and a most efficient committee and le affairs of the School. It is to !wardship that I come before you to Eunice Sheldon Weaver, our ort of the work of the various staff. But may I say in passing ad at all times among the staff cooperation and a loyalty to the the School was founded. I am s brought about largely by the of Eunice Weaver and by her to make the Settlement School unity even as was visioned by ho, back in 1910, went into the md needy community that could tions in Gatlinburg have changed time. Our work there has grown acted with it in those early years riled. It is the changes that have e last two years to which I wish ntion at this time. ivided into three parts, the school, ., and Arrow Craft. I hope that se you by using the word school q times we use the term School !rm Settlement School. In writing I S for this School, meaning our chile school with a small s means .rt of our work, namely the ele school work. This distinction n the spoken word so I shall be e full term Settlement School for role and school alone will refer to rk. myself for the most part to the the supposition that each of you of the history of the School up [, if you have read the reports in News from Little Pigeon, the of News Letter, and the letters vince and national officers, you ;mat deal about the last two years. going to repeat part of that inlere are some things which I wish your minds. 1ded my first Committee meeting ree years ago this month, at the tr people there, and to give the pity for education that the chil dren deserved, we put in the third year of high school work. Up to that time we had had a two-year or junior high school only. We did this in cooperation with the county board, the county paying the salary of the extra teacher needed and we took care of the extra equipment. We had the average attendance of fifty pupils required by the state for a standard three-year high school. Two years ago, when I took over the chairman-ship, the high school was ready for the fourth year to be added, as there were the required number of seventy-five ready to enroll that fall. So the fourth year was added, again with the county adding the salary of the extra teacher, and we took care of the extra equipment for a science laboratory. In May, 1937, the first class to graduate from the four-year high school numbered twenty-two young men and women. Mrs. Weaver said that when she saw those twenty-two in their cans and gowns receive their diplomas she felt that if we never did anything more, we were repaid for all our efforts This year's class numbered fourteen. Many of these graduates are going on to college, some to business school, and others have positions. While this increase in high school attendance was taking place, the elementary school was growing rapidly. Our elementary building has five rooms. Three years ago the number of grade pupils was so great that they could not all be accommodated in the elementary building so the seventh and eighth grades were put into one of the large high school rooms. The county furnished the extra teacher. Next fall another high school room must be used for an elementary grade and the county has promised to furnish another teacher. This brings me to an explanation of the way that the county cooperates with us in the support of the grade and high school. The county pays the salaries of all the elementary teachers. There will be seven of them next year. The county also pays us $100 per month rent for the elementary building for the eight months that the grade school runs. So you see that the grade school is really no expense to us. The county also pays the salaries of three high school teachers, those teachers who teach the regular academic subjects. We pay the teacher of home economics and the part of the agriculture teacher's salary that is not taken care of by Federal aid, and we add enough to our principal's salary to make it $150 per month. To give you just a few figures, we have paid for salaries in the past school year: Home economics $1,008.00 Principal 342.00 Agriculture 710.00 Total $2,060.00 We have received from Federal Smith-Hughes aid: Agriculture $ 940.00 Sevier County has paid for teachers' salaries the past year: THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 6 elementary teachers $4,476.00 3 high school teachers 3,024.00 Total $8,400.00 The county has paid rent for elementary buildings: Rent 800.00 We furnish the building and equipment for the high school. We are adding the vocational training to what the county gives the boys and girls. Next year we will receive $200 more from Smith-Hughes for Agriculture, and we hope with the new laboratory to get our home economics on Smith-Hughes and will receive $600 aid for that. Going back now to the increase in attendance. This past year there were 287 in the grade school and 92 in the high school. Next year there will be more. The elementary school will occupy two rooms of the high school building. This does not leave enough room for the four-year high school with its increased attendance. The state inspector said last fall that we must have more room, larger laboratories, more equipment, and a study hall, if we were to remain on the list of standard accredited high schools. After much correspondence he agreed to leave the school on the list this year if we would promise to make the necessary expansion for next year. Knowing that there was a feeling among some of the alumnae that the support of the school should no longer be borne by the fraternity but that if we were to continue with our share of that support we must add some laboratory space, the Fraternity sent me to Gatlinburg last February. I spent ten days there, going over various plans, inter-viewing officials, and trying to decide what was best to be done. The last three days, I was joined by H. Lutcher Stark and my husband, Edwin L. Holton, both of whom came at their own expense and made surveys of the present and future needs of the school. Mr. Stark's long acquaintance with the Settlement School, his business experience, and his interest in and work with educational institutions of Texas made his assistance most valuable. Mr. Holton has been in school work all his life, having had experience in public school work before becoming head of the department of education and Dean in Kansas State College. He has conducted a number of surveys of school systems. I have with me copies of these reports which these men made to the Grand Council and committee, as well as my own report. Mr. Stark and Mr. Holton went over the plans which I had worked out with Mrs. Weaver, Mr. King, Mr. Barber, our architect, and various other people during the week that I had preceded them there. We went into the various phases of the county and Fraternity financial support of the school. A long interview with the county superintendent affirmed the fact that the county is doing all that it is able to do in supporting the school, and the present Committee has no desire to depart from this procedure. The fact that this year the county has paid the salary of an addi tional teacher and will add still another next year is proof of that fact. We are educating the people to help themselves, and I feel that when the county is ready to bear the whole burden of the school, the Fraternity should and will allow the county to do it. But that time is not here yet. As I said before the county is now pa all the elementary and three of the high sc teachers, and we are paying the salary of high school teacher and part salary of two of The county is paying us rent for the elemei building. The county allows us to choose the mentary as well as the high school teachers, we have supervision. We have about an c number of Pi Phi and local teachers. All have degrees, so that the standard is higher in many schools. The course of study foil( is that arranged for standard schools of Tel see. The work given has been such that our st has kept its rating as a standard school. In ( to keep that rating next year the high s( building must be enlarged. That is the conch that we always came back to after our discuss In order to finance the addition to the school, the Grand Council gave perrnissio sell a small piece of land (four and one acres) which is not connected with our property, use two bequests which together about $1,000, and the $1,000 which we ha\ our budget this year to pay on the debt tc endowment. The land has been sold for $3 making a total of $5,000. The plan whid are using was drawn by Mr. Barber and is 1 carried out as planned except for the home nomics suite which had to be omitted becau would not come within our budget. The cot has been let to Walter Cardwell, a fine builder, and work has already started. This necessary in order to have the building for the opening of school the middle of AL This addition should make our school buil, adequate for at least three years. I regret having to give so much space t( buildings, for although they are most nece: it is what goes on within the buildings th the vital part of any school. One accomplish of the past year was getting our agriculture partment back on the Smith-Hughes basis. had been without this aid for three years, Mr. Coe, our new agriculture teacher, has most successful in teaching and also in m ing our farm. Mr. Price has been in char the elementary school, thus leaving Mr. only the high school to supervise. Both men full teaching loads. An earnest and efficient of teachers, working under the supervision o King and Mr. Price, have improved the sta of the academic work, making this year the since I have been on the committee. With and better equipped quarters and an equal] ficient staff increased by one teacher, our s should and will serve the community next with increased efficiency and will stand as a i for schools in east Tennessee. Along with our school we have develoi Health Service that is outstanding. Sevier C is a large county and has no income to spe except from farming, and there is only a proportion of good farm land in the county county has a health service but provides onl nurse. In the large territory which she must two or three visits a year would be all the community could expect. So the work o nurse is still most necessary. I could fill with the statistics of the calls, the inocula the dressings, and other things that Mrs. Ma Chalmers, our nurse, reports to the county </p>
      <pb ref="arr5510079_0002" seq="02" n="80-81  "/>
       <p>THE SEPTEMBER ARROW s. The county furnishes serums ies. I wish you might have a Iue Ribbon parade in Sevierville from all county schools compete ;e children must have met cerements to get their blue ribbons, . Phi group, 180 strong, again with our banner the group of mpeting. Or, I wish you might others carrying their healthy and in the better babies contest on These are times when we can ud of the results of our health Jork that accomplishes these re-long hours by day and by night, lmers is always ready to go when needed. ome to Arrow Craft, that part ch has been built up in the last e work in the revival of the e Highlands is one of the most worthwhile things that Pi Beta the Smoky Mountains. When I on the Settlement School Comat, having been a teacher for a aving lived with a teacher for knowledge of school work would ground for the Settlement School )n learned that there was other sary. So I set to work to learn uld about the handicrafts of the enthusiasm has grown as I have nformed. Our handicraft center )le position among the twenty-:he Southern Highlanders Guild. and of quality of material, the rkmanship, and the beauty of de-oven products outstanding. When on the Committee, Arrow Craft ng to make a profit. The favor-Gatlinburg right at the entrance Park has done much to increase school enrollment and to make n.ore complex; but it has also in-,ur Arrow Craft business. If you x annual reports, you will see profits for the year 1934-35 were r the year 1935-36 they had in-?, and in 1936-37 to $5,694, and ,ding June 30, 1938 the profits may ask where have these profits you who have had experience know that the larger the busimoney it takes to carry on that must be more supplies kept on List be a much larger stock of s kept ready for sale. So a part has been kept in the business. drawing interest in a savings ac-le time, in the not far distance, row Craft shop must be built in year $2,500 of Arrow Craft profit he debt to the endowment, and me amount will be paid on that benefit of some who do not unthat debt to the endowment is, hat when the present high school [It, some of the Settlement School used to finance the building. This on the books as "due the Settle-Ldowment Fund from the Settle ment School." At the beginning of my term as chairman this debt amounted to $13,042, and it has been reduced to $9,096. I had hoped that by the end of my term next June we might have this debt wiped out, but that was before the necessity of adding to the high school building became apparent. I wish to make it very clear that this addition is being financed by funds al-ready available, as I have stated. There will be no extra burden on alumnm or active contributions, and no debt will be incurred. My speaking of the debt to the endowment fund may have made you aware, if you were not before, that our national project, namely the Settlement School, has an endowment fund. This endowment fund at the end of this year will have reached about $35,000. The interest only from this fund is used. I have been telling you of the increase in our Arrow Craft business. This is not due alone to the increase in the tourist trade in our two shops in Gatlinburg. To that is added sales that are made through the ,Southern Highlanders, Inc., which was organized three years ago to furnish an outlet for the products of various handicraft centers. We have thirteen shares of stock. Two shops are maintained, one at Norris Dam and one in Rockefeller Center in New York City. In the last report, sales of our products were second only to Berea. At Allenstand, the shop run by the Handicraft Guild in Asheville, Arrow Craft led all the centers in the amount of products sold. However, the sale of products through our alum= clubs and chapters is still of paramount importance. Your assistance in marketing Arrow Craft goods is most essential. You will be interested to know that the club farthest away from Gatlinburg sold the largest amount. The Honolulu club led all other clubs by selling $1,015 worth of Arrow Craft products. Sabine District was next with $915. Then came Cleveland with $621; Dallas, $503; Denver, $494; and Pasadena, $413. We thank you for what you have done, and we urge your continued participation in this part of our work. This increased business has been of benefit to the Settlement School, but the great good that it has done has been to the people of Gatlinburg. When you go to Gatlin-burg, talk with some of our hundred weavers, and with some of our basket, fan, or chair makers, and learn at first hand what our handicraft work means to them. It means not only shoes for their children and seed potatoes for their gardens, but it is a means of expression for them, and it en-riches their whole social life. Mollie Moore comes down the mountain to get materials, then back to her cabin to make the whig rose runners. Mary L. Owenby, in her home in the Glades, makes the ladder back chairs with oak split seats, and also weaves our peasant runners. Also in the Glades, which by the way is a valley six or more miles from the burg, lives Cordie McCarter who weaves luncheon sets, and farther up the mountain is Mom Proffitt, who makes them in another color. Another weaver is Izora Keenor, who has figured out that she walks seven miles in putting her warp on for the rain-bow shawls. Aunt Lizzie comes down from a cabin on Roarin' Fork to use her loom in our weaving building to make her old fashioned twill. From up Baskins and down Big Ridge they come, these mountain women, to whom this work is of such great importance. On the days when THE SEPTEMBER ARROW the Weavers' Guild or the Garden Club have meetings, their pleasure in this added social and educational contact is unbounded. I cannot leave the subject of Arrow Craft with-out expressing great appreciation for the work of our Arrow Craft Director, Mrs. Ethel Snow, whose careful management has made so great a profit possible, and to Winogene Redding, our weaving supervisor, for her beautiful designing, careful supervision of making the products, and her interest in the lives and the welfare of the weavers. These three departments of our Settlement School project are coordinated and unified by our director, Mrs. Weaver. You will visit Teachers' Cottage, Stewart and Pollard Cottages. In these three houses in the winter live seventeen of our staff of twenty-five. The others live in the village. In addition, Stewart and Pollard house eighteen boys and girls, who live too far away to attend high school if we did not have these dormitories where their work helps pay for their board and room. I have tried to make clear to you two facts: first that Arrow Craft is now on a paying basis, and second that the county is paying a large share of the support of the school work. You may be wondering what is done with the money that you give. As I have stated, our share of the teachers' salaries is about $2,000. Now when you come to Gatlinburg and see that there are thirteen buildings necessary to house our various activities and realize that these must all be kept in repair, and repair means something with four hundred children and probably as many grown-ups going in and out. Then there is a water system to run. Last year in order to insure the purity of our water, a chlorinator was put in at a cost of $300. There are heat and light which are no small items, and insurance is another thing which runs into money. Other running expenses, too numerous to mention, must be met. Then you will realize -that all of these activities need coordination and supervision and this is done by the director whose salary is paid from our budget. Our director is also the leader in all community work, in which all members of our staff take part. Our budget also takes care of the salary and car expense of our nurse, and out of it comes the expense of keeping the dormitories. The boys and girls all work, but of course they cannot pay the entire cost of their living. Thus you may see that there is still a great deal for us to do. Now I represent the Settlement School Committee of five members appointed by the Grand Council and responsible to them and to the fraternity for the management of the Settlement School. Since there have been some suggestions by alumnae as to changes in this Committee, I am going to explain to you how this Committee functions. We have an annual meeting at the Settlement School in June or July. At this annual meeting our Grand Council adviser, who during my term of office has been our Grand President, spends at least two days with us. Miss Onken has been of great assistance to us at our meetings and advises us continually in the interim of the annual meetings. The meeting usually lasts six or seven days. We begin our sessions at eight in the morning and continue them until eight or nine o'clockat night. We begin with reports from our mittee members and members of the staff cussing recommendations that the various bers of the staff may make. We inspect a buildings and decide on the necessary 1.c needed equipment, and improvements. We view the county officers and the school 1 and visit with as many of our local pear possible. We decide on future needs and po We make the budgets for Arrow Craft an School and this is no small task. The .i Craft budget ,for this past year was for Making it was not so difficult, for we fell that the income would exceed that, but w1c came to the School budget, it was not so There our income is uncertain, and there a many things that we want to do. We count $12,000 from Alumnae clubs, $2,000 from ters (three-fourths goes to endowment), $2,100 from the magazine agency. Interest the endowment fund brought this income $15,000, and we budgeted our expenditut come within that amount. When you thint the salaries of the director, nurse, housek cooks, janitor, $2,000 of teachers' salaries maintenance and operation of our car and lights, fuel, laundry, furnishings, repairs, al manent improvements and insurance for th buildings, and the travel expense of the mittee must come within the budget you realize our difficulty. However, Josephine Cleverty, our treasurer, tells me that we finish the year June 30 without a deficit. The meeting of this budget has been possible by the generous contributions of of five chapters and alumnae clubs. This year I land and Los Angeles clubs lead the list $900 each. Then comes St. Louis with Kansas City, $500; Denver and North $400. Chapters giving largest contributions California a and California r, each $150; rado A, Illinois Z, Missouri B, $100 each. contributions are outstanding for their size are greatly appreciated, but we also appreck other club and chapter contributions, and I that time would permit mentioning others members of the Committee are all memb clubs and know the time and energy us making this money, and we endeavor to m go just as far as possible. You will hear a separate report of the zine Agency which had had its best year an nished $2,445 for the support of the S This is also due to the fine support of chit chapters as well as to the excellent wo Edith Updegraff Stephenson and her assi The Los Angeles Club has turned over made from the Pi Beta Phi Cook Book $! this is being used for furnishings and adder facilities in Teachers' Cottage. The other will be used to equip the new home ecos laboratory. If you will look in the front of your As you will see how the work of the Commi divided among the members. One member is tary, and she gets out copies of our minus all Council and Committee members as sc possible after the annual meeting has as:lie Marie Bacon Hagee, Missouri B, has also a new list of "Ways and Means of 3 Money." Our treasurer keeps a set of bo addition to those kept at the school, wh( </p>
      <pb ref="arr5510079_0003" seq="03" n="82-83  "/>
       <p>THE SEPTEMBER ARROW bookkeeper. Reports on Arrow expenditures are got out each ookkeeper and our Committee as each a monthly report. All ae School go through her hands. exacting and requires a great sephine McCleverty, Kansas A, easurer for the past four years efficient in handling this work many hours of her time each ber who has charge of the pro-is kept busy most of the winter material to various clubs for programs. Jeffries Green Pace, charge of this and in addition at deal of interesting material ig it out, she had a beautiful a School made at her own ex-member of the Committee edits Little Pigeon." I did this the was on the Committee, and I rience that. it takes a great deal meeting next week we will de-member will take which work aittee members may not be re-their four-year term has expired. Wisconsin B, has accepted one hel Hogan Copp, California r, r new member. The chairman of nakes an inspection trip to the 1 each fall. Our business, except leeting, is carried on by letters, 3eing sent to all Committee mem-[ President, who has been our the Grand Vice-President. A rom each member in answer to one from the director and one from the chairman is required. Many more are written, and the air mail and telegraph expedite our work. As chair-man, I have kept in constant communication with Mrs. Weaver and also with Miss Onken. addition I have written and sent copies of the "Settlement School News" to all clubs and chapters twice each year, and Mrs. Weaver has written the January issue. Then there has been a great deal of general correspondence to take care of, talks to clubs have been made, reports written; in fact, I have found it to be a real job to be a member of the Settlement School Committee. There is a school system, a health service, and a good sized business to manage. Before I close I want again to refer to Mr. Stark's and Mr. Holton's surveys. In the main, we three agreed on the present and future needs of the school. I have tried to outline to you what we must do in the immediate future in order to keep up the high standard of work that has always been done by the Fraternity in Gatlinburg. When Sevier County is able to take over more of the financial and administrative burden of the elementary and high schools, we have on our beautiful property in Gatlinburg, a wonderful opportunity to continue our health and social service work, and enlarge our Arts and Crafts work. No where could a more favorable location for a Handicraft and Art center be found and what more laudable and more interesting project could be found than this one which Pi Beta Phi has nurtured until it already has nation-wide recognition. Respectfully submitted, LILLIAN BECK HOLTON EIPOIT OFD., HOLTON ON THE SETTLEMENT SCHOOL At the request of the Grand Pi Beta Phi and the Chairman of charge of the Settlement School, attending the annual meeting of kssociation of School Adminis-:ic City, via Gatlinburg, for the ing a survey of the Settlement Gatlinburg from Thursday, March larch 6, 1938. I secured my in-is report by interviews with Mrs. the Director; Mr. William King, d the other members of the staff; Superintendent of Sevier County dents of Gatlinburg. Fars of Service. Pi Beta Phi has be proud of the outstanding sere-, has rendered to these mountain he past twenty-six years by its it project. Before entering upon fraternity spent a great deal of in locating a community where eatest for the services of a Settleiich the fraternity had definitely dish. The U. S. Bureau of Eduhem that no other people in the !re in greater need of educational ces than the mountain people of !es After advising with state aunessee the fraternity selected the munity for the location of its DI. At that time Gatlinburg was made up of mountain white people living in cabins and shacks in the narrow but b6autiful valleys of the Little Pigeon river and its tributaries. These mountain people and Sevier County were financially unable to support even an elementary school at that time. Modern civilization had passed by these descendents of our first Americans and left them stranded in the unproductive mountain valleys and "hollers." They eked out a meagre living by raising patches of corn, beans, tobacco, and other crops adapted to that region. The arts of weaving, basketry, wood carving, and furniture making which they once practiced in their homes had become almost lost arts because there was no outlet for selling their products. In fact Gatlinburg was an ideal community in which to establish a Settlement School such as Pi Beta Phi had planned. The leaders in this project decided to cooperate with the local people and the county school authorities in everything they did. They established the wise policy of educating these mountain people to help themselves rather than giving them relief to make them independent rather than dependent. From the beginning, the Settlement School emphasized the teaching of agriculture and the "lost arts" of weaving, basketry, wood carving and furniture making, as well as the essentials of an elementary education. The wise policy of permitting Sevier County to pay all it was able to pay on the salary of the elementary teacher or teachers, has been followed THE SEPTEMBER ARROW from the beginning. The fraternity added enough to the county aid to secure well qualified teachers. This wise policy has been followed until today the county is paying in full the salaries of the six elementary teachers and what is equivalent to the salaries of the teachers of the academic subjects in the high school. The work in agriculture, home economics, health service, and industrial arts has been developed as outlined by the founders of the Settlement School. This work has been placed under the wise policy of making the community self-supporting. I believe this policy of the Settlement School is largely responsible for the fact that there is not an individual in the entire community on federal relief, and there hasn't been throughout the depression. This is a unique record for the entire country. There is a story in this record that has very great news value. The Settlement School project has developed from one teacher in a one room school in 1912 into an up-to-date elementary school with six teachers, and 300 pupils enrolled, housed in a good standard building; a standard four-year high school with five teachers and 92 pupils housed in a modern attractive building; a trained visiting nurse and a well equipped hospital; arts craft work well developed, with 100 women doing weaving work in their homes, and many men en-gaged in handicraft work; health service for children and adults; vocational agriculture with a laboratory and a demonstration farm; vocational home making and industrial arts in the high school; and a broad program of community service for the entire community. I visited all the class rooms and found every teacher doing excellent teaching. They were all practicing modern methods of teaching. They were stimulating their pupils to think, which is the main characteristic of a good teacher. All the teachers, except one, are college graduates and this one exception is an elementary teacher who had had two years of college education. There are few school systems in the entire country that have as well trained teachers as the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School. Great care has been used in the selection of the teachers. In addition to having a college education they have the social welfare point of view. RECOMMENDATIONS 1. The Proposed Building Project. There is an urgent need for an additional teacher in the elementary school, and enlarged laboratories for the agriculture and home economics. I examined the architects' plan for an addition connecting the high school building and the Voorheis' building. I recommend that this addition be completed before the beginning of another school year. This addition will furnish rooms to meet the present urgent needs. 2. The Elementary School. I recommend that the entire control of the elementary school be turned over to Sevier County as soon as the county is financially able to support it. I have read the history of the Settlement School, and I am convinced this recommendation is in harmony with the spirit of the founders. As stated above, Sevier County is now paying in full the salaries of all the elementary teachers and a fair rental value for the use of the elementary school building. The fraternity should notify the county in advance the date this action, (Signed) EDWIN L. Heal Kansas State College Manhattan, Kansas if taken, will go into effect. In my judgmer can and should be done within the next ti three years. 3. The High School. The Fraternity shout( tinue to administer the high school with inc: emphasis on home projects in vocational a ture and vocational home making. Add cour handicrafts for both boys and girls. Perhaps courses should be weaving for girls, and carving, basketry, and furniture making for Sevier County should continue to give fin support to the limit of its ability. It seems rl able to believe the county will be able to over the entire support and control of the school within the next few years, especially proposed federal aid bill should become a la 4. Music Teacher. There is a need for a trained teacher of vocal and instrumental This teacher should supervise the music i elementary school as well as teach it in the school. He or she should be able to direct a school band and orchestra. 5. The School and Public Health Service. work is most efficiently carried on by Mrs. jorie Chalmers. It is an absolute necessity in mg a community in which to rear and e( happy and healthy children. It should be cont The county should continue to give financia port to this work. 6. The Arrow Craft Work. This work witf Ethel Snow as Director and Miss Winogene ding as supervisor of weaving has brought able comment on the Settlement School from all parts of the nation. This work shot continued in Gatlinburg as a permanent II project. During the past quarter of a centui spirit of II B cl, has been a dominant factor development of this community. The mountaii ple in the Little Pigeon valley and "up' the he in the Gatlinburg community hold II B I) in est esteem. 7. A New Arrow Craft Building. The frat should build an adequate and artistic buildit both the production and selling departments Arrow Craft work. The fraternity should de the production and selling of the Arrow products until it is favorably known in every munity in America. 8. Add Painting to the Arrow Craft A recommend that in the near future paintil added to the Arrow Craft arts. The work be introduced by putting art in the high si It is reasonable to think that II B 4) will b( to attract artists to spend their vacations is community and send art students to Gatlinbu study. This work, if introduced, should be i ally developed over a long-time program. I b by adding painting to the Arrow Craft arts, are already so well developed, Gatlinburg c made a nationally known art center. Gatti has advantages in location over other art cent have in mind such art centers as the one in I County, Indiana, and Taos, New Mexico. C count of this quarter of a century of experiei Gatlinburg, and its alumnle clubs in all pa the nation, II B 4, has a wonderful oppor to make Gatlinburg the art center of the nat II B II, continues to be the guiding hand development. </p>
      <pb ref="arr5510079_0004" seq="04" n="84-85  "/>
       <p>THE SEPTEMBER ARROW T OF MR. LUTCHE STA K ON THE tai PO SETTLEMENT SCHOOL with the wishes and request of esident of II B I visited Ten-., 4th, and 5th, and 6th, of March, Nashville where I secured all of )ossible with regard to the educaits of Tennessee, driving on to the for three days, and then to John-see, to interview Mr. Derthick. to you my appreciation for the !visiting Gatlinburg and familiarth the 1938 conditions there. I Tress my further appreciation to had the opportunity of spending days with Mr. and Mrs. Holton embers of the staff at Gatlinburg. tle to add to the reports of March :an, Kansas, but I believe I should Df Gatlinburg and the Settlement it. :o Gatlinburg was made some time I hired an automobile in Knoxght hours of strenuous work upon to school discovered that we were )ile that had been able to get into in two months. That should give the type of community in which Dcated, one totally dependent upon Settlement School for a viewpoint ngs of life putting education in Gatlinburg the other day in about :noxville on a fine road. I found a nity and some 1000 to 1500 intg the summer there are probably 00 to 3000 people there all of the community with high lines supplyght, a fine school, good hotels, and :ed, some good and some bad tour-lo relief rolls; in all, a picture of stained independence. I found the !ttlement School and the II B the same as in the beginning, with ar difference, and this please note: s II B (I) had been the leading and aence in the community, bringing an .enlightening viewpoint of the orld, and rearing their children to ly into the affairs of modern citi suit of this early work is all too homes and livelihood of these first ttion, time, and progress with good .d light, the gateway to a National ark have arrived, and II B cl) is to do the same job that they did lg, but conditions have changed. ad has increased until II B c1 has inevitable decision as to its con-'uture. No one can take from II B part she has played, but the future minent role for II B cl) unless the I B 4) is permitted or forced to be with the development of the comas an example: I was shocked and .11 be too when you think of the of the community being forced to ool facilities by threat of loss of ag. This is no position for H B to occupy. Whether II B cP wishes to continue to supervise and direct the elementary grammar school is a question for you to determine. The county is at present paying all of the grade teachers and paying a rent of $100.00 a month to the Settlement School for the use of the space. In fact, at the meeting held with Mr. Hodges, Mrs. Weaver, Mr. King, and Mr. and Mrs. Holton, it developed that II B (I) was receiving from Sevier County an educational apportionment of $36.00 per elementary student in average attendance the preceding year. It also developed that Pi Beta Phi Settlement High School was receiving from Sevier County an educational apportionment of $50.00 per high school student in actual attendance the preceding year. May I explain to you that the educational apportionments are made in the state of Tennessee to the counties and from the counties to the schools upon the basis of the average daily attendance the preceding year, and if it happened that the average daily attendance the preceding year was 100 pupils and in the succeeding year the average daily attendance was 300 students, there is nothing in Tennessee that anyone can do about it. It might be interesting for you to know that in the state of Texas the apportionment per scholastic anticipated attendance each year is about $22.50. All other funds for the conduct of school are supplied in Texas either by Independent School District taxation, County taxation, or city taxation. I join Mr. Holton in recommending to you that some near date you surrender the elementary work to the county. The four year high school idea is a development of II B t. in answer to the request from the community, and if II B cl) were to surrender this, I am sure this work would be allowed to drop by Sevier County. This high school work, I think, should be continued until the community has become so accustomed to it that it can make plans to take this work over. In order to keep in step with progress in the community and the demands of the educational authorities of the state, more room will have to be provided for the various school work above the elementary grades. I studied Mr. Derthick's report and personally made a room to room inspection, and his demands for repainting and for additional space are, I think, well justified. The sketch plans submitted by Mr. Barber, I think to be about the answer to Mr. Derthick's recommendations. In fact, Mr. Derthick told me that he would approve their continued affiliation for the next two or three years provided the enrollment did not increase too rap-idly, only upon the understanding that this was merely for the time being. I spent quite some time discussing with the authorities the advisability and legality of organizing an independent school district in the community so that the scholastic burden could be taken of B l and II B cl) allowed to devote her time, attention, ideals, and energy to the leadership in adult education and the arts, both commercial and otherwise. I discovered that there is no such thing as an independent school district other than in an incorporated community. I see little hope of this incorporation in Tennessee, because of the very prevalence of unincorporated towns much larger THE SEPTEMBER ARROW than Gatlinburg in that state. Mr. Cardwell, a very capable contractor, judging from the quality of his work which I inspected carefully, estimated that the sketch plans submitted by Mr. Barber, a man whose choice I concur in unquestionably, estimated that II B could do the needed building and repairs for about $5,000.00. Probably it could be done. Mrs. Holton said that they had about $2,000.00. There are many sources from which $3,000.00 to $5,000.00 could be secured to complete this building. II B owns three and eight tenths acres in almost the entrance to the Burg. It does not own the old mill which has been demolished and the property only goes to the river and up the hillside. .Considering the way people from Knoxville are building summer homes and swallow nests all over the sides of these mountains, I would recommend that now is the accepted time to sell this property. The Burg is built along the main road, up to the entrance of the park and can go no farther. There is quite a large meadow which runs along the side of the park, back to the road, going up to Mr. Voorheis' place. It is not large enough for a golf course, but probably will be used for one if someone does not cut it up into building lots. The building lots upon the mountain all around the school are being acquired, and all of the valleys are being thickly settled. Mr. Medlin and others are opening up the mountain sides across the river from the school and also down toward Sevierville. If the trend of homes drifts to the top of mountains away from the Burg, this three and eight tenths acres will rapidly decrease in value. At present I think it could be sold if cut up into building sites and a road put up there, which would be difficult, somewhere in the neighborhood of $5,000.00 net, but not cash. I attempted, through Mrs. Weaver, to secure a purchaser for this land while in Gatlin-burg. The highest offer we received was $3,000.00. The Future: II B et, cannot leave Gatlinburg. There is no other locality to which it can go. There is no other work in view of the competiti Junior League and other organizations in wl can hope to unite its membership, but the tions in Gatlinburg today are those of 1938 i other locality, with the exception that throul work of II B ' throughout all the years tl no relief roll in that community, but II B should be more in advance of the progress 4 community. II B 4 should be teaching music, hand, stenography, bookkeeping, and all tho cational subjects which I think will do the munity much more good. II B it, should I voting its attention and enthusiasm to adull cation, the development and sale of the hanc products of the mountains. Week-ends are the days in the community when hotels and t camps are crowded and people by the thot are driving by the door of the Arrow Craft which is securely locked. While at Gatlinl recommended that II B put show windows the road so that the wares could be displa3 the traveling public. May I close this report by expressing rr preciation to all with whom I came in cony wish to state further that I was highly plea the presence of Mr. Holton who is a very c educational director and who has himself personal surveys of educational institutions i; ing the University and school system of Mar I wish to state unequivocally that I am n implying nor expressing any particular or g criticism of any individual or any committ Council in the past or present conduct or making of the Pi .Beta Phi Settlement Schc Gatlinburg. But, the impression I gathered i the time has come again when the inevitab: cision has to be made for the policy under the work at Gatlinburg will be conducted 1938 onward. Respectfully submitted, (Signed) H. J. L. ST) ]SPORT OF THE DII ECTOR OF THE PI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL, 1937.38 It ETA PHI Community TO ENUMERATE the changes and improvements in Gatlinburg, in relation to the Settlement School would make a long list. I will mention only the most important. The Gatlinburg News, a weekly newspaper, a small and unusually interesting publication records the events of the "Burg." A moving picture theatre is a welcome addition. Our gymnasium has for five years been used as a moving picture theatre once a week in winter and twice a week in summer, and while this brought in quite a little revenue, we were not sorry when Squire Maples built a regular movie theatre for our gym is in constant demand for athletic and other school purposes as well as for social gatherings. An acre of wooded ground on the opposite bank of the Little Pigeon from the school grounds, is being beautified by the Garden Club and will be used as a little park--a place for visitors to rest and enjoy the beauty of the mountains. The various organizations functioning in connection with the school have continued to grow,the Parent-Teachers and the Weavers Guild year the school sponsored a Girl Scout Troop year the business men organized the Boy S Right of way has been promised for a highway, connecting the recently completed way through the Smoky Mountains National with the highway at Knoxville. A water company has secured a franchis may install a water and sewerage system i near future. Because our water supply was shown to I pure last summer, in September we instal chlorinator and made a new septic tank ft teachers' cottage. Old Timer's Day was celebrated at the on June 4 with the usual good time. There more than the usual number of entries in the tests, even the one for being the homeliest Experts came from miles around to compel prizes in cornshucking, shingle splitting, ho, ing, and a host of other accomplishments. year this occasion is pronounced the best w, had. At the Smoky Mountain Wild Flower Fe </p>
      <pb ref="arr5510079_0005" seq="05" n="86-87  "/>
       <p>T E SEPTEMBER ARROW )urg won first prize for its float which reprea giant azalea in front of which sat three of !ttiest mountain girls, students of the Settle-;chool. high school enrolment was 92 for 1938, grade school was 285 making a total en-t of 377. The plan of having principals for igh and elementary schools made for effiand better attendance during the past year. :ng. was in charge of the high school, teach-;wry and science. Mr. Fern Price, formerly el of Sevierville elementary school, took of our grade school, teaching the seventh ;.hth grades. rder that students living in the vicinity of Forge might attend school, Mr. Fleming, ves there, drove our school truck, bringing !en high school students with him every day. these students were seen long after school waiting patiently for the truck which had t arrived from farm duty or other errands, them home. )re we had fairly launched on our four year chool program, we had outgrown the build-Id by the second year, were advised by the Sigh School Supervisor that we should have oom for our home economics department and laboratories. The Smith-Hughes vocational vent also recommended a class room of larger ;ions than we could offer. With the promise would enlarge our quarters by another we continued as we were through the past 3etween faculty and students there was fine ation. ang the new projects undertaken in the elery school, was a safety patrol, organized with h and eighth grade boys as patrolmen. They 1 the smaller children to cross the often ed highway, and as a result, no students were this year. ,rogram of physical education was started in volleyball, basketball, football, and socker played, and the large playground was kept During two weeks of January both elemen-Id high school were assisted in play and folk by Richard Seaman, director of supervised junior and Senior plays of the high school :oached by Stella Huff Cox. All of the grade children were included in the Christmas iinment as usual and were directed by the Italy school staff. enty-one graduated from the eighth grade 11 intend to enter high school next year. !en graduated from high school this spring )s and gowns, with class day in the gym-a and baccalaureate sermon in the little Bap-lurch. Some of these students have arranged :er college next fall, where they will have [me work with which to pay their way. h school buildings were. painted a year ago :reens were made for the grade school. Home Economics Home Economics department, perhaps the practical in the school, was under the dime-)f Rosalie Ellis, Kansas B, of Manhattan, .s. primary purpose of this department is to ve the living conditions in the present homes Einburg as well as the future ones. For this adult classes in sewing, cooking, home imrnent and beautification, were held alongwith the regular school classes. Eighteen freshmen and ten sophomore girls were enrolled in the home management classes this year. The practical rather than the theoretical side of the work was stressed. Frequent trips were made to better homes for demonstration work and each girl carried out one or more projects in home improvement. Two weeks were devoted to teaching the agriculture boys some elementary household duties. And while this was going on, the girls were learning chicken raising and gardening from Mr. Coe. The Home Economics club, a social organization, gave several interesting parties during the year, including a dinner for the staff, which showed thorough training, good taste, and originality. The Home Economics laboratory was painted a soft cream color, new curtains were made, and a new stove and kitchen cabinet were added to the cooking equipment. We have every reason to believe that with a larger Home Management laboratory, we will be granted Vocational Home Economics by the State Department. Agriculture William Coe, Manager. Ambers Ogle, Stock Assistant. Arlie Watson, Gardener. For the first time since 1933, the State Department placed our school on the Smith-Hughes Vovational Agriculture list, and we secured Mr. William Coe from the University of Tennessee as teacher. To make agriculture an interesting study to boys who come from farms situated in a more or less mountainous section, is not an easy task. They were encouraged to practice the improved methods of farming learned in class at their homes. Prizes are a great incentive, and when Sears-Roebuck Company offered a pure bred prize pig to winners in an essay contest, our Future Farmers of America competed and won four pigs. They exhibited shop work at the County Fair, judged cattle at the University of Tennessee, and will be one of the first with hybrid corn to be grown on Tennessee farms. Smith-Hughes stresses the importance of outside classes not only for boys who have dropped out of school, but for the adult who wants to learn new methods. Mr. Coe said, "This part of my work, I consider one of my best accomplishments of the year, for the farmers are practicing the improved methods which were discussed in the evening meetings." These meetings were held in little country school houses, Laurel Grove and the Glades. On many cold winter nights, when it seemed to me that few would leave the home fireplace, Mr. Coe reported that a good number had turned out to discuss soil conservation or feeding problems. A class also for boys out of school was held in a C.C.C. camp four miles away. Mr. Huff, our neighbor, has put up a new fence on our east boundary, and to keep our little pigs at home, we have had to add an electric fence wire to the rest of the enclosure. Last fall we showed some dairy heifers at the County Fair, won grand championship with one and prizes with each of the others. We more than paid expenses and at the same time won some advertisement for the school. Prizes were taken also on chickens and vegetables. THE SEPTEMBER ARROW When money was needed for outside activities, as equipment for baseball, entertainments were given. Arrow Craft Mrs. Ethel Snow, Manager. Assistants, Veatrice Parton, Edna McCarter, Ava Clabo. Mrs. Ethel Snow, manager of Arrow Craft, feels that the handicraft has moved more smoothly and profitably during the past year than ever before. This was partly due to a better understanding among the clubs at the time for ordering. Orders came in early and were filled in most cases before the re-orders arrived, and a Christmas rush was avoided. A new and able assistant was added to the force Edna McCarter, and later, Ava Clabo, both graduates of the school. By an arrangement of exchanging hours between employees, both Arrow Craft Shop and its branch shop in the Mountain View Hotel were kept open full time. Two large front show windows with small panes have been added to the Arrow Craft Shop and the front room has been made a basket room. In the Hotel shop, Mrs. Duffield still finds time in the winter months to weave her afghans. The Southern Highland Handicrafters Guild, through AllenStand Shop in Asheville, has been the outlet for quite a bit of our goods. Our membership in Southern Highlanders Inc., has now convinced us it is going to be worthwhile and through it some desirable contacts have been made. Just a little thing like a fly swatter can be good advertising when featured in Harper's Bazaar, through the Highlanders. Our shares of stock have been increased to the amount of $115. Sales have been very good through the New York shop and Norris Dam. Some of our best articles were on exhibition at the Rural Arts Exhibits in Washington, last November; also at the Rural Arts Exhibit at Jordan Marsh Store in Boston. At the Knoxville Fair, Arrow Craft took prizes. Three of us attended all meetings of the Handicrafters. At the spring meeting Mrs. Snow's duties as secretary of Southern Highland Handicraft Child terminated. Mr. Allen Eaton's new book on Handicrafts of the Southern Highlands, sponsored by the Russell Sage Foundation, has given us some publicity. Weaving Gene Redding, Supervisor. aura Owenby, Assistant. For thirteen years weaving has been taught in our school, either in the eighth grade or the high school, but we are now a step nearer to vocational weaving, for Gene Redding, supervisor, has met the requirements for Tennessee high school vocational work, by taking state examinations. In the stock room are to be found many articles which Miss Redding has designed for the coming year. Weavers have been encouraged to do some original designing and the results have been excel-lent. As the business grew, it became necessary to plan a schedule for the entire year. "We are proud ,of the fact," says Gene, "that so far, there is not a single family in Gatlinburg on relief. We are confident that the weaving donein the community is responsible for i Visitors to Gatlinburg who are gi Mountain View Hotel are much inter moving picture of the process of we color. The picture was taken in our we ing by Jerry McCutcheon, clerk at the The Weaver's Guild had many inter tainments during the winter, and lectt subjects. than their own occupation ciated. Out of these meetings grew Club with its flower shows and instru dening. The Jennie Nicol Memorial Health tinues to be the center of Gatlinburi and the center of importance to the o is sixteen years old and the routine ( varied a little with the growth of tht Marjorie Chalmers has faithfully ca work for two years, knows most of folks and their troubles, and is motheJ many. We have had the cooperation of Health Officers with serums and lit aid in well baby clinics, and tuberculc phases of the work are important. F side nursing, prenatal care, infant w, inspection, preventive measures, ad` struction. Regular office hours are kel Once a month the dentist's chair and Dr. Mayberry from Knoxville the tooth troubles that are sure to b him. The village doctor cooperates i Marjorie says that the problems of pre ures are lessening. Many children an( for their inoculations as soon as t Health talks and lessons in first aid school and to Parent-Teachers and ''V'O A. small garage has been placed hospital, for the convenience of the n Our school children have won t cup again this year the annual Blue to larger schools from the County Bo; Once more will make three success and the cup will be ours to keep. Dormitories Mrs. Smith, Housekeeper. Assistants, Bess McCarter, Bell L Laundress, Mertie Ogle. In September of 1937, Mrs. Smiti ger, and mother of one of our seni charge of the dormitories and of the During the summer, Ben and Josef carried on the work until Mrs. Smi It seemed to me that the dormito '37-38 were a more studious group an closely at the school than in forme they took an active interest in the y meetings at the church. Both Mr. King and Mr. Coe wi roomed at the boys' dormitory. 5 promised to take ten boys, we were up a room in the high school buil formerly been used as a small offic with two teachers and Mrs. Smith girls' dormitory. A few students remained after school to help with housecleaning working out their room and board. Health Center </p>
      <pb ref="arr5510079_0006" seq="06" n="88-89  "/>
       <p>THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 0,gce 1, farm, and handicraft business reflected in the office where the been done during the past year n, Missouri r. A very great help house, has been her patience in accounts of so many departments. came, during the holidays, genet-axes from Clubs, that have made ppy; books for the library, checks from Pi Phis with a note, "Use this where it is needed the most," and new furnishings for the Teachers' Cottage and director's bed room, and so many things that made us happy. Let me here ex-press our thanks and deep appreciation for the support by all members, officers, Committee, and Council who stand behind us so loyally. Respectfully submitted, EUNICE S. WEAVER TA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL REPORT ON IT OF TEASURE i''S ACCOUNTS YEA ENDED JUNE 30, 1938 1 July 28, 1938 cCleverty, Treasurer ement School Ion .-LEVERTY: e an examination of the accounting reasurer of the cl) B. II Settlement !ar ended June 30, 1938. We have of the report of Homer K. Jones Public Accountants of Knoxville, ing the operations of the Settle-I Arrow Craft Shop for the year are reflected by the accounts that ttlinburg. We have given effect contained in this report in the s, and have prepared therefrom and e financial statements as enumereding page. FIXED ASSETS $68,195.77 are stated at cost less re stock is included at inventory ed from Gatlinburg. A tract of Lnd was sold for a cash considera-)0, which amount is included in nd in the balance sheet together t of $2,515.34 allocated from the s for the construction of a laboramecting the . High School and the ng. The amount of $170.00 had n the start of construction at the ace sheet. NET WORTH General Surplus, Exhibit 2 amounted to $110,734.53 on June 30, 1938. Total Net Worth, including the Reserve for Endowment Fund and the unexpended balance of Cook Book Fund, amounted to $152,671.20. INCOME AND EXPENSE STATEMENT This Exhibit shows the operating accounts of the Settlement School combined with those of the Treasurer, resulting in a net income of $5,639.26 which is carried to Surplus Exhibit 2. ARROW CRAFT SHOP The accounts of the Arrow Craft Shop show a net income of $8,938.73 as stated in Exhibit 4. More detailed analysis of the operations is given in the report of Homer K. Jones and Co. No charge is made in this statement for depreciation on buildings and equipment used by the Arrow Craft Shop, these charges being carried on the Treasurer's books. CONTRIBUTIONS Contributions from Alum= Clubs and Active Chapters are summarized in Exhibit 8, with accompanying detailed lists. In our opinion the accompanying balance sheet and related statements fairly present the financial position of the (D B Settlement School at June 30, 1938, and the results of its operations for the year. BALANCE SHEET June 30, 1238 Ass: Ts Respectfully submitted, R. C. MOUNSEY, Certified Public Accountant and at Banks $ 16,470.59 ;Building Fund) 5,513.34 $ 21,985.93 tble Arrow Craft Shop 4,666.79 ............... . . . .................................................. $ 911.27 Shop 16,458.19 'lies 5,233.37 22,602.83 nt Assets $ 49,255.55 ent Fund Exhibit 5 $ 32,262.01 33,832.78 Closed Bank 1,570.77 , Equipment and Live Stock Exhibit 6 68,195.77 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW Deferred Charges: Unexpired Insurance Exhibit 7 Total Assets Liabilities: Note Payable to Bank ".". "."."."."." ".".".".".".".."." $ Net Worth: Reserve for School Endowment Fund 41,232.61 Cook Book Fund General Surplus Exhibit ~'~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 110,7704.06 34.53 152,( Total $152,1 * Amount due School Endowment Fund: Reserve , $ 41,232.61 Fund Principal (Exhibit 5) 32,135.75 Due Fund ANALYSIS OF GENERAL SURPLUS June 30, 1938 Balance June 30, 1937, per Audit Report *10o Add Net Income for the Year Ended June 30, 1938' School Treasurer Exhibit 3 z,t Arrow Craft Sho Exhibit 4 8,! Deduct: Contribution Illinois Beta to Endowment Fund $ 1,806.25 Three-fourths Active Chapter Contrib=tions, to Endowment Fund 1.598.99 ___ School Treasurer's Income: Books Books T $ 2,12$ Contributions-To Endowment Fund, Illinois Beta Alumn 1,806.25 1,1 Bequests 1,015.34 1,1 Interest Earned Magazine Agency 2,44594.09 2,, Cook Book Funcl 1,018.50 ( Smith-Hughes Agriculture $ 47.58 Smith-Hughes Home Economics 117.23 Hospital Farm (Including products for ~~~"~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 2,933.84 z Inventory Increase, ~ Livestock 736u0 Living 3,202.46 3, Picture Show 516.54 Rent Buildings Rent Photo Shop .~~~^~.~~~~~~~~~.~~~_ ~~~~~ ~.~~~ 800.00 Tot, Income $ 7,772.15 $21,76 5.06 m29,' Expenses: Administration ." '.."...' ' $ 41.25 $ 76.88 $ Auto Expense ".' "."..".' 100.69 Farm Expense 1,931.53 o~ Fuel 667.59 234.01 Furnishings Health Unit 158.58 n 314.44 z Insurance 63.62 236.72 Lights Living " 643.75 2,037.82 3,050.00 5,1 Miscellaneous ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 227.51 y 165.70 Office ".".."."."." "....' 38.19 225.00 Postage and Hauling Improvements 97.96 Publicity Repairs and Upkeep ~~~~~~~~~~~_~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ o~~~ Renlacements and " 453,79 ~o3,115004.0605 ~' Salaries 3,115004.0605 540. School Exnense School Salaries .. . ' 800.00 550.00 ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~.~~~~~~~~ 138.42 '772.24 Telephone and Smith-Hughes Telegraph ` 148.71 Travel -"."."."."._".". " .". " . . " . " .".".' 376.55 Truck Expense 20.52 $14,641.43 $23. B^la,ce Being Net Income, to Exhibit 2 ".".". $ ~ LIABILITIES AND NET WORTH INCOME AND EXPENSE STATEMENT Year Ended June 30, 1938 Total Expenses ".'$ 9,256.52 </p>
      <pb ref="arr5510079_0007" seq="07" n="90-91  "/>
       <p>THE SEPTEMBER ARROW ARROW CRAFT SHOP, INCOME AND EXPENSE STATEMENT Year Ended June 30, 1938 Gross Profit ". $ 343.32 g 10,073.67 Stools, etc. 146.47 .~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 659.25 a meous Items nd Tufted Articles " 1,sO2.89 tads $16,431.28 ssions Hotel Sales $ 632.50 Hotel Shop ~~~ 24Drtation, Cost (Net) Hotel 0.00 223.01 ial Expense ial Salaries ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 5,151.22 i i~ ~X~~~~~~'~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 40.00 214.60 63.80 "ce 356.51 160.32 Expense 55.16 94.88 =~. Upkeep ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 94.71 ements and Improvements 207.54 ~~~~.~~~~~~.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 321.79 24.00 Tnse 104.80 pen= 55.49 Dtal Expenses 8,052.46 )m Operations $ 8,378.82 )f Tennessee, Weaving $ 500.00 t n=' Savings Account 77.11 577.11 Sales Discount 17.20 559.91 "me'* .to Exhibit ~ 1 $ 8,938.73 abject to depreciation and insurance charges on School Treasurer's books. PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL FIXED ASSETS June 30, 1938 tate 4,900.00 ~ and ~~ . . .~ -~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~. $ 4,900.00 _- uild.~~ and Equipment 78,844.12 ?^~.~.Reserve ' 17,384.35 s and Equipment, Net Inventory ' 1,836.00 CONTRIBUTIONS, YEAR ENDED JUNE 30, Alumna Active Clubs Chapters 4 769.49 $ 135.00 .......................... 1,944.00 176.12 ......................... 331.00 131.00 ........................ 682.39 108.00 1,285.60 ......................... 197.50 110.00 .......................... 1,784.15 92.00 .......................... .585.00 '''''''''''''''''''''''''' 887.38 239.37 '~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 3977.24 20.18 ~~6 .......................... 1,632.47 *30.00 ---- ' THE SEPTEMBER ARROW ALUMME CLUBS Albany, New York ^ $ Boston, Mass Buffalo, N.Y Burlington, Vt Halifax, N.S Hartford, Conn London, Ontario Montreal, Quebec New Haven, Conn New York City Northern New Jersey Portland, Maine Rochester, N.Y Syracuse, N.Y Toronto, ~$ 769.49 Alpha Province 5.00 65.00 50.00 Massachusetts A Nova Scotia A 175.00 Ontario A ''''''''''''''''''''''''' 7.50 Ontario B i .00 New York A 3.00 New York r 184.27 New York ~ 75.00 13.00 50.00 50.00 25.00 65.12 ACTIVE CHAPTERS Beta Province Akron, Ohio $ Athens, Ohio Bradford, Pa Central Pennsylvania Charleston, '''''''''''''''''''''''' Cincinnati, Ohio Cleveland, O ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ Dayton, Ohio 30.00 Harrisburg-Ca.rlisle, Pa 100.00 Mahoning Valley 30.00 Morgantown, W.Va 5.00 Ohio Valley Club 10.00 Philadelphia, Pa 350.00 Pittsburgh, Pa 26.00 Southern New jersey South Hills, Pa. '~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 40.00 Toledo, Ohio .' 100o0 Delta Province Baltimore, Md. Chapel Hill, N.C. .~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~. 80.00 Maryland A 30.00 Dist. of Columbia ~.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ Columbia., S.C. ~~~~~~~~~~~~.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 402.00 Virginia A .00 Virginia r ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~.... Richmond, Va. Washington, D.C 179 0 'Nortu Carolina A North Carolina B $ 331.00 South Carolina Delta Province Ann Arbor, Mich $ Bloomfield Hills, Mich. ".".".".r".".' Bloomington, Ind Detroit, Mich Flint, Mich Ft. Wayne, Ind Gary, Grand Rapids, Mich 7.94 Hillsdale, Iqich 2.50 Indianapolis, Ind 220.95 Lafayette, Ind 50.00 Southwest Indiana Southwest Michigan ~ ~~ ~ ~~~ ~ ~~ ~ ~ ~~ ~ ~~ ~~ ~ ~ 715 ~0 Terre Haute, Ind ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " . ' ' ' ' ' ' . ' ' ' 4.00 $ 682.39 5.00 Ohio A 8.00 Ohio Beta ~~' ~ '~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ mxo W Ohio A est V~ 900.00 ........ 60.00 Michigan A 75.00 Michigan B 25.00 Indiana A 150.00 Indiana B 15.00 Indiana r 25.00 Indiana ^ 25.00 Chattanooga, Tenn. ..".".".'."."."."m Columbia, Mo Gatlinburg, Tenn Kansas City, Mo Louisville, Ky Memphis, Tenn Nashville, Tenn St. Joseph, Mo Epsilon Province 60.00 Missouri A 55.60 Missouri B 10.00 Missouri r 500.00 K 50.00 T~~~~~ ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 5.00 5.00 5.00 590.00 5.00 </p>
      <pb ref="arr5510079_0008" seq="08" n="92-93  "/>
       <p>THE SEPTEMBER ARROW Zeta Province 100.00 Alabama A $ 30.00 2.00 Florida A 5.00 Florida B 50.00 30.00 Florida r 30.00 5.00 $ 110.00 36.50 10.00 197.50 Eta Province $ 7.00 20.00 13.00 7bana, 111 100.00 Less Women 75.00 h Club 300.00 t Club 200.00 Suburban 75.00 50.00 ............................... 20.00 55.00 L 50.00 [11 1.00 3.00 ;, 40.00 his 225.00 1 10.00 :dub 400.00 er Forest 55.00 45.15 10.00 11 30.00 $1,784.15 ............................... Ala h, Fla . Fla ........................... O ............................ Fla Fla 5.00 4.00 ............................... Wisconsin A $ 50.00 Wisconsin B 11.00 Illinois A ................................. 1.00 Illinois B................................ 35.00 Illinois E ................................ 25.00 Illinois Z .................................. 100.00 Illinois H 20.00 $ 242.00 $ Ewa Iowa Iowa Iowa n N.D wa ............................ Minn Iowa In owa anitoba Theta Province 20.00 Manitoba A $ 10.00 40.00 North Dakota A 2.00 50.00 Minnesota A 25.00 5.00 Iowa A 5.00 100.00 Iowa B 10.00 50.00 Iowa r 15.00 5.00 Iowa Z 25.00 5.00 50.00 92.00 100.00 25.00 100.00 20.00 15.00 $ 585.00 Iota Province $ 40.00 50.00 yo 25.00 ngs, Colo 25.00 400.00 D 20.00 Ln 29.18 25.00 :an 125.00 93.20 7, Colo 5.00 . .............................. . .............................. 40.00 1 10.00 D $ 887.38 Kappa Province Colorado A $ 100.00 Colorado B 40.00 Kansas A 30.00 Kansas B 41.19 Nebraska B 5.00 South Dakota A 3.18 Wyoming A 20.00 239.37 la $ 14.68 100.00 La ti, Tex 24.57 200.00 Ark 10.00 rk 25.00 'ex c 200.00 Axk 15.00 Oklahoma A $ 50.00 Oklahoma B 25.00 Arkansas A 13.50 Texas A 50.00 Texas B 25.00 Louisiana A 50.00 Louisiana B 10.00 223.50 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW Muskogee, Okla 10.00 New Orleans, La.. . 50.00 Norman, Okla 17.50 Oklahoma City Okla 50.00 Okmulgee, Okla 15.00 Sabine District, Tex 86.39 San Antonio, Tex 50.00 Shreveport, La 20.00 Stillwater, Okla 10.00 Tulsa, Okla 50.00 Tyler, Tex Texarkana, Tex 28.10 Waco, Tex 1.00 $ 977.24 Lambda Province Boise, Idaho $ 40.00 Bozeman, Mont 1.00 Calgary, Alta 3.00 Corvallis, Ore 2.50 Edmonton, Alta 5.23 Eugene, Ore 5.00 Olympia, Wash 1.00 Portland Ore 75.00 Salem, Ore 5.00 Seattle, Wash 82.45 Spokane, Wash 25.00 Tacoma, Wash 50.00 Wenatchee, Wash 20.00 Yakiqa, Wash 5.00 $ 320.18 Mu Province Albuquerque, N.M $ 20.00 California A Berkeley, Calif 150.00 California B El Paso, Tex 5.00 California r Fresno, Calif 25.00 California A Glendale, Calif 50.00 Nevada A Hawaii, T. H 50.00 Arizona A Long Beach, Calif 24.79 Utah A Los Angeles, Calif 916.40 Nevada Alumnae 5.00 Ogden, Utah 5.00 Palo Alto, Calif 5.00 Pasadena, Calif 100.00 Phoenix, Ariz 21.28 Sacramento, Calif 5.00 San Diego, Calif 100.00 San Francisco, Calif 50.00 San Jose, Calif 30.00 Santa Barbara and Ventura, Calif 5.00 Santa Monica, Calif 10.00 Tucson, Ariz 5.00 Utah Alumni 50.00 $1,632.47 Alberta A Montana A Idaho A Washington A Washington B Oregon A Oregon B INCIPAL'S ANNUAL REPO T, 1938 I \ it P T HE twenty-sixth session of the (1) B II Settlement School opened on August 11, 1938, with the largest first days attendance on record. The teaching staff was composed of William King, principal, history and science; Ben C. Fleming, mathematics and French; Stella Huff Cox, English and history; William Coe, vocational agriculture; Rosalie Ellis, home-economics; C. Pern Price, elementary principal, seventh and eighth grades; Mary Durkee, fourth and sixth grades; Eleanor Pack, fifth grade; Pauline Toney, third grade; Mary Glen Walker, second grade; and Eleanor Brabson, first grade. Four of these teachers were new to our staff and three were beginning teachers. Mr. Price, a ,graduate of the University of Tennessee, had been for several years principal of the Sevierville ele-mentary school, and had taught for ten Coe is a graduate of the University of College of Agriculture. Miss Pack is a versity of Tennessee graduate, while came to us from Kansas State College specialized in home-economics. From the first day it was evident th rollment was going to exceed that of an year. Mr. Fleming drove the school t Pigeon Forge and brought seventeen h pupils from that section. In order to get Federal aid on vocational agriculture it sary that we have more boys who live and who intend to farm as a vocation. get the required number of farm boy operated the school truck as a school average daily attendance did not drop ^ </p>
      <pb ref="arr5510079_0009" seq="09" n="94-95  "/>
       <p>THE SEPTEMBER ARROW the as much as in former years, because people living here now are permanent )llment and promotions by grades were: ,EMENTARY SCHOOL ENROLLMENT Boys Girls Total .............. 33 45 78 ................ 27 14 41 ................ 18 15 33 ................ 13 10 23 ................ 21 24 45 ................ 8 16 24 ................ 10 8 18 ................ 9 14 23 ................ 139 146 285 HIGH SCHOOL ENROLLMENT Boys Girls Total ................ 20 19 39 ................ 10 13 23 ................ 4 11 15 ................ 4 11 15 ................ 38 54 92 rollment 177 200 377 ROMOTIONS ELEMENTARY SCHOOL Boys Girls Total ............... 23 33 56 ................ 22 11 33 ................ 17 12 29 ................. 12 7 19 ................ 18 20 38 ........... .. 8 14 22 ................ 10 6 16 ................ 8 13 21 , 118 116 234 PROMOTIONS HIGH SCHOOL ................ 17 18 35 . ................ 8 8 16 ................. 3 10 13 ................. 4 10 14 ................. 32 46 78 ornntions 150 162 312 ally attendance .. 312 griculture-Home-Economics curriculum in the high school as outlined by the State Department of High Schools. The study offered this year consisted of four tiglish, four of mathematics, three in ice, three in agriculture, two in home-two in science (chemistry and general rid one in French. Vocational agriculture ed to the curriculum this year after one ion-vocational agriculture. Now high s have the opportunity of taking four lriculture if they so desire. Ts' basketball team was not as strong as s all the last year's team was graduated. of the sixteen games played, our boys nd lost several others by close scores. ng kept the team spirit up splendidly seemed as eager to play as when they ing every game. Girls' basketball as a sport was discontinued this year. comprehensive physical education pro gram was undertaken this year in both the elementary and high schools. Mr. Price and Miss Torley worked with the grade pupils, and all the teachers took more interest in playground super-vision and organized play. Volleyball, baseball, and softball were played in season. Several community parties were held in the school gymnasium. These parties were well at-tended and thoroughly enjoyed by young and old alike. The Hallowe'en carnival was quite a spooky affair; it also netted thirty-five dollars which was used to buy books for the grade school library. Mr. Seaman spent two weeks with us after Christmas teaching folk games. He concentrated his efforts on teaching a number of the pupils these games thoroughly with the idea of developing some local leaders. The Junior class presented the play "Mama's Baby Boy," before the Christmas holidays, and the Senior class gave the play "My Mother-in-law," as their commencement play. These plays were coached by Mrs. Cox and were very well done. The Christmas entertainments as usual included every child in the grade school. Over one hundred new books were added to the high school library this year. The exterior of both the elementary and high school buildings was painted last summer, also the north rooms of the high school building. The home-economics room was painted Christmas. This interior painting has greatly improved the lighting in the high school. New tables and chairs were bought for the second grade room. The high school supervisor on his annual visit insisted that our home-economics and science lab-oratories were too small, and that we needed more home-economics equipment, especially cooking equipment. A new oil range and a new kitchen cabinet were purchased to meet our needs for this year. He accepted these additions as satisfactory for this year, but insisted that more space be found for these two departments for next year. The super-visor of vocational agriculture also wants More space for the agriculture department. Fourteen high school seniors and twenty-one eighth grade pupils received diplomas this year. Rev. C. V. Bellamy preached the baccalaureate sermon, and Dr. A. E. Cate, Dean of Carson-Newman College, delivered the commencement ad-dress. The rapidly growing community, the increasing interest in education, and our expanded program to meet this increased need has taxed to capacity our physical plant as well as the energies and resources of our teaching staff. The fine spirit of cooperation among the staff and the friendly interest of the parents has made possible a very successful school year. Respectfully submitted, WILLIAM KING LEPO T OF THE VOCATIONAL AG TEACHER, 1937.38 ICULTU All Day Classes ar's enrollment in this group reached the !r of thirty-four High School boys. Two re taught to the High School boys in Agriculture. One of these classes was made up entirely of Freshman boys while the other class was made up of Sophomores and Seniors. It is expected that within the near future, as more farm boys enter our High School, we will be able to offer three classes in Vocational Agriculture. THE SEPTEMBER ARROW These boys are expected to carry on a Supervised farming program this spring and summer on the Home Farm. We believe that this is really where the student does. a great deal of his learning and the teacher may get a chance to see the students put into practice some of the things he has learned in the class room. This year we had twenty-six boys who completed the entire school year out of thirty-four who entered. These twenty-six boys are at present carrying on very complete supervised Farming Programs consisting of the following: Number Name of Enterprise Enrolled Scope Feeder Hogs 8 59 Brood Sows 4 7 Gilts 6 9 Boars 2 2 Dairy Cows 2 6 Dairy Calves 2 5 Feeder Steers 1 14 Poultry 1 97 A-Laying Hens B--Baby Chicks for Broilers 12 2,797 C-Baby Chicks for Laying Hens 1 5,000 Irish Potatoes 8 3% Acres Field Corn 11 21 " Hybrid Corn 4 1 Apple Trees 1 10 Trees Home Garden 4 2 Acres Beans 1 1 " Tobacco 1 Y8 Lespedeza 2 18 Permanent Pastures 9 14 Evening School Classes Two night schools were conducted in two Rural Communities for those men who are established in the business of farming. One of these Evening Schools was held in the Laurel Grove Community which is located 17 miles from the School. The other Evening School class was held at the Glades Community School which is located 5 miles from here. I met each one of these Evening Schools one night each week beginning November 11 and continuing through February 4. The subject of the course was based on Soil Conservation and Feeding Problems. This part of my out-of-school work I consider my most successful. In these groups lots of interest was shown and plans were made for putting into practice some of the improved practices they had learned and discussed in these meetings. Each of these communities has expressed a desire to have these classes next winter after the crops are harvested. Day Unit Classes The teaching of Vocational Agriculture to the eighth grade boy has been practically eliminated by the State Department. They believe that this boy will later enter High School and will take Vocational Agriculture or he will quit School, and in that case he will become a member of the part time class which is offered for out of school farm youth. Part Time Classes This year one class is being taught to this group and that is at the C.C.C. Camp which is located five miles away from the school. The class was started April 13 and is to continue through June 1. The enrollment in this class has been from 12 to 16 boys who formerly lived on the farm. The F.F.A. Chapter The Future Farmer Chapter has j what we think of as being a very st We have taken part in the followir tivities of the School. 1. Essay writing contest in whic future farmer boys won four pigs and one purebred boar. 2. Showing Cattle at County Pal. 3. Exhibiting Farm Products, Work, and Poultry at Count 4. Sponsored F.F.A. and Home cials. 5. Sponsored Future Farmer Pr District meeting at the Univ( 6. Livestock and Dairy Cattle , test at the University of Tenr 7. Public Speaking Contest at in which our representative place in our District, consis Chapters. F.F.A. Baseball and Basketbai Presentation of the F.F.T. cup around High School Girl. 10. Plans are in progress for tl of Hybrid Seed Corn by four boys. This seed was furnishes versity Agronomy Departme, two year project in which i furnish hybrid seed for the T( ers if it proves superior in yi( variety, Neal's Paymaster. 11. Three boys and myself atten Convention of Future Farme. of the Tennessee Association ville on April 29 and 30. The School Farm The School Farm serves as an c for the Agriculture student to pra the improvable practices he has 1( classroom. This year we had ten dormitory. Eight of these boys took A two of them selected French or some rather than Agriculture. Those boys Agriculture were given work on the other two boys were given Janit of these boys was given charge of which they liked such as dairy cows hogs, poultry (broilers, pullets ant etc.). This seemed to work very sL I feel more work was accomplished time providing the boy with. good t enterprise. Last fall we showed som heifers at the County Fair at Sevier Grand Champion in jerseys with on( placed with each of the other anim than paid our expenses and at the s some advertising. We also won se( white leghorn pullets and third r potatoes. This year we have expanded our prises somewhat in that we have tri broilers to meet part of the Gatlin. This we have done very successfully with 1200 Baby Chicks. This year bated our own. eggs to produce o pullets for the laying flock. The hogs have been a profitable that our brood sows have farrowe 8. 9. </p>
      <pb ref="arr5510079_0010" seq="10" n="96-97  "/>
       <p>THE SEPTEMBER ARROW A 0 \AI n /I\ PROVINCE NO. OF .NO. OF CASH DECEIVED GODS 'CLUI5S CLUt3S IN PROVINCE SELL INC ALPHA. 16 12. $ 1,931 52 5ETP. 1E5 10 1,49 91. GAMMA 6 3+ 2.1 90 DELTA 16 14 1,242 45 it EPSILON 10 1 1 8 8 4 ZETF 11 .5 1 8 1 11 ETA Zl 13' 1,6 15.10 THETA 14 10 1,735 2.4z 1 0TP\ 15 6 1,034.17 KAPPA 2.3 13 2,813 09 I LAI-15DA. It 12. 1 , 1 51 M U . 2.1 I L 92 2 9 ? T refreSerd buS,neSS 0T ClUbS w~u ThqArro-cralt duly t .1931 May 5 1935 WEAVING DEPARTMENT s\, EPO T JULY 1937.JUNE 1938 ANOTHER year of growth is behind the weaving department. Both the cash sales in the two Gatlinburg shops and the Alumni Club sales have shown an increase and that means that the weaving department has had to keep pace by increasing production. This we have done to the best of our ability. Our 92 weavers are a conscientious group of women who do all in their power to fulfill the duties of weaving the articles we assign to them. This year we have had a few less weavers than the year before which has made it possible to give each weaver more work, especially in the group that needed it the most. The few new weavers that we have taken on as vacancies and extra production have warranted, have been thoroughly investigated to see if they have ability and need the weaving to provide an added income in the home. With so much tourist money coming into the town, we are inclined to forget that many of the mountain people, especially in the out-lying districts, still need help. By having the opportunity provided to earn this necessary income, both their need and their native pride are taken into consideration. We are proud of the fact that so far there is no family in Gatlinburg on relief. We are confident that the weaving done in the community is responsible for this record. This winter I took the required examination and am now qualified to teach weaving for credit under the Tennessee Vocational High School re-quirements. These call for a class ( and three continuous clock hours da are given for the course. I am still carrying on the course as prescribe help. As it is now it takes all ou on the weaving for the Arrow Cra] The weaving meetings have c an important source of enjoyment We celebrated Aunt Lizzie's 80th 1 Christmas at another, the April me, day" and all the babies born to the the year were brought in for displa a talk on hens at one meeting; as anything of interest that comes o for programs. The weavers recei. on weaving meeting day. They a from attending unless a reasonable vided. The Gatlinburg Garden Club outgrowth of the weaving meetiz most successfull year. One of our a elected president for her second to flower show was held in October building where the monthly meeting A clean-up campaign for the town and had good results. Mr. Huff ga: mission to clean up an island in belongs to him. The result is lr enjoyment of all. By centering the women's activi </p>
      <pb ref="arr5510079_0011" seq="11" n="98-99  "/>
       <p>98 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW possible in the weaving building where our weavers already feel so much at home, we are promoting a fine spirit of cooperation and tolerance between the mountain women and the women who have moved in from the outside. This, I believe, is a most important phase of our work here in the community. New weaving designs have been made for the summer and fall business. A few are new articles, others are the old things redesigned. The yearly schedule of planning the work for the different months is a great help toward the efficient running of the department. It will always be difficult to look ahead and prepare just the right colors and quantities of weaving for the clubs in the fall. It is my sincere desire that everyone who buys the weaving will find it satisfactory and enjoy it. Respectfully submitted, WINOGENE B. REDDING Here are a few rules under which the weavers work for us. No woman weaving for the school can weave for other shops in town. This has been forced upon us by the increasing competition. No woman can weave two months before or two months after the birth of a baby, and then only with the permission of the nurse or doctor. Every weaver must call at the weaving building at least twice a month during the time she is weaving. Weavers must understand that the work is staggered among the number and be willing to take their turn. Loyalty to the school is understood. No children of the weavers are allowed to come to the weaving building on errands while school is in session. Neither is the weaving to be made an excuse for keeping children out of school. EPO T OF THE HOME ECONOMICS DEPARTMENT 1937,38 First Year IN THE first year Home Economics class, there was an enrollment of eighteen first year girls. During the first week of school a short unit on Food Preservation was studied, the girls canned apples several different ways, and learned many things about the course, as a whole. The next units studied were on Home Courtesies and Personal Grooming. In these units we tried to set standards of good grooming and habits of courtesy. The next unit was Clothing, selection and construction and care .of underclothing. The problem was the construction of pajamas or a night gown. It took five weeks to complete this unit. Most of the girls had never sewed before, but their garments showed excellent work. The next unit was Foods planning, preparing, and serving breakfast. Each girl planned, cooked, served a breakfast. Members of the faculty were invited as guests. The next three weeks were spent in studying the Child Care unit. In this unit we tried to get a better understanding of Child nature and needs. Mrs. Chalmers gave a very instructive demonstration on bathing the baby. The two weeks before Christmas were spent in studying about parties and making candy. The freshman girls made favors and decorated for the Christmas dinner given to the Staff. Second Semester: The first unit this semester was Clothing the selection, cutting and construction of a school dress. Their dresses were very attractive and serviceable. It took the girls five weeks to plan and make their dresses. The next unit was Food planning, preparing, and serving a lunch. The girls cooked vegetables, bread, casserole dishes, and deserts. They worked in groups of four and served a lunch. Faculty members were invited as guests. For the next two weeks the girls took Agriculture. I taught the freshman boys. I taught lessons on etiquette, balanced diets, setting the table, per sonal grooming, and candy making. Mrs. Chalmers gave a demonstration on bed making. The boys were very interesting. The last two weeks were spent on the House Unit selection, construction and use of furnishings. The girls planned a model kitchen. We also visited a model kitchen here in Gatlinburg. Second Year In the second year class there was an enrollment of seven sophomore girls and three senior girls. The first unit studied was Food Preservation. The girls canned fruits and vegetables. They also made jelly. Different methods of canning were studied in class. The next unit was a short unit on Budgets and Accounts. This took two weeks. The girls made a budget for them to keep the rest of the year. In the Clothing Unit the girls planned, selected, and constructed a tailored wool dress. This project took six weeks. The Foods Unit, planning, preparing, and serving dinners lasted until Christmas. The girls worked in groups of fours and served dinners. Members of the faculty were invited as guests. They completed their study by preparing and serving a dinner to the entire staff. The House Unit was studied after the Christmas holidays. The girls furnished a whole house and made floor plans of arrangement of furniture in the house. We made several visits to attractive homes here in Gatlinburg. The next four weeks were spent on the Child Care Unit. We tried to get a deeper appreciation and understanding of children. We studied about heredity and environment, which is not studied in the freshman year. Each girl made some garment for the baby or preschool child. Most of them made clothes for some member of the family. In the Clothing Unit the girls made dresses of silk or thin cotton material. The girls showed originality in their designs. Some of them made their own patterns. The girls took Agriculture for two weeks. I THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 99 taught the Sophomore boys. They were taught the same thing as the Freshman boys. The last two weeks were spent in individual projects selected by members of the class. Some of them made over garments, and some made dresses. The Home Economics Club had twenty-five members. We sold candy during the year, making twenty-five dollars in all. The Club belongs to the State and National Home Economics Student Club Association. The Club gave three parties for the F.F.A. during the year. Besides the Home Economics class, I taught forty hours of outside adult teaching, planned the school lunches, and helped the girls with home projects the last period of each day. The last four weeks of school I taught the fifth grade one period as Miss Pack helped with the music at this time. Respectfully submitted, ROSALIE ELLIS ELEMENTA Y SCHOOL EPO T, 1937.38 T HE II B Elementary School opened August 9, 1937 with an enrollment of 252 students. The total enrollment for the year was 285 students. The average daily attendance was 229 students for the year. This was better than last year, the average daily attendance being 199. Two hundred thirty-two students were promoted to the next grade. There were only 13 failures for the entire school. Soon after school opened a Safety Patrol was organized. Boys in the seventh and eighth grades were used as patrolmen. The purpose was to help the smaller students to cross the highway in safety. The Tennessee Highway Department was asked to paint danger signs and crossing lanes at different points along the highway. They were very helpful in this respect. Soon after the patrol was organized there were very few violations both among the students and the people driving automobiles. No students were injured in going to or from school this year. Last year the state rating on sanitation was 67%. The final rating on sanitation this year was 87%. With a few improvements we can have the highest rating of any school in Sevier County. Programs were given by the students at the Parent-Teachers meeting this year. The smaller children seem to enjoy entertaining their mothers at this meeting. A program of physical education was started this year in which we had volleyball, basketball, playground ball, football, soccer, and many other games in which students of all ages and sizes took a part. We hope to do much more in this department next year. The programs at Christmas were given in two parts. The first four grades gave a play, "Christmas in the Circus." The fourth through the eighth grade gave a play and sang carols. This program was given at night. On Thursday, March 31, the eighth grade gave their play, "Her Blessed Boy." On Friday, April 1 the Eighth Grade graduation exercises were held in the auditorium. The speaker was Dr. John J. Fuller of the University of Tennessee. The elementary school chorus sang at this program. The stage was decorated with red bud and dogwood and ferns. Twenty-one students received their diplomas which were presented to them by Superintendent Theron Hodges. Superintendent Hodges asked how many students intended to enter high school next year and all of them said that that was their plan. These students voted to use the money they received from their play to buy a cabinet so that the cup that was won in the Blue Ribbon contest could be placed in the elementary school. The enrollment has been so large this year that we have had to ask for an extra teacher. There has been an average of 42 pupils per teacher this year. Respectfully submitted, C. PERN PRICE, Principal I* \ JENNIE NICOL MEMORIAL HEALTH CENTE MAY 193 7.AP1938 HE sixteenth year of service of the Jennie T Nicol Memorial Health Center has been completed, with its manifold duties and responsibilities. In spite of its wide spread service or, perhaps, because of it it operates, as do hospitals the world over, at a financial loss. That is unavoidable, taking into consideration the community it serves. Those who can pay, can afford a doctor. Those who cannot, are the ones who need us most. It matters little whether one reaches a case on horse-back or in a car; whether one must remain ten hours or ten minutes; it is important that the needed thing be done. All phases of the work are important first aid, bedside nursing, pre-natal, infant welfare, school inspection, preventive measures, advice and instruction. With the increasing population, it is impossible to do routine calling annual calls on school children, bi-annual calls on pre-schools, for instance. But the most necessary things are done as far as time permits. All sick and emergency calls that reach us, are answered, regular office hours are established, and inoculation and education stressed to the fullest extent. The Home Economics Courses include some things that are more easily taught by a nurse, and classes are occasionally brought to the hospital for demonstration and lectures. Short health talks are given in the schools, and, at times, to groups of adults, such as the Weavers Guild, or the Parent-Teachers Association. Some instruction is also given to the Boy and Girl Scouts, with lessons on First Aid and Home Nursing. A new filing system has been inaugurated for Diptheria immunization, enabling a closer touch on the shots that are due. Out of the less than .three hundred children of pre-school age on our records, about two thirds are immunized. Of the rest, more than ten per cent are still under the required age. So we feel the record one of which to be proud. Preventive measures can easily be handled in </p>
      <pb ref="arr5510079_0012" seq="12" n="100-101  "/>
       <p>WO THE SEPTEMBER ARROW :he schools. It is a bit more difficult to reach those people of pre-school or past school age. Health education has not yet reached the point where prevention is carried along by its own momentum, and it never will. But many children and adults come in for their inoculations as a matter of routine as soon as they are due. However, it takes a scare now and then to keep folk from backsliding. At any rate, our problems in this line are lessening gradually. Once more, the II B 4. school carried off the honors for large schools in the annual Blue Ribbon Health Contest, and brought home the big silver cup for another year. In the seven schools in the district, there were 248 Blue Ribboners, in good physical condition, alert in their studies, and free from remedial defects about a third of the enrollment. Two crippled children in the community have been hospitalized at Knoxville the past year. One is on the road to complete recovery, via surgical correction and a series of braces. The other has, we trust, been granted a little more comfort for a time, at least. Sixteen Christmas baskets were distributed to needy families, and lists made for the church charities. A few layettes were furnished destitute mothers, and many things loaned from the supply closet, which is getting to look like Mother Hub-bard's cupboard. It is quite easy, these days, to get an emergency case under the doctor's care, and but rarely are we called upon to treat a bed patient at the hospital at Gatlinburg. Though the sterile supplies seem to melt away all too rapidly, there are always things in readiness for first aid or surgery. Frequently, a patient may be sent home from a hospital by a doctor days earlier, because the routine care may be' done by the "nurse at the school." It is gratifying, in a sense, but some times the responsibility is over-powering. The Health Center has had the cooperation of the County Health Officers, and furnished with an abundance of serums, report and record blanks, and literature. They have aided us with Tuberculosis and Well Baby Clinics, and made necessary tests, and examinations. Dr. Mayberry, from Knoxville, continues his monthly visits to the hospital, and is a decided help in dentistry. Dr. Conroy, our village doctor, is ever ready to lend a helping hand, and the doctors of Sevierville, Maryville, and Knoxville have given splendid service. Staff members are always ready to aid in any way possible, and their friendly help is, at times, of untold value. No request for assistance has ever met with a refusal. However, the friendship of the people them-selves, their willingness in nearly every case, to take suggestion, their confidence in our judgment, is of the greatest importance in our usefulness. Without that, and the interest and cooperation of the members of the Fraternity, the work could not continue. . It is true that the district has changed materially in the past few years, and the work of the Health Center has changed in character to some degree. But it is our sincere belief that for many years to come, the little Memorial Hospital will be of prime importance to the entire community. Following is the summary of the year's work, in comparison with that of the year preceding; Class of Work 1937-38 1936-37 Field visits 1,504 1,380 Office Calls 3,371 1,831 Surgical Dressings 2,679 1,909 Individual Pupil Inspections . 1,128 1,343 Class Room Health Talks . 128 166 Total Typhoid Shots 819 1,408 Completed Typhoid Series 274 404 Diphtheria Immunization 89 59 Schick Test for Diphtheria Im62 129 munity Small Pox Vaccinations 225 242 Blue Ribbon Awards 248 242 Average car mileage per month 830.9 833 MARJORIE CHALMERS, R.N. MITO Y REPO T, 1937.38 1\ It \ DO TOOK up my work as house manager and matron on August 14, 1937. There were ten boys and seven girls in the dormitories. This was fewer than in previous years, but it was thought that they should have more room and more comfortable quarters. Bess McCarter continued to do the cooking and after a few months because of the illness of Kate McCarter, Bell Lowe took up the work as helper. Only a few changes were made in my household management. . Mertie, the laundress for so many years, was ill a good part of the winter, and there was great rejoicing when she returned in March. Respectfully submitted, MRS. SMITH New address, PI BETA PHI MAGAZINE AGENCY, Central Office, Marshall, Illinois THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 101 Committee 1110. eports COMMITTEE ON EXTENSION T HE Committee on Extension submits the following report of their activities without the addition of a petition to Convention for a new chapter. Several prospects for a field for a new chapter of II B I failed to materialize. One group, that of the University of Georgia, will be presented to Convention for its consideration. Correspondence has been carried on with alum-= or local groups at twenty-two schools. Several of these, in states crowded with chapters, were not encouraged. Some schools were found to be lacking in meeting the requirements set up in our Constitution for a chapter. A few schools will soon allow national fraternities on their campuses for the first time. Careful investigation is being made of local organization on these campuses. Inquiries as to our policy of extension were received from groups on the campuses at Eureka College, Florida Southern, Louisiana Polytechnic Institute, Marquette, New Mexico, Baylor, University of Buffalo, Denison, Kent State, and Susquehanna University. Inquiries were sent to alumnae near the following schools British Columbia, Lake Forest, McGill, Queen's, Mississippi, North Carolina, Connecticut State College, Tennessee, and Creighton. This Committee is greatly interested in prospects at Willamette University, and the University of Kansas City, but since school officials have not yet opened the doors of the colleges to nationals, little can be done at present. The Committee chairman has had excellent co-operation from her committee members this year. All report excellent cooperation from alumni who answered their inquiries, however, many letters were not answered by the alumnae addressed. It is only through alumnoe near schools who write us about our extension policy, that we can hope to learn how worthy the group may be. A new file and filing system has been set up so that the correspondence with different groups may be kept permanently. This Committee welcomes letters from alum= suggesting schools in which there is an opportunity for II B Thanks must be extended to those who have been alert to our opportunities, to my committee members who haye been so prompt and helpful, and to the Grand Officers who have so willingly assisted us. Respectfully submitted, ELSA BARKER ESKEW COMMITTEE ON SCHOLA SHIP, 1937.38 T Is difficult to report on the progress of the work on scholarship when the grades reported are for last year and the effectiveness of this year's work will not be known until the grades come in next November. However, the committee feels that real gains have been made this year, for: many more of the chapters have corresponded monthly with the super-visors and have received help in their scholarship problems before it is too late, the lowest chapters have been very faithful in their correspondence with the national chairman and are all making a big effort to improve their scholarship, and the check of the chapter chairman's file by the Province President has been a great help in keeping each newly elected chairman well informed about the work. Last year's improved blanks were used again this year with the addition of checking the dates when due, against the Official Calendar so that no misunderstanding could arise. In addition, Blank No. 2 was sent to each Province President. Graphs compiled from the November reports on scholarship were published in the February ARROW. The position of each chapter and each province was shown, with the exception of Zeta Province from which some returns came in too late for that ARROW. This year as an added incentive for improved scholarship the committee compiled an Honor Roll, consisting of the names of those making the greatest improvement in one semester and those making the highest grade. Since official grades are released very late in the following semester the first Honor Roll was compiled too late for the May ARRow. It will be published in the September ARROW. The scholastic average for 1936-37 is slightly higher (24.4) than for 1935-1936 (24). There is also a slight increase in the number standing first, from ten to eleven. Thirty-eight chapters are in the upper third and only thirteen are in the lower third on their campuses. Four provinces, Delta, Epsilon, Zeta, and Theta have a general average of 29 or higher, well in the upper third. PI BETA PHI HONOR ROLL FALL TERM, 1937 There are many individual members of the Fraternity each year making a big effort to attain some of our ideals and in recognition of such attempts the Scholarship Committee has decided to publish an Honor Roll each semester. This Honor Roll will list for each chapter the name of active or pledge making the greatest improvement in scholar-ship and the name of the active or pledge with the highest grade. Official grades are needed to gather these facts and, since most colleges allow from six to twelve weeks for working off "incompletes," official grades are always released late in the next semester. For that reason this first Honor Roll was not ready for the May ARROW. We hope the next one will be ready for the November ARRow. This Honor Roll is not complete for some chap</p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



