<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr5740441_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name> Pace, Jeffries Green </name></author>
                        <author><name>Hagee, Marie Bacon </name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>May 1941</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr5740441_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">May 1941</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name> Pace, Jeffries Green </name></author>
                        <author><name>Hagee, Marie Bacon </name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 440-441</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">39</note>
                        <note type="Folder">9</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 57, Number 4 (May 1941), Pages 440-441.</note>
			<note type="document">arr5740441_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">A Message from the Settlement School Committee</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>
                                <item>Tourism</item>
                                <item>Funding</item>
                                <item>Government</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr5740441_0001" seq="01" n="440-441  "/>
       <p>NEWS F Edited by JEFFRIES GREEN PACE, Virginia A 1 OM LITTLE PIGEON A Message from the Settlement School Committee By MARIE BACON HAGEE, Missouri B, Chairman In the past two weeks two letters have come, requesting information about our Settlement School, and because the questions in them were those which some of the rest of you 32,000 Pi Phis may be revolving in your minds, you will be interested in having them answered here. These questions fall into three general groups: the first, dealing with how the School is financed, and what County, State, and Federal aid is received; the second, with the ability of Arrow Craft to take on more support of. the School; and the third, with what type of person is now being helped, and whether the need for that help is still great. The picture of how the School is financed is accurately and completely presented in the Information numbers of your ARROW. Look up the reports and when you have read them, add to them these figures for 1939-40. Amount paid by the County Grade School Salaries $5,344.00 Grade School Rent 800.00 High School Salaries 2,862.00 $9,006.00 Amount paid by the State Vocational Agriculture $1,060.00 Vocational Home Economics 600.00 Arts and Crafts 750.00 Weaving 454.50 $2,86'4.50 This year there have been 8 grade school teachers, and 5 high school teachers. County and State aid has increased from $1,200 in 1913-14 to $11,870.50 in 1939-40. There has been no Federal WPA received because no one has been on relief. These mountain people do not like charity. For what they receive from us, they pride themselves on being able to give something in return. For example there was the small boy last summer who waited each day for the nurse to come down the path from making her visit to his mother, and presented her with some gift. Sometimes it was a bunch of flowers, and once only a few pickled beets. One more detail should be added to this financial picture and that is whether the County is now able to do more to build and maintain its own schools. To that the answer is "no, not at present." Sevier County is a poor county, in that it has few factories and comparatively no railroad mileage. These are the main sources of a county's revenue, not individuals. With deep regret we learn that ill health has forced the resignation of Eunice Sheldon Weaver, Illinois Z, as director of the Settlement School, be-()inning April 1. The news comes too late for fitting tribute in this issue to Mrs. Weaver's fine service in the seven years of her administration. There is only time to say that in those years the Settlement School has reached a peak of efficiency ; cooperation between school management and committee has been excellent ; the staff has been capable and happy; the community has been drawn close to the school through its confidence in the Director and its appreciation of her work. Pi Beta Phi owes a real debt of gratitude to Mrs. Weaver and we hope to express it more fully in a later issue of the ARROW. 440 THE MAY ARROW 441 Now for the second group of questions, those about Arrow Craft's ability to assume more support of the School. It is true that Arrow Craft is a thriving industry, thanks to our alumni club sales and to the tourist trade, but we ought not to depend too much on its income to supplement our donations. Its profits are an uncertain amount, dependent on many outside factors. So far we have enjoyed exemption from taxes because of our status as a school, but with demand for in-creased national revenue, no one knows how long that may continue. Besides, that part of Arrow Craft's prosperity which comes from the tourists is not a stable thing. In a town without a water supply or sewage disposal, the outbreak of an epidemic is not an unlikely thing, and even a most minor one might result in tourists giving the town a wide berth for a while, with consequent great loss to our shop. For another thing, there is no fire protection, and while our Arrow Craft stock is adequately protected by insurance, it would take time to replace it. In case of fire, we might easily lose the great part of a season's trade. Without being too gloomy, business is certainly in the midst of some uncertain years, and while we hope, by sound, conservative management not only to survive these years, but to prosper, we feel that we must use Arrow Craft profits to build up a surplus to fall back upon if things do not go well. As for the third class of questions whom do we help and is our help needed? Certainly with the opening of the Smoky Mountains National Park, life changed for those living along the highway leading to it, for tourists flocked in. With native shrewdness, however, these mountain people have kept outsiders from coming in and exploiting them. When need arose they built tourist camps, sold native handcraft, and tried to avail themselves of the seasonal opportunities at their doors. A few businesses have prospered and developed, among them our own Arrow Craft. But back from the high-way, there are still the reserved, independent, but poor, mountain people, living in one or two room cabins, and tilling small patches of up-and-down land. From these homes come children to our school and weavers to our Weavers' Guild. Now, as has been the case in past years, the cash received for weaving often represents the total cash in-come for the family. We pay fair wages, enforce certain regulations, and require high class work in return. Perhaps this note of thanks from our School nurse, Marjorie Chalmers, can tell you far more graphically than I, whether our help is still needed. "I wish I could express to you my feelings and my gratitude. Such a wealth of material and at this season when such things are even more welcome. Already some of the things have been given, though I try to be careful about unwise distribution. "For instance a young mother with the flu had her month-old baby in bed with her. Arrow Craft was raided for a carton, the laundry for worn-out blankets for padding, you provided fresh clothes and little pad for the bed, and a baby blanket contributed by one of the alumnx here wrapped a freshly bathed young Marjorie. The new "baby bed" was placed on a box just outside the bedroom door. (There wasn't room inside the tiny bedroom for the carton, either at the side or foot of the double bed. Except for barely room enough to squeeze through on two sides, the bed filled the place from wall to wall.) The five-year-old girl built and kept a fire in the stove to heat water, while I collected necessaries. With her help, Mother was bathed and freshly clothed, the bed changed, house swept and straightened, wee Bobby and Billy washed, combed, changed and advised no, ordered to keep shoes on and tied. "One hour and a half and what a change. Daddy has a job now, and must keep it. A married sister comes in whenever she can, and an unmarried one has come from North Carolina. So all is right once more." Yes, we are still needed at Gatlinburg, sometimes I think more now than ever be-fore. In this day of conflict and confusion, if we can quietly continue our efforts for them, we will contribute to security in one small part of the world at least. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



