<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr5530959_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name> Pace, Jeffries Green </name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>February 1939</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr5530959_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">February 1939</date>, News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name> Pace, Jeffries Green </name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 959-962</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">39</note>
                        <note type="Folder">6</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 55, Number 3 (February 1939), Pages 959-962.</note>
			<note type="document">arr5530959_0000</note>


	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Promotion</item>
                                <item>Handicraft</item>
                                <item>Tourism</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr5530959_0001" seq="01" n="958-959  "/>
       <p>958 THE FEBRUARY ARROW tributed to "soupmeat." The food is never purchased and the cook takes the pennies for his own, sometimes paying his "boys" with this money. The term for the practice is the "squeeze," or "cumshaw." Mrs. Johnson has been very active in the Girl Scout movement in Peking. The Girl Scouts had been organized prior to Mrs. Johnson's arrival, but had not been especially active. It might be said here, the Girl Scout organization is composed of girls of seven different nationalities, including the Chinese. These girls all attend the American school in Peking. The organized movement was begun in 1932 and for four years a camp was held in a garden, loaned for the occasion by an old Manchu prince. As Mrs. Johnson pointed out, locations for these camps are not as abundant as in the United States, they have to be chosen with care to avoid any danger of polluted water or roving bandits. Regarding the language, Mrs. Johnson said, "My husband suggested that I learn the Chinese language to increase my enjoyment of life in China." The Peking dialect is really the closest to the language of the Court and has four "tones," while Cantonese involved seven or eight "tones." Therefore, in the Peking dialect, one word may mean four different things, according to the tone inflected. Mrs. Johnson told many amusing incidents which happened to her when she was inexperienced in the confusing language. When asked if the Chinese culture adhered to the ancient caste system, the Ambassador's wife stated, "No, their society could rather be termed as a `scholarship aristocracy,' " adding, "in the last ten years Chinese women have been going into all kinds of professions. It has been a transition-al period, and many of the old customs with regard to marriage and feminine education have been questioned and eliminated by the younger people in China." We inquired if this change was due to the foreign influence and if such influence was a detracting agent to the Chinese culture. Mrs. Johnson said she thought not, that the west had something to give to the east, and they, in turn, had something to contribute to our culture. Pi Beta Phi Founders' Days were celebrated when Mrs. Johnson lived in Peking by eight members. But there was no organized alumni club because all the people were too transient, being connected with various governmental services, however, in Shanghai the B alumnre club comprised of ten to eighteen members, met quite regularly. Mrs. Johnson said she often tried to arrange her trips to Shanghai for those affairs. With the multiple duties of an Ambassador's wife, such as official luncheons and dinners every week, entertaining two or three hundred Americans at tea during a week, participating in all Embassy and community society, attending board meetings (Girl Scout, Women's Board of Yenching University, Woman's Club, etc.) , managing a large household and many servants, and the two small children, Mrs. Johnson lives a busy and exciting life. Among twenty girls who were chosen as the loveliest in the university to cheer on the Duke University football team when it came to Pasadena for its Rose Bowl Game were two members of North Carolina B Mary Elizabeth Crawford and Rosemary Forsythe. NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON Edited by JEFFRIES GREEN PACE, Virginia A 1.111111.1.11.11111.111111.11111.111.1111111I 1111111011111 1.111111.11,IIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIII11111111I 111111111111 II 1111110111 1111111111 Convention Day at the Settlement School had come at last. For years it had been dreamed of and since the summer before when it had moved into the realm of reality, the committee as well as the staff, had alternately cheered its possibilities for good, and shivered over possible unfavorable impressions left with our expected guests. The sky was not completely cloudless but only the cheerful little fleecelings that accent a lovely mountain day, floated over Le Conte and augured luck for our venture. The Committee, en masse, sat stiffly on the porch of the Teachers' Cottage at nine o'clock in the morning, dressed collectively in their best bib and tucker and hoping that our school would keep its dress clean until the company arrived. All arrangements had been completed by the Gatlinburg alumnae club and everything should go off like clockwork. At Arrowcraft Shop, Edna McCarter, Ava Clabo, Blanche Whaley, Mary Durkee Pritchard, Dorothy Manley, and Jane Snow alternately walked the floor and fingered the displays to be sure that nothing was lacking. Under the trees along the creek on the way to the Weaving Building, lots of activity was being exhibited. Harrison Mc-Carter and his wife were already making baskets, Elmer Carr and his brother, brooms. Arlena McCarter and her husband sorted their colorful material preparatory to starting fans and flyswatters. Fred and Mat McCarter had arranged a work bench for their chairs and had provided Mrs. Husky with one on which she could begin putting a seat. The sunlight fell in dappled patches through the trees, the smoke from a small fire floated upward, and the creek chattered busily in pre-tended imitation of the workers alongside it. In the Weaving Building, Lura Owenby looked with satisfaction at the well brushed and tidied rooms. Aunt Lizzie and Izora sat thumping steadily away on their looms, perhaps feeling that these leisurely people from over the mountains had let the best of the day slip by. The loom room was bright with colored wools hung on the walls and twisted on racks beside the looms. Flowers contrib uted by Mrs. Voorhies from her gardens and gathered from the fields by Gene Redding, relieved the severity of the bare brown walls. In the High School, Mr. and Mrs. Ben Fleming and Mr. King were on hand to receive the guests, and in the grade building, Mr. Price, Eleanor Pack, and Eleanor Brabson checked up on school exhibits and drawings to be sure they were all in place. Mrs. Whaley represented the town at the Teachers' Cottage while Henrietta Huff sat in the business office with the gay yellow, green, and white patch-work quilt spread out for raffle for the benefit of the Parent-Teachers' organization which made it. We all hoped that it would provide many hot lunches for the coming winter. At the girls' dormitory, Mrs. Smith and three dormitory girls were stationed as ushers, and Mr. Coe with several boys, were at the boys' dorm. Marjorie Chalmers was on duty with Blanche Huff Arthur in the hospital where everything shone with extra, extra cleanliness. Across the way Mrs. Newt Clabo and Mrs. Mary Ogle, looked hospitably out the doorway of the log cabin, prepared to ex-plain the oldtime furniture to those who were not familiar with its uses. The climbing roses all about seemed to have put on a special burst of bloom, expressing the will and the hope of the school to please. Miss Georgia' clung loyally to her shop with Miriam Swann as assistant, though, contrary to the usual situation she was a bit off the beaten track in the Mountain View Hotel. The Boy and Girl Scouts who were serving as guides rushed in and out reassuring them-selves that they were well supplied with booklets and that they had their instructions down to the letter. The minutes dragged wearily along for everyone. From time to time someone would take a looksee in the neighborhood of the bus station and come back more discouraged. The bus, bringing lunch and waiters from the Grove Park Inn, created a flurry by its arrival but still no Convention! The enthusiasm of the youthful guides drooped sadly, 959 </p>
      <pb ref="arr5530959_0002" seq="02" n="960-961  "/>
       <p>SOME OF OUR WORKERS "op, left: The Carr brothers made brooms. Right: Harrison MacCarter and his wife made baskets. Center: The MacCarter rothers made chairs. Bottom, left : Arlena MacCarter and husband made fans and fly swatters. Right: Mrs. Husky puts in a hair seat. AT GATLINBURG Top, left : Wiley Oakley and his Smoky Mountain Ramblers. Right : The Weaver's Play Cast. Bottom, left: Elder Ogle's lads sit on the outskirts consoled by a hearty lunch. Right: Molly Moore spins for the play. </p>
      <pb ref="arr5530959_0003" seq="03" n="962-963  "/>
       <p>THE FEBRUARY ARROW veryone began to talk about food Mrs. Veaver sent over for some chocolate bars to oost the spirits of the children on duty, who rere accustomed to early dinner. A few, early 'i Phis from private cars, straggled in but ae day couldn't really begin without the bus-)ads of Asheville folks. All at once and without warning the heavris seemed to have opened and rained Pi his. They were all over the place at once rid we soon felt pitifully inadequate to do istice to all of them. Fortunately for us, Dme of the crowd lingered at the luncheon doles set under the trees, before making the Dunds and soon the more adventurous ones .rifted back, attracted by the sound of sing-1g from Wiley Oakley and his Smoky Mounlin Ramblers. Wiley, as usual, was dressed corduroy breeches stuck into heavy boots rid topped by a bright plaid shirt. He had pent part of the morning on the porch of ae Teachers' Cottage, telling of his trip to few York. "You know," he said, "I took a ew suit along to wear but they wouldn't let ie wear nothing but these same old clothes." Mrs. Libbey's brave and sturdy little figure ras easily distinguishable in the crowd. The 3ng pull over the mountains seemed only to ave exhilarated her and everyone stood to .o her homage. I saw her in several places n the school grounds and feel sure that her adomitable spirit allowed her to miss nothag. She went into the Weaving Building, rid squired by Mrs. Holton had a real get-Dgether with Aunt Lizzie. Very filling lunches were served in boxes the Inn waiters in crisp white coats. They were most generous with the extra ones and ome of the weary Girl Scouts sat about enhusiastically disposing of them and the hocolate covered ice cream offered to every ne. Dorothy MacLean circulated about hrough the crowd taking pictures of the lifferent groups with Frances Brown to lentify them for her. Meantime the weavers were excitedly be-rig made up on the second floor of the Weaving Building for their contribution to the momentous day. The stage in the High School had been papered with newspapers like an old mountain cabin, and arranged about the pasteboard fireplace was the old furniture, including loom and spinning-wheel. The auditorium was oppressively hot and some of the weavers had to wear bonnets, which did not help them to keep cool but anyone who could have witnessed one of their rehearsals on the hottest day of the past summer, with a thunder storm brooding in the offing, would have known that the play would go off with the usual smoothness and dispatch. The audience was plentiful and appreciative and cheered the actors on to renewed success. So again they lived over, upon the stage, a simple story of a neighborhood gathering in a mountain cabin and all the local gossip, which to them was so familiar, because all had had a hand in working up and arranging the material. The only thing that marred the day in any way was the over-developed professional pride of two of the bus drivers, which carried them off the road on a private sightseeing trip of their own to Klingman's Dome, which so delayed the ar4,',bf the two buses in Gatlinburg that their occupants had little opportunity to see the school. We hope that they will return at some later date when they can pass on the new additions for the fall term a science and a home economics lab-oratory. All too soon Mr. Price made the announcement heralding the departure of the buses for the return trip and the play was barely over, when the crowds began to dribble wearily out on to the road on the way to the bus station and eventually to Asheville. From many mati,i,f!estations, we feel that Convention was pleavd with our efforts and hope enthusiasm f4r school will increase from year, to year until our dreams are fully realized. Whatever the school has accomplished and whatever it grows to be it owes to a great degree to the untiring efforts of Mrs. WeaverOhe director, and her loyal and enthusiasts 'staff. Please send all magazine subscriptions and renewals to Mrs. C. M. Purdunn, Pi Beta Phi Central Office, Marshall, Illinois. OM PI PHI PENS Edited by MERCEDES BAKER JORGULESCO, Massachusetts A 111111112111111111111.1111111.1111.,111111111111111.111111110111111111101111111 III 111111111111 1111111111 .1 1111111111111..11111 lllll 11111111 lllll II MERCEDES JORGULESCO Canoe Country, by FLORENCE PAGE JAQUES, illustrated by Francis Lee Jaques. University of Minnesota Press. $2.50. Perhaps the greatest pleasure a bibliophile, may have is to come into possession of a rare first edition, a fine old book or a beautifully written and illustrated volume. Such pleasure Canoe Country by Florence Page Jaques, Illinois H, generously bestows. In Canoe Country, Mrs. Jaques delight-fully records in diary form a three-weeks canoe trip into the wilderness of the Border Lakes country of Minnesota and Canada. To supplement her charming impressions, her husband, Francis Lee Jaques of the American Museum of Natural History, has supplied superb black-and-white drawings, end papers, and cover illustration. "Hundreds and hundreds of lakes scattered through forest, like pieces of a mammoth jigsaw puzzle scattered over a table. Scraps of rivers lace the lakes together. There are no roads, no paths except short portages ; one can travel only by water." Into this primeval wilderness two good companions journeyed. Traveling without a guide, they wandered wherever their whims took them, through these lakes and rivers. At night they camped on shore under the evergreens. The animals and birds were "as good company as one could ask." Mrs. Jaques' diary of their trip is intimate and informal, written with the acute awareness of one who is having a new experience, yet always gay and charming. At one time she writes: "Freedom surrounds us. We are finding more than peace here. This is an authentic and profound release from modern intricacies." There are paragraphs of prose with the lyric quality of exquisite poetry, such as the closing paragraph of the book. "But I don't want to leave. I'll always remember this place and long for it a little. Islands of gold and green, the wind in great branches, an owl's call in the rainy dusk, the scent of our wood smoke drifting across the moonlight. It will be like a lost kingdom." Mr. Jaques' drawing, are the work of an outstanding nature artist who has long known the north country. His renderings are at once authentic and bold. These congenial collaborators give you a perfect feeling of being along on the jour FLORENCE PAGE JAQUES This experience is filled with utter harmony ney. They bring you the thrill of seeing. a loon running madly on a lake, a moose discovered at his bath, a young kingfisher pre-tending to be an austere and steady fisher-man, tiny wood mice clearing the crumbs. Commendation is due the University of Minnesota Press for the good taste they displayed in book design and typography. THE AUTHOR AND ILLUSTRATOR: Florence Page Jaques graduated from Millikin University and studied in the graduate school of Columbia University. John T. Frederick of The Midland and Harriet Monroe encouraged her in writing poetry, and published some of her verses, "but," says Mrs. Jaques, "I slipped from that into writing nonsense rhymes and stories for children." And now her work has "slipped" into such fine antholo 963 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



