<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr5020179_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Los Angeles Settlement School Benefit</title>

                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>November 1933</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr5020179_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">November 1933</date>, Los Angeles Settlement School Benefit</title>

                        <extent>Pages 179-181</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">38</note>
                        <note type="Folder">11</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 50, Number 2 (November 1933), Pages 179-181.</note>
			<note type="document">arr5020179_0000</note>


	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Funding</item>
                                <item>Promotion</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr5020179_0001" seq="01" n="178-179  "/>
       <p>178 THE NovEmBER ARROW New Members of Arrow Staff ECENTLY several changes on the ARROW staff have been made due to the resignations of some of the former staff members. The new Alumnae News Editor is Lotta Johnson Weir (Mrs. Benjamin), Illinois Z. After leaving the University of Illinois she married Benjamin Weir, and moved to Chattanooga, Tennessee. At that time, there was no chapter of II B ,.I). at the University of Chattanooga, and it was her pleasure to recommend the petitioning group there. Since re-turning to Illinois, Mrs. Weir has renewed her association with her own chapter. One of her daughters, Frances Hale, Illinois E and a member of I) B K, graduated from Northwestern University in 1933. The other daughter is a freshman at Texas State College for Women. Mr. Weir is the owner and publisher of a daily newspaper. Mrs. Weir has many interests including golf, riding, genealogical research, and education. She has been president of the local Panhellenic Association of her town, and is keenly interested in the matters of the fraternity world, and alumnae club work. Juanita Day Carman (Mrs. Ernest), Minnesota A, is the new Exchange Editor. She graduated from the University of Minnesota, and then taught in Puerto Rico, Honolulu, and Peking, China, besides various and sundry places in the United States, finally teaching Spanish in a Minneapolis high school. She married a Philadelphia lawyer, Ernest Car-man, and lived: in Minneapolis until six years ago, when they moved to Los Angeles. Mrs. Carman ' has attended three Conventions New Orleans, Berkeley, and Pasadena and was president of the Minneapolis and St. Paul Alumnae Club for two years. This past year she has been chairman of the New Book Review group in the Los Angeles Club. This is an innovation which has become quite popular and has an attendance of from twenty to forty each month. Her father owned and edited a newpaper for fifty-five years, and so, as she says, "I should be interested in publications !" She has one son. For the past two years she has served as an interested and active contributor on the ARROW staff. Mercedes Baker Jorgulesco (Mrs. Jonel) , Massachusetts A, who also has been a contributor on the ARROW staff for the past two years, has accepted the appointment as Book Notes Editor, to edit the department From Pi Phi Pens. She is exceptionally well qualified to do this work because she is engaged in book review work for several news-papers in and about New York. An ac-count of her life and activities was given in the May ARROW in the article about ARROW contributors. DENVE STUDENT HON RED I\ "Miss Colorado University, 1933" is Edith Jane Sturgeon who was chosen for the honor last night by the Associated Women Students of the university. The girl student outstanding in leadership and scholarship is selected each year as "Miss Colorado University." Miss Sturgeon is a member of Colorado A and is active on student publications. There were six maids of honor selected by women students of Colorado University. Competition is keen for the posts of "Miss Colorado University" and her maids of honor. Only students who have made substantial contributions to university life are considered for the places. THE NOVEMBER ARROW 179 Los Angeles Settlement School enefit HE LOS ANGELES ALUMNA CLUB gives annually a Settlement School benefit bridge tea. The success of these affairs is due to the splendid cooperation of the members of II B 1) in Los Angeles and vicinity. This past year it was given in February. The committee in charge of the benefit was selected in early fall. There was a general chairman appointed by the President, and ten committee chairmen, namely, ticket; reservation; fashion show; candy; prize; publicity; ushers; mimeographing; and printing and equipment. It was decided, first of all, that the benefit be held at the Biltmore Hotel. The Biltmore gave us the best price sixty-five cents per person, which was quite an item, as it was necessary to re-duce our admission charge from $1.50 to $1.25 per person. With the date and place of the benefit decided, in October, the chairman of the Fashion Show approached Rausohoffs, hoping to persuade them to put on a fashion display for us. Six weeks before the day of the party, the ticket chairman mailed a letter, announcing the party, and enclosing four tickets for the same, to each Los Angeles Pi Phi, and to Pi Phis in southern California, who had supported previous benefits. Approximately seven hundred letters were sent. The letter, written by the general chairman and signed by the committee chairman, told the place at which the party was to be given; the date; and time; the price of each ticket; the special features of the party. The letter stated that checks should be made out to Pi Beta Phi Benefit and mailed to the reservation chairman, and requested that tickets not used be returned ten days prior to the party. After the deadline for returnedtickets, the ticket chairman and her committee telephoned the Pi Phis who had neither sent in their checks nor returned their tickets with the hope of persuading them to come to the Benefit. The duties of the reservation chair-man commenced immediately after the letters and tickets had been mailed by the ticket chairman. The reservation chairman had been given the alphabetical list of Pi Phis and the serial numbers of tickets sent them. The reservation chairman received (1) checks for purchased tickets; (2) returned tickets; and (3) telephone reservations. The reservation chairman, the chair-man of ushers and the general chairman were responsible for the placing of seating arrangements. Four duplicate charts of the table floor plans of the Sala de Ora were secured from the hotel and on them, the guests' tables were numbered, checked, and assigned. The candy chairman was responsible for the solicitation, the wrapping and the sale of candy at the party. She selected a committee to assist her. They solicited candy shops and all Pi Phis for donations. The latter were asked to contribute two pounds home-made candy or money. The goal was set for three hundred pounds, and more than that was furnished. Ways and cost of wrapping the candy were investigated by the chairman. After considerable shopping, the candy was finally packed in one-half pound white paper boxes tied with red ribbonzeen at the cost of two cents a box. Cellophane wrapping is very attractive and the same price, but it had been used for several years. The candy sold for twenty-five cents a box. As candy prizes were to be given at the party, a number was packed in each box. Duplicate numbers were given to </p>
      <pb ref="arr5020179_0002" seq="02" n="180-181  "/>
       <p>180 THE NOVEMBER ARROW the prize chairman before the party. The chairman of prizes was responsible for securing all the prizes to be given at the party, and for the distribution of them at the party. They included twenty door prizes, two candy prizes and individual table prizes. The chairman approached leading shops and stores that might contribute gifts. Prizes included various items as: an order for a miniature painting, by a well-known artist; linens; pottery; china. The chairman brought the prizes to the party, displayed the door and candy prizes on a table near the entrance and attended to their being transferred to the stage before the drawing of numbers took place. The table prizes, which were Settlement School mats, were distributed by ten ushers, who appeared from the stage in white dresses, carrying red glazed band boxes with ties and bows of red and white tulle. They descended from the stage to their assigned places in the different sections, as the tea was being served. The printing and equipment chair-man was responsible for having the tickets and programs printed and for the equipment needed at the party. The tickets and programs were printed in red, on white paper. The tickets set forth the name of the organization, place of party, time, price of tickets, name of firm presenting fashion show, and a serial number. The second and third pages of the program contained the item that there were no bridge rules, and the names of those shops, stores and firms, contributing in any way to the party, and also the names of the committee members. On the last page was the door prize number. The chairman of ushers was in charge of ushers and ushering. She also worked with the reservation chairman and general chairman to chart seating arrangements. The chairman selected the ushersand instructed them as to their duties. Because of the importance of securing the promise of a fashion show, from some exclusive store or shop, the fashion show chairman interviewed in October, the owner of a shop of excel-lent reputation in the city. This feature plays a very large part in the success of the party, and if the committee is fortunate to secure the services of a fine establishment, a major worry is eliminated. Our committee was very elated when the fashion show chairman was in-formed that Rausohoffs would stage the fashion display for us. Rausohoffs had never given a Fashion Show in Los Angeles, so we had reason to be jubilant. Because of their excellent reputation, we knew that many guests would be especially interested in seeing their display, and we were confident that everything would be handled perfectly. Models for the Fashion Show were selected by Rausohoffs by means of try-outs. The chairman secured actives, girls from the University of Southern California and the University of California at Los Angeles chapters and younger alumni members, who were five feet six inches tall. They met one evening at Rausohoffs, where they modeled garments given them. When the models were finally selected, they were requested to spend a total of eight hours modeling at Rausohoffs to gain poise and assurance. The day before the party, Rausohoff rehearsed the models at the Biltmore's Sala de Ora, with the orchestra. The stage made a beautiful setting for the Fashion Review. The back drops were white taffeta. The drops on either end were dark blue velvet. The ceiling of the stage was white taffeta draped to the back drops. In the center of the white (back) drops was a large gold frame (representing a picture frame). Dark blue velvet curtains were inside the frame. These were pulled aside to reveal a model. The background of the picture was dark blue velvet. On either THE NOVEMBER ARROW 181 side of the picture frame were huge, light blue pottery vases filled with red cherry blossoms. As the outside curtains, keeping the stage setting from view during the earlier part of the afternoon were drawn aside, the lights were dimmed and three spotlights, one from each side of the room and one from the back, were thrown on the stage and frame. The music was playing and the show was on ! There were always two models on thefloor, one of them was completing her line of march, when one of the spot-lights picked up a third model in the picture frame. After the girl stepped out of the frame, she walked the length of the stage before descending to the main floor. Each model was on the floor approximately three minutes. The tempo of march was fairly quick. The display was made even more interesting because of individual guest programs designed by Rausohoffs. MRS. CATT REVIEWS HER REFORM WO R EFORMS are very much alike. There is indifference. Education goes on and on, and by and by it grows enough so that the army enlisted on behalf of the reform has become sufficiently large and powerful to attract public attention. And the public thinks the movement has just started!" Thus does Mrs. Carrie Chapman Catt discuss a lifetime devoted to great causes. Her first cause, woman suffrage, enlisted her militant support almost fifty years ago, under her leadership it be-came an accomplished fact in 1920. Since then her efforts have been devoted to the cause of world peace and now at the age of seventy-four she is the leader in this country of the movement for world disarmament. "There is one great difference," Mrs. Catt observed, "between the suffrage movement and the peace movement. There was no financial investment in the woman suffrage movement, although brewers, distillers and employers did unitedly oppose women's enfranchisement. But that was nothing as compared to the investments in the business of war. Why, last year the United States spent for war purposes a sum greater than its national income! "The manufacturers of munitions of war are one of the great obstacles in the cause of world peace, of substantial commitments toward disarmament. Munition makers profit greatly by war I\ K and their profit is almost as great in peace time. Not guns, cannon and bombs alone are war material; there are also shoes and caps and brass but-tons. "Coupled with this fact or the world conference was retarded by the presence of generals and admirals among the delegates, sent there to work out the method of disarmament but soon revealed as a potent stumbling block to any concrete steps in the cause of world peace. "The third factor has been, of course, the emotion of fear that motivates the whole world. Suspicion, jealousy, hate, greed and ambition have formed a mighty obstruction to clear thinking and honest action for world disarmament. When we get that fear out of the way it will lead the way to the new order." Mrs. Catt spoke vigorously, militantly, choosing her words with the facility of a trained platform speaker and delivering her thoughts crisply and with conviction. What of the future of this, the second great cause of her life? Mrs. Catt preferred not to speak of it. Like Ma-dame Defarge she is not looking for fruition. "It is very unusual to see one reform take place," says Mrs. Catt quietly. "It would be unfair to expect to see more than one." New York Evening Post </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



