<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr5310063_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Settlement School Reports </title>
                        <author><name>Hill, Frankie C. </name></author>
                        <author><name>Weaver, Eunice S. </name></author>
                        <author><name> McCleverty, Josephine</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>September 1936</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr5310063_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">September 1936</date>, Settlement School Reports </title>
                        <author><name>Hill, Frankie C. </name></author>
                        <author><name>Weaver, Eunice S. </name></author>
                        <author><name> McCleverty, Josephine</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 63-74</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">38</note>
                        <note type="Folder">17</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 53, Number 1 (September 1936), Pages 63-74.</note>
			<note type="document">arr5310063_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Chairman Settlement School Committee; Director of the Settlement School; Pi Beta Phi Settlement School - Report on Audit Treasurer's Accounts Year Ended June 30, 1936; </note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Staff</item>
                                <item>Facilities</item>
                                <item>Funding</item>
                                <item>Curriculum</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr5310063_0001" seq="01" n="62-63  "/>
       <p>THE SEPTEMBER ARROW years that I have had. It has been e joys and pleasures of working with roup of women. Their interest and as made it indeed a wonderful ex I shall not forget very soon. My wince vice-president could not have able and as successful at it has been,had it not been for the untold help and constant readiness to assist of the Grand Council in its entirety and the different committee chairmen. It has been a rich experience serving II cl) and knowing her leaders, and I am truly grateful for this privilege. CARRIE WILLIAMSON LAM DA P OVINCE VICE,P ESIDENT '' It \ acially fortunate that my first year as vice-president was the year for club quaintance with the personnel of the an understanding of the different club .oblems, and accomplishments has been due. I am assured that these personal nutually beneficial, and the work be-)vince vice-president and the club offinbers has been that of the happiest nd friendliness. province could have more wonderful we have here in the Northwest ; they ninded, and realizing their importance al organization and their obligation giving generously of their time and a carrying out the programs of the tch club is actively interested in one pters and their achievements in this far-reaching and creditable. included ten of the twelve clubs. ub had the pleasure of a visit with the President, Ruth Barrett Smith, and ince President, Lillian MacLeod Rusch, nton and Calgary clubs; it is hoped neet with these Alberta Clubs early im clubs and all active chapters are to the Loan, Endowment, and Settle-Funds. Eight clubs have had successful sales, and there is an increasing he Settlement School. All clubs are row Craft sales next year as well nstructive program for raising funds by cause. s, Corvallis, Edmonton, Eugene, and active chapters located in the same ad): case close affiliation and understs; and these alumnae clubs are of value to the chapter. fort has been made by the clubs to tsident Pi Phis and the membership ceased in seven of the clubs. Last year since reported 290 paid members of !re in clubs and fifteen were isolated is year there are 336 paid members ; and forty-five paid members of the mnm department. Spokane has the in new members, while Seattle has )aid membership ; Corvallis increased her membership of eight last year to thirteen this year. Wenatchee, with a paid membership of twelve, and Corvallis are two of the small clubs of the province but are 100 per cent paid membership and contributions to all funds. Perfect response has come from all active chapters in sending in senior dues for the national alumnae department ; many of these outgoing seniors will be located in towns where there are clubs where they will receive a very warm welcome next fall. Fifty-two seniors will be graduated this June from our seven chapters. Lambda Province has the signal honor of having as an active member of one of its clubs, our beloved Founder, Inez Smith Soule; Tacoma is the fortunate club, but Seattle and Washington A chapter also have the privilege of knowing her intimately, and Founders' Day each year is made more real and impressive by her presence as guest of honor at the celebration held by the three groups. Mrs. Soule is truly a living example of the ideals upon which our Fraternity was founded, and fortunate indeed, are those Pi Phis who live near her and are constantly inspired by her beautiful character and personality and her loyalty and devotion to Pi Beta Phi! She is young and interesting at the age of nearly ninety years. Perhaps the living of Pi Phi ideals is the "Secret of Youth !" Founders' Day was celebrated by all clubs and chapters; on this day the Nancy Black Wallace Club of Salem had the honor of sponsoring the memorial service and unveiling the bronze marker given by the fraternity for our Founder, Nancy Black Wallace; the ceremony was most inspiring and impressive and was attended by members of Mrs. Wallace's family and alumna: and actives from Oregon clubs and chapters. As a province officer this year, it has been an added joy in my fraternity .life to have had the privilege of greater service to Pi Beta Phi, and it is with sincere appreciation that I think of the generous assistance given me by national and club officers and the splendid cooperation and hospitality of province Pi Phis. May I at this time thank you for your courteousness and help throughout the year? Respectfully submitted, SUE FLETCHER MU PROVINCE VICP \ ESIDENT ;neat pride that I bring to a close the Hub activity of Mu Province for the It has been outstanding in the case anx club, and has been marked with and achievement in all departments of ictioning. an increase of around forty members, i that is not as large as it should be, it is a start for the future. Mu Province has many isolated Pi Phis. There is a paid membership of 641 out of a resident alumnle of around 2,500. The past year has found the clubs of the province very conscious of the fact, and with their cooperation in the future, it is hoped that we can contact many loyal Pi Phis who have not been reached in the past. THE SEPTEMBER ARROW I am most proud to report that the clubs of the province are 100 per cent in donations to the Loan Fund, the Endowment Fund, and the Settlement School. The Los Angeles Club, with the aid of California r and California t1, gave a Settlement School tea and raised between them $1,300.00. The one check from the Los Angeles Club is the largest single donation ever received for the Settlement School. I wish to thank the members of the club and the efficient officers for this splendid achievement. I have been most gratified by the way the clubs and chapters have responded to the Endowment Fund. In many cases the amount donated doubled last year's, and in many others it was a new item on the budget. This year also marked a happy experience in my life. I visited sixteen of the nineteen clubs in Mu Province. Each club stands out with.its own personality, its own pleasures, and its own problems; but all, large and small, with the same true Pi Phi spirit to work for the ultimate goal the realization of the ideals of Pi Beta Phi. I wish to thank each club for its hospitality and for themany pleasures they afforded me. They were are my inspiration to carry on for Pi Phi it matter what capacity I find myself. I wish to thank the members of Grand Col and Marianne Wild for their fine assistance. "I inspiring letters and aid at times of distress helped me greatly. To Ann D'Aule I extend thanks for her splendid cooperation in helpini with the active chapters of the province. To the club officers and committee merr I also extend my thanks. Without their assist the record of the province could not be attai All in all, it has been a real pleasure to the Fraternity as Mu Province Vice-President, what progress has been made is due to the coo] Lion of these splendid women who have given time and enthusiasm to the achievement of plans of the Fraternity. To Mu Province as a whole I gratefully ex] my thanks for all you have given to Pi Beta May it all be returned to you in the riches have been mine in this last year of contact you. ETHEL LUNSFORD FRO C AIRMAN SETTLEMENT SCHOOL COMMITTEE Community A THE close of my four years' work as chairman of the Settlement School Committee, I am happy to make a report to the Fraternity. It is most gratifying to feel and to know that this last year has been the best for the school during my term of office. The most outstanding feature of the year was the addition of the third year to the high school. This fact increased the enrollment and the students, as well as the staff, took a keener interest in their work. I have written twice within the past year to the alum= clubs and active chapters, and I tried to picture as best I could the activities of the school. Mrs. Eunice S. Weaver, Illinois Z, continues to serve as director. She has endeared herself to the staff, to the children, and to the entire community. She is doing a splendid work for the Fraternity in the position she holds. She has created an atmosphere of charm and hospitality at the school for every one who comes whether for a short visit, or to work for a year. Many of the visiting alumnx and friends commend her for her interest in their visits to the school. Unless one spends a while at the teachers' cottage, it is impossible to realize the great number who are interested in seeing the work Pi Phi is doing. Mr. William King has completed five years as principal of the school. He has lived in the boys' dormitory and has meant much in training them. He has worked with the children in school and out; he has been the coach for athletics, assisted by Ben Fleming. Our boys' basketball team has had a most successful season, and the girls' team, while not always victorious, was most creditable to a school the size of ours. Two ex-students of our school, Stella Huff and Ben Fleming, were teachers in the high school. Their recent articles in the May ARROW reflect their love for the school and their appreciation of the work Pi Phi has done for the mountain children. The Smith-Hughes agriculture and home economics teachers have continued the vocational work which our school hasdone for many years. The Pi Beta Phi ch: of Future Farmers of Tennessee has held its 1 lar meetings, and our boys have won various p in the county fairs. The home economic girls similar meetings and join the Future Farmel Tennessee in their social gatherings. It wa: pleasure to enjoy the January party and I never seen a more entertaining group of chi, nor a party where every one had a better time The grammar school building was crowded this year. Eleanor Brabson and Miriam SN, two east Tennessee girls, were our primer first and second grade teachers. They have faithful to the school and the children for and five years, respectively. The third, fourth, and sixth grades were taught by Pauline Caml Oregon B, Mary Louise Durkee, Nevada A, Rosemary Moorehead, Illinois H. These Pi came to us with great enthusiasm and were fai in their work. It is always a great joy to the mittee to know that our active chapter girl: thinking of our school and want to come the work. Visiting in the classrooms is a delight one recognizes at once that the teachers are to train the children and give them every oppo ity to develop personality, as well as to teach the three R's. This year I found many new being sung to our beloved Pi Phi tunes new teachers had busied themselves in writing words and had taught them to the childrel their Christmas and Thanksgiving programs. of these performances are to be commended-audience acclaimed them the best the schoo ever given. An outstanding feature in the gram school was the work of the verse choir, was trained by Rosemary Moorehead. The tea have been most vigilant in visiting the hom the absent children the truant officer is n helpful. The Jennie Nichol Health Center continu wonderful work in ministering to the physical of the school and the community. Two r have served during the past year, Virginia .I\ </p>
      <pb ref="arr5310063_0002" seq="02" n="64-65  "/>
       <p>THE SEPTEMBER ARROW [ber to assume a position with the Department, and Mrs. Marjorie 3alesburg, Illinois, is her successor. beloved by the children as well as ilies in the ten-mile area she serves. r a small room in the high school fitted up to be used as a clinic for uring the morning recess. There was hat the nurse did not find children a dressing to be put on a cut, for an to be relieved, or for some other doctored. The usual inoculations for heria, scarlet fever, and so forth were clinics were held at the hospital and le children had tonsils and adenoids community in the vicinity of Gatlinne so populated that the work of our strenuous. Ella McDonald has completed of service as housemother. She has of the dormitories as well as super-)arding department. Too much praise !n her for her untiring work. A peep y in the late fall is proof enough of spends during the summer in prenning the fruits and vegetables which r gardens and orchards. The children as a mother and the staff are ever ,ke of her tempting repasts. Craft Shop has completed its tenth ess, and I may also add that it has years in the amount of sales. Mrs. owa r, has been director for eighteen o her goes much commendation. The !rvispr is Miss Winogene Redding, added a number of beautiful new Lr stock during the past year. Miss to the shop in the beginning and has than half of that time as weaving building which was given to the Mr. Louis Voorhies five years ago zed this year by the weaving depart-)ms are placed in the largest room in and here the weaving classes for the girls are held, and the Weavers' is composed of the more than eighty weave for the shop, holds its meeting. s' meetings are well attended and are le to the women, as interesting pro-pared by the weaving supervisor. Miss started a library for her women, and collection of books and magazines is 7 office. For the first time in its his-row Craft Shop can claim adequate ;forage space. Mrs. Georgie Duffield be in charge of the shop in the Hotel. The newness of the Smoky ational Park brings many visitors to viiss Pauline Requarth, Illinois H, has !r first year as bookkeeper for the work has been most satisfactory and as well as the staff are delighted that to join our staff of workers. y term of office we have succeeded in $10,000 mortgage to a small amount, une 30 that debt will be wiped out le debt to the Endowment Fund has luced $1,500 during my regime. The )uilding and the teachers' cottage have d ; several buildings have had coats of )ors in the teachers' cottage have been iew living room furniture has also been added there. Concrete flooring has been put in the barn, and new walks have been placed between the houses. An electric refrigerator has been put in; the furnace has been bought for the girls' dormitory, and minor repairs have been made wherever necessary from year to year. The Woodcraft Shop has been remodeled to be used by the weaving department. A car a Ford V-8-has been bought for the use of the staff. The Sugarland Teachers' Cottage was sold for $3,500, and this money was applied to our mortgage. The outstanding progress in the life of the school was the changing from a two-year high school into a four-year high school. The third year has been added this year and the fourth will be added the following year. This will make the third four-year high school in Sevier County. The prospects for an increased enrollment are very bright. The local organization of P.T.A. has given much help to the lunch room which is now fostered by the school. There is also a local committee of five members to assist Mrs. Weaver in local matters. The formation of the Little Pigeon Alumnie Club in June, 1935, has also added new life among the staff who are Pi Phis, and among Pi Phis in Knoxville and nearby towns. The continued support of the Settlement School presages the loyal interest of the alumnae clubs and active chapters. To Los Angeles and Cleve-land Alumnae Clubs go the blue ribbons for the largest donations. Los Angeles gave $1,050 and Cleveland $908. The following active chapters have contributed $100 each: Colorado A, California A, Illinois Z, Florida B, and California F. On behalf of the Settlement School Committee I want to commend these clubs and chapters and I want to extend the deepest gratitude for the donations from every club and chapter. We know they represent work, hard work, and hours of devoted service to the Fraternity. If you know the intimate workings of the school, you will feel well repaid for your efforts, as they are reflected in its accomplishments. Thank you and again I say you have not labored for naught. The Settlement School deserves the best efforts of every member of Pi Phi. It has been a joy to work with my committee this year, and each of my four years of service. To me one of the greatest joys of working for the Fraternity is the deepening of friendships which we form in our work together. I shall have an abiding love for every member of the committee from 1932 to 1936 shall I name them? Helen Tottle, Grace Post, Mary Frost, Mary Gibson, Charlotte Brown, Josephine McCleverty, and Lillian Holton. Each one has given generously of her time and has done her work well. The members of the staff from year to year have shown loyalty and cooperation, and without these helpers the school could not have progressed as it has during these four years which have not been easy ones for the altruistic schools and colleges. We have not lost step in our forward progress which has marked each year in the school's history. My greatest thanks go to the members of Grand Council who have so stalwartly stood behind the committee and who have given their counsel in everything we have tried to do. Words cannot be spoken which could express my appreciation for this honor which has been mine. I yield my chairmanship to my successor, Lillian Holton, and to her I give my best wishes for as happy years of service as THE SEPTEMBER ARROW I have enjoyed. I shall ever love the Settlement School and shall continue to be interested in every phase of its life. It is a wonderful tribute to our Founders, an institution which should hold the interest and loyalty of every wearer of the ' and Blue. Respectfully submitted, FRANKIE C. I ECTO OF THE SETTLEMENT SCHOOL Community THE YEAR 1936 found Gatlinburg with a number of changes. Since much of the government road construction in the Smoky Mountain National Park was completed, many government employees and their families and the C.C.C. camp at Elkmont moved away. The few mountain families still lingering in the Sugarlands and upper Baskins were forced to move elsewhere by January 1, and finding other homes in or near Gatlinburg was quite difficult in mid-winter. The young mothers in the government-employed families who were so helpful in P.T.A. work for the past two years, with their interest in improving the school and their efforts in helping to furnish funds for the noon lunches in the grade school, have been greatly missed. A Business Men's Association was organized for the purpose of improving living conditions and promoting the completion of the highway from Knoxville through Gatlinburg to the Park. Road signs showing school zone and speed limit give us reason to hope for fewer accidents. A campaign has been on foot for the last six months to beautify the "Burg" and sanitary officers have been influencing the people to make improvements. The P.W.A. loan for water-works was not approved. The organization of a private water company has been proposed, but has not yet materialized. The Pi Beta Phi Alumnae Club which was organized a year ago with a membership of twenty extending from Gatlinburg to Sevierville, Norris, and Knoxville, has been and will continue to be a benefit to the school. The club celebrated Founders' Day with a dinner in the Mountain View Hotel. Ten different chapters were represented by the fifteen Pi Phis present, and three other Pi Phis who happened to be stopping at the hotel came into the dining room before we had finished. The amateur contest, sponsored by the alumna club, will not soon be forgotten by the people of the community. Gatlinburg has splendid talent, and those who took advantage of the chance to perform afforded an evening of rich and rare entertainment. There were twenty-five applicants, and but for the stormy night, I fear the auditorium would not have held the audience for there was scarcely standing room left. We hope to make this a yearly event, for it is not only good entertainment for the community but gives the talented ones a chance for expression. Our school building and grounds have been open, as usual, to Old Timers' Day, harp singings, the farm women's organization, and the customary social events peculiar to our community. The influence of a full time minister at the little Baptist Church is felt in the community life and the whole place shows signs of progressive spirit. In spite of the fact that Gatlinburg has grown and appears, along the highway, much more enter-prising, the school's influence seems just as necessary and is as deeply appreciated as ever. School We opened school on August 19 this year a third year class added to our high school. required an extra teacher. A former student c Settlement School, Ben Fleming, who had graduated from Tusculum College, was chose the position. Both the school and the comm soon realized the necessity for a four-year school, and if we are fortunate enough to seventy-five students attending high school year we are promised still another teaches the fourth-year class by the County School E Mr. King, our principal, put special emr on athletics this year. We thoroughly enjoye basketball season which was the most successfi school has ever had. Only one game was during the regular playing season and eig games were won. Our team went to the finals in the district tournament and one was awarded a place on the all-tournament For this occasion, nice looking sweaters were ished the players by the business men inteJ in them. A girls' team was experimented playing a light schedule. Measles and such snowstorms as have not known in Gatlinburg for many years kep attendance down in midwinter. Other mot schools did close for two weeks. The total ^ meat was 364 and sixty-five of these were school students. Our Christmas entertainment was, as usua principal function on our entertainment list. C and boxes of toys and clothing were received clubs, chapters, and individuals to help in m this a wonderful experience for the children. ing the year plays were given by the sevent eighth grades and high school classes. E' beauty contest was held. A verse choir corn of twelve fifth and sixth grade children was novelty. In their little choir robes, led by teacher, Rosemary Moorehead, the members r many kinds of poems and were in great del= Our library has had good care. Two girls received six dollars per week from the Na Youth Administration fund for two hours' each day spent in caring for the library. The grade school basement where the children have their lunches at noon, has freshly painted by the Parent-Teacher Assoc Our closing exercises, because of the add. high school class, were somewhat changed the regular commencement activities, onl eighth grade pupils receiving diplomas. Paine of Sevierville, an old friend of the s delivered an excellent address. The F.F.T. presented their silver cup to the outstandini school girl and the Pi Beta Phi Alumnae awarded a cup to the outstanding boy. The staff for 1935-36 was: Eunice Weaver, Illinois Z, director. William King, principal. E. F. Kite, vocational agriculture. Gussie Smith, home economics later Lu </p>
      <pb ref="arr5310063_0003" seq="03" n="66-67  "/>
       <p>THE SEPTEMBER ARROW interest in every phase of the work. In her first year class which consisted of four-teen girls, beginning with home courtesies and personal grooming, the problems of clothing, foods, and planning and furnishing homes were taken up. This was followed by instruction for both classes by the nurse in child care and health of the family. The class of eleven sophomore girls took up canning and preserving, and later, clothing, ending with a fashion show at assembly for the whole school. Each girl had a tailor made dress. They planned, prepared, and served a dinner to the whole staff, the first year girls making favors and decorations. This was a wonderful occasion and showed originality. In March Lula Lee Carlock of Knoxville took over the work and carried out the regular program for the rest of the year. The home economics classroom is the busiest spot in the high school building. One is apt to find, outside of regular class hours, neighborhood women receiving instruction in dressmaking and other problems, costumes being made for some coming entertainment or perhaps a County Demonstration Agent explaining a new cooking gadget or attempting to interest the women in starting a wayside market. One of the greatest treats of the year for the girls is the trip to the University of Tennessee on Open House Day in the home economics building. The trip is made in the school truck and the greater part of the day spent in seeing the exhibit of the school of home economics and practice. In addition to her regular classes, the home economics teacher must be actively interested in the P.T.A., giving menus for the noon lunches. Also she gives a day each week to helping the nurse in the hospital. The school receives compensation from the state according to the number of hours she spends on adult work. Miss Smith accomplished 100 hours of outside work. Several programs for entertainment were given by the Home Economics Club for assembly. Agriculture Elmer Kite, graduate of the School of Agriculture, University of Tennessee, has been in charge of vocational agriculture the past year. His time has been divided between his classes in school, doctoring sick cows and horses in the community, answering inquiries along the line of crops and gardens, and conducting outside classes. As usual each boy had a project which was carried out at home or on the school farm. One day unit class of seventh and eighth grade boys was taught at Banner School in the fall to stimulate an interest in agriculture class work and induce them to come to school. Part time classes were taught in fall and spring, made up of boys of high school age who were not in school. These classes met one night each week. Due to a dry fall and a severe winter, very little use could be made of winter pastures ; consequently, more feed had to be bought than usual. The dairy herd was increased and milk production was good. Livestock, farm, and shop work were exhibited at the county fair, and six prizes were taken. A livestock judging team was taken to the University of Tennessee and the boys made several field trips visiting the best dairy herds in the county. English, history. math, French. foorehead, Illinois H, 5th and 6th !e, Nevada A, 4th and 5th grades. 1pbell, Oregon B, 3rd grade. nn, 1st and 2nd grades. bson, primer. edding, weaving supervisor, Iowa Arrow Craft Shop mana ffielcl, hotel shop. uarth, Illinois H, bookkeeper. almers, nurse. McDonald, dormitory and house r, weaving assistant. ton, Arrow Craft Shop assistant. e, farm. an, farm. ter, cook. Dormitory the usual run of attendance in the re were twelve boys and eight girls. umber of boys were third year high ;, as were three of the girls. Mrs. s, as usual, in charge. There has rit of harmony and cooperation and average of these students has been tt of the school as a whole, some t A's. dollars a month in cash, the balance and a half dollars for their room e worked out. Some students, how-worthiest are not able to pay even , and for them plans are made for ring the summer months. The fact to pay for the greater part of their foes not seem to interfere with their activities. We have been truly proud nts. maid lived in the dormitory with King and Mr. Kite stayed in Stuart e place had quite the air of a men's the boys living there, too. The boys er seem to lack amusement, for hours are over sounds of music, ng with guitar accompaniment, can often. Mrs. McDonald is a splendid )r in encouraging good work, she it a reasonable amount of recreation close family life, we become strong-each other during .the year, and ool is over. It is a deep pleasure to )ers to feel that we have had a part )ing of their characters and person-,e boys and girls seem thoroughly the advantages the dormitory life Home Economics artment of home economics, Miss a graduate of the University of Ten-e position of teacher until February was offered a position of Home Agent for Jefferson County, Tenrls adored Gussie and showed great THE SEPTEMBER ARROW For the first time we were represented in the F.F.T. speaking contest. Jimmie Hatcher won first place in the district contest his subject "Soil Conservation." He also entered the East Tennessee con-test, and, although he did not win, he made' a very good showing. Future Farmers of Tennessee The Future Farmers' organization held their meetings twice a month having fifteen members. They gave one party and had two picnics. A minstrel show was given to obtain funds so that four delegates could be sent to the state F.F.T. convention at Nashville this spring. Arrow Craft There is a steady growth in Arrow Craft. Alumnie clubs are in closer contact with it than with any other department of the school. Mrs. Snow, the shop manager, reports that 119 clubs, fourteen shops, sixty-seven individuals, and two active chapters handled Arrow Craft products this year. The branch shop in the Mountain View Hotel has been enlarged, making it possible for the manager, Mrs. Duffield, to display her stock to a better advantage. There arose a need in the Southern Handicraft Guild in which we hold membership, for an organization for promoting a larger market for its products. A corporation was formed in May, 1935, called the Southern Highlanders, Inc. Membership is composed of schools, philanthropic institutions, groups, associations, and individuals who are producers of handicrafts. Two shops were established one at Norris Dam and one in the Rockefeller Center in New York City. In these two plac well as at Allanstand in Asheville, our articb sold with those of the other handicraft center! it is hoped that the Smoky Mountain Park cc siori may also be obtained. The weaving department is now installed building of its own. This has made it possil take care of more weavers, furnishes comfo room for the weaving meetings, and room fc bulk of the Arrow Craft stock. Mr. Voorhies gave this building to the school, is greatly pl that it is so useful for the weaving, and ht helpful in putting it in order for that purp( Gene Redding, the weaving supervisor ar signer, has been eight years with the school. has given her close acquaintance with more one generation of weavers. Three courses of ing lessons were given to the weavers durir year, and fifty-five took these lessons. The ( grade girls attended a weaving class every noon from 1:45 until 2:45. Their last proji the year was making woolen material whict made into graduating dresses. Among the woven articles sold in the shot of the most popular was the Smoky Mist The gay colored fans made nice favors for p Recently at an A.A.U.W. convention dinr Knoxville, our fans were used as favors..A attached to each fan said: "Deep within the purple iris, Lies a heart of purest gold; So within our Smoky Mountains Countless beauties may unfold. Nature's treasures for the seeking For the traveller who sees. KKOC KI PROVINCE NO. CLUBS NOV. NO CLUBS StLLLN4, cAst-i Rectivu) oolD5 ON tti P 14 in i .zs s 678.92.. 5LtA z o z. .96157 285.17 CAMM(N s 3 ?748 is.7z D t.A..T (. 14 2sG.00 5ILON\ 10 8 566.05 49 Z7 ZETN 11 7 ZIS 71 331.zG L.Te\ z o 1 1150.78 95 T 1-1 LT P\ 4 1 1425.12 434 z; I OT I I10 00.78 505 BZ A PP(N Z 1 12 1960.45 3t zB L.P.\rNbD 7. 6 *50 56 313.8Z M.) 19 ., 2479 33 Tit Y1fuRt-5 REPRESENT WHOLESALE PRICES e,No ARE' A REPORT OF 6USINE55 \4 Tti~ 611385 TO rl P^'f 31 195G </p>
      <pb ref="arr5310063_0004" seq="04" n="68-69  "/>
       <p>THE SEPTEMBER ARROW -ithin this tiny favor may find a mountain breeze." Hospital ^er 1, Virginia Moore, who had been e past four years, gave up her pobe Public Health Nurse in Clarks-!e. Marjorie Chalmers of Galesburg, ook up her work. years of experience in family re-'are, and kindergarten training, aside Liar nursing experience, have given ackground for this position. Quoting "All sick or emergency calls have rt: [ either to aid the doctor, to give Ltment, or to make sure that home erly understood. School inspections ns were completed, pre-school and ere held, and a great many follow-up de. We have tried to keep up all infant welfare work, for we realized of a proper start in childhood. [cation has been carried on by classes d physiology, home hygiene and care classroom health talks, by distributand by friendly visits at home or in gical dressings and treatments have )spital equipment loaned in time of th patients to Sevierville, Knoxville, have been made when necessary. Id not be paid for by the patient, the Friends of the Mountain Children fling from 8:30 to 9:30 and each an, the hospital is open for dressings, ,culations, and advice. The fourth ch month continues to be a busy day rice." ter sanitation and better preventive treatment of disease, community higher standard than formerly. Stu dents in their homes, after having lived in the school, are responsible for much of this improvement. The County Health Department Blue Ribbon Day is a great incentive for keeping well. Children try to outdo each other in the matter of teeth, tonsils, inoculations, keeping clean, so as to be able to go to Sevierville and march in the parade on Blue Ribbon Day. We took first prize among the larger schools this spring, having 178 blue ribbons. Dr. Conroy, resident doctor, has taken a share of the responsibility from the shoulders of the nurse, especially in cases of pregnancy. The Health Center remains one of the most important phases of the business and service of the school, a worthy accomplishment. Office The office work has gone very smoothly and efficiently. Pauline Requarth, Illinois H, Decatur, Illinois, has been the bookkeeper the past year. The new system of cost accounting started in 1934 in Arrow Craft has been continued, and there has been no confusion in handling the accounts of the various departments. Keeping within the Arrow Craft and school budgets is the bookkeeper's foremost aim, and so far this year almost every account has been kept within its specified limits. With the cooperation of the alum= chairmen of Settlement School and their committees, many old accounts on the Arrow Craft books have been straightened out, and most of the accounts opened this year have been very successful. To you committee and Council, officers and loyal Pi Phis we are truly grateful. Your constant, warm-hearted interest and thoughtfulness have made it possible to continue this work of which we are so proud. It is almost too much to express in words, but as one of our smallest boys said to the nurse, "We'uns couldn't hev it, 'thout you-all to holp." Respectfully submitted EUNICE S. WEAVER PHI SETTLEMENT SCH EPORT ON AU IT L kit 3URER'S ACCOUNTS YEAR. ENED JUNE 30,193C August 7, 1936 e McCleverty, Treasurer ettlement School 5.2gton [CCLEVERTY: impleted the audit of your accounting !asurer of the Pi Beta Phi Settlement e year ended June 30, 1936. We a copy of the audit report of Messrs. aes and Co., Certified Public Account-vine, Tennessee, covering the opera-Settlement. School and Arrow Craft fiscal year as reflected by the books in Gatlinburg, Tennessee. We have ) the figures contained in this report s, and have prepared therefrom the ncial Statements showing the corn-of your operations for the year. ,ANCE SHEET-EXHIBIT 1 eposit at the Seattle-First National rifled by checking receipts and disa detail and reconciling with the ent. The remaining Current Assets were taken from the report of Homer K. Jones and Co. Endowment Fund Investments, listed in Exhibit 5, were verified by correspondence with Mrs. Lois F. Stoolman, Chairman of the National Board of Trustee Funds, and with the Harris Trust and Savings Bank, Trustee. Your books were adjusted to reflect changes in the investments and cash held in the Endowment Fund during the fiscal year. Fixed Assets are shown in detail in Exhibit 6, at cost and net depreciated values. Live stock is stated at inventory value as reported from Gatlin-burg. The Mortgage has been reduced by payment of $1,000.00 and a contribution from Mrs. H. Lutcher Stark of $325.00 to a balance of $500.00 on June 30, 1936. Interest was paid in full to June 30, 1936. NET WORTH The General Surplus is stated separately in Exhibit 2, showing the charges and credits during the fiscal year, resulting in an increase from $82,963.83 to $93,741.10 on June 30, 1936. Total THE SEPTEMBER ARROW Net Worth after adding the Reserve for School Endowment Fund ($35,926.33) was $129,667.43. SETTLEMENT SCHOOL INCOME and EXPENSE The combined results of your activities at Gatlinburg and the activities of the Settlement School Treasurer are stated in Exhibit 3, showing a net income of $222.68, which is carried to Surplus, Exhibit 2. ARROW CRAFT SHOP INCOME and EXPENSE The business of the Arrow Craft Shop resulted in a Net Income of $4,629.94, as shown by Ex-hibit 4. This amount is carried to Surplus hibit 2. CHAPTER CONTRIBUTIONS Exhibit 8 is a summary and accompanyin tailed lists of contributions by Alumna Club Active Chapters during the fiscal year. We found the books well kept. All nec adjusting and closing entries have been mac your books to bring them into agreement this report and to close the books as of Jun 1936. Respectfully submitted, R. C. MOUNSEY Certified Public Account BALANCE SHEET June 30, 1936 AssETs Current Assets: Cash on Hand and at Banks Accounts Receivable Arrow Craft Shop Inventories: Hotel Shop $ 628.14 Arrow Craft Shop 10,919.32 Weaving Supplies 4,806.92 16, Total Current Assets $ 29, Investments: School Endowment Fund Exhibit 5 $22,988.80 Deposits in Closed Bank 1,451.95 Total Investments 24, Fixed Assets: Land, Buildings, Equipment and Live Stock Exhibit 6 74, Deferred Charges: Unexpired Insurance, Exhibit 7 Amount Due School Endowment Fund Total Assets LIABILITIES AND NET WORTH Current Liabilities: Accounts Payable Arrow Craft Shop Fixed Liabilities: Mortgage Payable $ 500.00 Due School Endowment Fund 13,042.45 Total Fixed Liabilities Net Worth: Reserve for School Endowment Fund $35,926.33 General Surplus Exhibit 2 93,741.10 Total Net Worth Total Liabilities and Net Worth $143, ANALYSIS OF GENERAL SURPLUS June 30, 1936 Balance June 30, 1935, per Audit Report $ 82, Deduct: Light Plant written off, depreciated value $ 82, Add: Credit for depreciation taken on Woodcraft Shop Equipment returned, four yrs. @ 5% on $1,003.00 Mr. Voorhies Donation, Woodcraft Shop 7, $ 90, Add Profits for Year Ended June 30, 1936: School Operations Exhibit 3 Arrowcraft Shop Exhibit 4 4, $95, Deduct: Three-fourths Active Chapter Contributions, to Endowment Fund 1, Balance General Surplus, to Exhibit 1 $ 93, $ 7, 5,: 2, 13, ..--.. $143, 13, 129, </p>
      <pb ref="arr5310063_0005" seq="05" n="70-71  "/>
       <p>THE SEPTEMBER ARROW INCOME AND EXPENSE STATEMENT School Treasurer's Books Books Total Lctive Chapters, Exhibit 8 OumnM Clubs, Exhibit 8 ridividuals :y . ........................................................... .griculture $ 24.80 come Economics 80.00 ,.. . 107.85 products for living $1,889.98) 2,235.68 se, Livestock 3,529.43 296.15 579.11 nt ..... .. 4 00 . ........... . xe $6,981.82 $ 2,101.57 $ 2,101.57 11,721.63 11, 721.63 608.00 608.00 1,435.12 1,435.12 488.10 488.10 24.80 80.00 107.85 2,235.68 385.00 385.00 3,529.43 296.15 579.11 48.00 497.49 578.29 $17,236.91 $24,218.73 80.80 ........... ................................................. $ Ise (net) rice ense ............................................................ ............................................................ ............................................................ ............................................................ ............................................................ ............................................................ ............................................................ ............................................................ ............................................................ ............................................................ ............................................................ ............................................................ ................... . ...... slivery ........................................................... keep Id Improvements ..... . . . . ... .... ... . . . Lgriculture tome Economics Telegraph xses ............................................................ $ 77.49 $ 77.49 150.46 150.46 6.34 6.34 7.52 7.52 6.68 15.50 22.18 2,543.16 2,543.16 6.02 6.02 1,347.24 919.43 2,266.67 1,172.02 1,172.02 227,94 227.94 103.21 1,422.70 1,525.91 1,023.90 1,023.90 73.00 73.00 231.13 231.13 586.02 586.02 1,889.98 3,050.00 4,939.98 237.09 616.14 853.23 49.13 200.00 249.13 69.53 32.50 32.50 627.91 627.91 161.84 161.84 3,162.62 3,162.62 701.91 701.91 54.26 1,500.00 1,554.26 64.62 750.00 814.62 166.26 166.26 421.53 421.53 320.97 320.97 rise $8, 214.56 $15,781.49 $23.996.05 t Income, to Exhibit 2 $1,232.74 $ 1,455.42 $ 222.68 ARROW CRAFT SHOP, INCOME AND EXPENSE STATEMENT Sales Cost of Gross Goods Sold Profit $ 662.84 $ 421.28 $ 241.56 ........................................................... 16,072.93 8,763.85 7,309.08 ire 1.75 13.34 11.59 168.99 157.70 11.29 ifted Articles 1,364.41 1,018.99 345.42 :ems 3,930.79 2,898.92 1,031.87 Hotel Shop 4,209.69 2,350.72 1,858.97 $26,411.40 $15,624.80 $10,786.60 It. View Hotel Sales $ 580.68 Hotel Shop 205.00 Costs (net) 199.95 ise 119.60 ies ,316.72 4 city : 108.57 ;11aneous 151.32 50.77 71.20 Telegraph 595..49396 ,keep 174.55 270.60 :rise 47.40 37.49 87.89 -Southern Highlanders, Inc 75.00 ises ............... ............. 6,561.59 Lions $ 4,225.01 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW Other Income: Other Deductions: Adjustment, Accounts Receivable Short PI BETA PM SETTLEMENT SCHOOL FIXED ASSETS JUNE 30, 1936 Real Estate Buildings and Grounds: Fences and Walks $ 1,028.34 Water System 633.07 Chicken Houses and Root House 734.59 Barn 3,384.49 Hospital 2,000.00 Arrow Craft Shop 2,400.00 Mary Pollard Cottage 4,437.73 Industrial Building 25,006.57 Log Cabin '''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''-''''''''''''''' 114.91 School House 6,743.85 Stuart Cottage 2,011.02 Teacher's Cottage 6,727.71 Agricultural Woodcraft Shop 7,882.873 Small Buildings Shop 566.98 u64,02o6 Equipment: Industrial Building _ 3,405,03 2,745.00 Teachers' Cottaze 2,083.03 Mary Pollard Cottage ''''''''''''''''''''''''' 1,655.00 Stuart Cottage 1,000.00 Hospital 1,300.00 New Barn 650.00 Chicken Houses ~~~~~~~~'~~.~~~~~~~.~.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 250.00 Automobiles 1,48 5.10 14,573.1e Total ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' .' ' ' ' ' ' ' $78,594.22 Reserve _'_ Buildings and Equipment, Net Live Stock Inventory Total Fixed Assets, to Exhibit 1 CHAPTER CONTRIBUTIONS YEAR ENDED JUNE 30, 1936 Alumnx Active Clubs Chapters Alpha $ 784.95 $ 107.00 Beta 2,132.95 _ Gamma 380.00 . Delta 838.23 95.00 Epsilon 932.29 165.00 Zeta 296.00 164.00 Eta 1,725.00 Theta 675.36 Iota 962.48 273.30 Eagada 667.60 198.00 435.85 120.88 Mu 1,890.92 362.35 ... 6 ALUMNAE CLUBS Boston, Mass o 57.29 Buffalo, N.Y 60.00 Hartford, Conn. '''''''''''''''''' 125.00 New Haven, Conn 10.00 New York, N.Y 254.60 Rochester, N.Y 103.00 Syracuse, N.Y 100.00 Toronto, Ontario Westchester, N.Y 425.06 5.00 $ 784.95 Akron, Ohio $ 150.00 Charleston, W.Va. Cincinnati, Ohio 315~~ Cleveland, Ohio ~~~0 Columbus, Ohio 80.00 30 0 Delaware, Ohio .~~.~~~~~~~~~~~~ 5.00 80.00 6 CHAPTERS Ontario A $ Ontario B Maine A Vermont A Vermont B Massachusetts A New York A Nov` Scotia Alpha Pennsylvania B '... .".".'u Pennsylvania r .' ' ' ' " . ' " .' Ohio A O Ohio hio B West Virginia A </p>
      <pb ref="arr5310063_0006" seq="06" n="72-73  "/>
       <p>THE SEPTEMBER ARROW ey $ 32.95 W.Va 10.00 Jersey 150.00 12.00 460.50 25.00 Jersey 41.50 30.00 75.00 $2,132.95 Gamma .................. I.C .................. 40.00 ,.C 275.00 $ 380.00Maryland A $ 25.00 Dist. of Columbia A 15.00 Virginia A 10.00 Virginia r 16.00 North Carolina A 25.00 North Carolina B 25.00 South Carolina A 2.50 $ 118.50 . $ 65.00 Delta Epsilon ich $ 116.88 Ls, Mich 100.00 nd 40.00 Ind 3.50 200.00 3.30 Ld 30.00 50.00 Mich 16.81 20.00 nd 182.00 50.00 Idiana 15.00 'Iichigan 7.74 nd 3.00 $ 838.23 Tenn $ 34.88 59.91 Co 326.00 25.00 L 30.00 16.00 435.50 5.00 $ 932.29Michigan A $ 10.00 Michigan B 45.00 Indiana A 10.00 Indiana B 5.00 Indiana r Indiana A 25.00 95.00 Missouri A $ 50.00 Missouri B 15.00 Missouri 15.00 Kentucky A 35.00 Tennessee A '35 25.00 Tennessee A '36 25.00 165.00 Zeta Eta $ 100.00 ,la 2.50 35.00 a 15.00 5.00 25.00 85.50 Fla 10.00 18.00 296.00 a $ 1.00 20.00 12.00 ma, Ill 100.00 Club 350.00 Club 200.00 ;s Women's Club 100.00 Suburban 40.00 erly Glenhurston) 25.00 105.00 10.00 30.00 50.00 s 200.50 10.00 lb 350.00 Forest, Ill 25.00 41.50 25.00 30.00 $1,725.00Alabama A $ 15.00 Florida A 25.00 Florida B 100.00 Florida r 24.00 $ 164.00 Wisconsin A $ 50.00 Wisconsin B 10.00 Illinois A 10.00 Illinois B-A 40.00 Illinois E 10.00 Illinois Z 100.00 Illinois H 20.00 $ 240.00 ......... ............. ...................... THE SEPTEMBER ARROW Kappa Ames, Iowa ' " . ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " .w 89.00 Burlington, Iowa 38.00 Cedar Rapids, Iowa 45.00 Council Bluffs, Iowa 5.00 Des Moines, Iowa 57.93 Duluth, Minn 50.00 Grand Forks, N.D 5.00 Indianola, Iowa 15.00 Iowa City, Iowa 60.43 Minn 100.00 Mt. Pleasant, Iowa 65.00 St. Paul, Minn. Sioux City, Iowa ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 3100 ~00 Winnipeg, Manitoba 15.00 $ 675.36 Boulder, Colo $ 40.00 Casper, Wyo 40.00 Cheyenne, Wyo 25.00 Colorado Springs, Colo 14.92 Denver, Colo 400.00 Laramie, Wyo 30.00 Lawrence, Kan 85.26 Lincoln, Neb 25.00 Manhattan, Kan. '''''''' '''''' 125.00 Omaha, Neb. 100.00 Poudre Valley, ~~~.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 5.00 Pueblo, Colo Topeka, K. ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 17.30 Wichita, Kan 30.00 $ 962.48 Austin, Tex. ".".".".".v 86.80 Corpus Christi, Tex 29.01 Dallas, Tex 200.00 Fayetteville, Ark 10.00 Fort Smith, Ark 25.00 Houston, Tex 50.00 Little Rock, Ark 10.00 Muskogee, Okla_ 5.00 New Orleans, La 25.00 Oklahoma City, Okla 85.00 Okmulgee, Okla 15.00 Sabine District, Tex. '''''''''''''''' 28San Antonio, Tex. .79 '' ' ' ' ' '' ' ' '' ' ' ' 5.00 Shreveport, La 25.00 Stillwater, Okla. Tulsa, Okla. ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 5~ . 00 Tyler, Tex *.00 $ 667.60 Boise, Idaho " ."."."."."n 50.00 Calgary, Alberta 2.00 Corvallis, Ore 2.50 Edmonton, Alberta 10.00 Eugene, Ore 25.00 Portland, Ore 100.00 Salem, Ore 5.00 Seattle, Wash 136.35 pokane, Wash 40.00 acoma, Wash. Wenatchee, Wash. .~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 5~00 Yakima, Wash 10.00 Manitoba A ". " .".".w North Dakota A Minnesota A Iowa A Iowa B ~~~ Iowa r 15.0C ` South Dakota A ".".' " ."."w Nebraska B '''''''''''''''''''''''' ^^'~ Kansas A Kansas B Colorado A Colorado B ~~~ Wyoming A 20.0( Oklahoma A $ 50.01 Oklahoma B 25.01 Arkansas A 13.01 Texas A ~ ~~ ~=~~~~"B .~ ~ ~ "."."."."."."." 35.0i Alberta A $ 5.0 Montana A Idaho A .[~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 25.0 Washington 50.0 Washington B "."."." . " .. um Albuquerque, N.M. ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " . "w Calif 37.37 '140.00 El Paso, Tex 21.00 Fresno, Calif 50.00 Glendale, Calif 75.00 Hawaii, T.H 50.00 Long Beach, Calif. 60.00 Los Angeles, Calif. ~~ ~~ ~ ~ ~~ ~~ ~~ ~~ ~~~ 1,100.00 Palo Alto, Calif 10.00 Pasadena, Calif ' 50.00 Phoenix, Ariz 42.00 Reno, Nev 5.00 Salt Lake City, Utah 50.00 Santa Barbara, Calif 15.00 Calif 58.55 Sail Francisco, Calif Calif 30.00 Santa Monica, Calif_ .625.00 2.00 Tucson, Ariz 10.00 California A ' "mzu California B California r " . " . " .' " .' ' ' ~ 1 0 0 . ( California A '35 ' m* California A '36 ' " .' " . ' " . ' ' . . . mo Nevada A A ~~~~ ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ ~~ Utah A ...^ zn </p>
      <pb ref="arr5310063_0007" seq="07" n="74-75  "/>
       <p>THE SEPTEMBER ARROW COMPARATIVE FINANCIAL REPORTS FOR SETTLEMENT SCHOOL 1918-1935 1918 1919 1920 1921 1922 1923 $ 2,623.06 $ 3,363.45 $ 6,439.53 $12,463.52 $16,116.2o $18,o7o.96 62.00 _ 4o7.18 1,138.12 2,779.85 1,899.34 3,859.91 5,437.36 10,659.89 23,483.13 26,271.33 28,279.22 3,031.76 4,029.60 7,077.69 26,368.69 16,840.40 26,030.95 NO DATA AVAILABLE 23,085.95 1,055.96 1,892.o3 1,757.11 5,339.32 11,884.69 14,133.95 1924 1925 1926 1927 1928 1929 19,862.24 20,769.58 18,345.43 19,481.08 24,011.75 23,564.37 ions 2,148.18 2,638.97 2,412.58 3,048.98 3,212.60 3,455.25 32,997.95 38,371,45 43,207.21 45,960.38 35,225.62 54,331.92 25,953.50 32,582.74 37,432.40 36,200.34 24,956.30 59,015.92 21,854.70 27,541.90 33,828.63 20,609.01 20,691.79 18,566.39 10,694.54 14,291.05 9,470.91 11,641.56 6,791.62 6,732.04 1930* 1931** 1932 1933 1934 1935 23,340.57 21,297.88 16,768.35 11,040.45 12,902.35 11,335.01 ions 3,886.30 3,814.15 2,451.17 2,077.34 2,162.86 1,824.86 28,929.82 26,899.89 25,205.80 18,040.28 28,461.29 22,311.98 30,199.06 17,891.76 25,946.95 21,500.83 18,994.58 23,769.76 28,466.70 30,646.32 25,880.84 16,917.26 23,926.42 24,435.92 12,921.75 13,982.78 10,925.06 5,132.85 10,618.44 8,696.90 snditures not included beginning this year. 1 salaries paid by County not included beginning with this year. OF THE NATIONAL PANHELLENIC CONG DELEGATE FOR PI BETA PHI ions ESS the past two years may have meant cities individually, they seem to have rnities as a whole a more honest of facts and a greater willingness !r for common goals. The meeting thellenic Congress held last Decem-!r Park, Mississippi, had an atmos-.iness and mutual confidence which :dly missing from the immediately rence and which gives a renewed he ability of the fraternity system atinue but to become increasingly two years before there had been a seemed to emanate from fear that ld be discovered, this past year there .fission of weaknesses and open de-correcting them. Some fraternities n ever before, it is true, but some serious loss of ability to initiate e presents grave problems. While Pi Beta Phi believes that each fra-.ccept responsibility for developing rather than expect other fraternito weaken their own groups, not but for the future, in order to take y placed or developed chapters of s, she could not be a believer in tternity membership without wantaternity to give its best towards a .nd fair attempt to make it possible N.P.C. fraternities to continue to college campuses. This place will believes, when fraternity womenst of all, members of the strongest le a true appreciation for the things nities give to those who love and e enough knowledge of the organilents, and personnel of other fraterthat every fraternity has much of ers may be proud, admits to herself hat size and age are of themselves on of strength, and acts upon a be lief that choice and not competition should be the basis for placing chapters and for bidding girls. Much of the difficulty of the less well-established fraternities can probably be traced to the fact that they have preferred to establish themselves on campuses already too well filled and that their chapters, so placed, have believed that they must draw their members not from women students as a whole but from the much smaller group of women rushed by the better established fraternities. To ask for a quota system to limit the number of pledges which strong groups may take when approximately sixty per cent of the women students on the campus are without fraternity affiliations of any kind and when each girl pledged to any fraternity had been rushed by an average of five fraternities these are actual statistics for one campus, this year seems to indicate that there, at least, invitations to membership had been given too largely on the basis least wise for any group competition. It is probable that there is no chapter of any fraternity which has not, at some time, found that its strongest and most valuable active member has been not the most sought-after "prize rushee" but a less well-known and less conspicuous rushee whose true worth became increasingly evident up-on acquaintance. May Pi Beta Phi's representative call upon the members of this fraternity to meet their responsibility not to love their own fraternity less or to feel less keen a pride in its strength and prestige but to make that affection and pride basically sound because they are founded upon a realization of the strength, true worth, and fine personnel of other fraternities as well as their own ! The most emphasized problem of fraternities continues to be that of saving chapters which have become so weak that they are unable to attract enough members to insure their future. That this is a real problem is evident from the fact that during the two years between the last two National Panhellenic Congresses, forty chapters were with-drawn and only thirty-one were installed by N.P.C. THE SEPTEMBER ARROW fraternities. The quota system, which has been presented as a solution for this problem, is being increasingly forced upon college Panhellenics even though National Panhellenic Congress as such took no stand whatever in regard to the system but apparently attempted to gain the same objective by issuing a statement that fraternity relations are possible only within certain definitely stated numerical limits. In speaking at National Panhellenic Congress on the statistics collected by the Committee on College Panhellenics, L. Pearle Green, Kappa , Alpha Theta, chairman of the committee said: "These figures confirm the conclusion of the National Association of Deans of Women at its February 1935 meeting: that the quota system has not attained the hoped for end an equal distribution of pledges." She went on to say that the committee next tried to answer the question as to whether the alleged reason for adopting the quota system, which was the wide difference between the number of pledges to groups, was a new thing or only one brought into the limelight by the depression. The committee collected figures for six years 1929 to 1936. These figures were complete for many campuses and more than 50 per cent complete for over half the campuses, and showed that there was never a year of the six when there was not a wide divergence in the number of girls pledged different fraternities on any one campus. The committee also found that there were seldom two consecutive years when the chapter of the same fraternity had either the largest or the smallest group of pledges. The dangers which Miss Green said the quota system had emphasized were: 1. Willingness to alibi failure to secure pledges, to blame other groups instead of carefully analyzing the rush and one's own mistakes, or facing squarely the chapter's handicaps on that particular campus. 2. Friction within chapter and with alumni, because many quota systems lead to omission of legacies. 3. Weakening of prestige on campus for any group short the quota system on pledge day (even if such shortness is by preference) . 4. Growth of anti-fraternity sentiment among in-dependents, by the talk of embittered girls that the quota system prevented receiving invitations from the groups they desired to join. 5. Strengthening the undemocratic charges against fraternities, because outstanding girls are not pledged; girls whom the community does not know preferred independence to joining any group quota restrictions gave them a chance to join." Pi Beta Phi's delegate continues to urge the fraternity to stand against a system which discounts years of conscious effort to achieve results worthy of recognition in ability to attract the best type of college girl, which is basically unsound because it is unfair not only to well-established chapters but also to rushees, and which has been proved not to do the thing for which it was or4 promoted make it possible for the weakest on a campus to pledge enough and strong e girls to enable them to continue, regardless wisdom used in placing the chapters on the c or in developing them after they had been lished. Surely a wiser and more lastingl: solution is the one of building up a finer of interfraternity appreciation and friendline of getting away from the apparent goal of in strictly competitive rushing. This Convention, like those of other fratei is being asked by National Panhellenic Cong approve additions to the Standards of Ethica duct which will mean that fraternity wome go on record as believing that "It is benea standards of fraternity women to approac rushee who has signed a preference for a hat other than the one which they represent, , proposal to refuse to accept the bid indicate to wait for another bid" or "To fail to c during exchange visits as guests, the rules, tions, and customs of the colleges, dormitori chapter houses, which they are visiting." standards are only those of clean rushing am living which Pi Beta Phi has long held befc own members; it should welcome the oppo to take an open stand for them in its Panh relations. The latter statement represents new stand taken by National Panhellenic Cc in many years for fine standards of living can be and is followed by other united star the things which mean character and so, represent the ideals of fraternities, Nations hellenic Congress will become at last the for good which it could and should be. W fraternity will accept will not be done by fro members! During the interim of conventions, Pi Bet delegate has served first as a member of a committee to make a survey of rushing co! at present as a member of the Committee c Panhellenics. She attended the twenty-four tional Panhellenic Congress as official deleg had the very great pleasure and gratificat being able to present there all other meml Grand Council. She believes that the incre common practice of fraternities to have all members present at National Panhellenic CI means increased strength for the Congress, 1 lege Panhellenics, and for each fraternity officers are thus given an opportunity to kno^ fraternities through personal contacts wit] officers' and who is able to be known throug same contacts with its own officers. She has tried to make evident Pi Beta Ph cere desire to be a constructively contributi operating and friendly fraternity. Respectfully submitted, AMY BURNHAM Or EPO T OF COMMITTEE ON EXTENSION \ THE Committee on Extension presents the Pi Beta group of Louisiana State University for the consideration of convention. This group was organized by members of Pi Beta Phi and has the enthusiastic support of active and alumni members of the Fraternity who know them. All provinceand national officers who have visited the gr endorsing them. Pi Beta is located in an ins which is considered so favorably by rival f ties who are aggressive in extension that Kappa Gamma recently chartered a gr( colonizing. In presenting Pi Beta we offer </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



