<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr5930289_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Sale, Mildred Odell</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>March 1943</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr5930289_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">March 1943</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Sale, Mildred Odell</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 288-294</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">39</note>
                        <note type="Folder">11</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 59, Number 3 (March 1943), Pages 288-294.</note>
			<note type="document">arr5930289_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Our Pi Beta Phi Settlement School Service Flag; Dividends for Pi Beta Phi; Meet the Arts and Crafts Advisory Committee</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Health care</item>
                                <item>War </item>
                                <item>Military</item>
                                <item>Staff</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr5930289_0001" seq="01" n="288-289  "/>
       <p> lllll 1181414, NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON Edited by MILDRED ODELL SALE, North Dakota A Isoututti.441. lllll .1elismusssliswe lllll stetti.s.1444144H.1144.14.4si,ututitseatsoutIluts....s4lItiter Our Pi Zeta Phi Settlement School Service Flag Not waiting for the draft, many of this year's High School students at the Settlement School have already enlisted. One of these, deciding to join the Navy, sold most of his clothes and belongings and started of, boasting he would not be back until it was over over there." But the recruiting office ruled him too young and sent him home again. So, Our Wintry Trees he bought more clothes and returned to school to stand the teasing of the school-mates before whom he had boasted. More fortunate in attaining their goal were Wade King, Lee Trentham, Jr., John Wilson, Reuben Reagan, and Ray Sutton, now doing their bit with the Navy and Dave King, a private in the Army. In the Air Corps is Charles Cope, while Ray Large is already in active service with the Marines at Guadalcanal. And with the WAACs is Edna Mc-Carter, formerly assistant to Ethel Snow in Arrowcraft. Two of last year's graduating seniors are also with the Army Army Corps Roger Huff at Lincoln, Nebraska, and Van Ogle at Miami, Florida. There are many other Pi Phi graduates in army, navy and air service. Were we to have a Service Flag at the Settlement School it would be bright with stars! The Settlement School serves as the center of all war activity in the community. Gatlin-burg is organized under OCD regulations for air-raid protection, with our Health Center an emergency First Aid shelter. Several practice black-outs have already been held. Our School facilities house all Civilian Defense meetings, registration for the Selective Service, and for sugar and gasoline ration books, and served as Headquarters for the Scrap Drive. With the aid of Settlement School children, a large wooden bin built on the Arrowcraft driveway, was filled twice to overflowing and netted 36,000 pounds to smash the japs! Even the curriculum is geared to wartime needs with emphasis on physical education, first aid classes and talks on nutrition, to assist our government in its plans for building strong bodies as well as strong minds. SURGICAL DRESSINGS, Too One of the biggest contributions of the School to the war effort is the Surgical Dressing Workroom. Located in the loom room, just off the Home Economics department, it houses four large work tables, covered with black oilcloth. Red Cross posters, and large. American and Red Cross flags on the walls look down every afternoon, and two evenings each week, on the busy hands of the women of the community folding bandages. At the evening sessions, the Settlement School teachers and staff are regular attendants. Mrs. Evelyn Creswell is Chairman for the County, with a different local woman serving as chairman each day. Since August they have supervised the making of over 59,000 dressings. Besides these Surgical Dressings, 150 "Buddy Bags" are being made, part of the money for which was secured from the sale 288 THE MARCH ARROW 289 of the scrap metal, collected by the School and donated to the Red Cross. Just before Christmas, some 125 gifts were packed for the patients at the Camp Forest Hospital. Members of the Gatlinburg Red Cross chapter also assist the Canteen in Sevierville, where workers serve hot meals to boys re-turning from Fort Oglethorpe after their first physical examination. OUR HOME FRONT But perhaps the most important contribution of our Pi Beta Phi Settlement School to the "Home Front" is its continuance to uphold the same high standards of education and citizenship it has always maintained, even though they must now be carried on by a staff sorely depleted by wartime calls, and among a community whose main source of revenue, the tourist trade, has been jeopardized by gasoline rationing. Some have found employment in nearby war plants, to be sure, but "our" weavers, unable to earn except by weaving, still rely on "you-uns" to educate their children and to market their products that they may continue to maintain the standard of living Pi Beta Phi has brought to their mountainside. Dividends for Pi eta Phi These two alert youngsters are future citizens of Gatlinburg. Had Pi Beta Phi not brought its Settlement School to the Tennes Future Citizens see mountains in 1910 these boys would face a future far from bright. They could then have looked forward to only a few years' education in a poor rural school, and after that a lifetime of poverty on their rocky mountain farm. But today the prospect is infinitely better. They will go to a school much above the average for rural Tennessee, and be able to complete at least a high school education. Chances of going still farther are about fifty per cent. Out of a class of 25 seniors graduating last June, twelve are continuing their education and two have joined the Army Air Corps, one of the most popular "institutions of learning" for the youth of today. Three of last year's seniors are at the University of Tennessee, two at Tennessee Polytechnic Institute, three at the Knoxville Business College, while others attend Carson-Newman College, Maryville, Lincoln Memorial University and the Berry Schools. Of the twenty graduating in 1941, Irene and Wayne Cardwell and Nannibel Whaley are attending East Tennessee State Teachers College for their second year. Stuart Medlin, salutatorian, attended the University of Tennessee last year; Annette Ogle, valedictorian, was at Stevens College; and Betty Ogle at Austin Peabody Normal. Two others took business courses at Knoxville, as did three of the 1940 graduates. Another 1940 senior attended Maryville College; while Edward Rochelle, after a year at the University of Tennessee, became a C.C.C. Sergeant and is now with the United States Army. But when these boys have* completed their education, what will they do ? Perhaps one of them might prove to be another Ben Fleming and return to Gatlinburg to teach in our Pi Phi School, as Ben after completing his high school at Murphy Collegiate Institute at Sevierville where his training as a dormitory student at Gatlinburg provided him with the experience needed to take charge of the school garden, and after receiving an A.B. degree from Tusculum College returned, and remains today as superintendent of the school. Other teachers who graduated from Gatlinburg include Buna Cardwell and Gladys Trentham, now married, both formerly with the Sevier County school system ; Henry Ogle, teaching two and a half miles from the Settlement School; Helen Ogle, teacher at Mc-Cook.-ville ; and Evelyn, her sister, formerly the teacher at Elkmont. Or these boys might follow in the foot-steps of one of the Carr children. This family deserves some sort of special mention in our Pi Beta Phi history book, for all eight of them have been closely associated with our </p>
      <pb ref="arr5930289_0002" seq="02" n="290-291  "/>
       <p>290 THE MARCH ARROW School, the oldest as one of those community-spirited citizens of Gatlinburg who donated to make the school possible, and all other seven as students. Isaac Carr finished at Carson-Newman College, attended a French University after having helped win World War I, taught in Tennessee, attended North Carolina and Duke Universities, and received his LL.D. from Carson-Newman in 1940. For fifteen years prior to last July he was Dean of the History Department at Mars Hill College; now a Captain in the Army Quartermasters, stationed at Arlington, California. While not a student from our School he surely evidences the great ability of Gatlinburg's people. Richard Carr also received his degree from Carson-Newman, attended a French University after service in the war, was elected Principal of the High School in West Jefferson, North Carolina, and served as Principal of Trenton and Bakersville High Schools be-fore retiring to take care of over 400 colonies of honey bees. G. Mitchell Carr entered Smoky Mountain Academy for high school after completing all Pi Phi then had to offer ; graduated from Carson-Newman in 1932, attended North Carolina University, and has since served as Principal at Belmont, North Carolina, and Superintendent of Schools, Dallas, North Carolina. And the Carr daughters ? They also went on to school Rose and Lytha one year each at Carson-Newman College, while Ethel not only graduated from this College but taught four years in Jefferson City grade schools. All are now married Ethel to a shop fore-man (Mr. Moore) and Rose to Mr. Huff, both with the Aluminum Company at Alcoa, Tenn. Lytha is also Mrs. Moore, and her husband is with the Southern Railway at Knoxville. Bertha and Charles completed only through the eighth and seventh grades at our Pi Phi School, as the family moved to Jefferson City, Tennessee, where both finished high school. Bertha went on to Knoxville Business College, married a T.V.A. employee, and Charles, after serving two years as Deputy in Jefferson County, is now training for M.P. duty at Fort Custer, Michigan. Or these youngsters on the steps of our Pi Beta Phi School may be like David Butler, who went on to Lincoln Memorial University from ,Gatlinburg, where he was head of electrical maintenance, and later worked part time as an electrical engineer at the Aluminum Company of America plant while at-tending the University of Tennessee, until his outstanding work in electrical installations made his full time demanded by Alcoa ; or they may find other positions with Alcoa as have so many recent graduates, including Clyde Houser, 1940 class; Ray Benson and the two Roys (McCarter and Ogle) of the 1941 class. Then there is Fred Cooper who attended the University of Tennessee, and returned to Gatlinburg as electrician, plumbing and heating engineer, and was given the contract for this work on Stuart Dormitory last year. Fred is now in active service "somewhere in the Pacific." Chances that these boys will return to Gatlinburg and become leading businessmen are great. At least three-fourths of the business houses and property of the Burg is owned and operated by former students. Be-cause of Pi Phi's educational contribution they were alert to their opportunities when the Smoky Mountain Park was opened, and met the need for tourist accommodations so adequately that the government did not build any in the park. The two Huff brothers, jack and Jim who married Pi Phis Pauline Whaling and Henrietta McCutcheon, teachers at the School, are numbered among Gatlinburg's businessmen jack owning and operating the Lodge on Mt. LeComte and Jim owning a lumber mill and also operating one of Gatlinburg's finest tourist courts. And Stella Huff Cox, who attended East Tennessee State Teachers College at John-son City, Virginia Intermont and Maryville Colleges, taught in Sevierville and then for five years at the Pi Phi School, owns and operates "Cox's Cabins" with her husband, Bill Cox, also a former teacher at the School. Then there is Mattie Huff Lawson, a Pi Phi from Ames, where she studied institutional administration, managing the tea room at the Rocky Waters Tourist Court. And the Oakley sisters, Martha (now Mrs. Rawlings) and Lucinda (now Mrs. Ogle), have the Rawlings and the Riverview Cabins. (You remember Lucinda and her family received a trip to the New York World's Fair as the most typical East Tennessee family.) But perhaps these boys favor hotels more THE MARCH ARROW 291 than tourist cabins. Here again their chances are good. Of the four Gatlinburg hotels, three are owned or operated by former Settlement School students the New Gatlin-burg Inn by Rellie Maples, who studied at the University of Tennessee to become a County Agent ; the Riverside by Bruce Whaley, who also attended the University of Tennessee; and the Greystone by Dick Whaley. Or will these boys be filling station owners? Perhaps not until gasoline rationing is a thing of the past. But here again other graduates have led the way, as evidenced by Bruce Maples and Mayford Clabo, a graduate of business college and formerly with the Bureau of Public Roads. Or like Arl McCarter, they may return from school to establish stables of riding horses for tourists. Or like Elder Ogle, they may join the Navy, and like him, return after four years, to be Gatlinburg's postmaster. Xan Davenport, after Murphy Collegiate Institute, was Director of NYA work in Sevier County, and now heads a large trucking crew in Panama. These boys may even equal the record of Earl Ogle, a graduate of the Tennessee Military Institute, who, when only twenty-one years of age, was elected to be the youngest squire in the county. Other graduates excel in varied occupations. Mrs. Dick Ownby opened the first gift shop in Gatlinburg and won the envy of others in the community by visiting Mrs. Coolidge in Washington. Two former students are aiding Uncle Sam in his shipyards, Tobie Blalock and Charles Conner; while Joy and Sherrill Clabo are among those assisting in the armed forces. Sanford Woodlief is in construction work with the Highway Department. A talented English student, Jeannette Newman, was assistant in the News Department of the Gatlinburg News from 1939 to 1942 ; and Rebecca Smith, daughter of a former Pi Phi School dietitian followed in her mother's footsteps at a cafeteria in Knoxville until her marriage. Besides Mr. Fleming at the Settlement School, former students of the School hold positions as assistants in the Arrowcraft Shop, and as the director of work on the school farm, and many hold clerical positions in Gatlinburg or Knoxville. Still others have taken advantage of their education in the crafts. Five members of the Los Reagan family are together in a wood-craft business, making beautiful furniture; Hettie Carr assists her mother with weaving and her father with his 97 beehives. Emma Franklin is the "farmer" at the Franklins, and Osa Ownby is raising poultry near Pigeon Forge using modern accepted methods which were unknown in Gatlinburg before Pi Phi's arrival. And so we might continue with many more former students of the Pi Beta Phi School on the hill ; but surely these examples are sufficient to show to all that there are real, tangible and heart-warming "dividends" from the time, talent, and money invested by members of Pi Beta Phi in Gatlinburg. And that these dividends are sincerely appreciated by their fellow citizens is evidenced, by the Chamber of Commerce, the only one of its kind in an unincorporated town in the United States, on whose board of seven, five Pi Beta Phi School graduates won places by election of the townspeople Dick Whaley, Jim Huff, Sue Cox, Elder Ogle, and Mayford Clabo. These and other former students are molding opinion in Gatlinburg, making it a city of which to be proud, and bringing continued respect and admiration for the teachings of that "bunch of righteous, resolute gals bent on givin' our young-uns book larnin' " who first brought a vision of a brighter future to the bare-footed children of an isolated mountain community. Meet the Arts and Crafts Advisory Committee By this time you have all had your In-formation Number of the ARROW and have read the enthusiastic and informative report on the Settlement School presented by Ethel Copp, Chairman of the Settlement School Committee. Just in case that issue of the ARROW arrived on one of those days when you hadn't a moment to spare and you tucked it away until you had more time, look it up now and turn to page 44. That is where Ethel's report starts, and when you come to page 46 you will read about the newly formed Arts and Crafts Advisory Committee and know that three members of the staff of the University of Tennessee, Miss Jessie Harris, Miss Ida Anders, and Miss Marion Heard, constitute that group. We on the Settlement School Committee </p>
      <pb ref="arr5930289_0003" seq="03" n="292-293  "/>
       <p>292 THE MARCH ARROW were mighty proud when these three grand people said they would serve in this capacity. It is fortunate for Pi Beta Phi that women such as these three have become so vitally interested in our Settlement School. As you know, Gatlinburg is only forty miles from Knoxville, the home of the University of Tennessee. Miss Anders and Miss Harris own a charming summer home in Gatlinburg and Miss Heard is a frequent visitor to the Burg. They are friends of everyone there. The staff members at the School seek their advice constantly, and the people of the community respect their judgment. The members of the new Arts and Crafts Advisory Committee know our School; they know our mountain people our weavers, our basket makers, our cabinet makers all of our crafts people who look to us to provide an outlet for the sale of their handicrafts. If you want a broader view of the really fine thing which is being done in Gatlinburg by Pi Phi read Allen Eaton's Handicrafts of the Southern Highlands. Mr. Eaton is from the Russell Sage Foundation and is greatly interested in the development of the native arts and crafts. He says, "Often the preparation of de-tailed designs is not as much needed as an advisory service on styles, colors and trends. This is true where there are good teachers and able weavers who can carry out ideas if given suggestions. If an advisory service could be made available to these teachers, they could continue to develop their own ideas and encourage the workers to do like-wise and thus adapt their wares to the market. This would encourage originality upon which the advancement of the crafts must always depend. The environment and temperament of the Highland people combine to encourage new expressions in various kinds of work, and a little good teaching leads to much independence and inventiveness." Mr. Eaton also goes on to say, "It is obviously easier to criticize suggestions made than to formulate workable substitutes. And it is far better that those who have ideas about improving the handicrafts should be encouraged to test them, for often to try out new ideas will be the only way to prove whether or not they are practical and feasible." "Leave wide open the doors of experimentation for all who participate. Through the freedom of a trying-out process will come the only way short of regimentation to pro mote production, and it is assuredly the only way to build up a body of rural arts which will have the vitality to endure. The cooperation of planners, designers, stylists, from both within and without the mountain area, is indispensable to the continuation of the handicrafts; but cooperation from the out-side will avail little if the people themselves are not encouraged to experiment continuously." Mr. Eaton emphasizes, "Cooperation from the outside will avail little if the people themselves are not encouraged to experiment continuously" ; that is where we are so fortunate in the personnel of our Arts and Crafts Advisory Committee. They know the people and are loved by them; they know the abilities of the mountain people and will provide the encouragement to "experiment continuously." We have a wonderful opportunity to help with an enlarged crafts program. Our set-up is ideal. Mr. Eaton says there are three elements involved design, production, and distribution and all must be worked out together. A few Pi Beta Phis may have suggestions for design (I'd love to hear about them if you care to write me) ; the mountain people themselves must take care of production, but each and every one of us can help with the distribution. If our plans are made and we are ready to help the mountain people increase their production, when the boys come back from the war and the munition workers return to their mountain homes; are we not contributing directly to the war effort ? Arrowcraft has always insisted upon the highest standards in weaving, and these standards have been a contributing factor in the improvement of quality, design, color, and serviceability of all articles sold through Pi Beta Phi. In the December ARROW there was an account of the lovely experience the Boston Club had at the Handicrafts Show held there October 6 and 10. Beth LeRoy is priceless! You must hear her story of their difficulties. This was the first of the Handicraft Shows it is wonderful to think that we were pioneers in the field of education in the Smokies and that now we may be in on the ground floor of a nation-wide handicrafts movement. Allen Eaton was at the Show and made the statement that we have only touched upon the creative art for which the mountain people THE MARCH ARROW 293 have great ability. So our opportunity to help is great. There are new things at Arrowcraft and we have plans for many more. In case you have forgotten what some of them are look on page 60 of the September ARROW where Mildred Sale tells about "Additions to Arrowcraft." It is such fun being on this Committee. I wish I might share the inspiration of it with each and every one of you. Our Arts and Crafts Advisory Committee is making a definite contribution to our work, so won't you, too, help with this wonderful project which binds us together so loyally, and which brings sincere admiration from those outside our Fraternity ? Remember to place your magazine subscriptions through the Pi Beta Phi Magazine Agency, and help with your sale of Arrowcraft products, and always keep alive that interest in your Pi Beta Phi Settlement School at Gatlinburg. The member of the Settlement School Committee who wrote the above article, and who is the contact between the Committee and the Arts and Crafts Advisory Committee, is Ann Leichliter Munn (Mrs. Hiram A.), Iowa r. She also serves the Committee as secretary. After attending Iowa State College, where she was a member of Iowa I' and of A (I) A, Ann graduated from the Chicago Academy of Fine Arts. Here she taught Costume Design, and returned to Iowa State as instructor in the Applied Art Department. Despite the fact that her three children, Fritz, Deborah Ann, and Elizabeth, keep her actively assisting with their various hobbies and activities, Ann is president of the Ames Alumnae Club of Pi Phi, secretary of the Investment Company which owns the chapter house, and secretary to the Ames City Planning Commission. But you would know Ann best if you could see the lovely photographs, the clever wood-carving, and the stunning and unusual embroidery which are just a part of her many hobbies. She too, modestly did not send us a photograph. Ida Adelaide Anders, Iowa r, is chairman of the Arts and Crafts Advisory Committee. She is professor and head of Textiles and Clothing at the University of Tennessee. She received both her B.S. and M.S. from Iowa State College, and is a member of 0 N, and was assistant professor in Home Economics. Formerly state supervisor of Home Economics in Florida, she did teaching in the summer sessions at the University of Illinois and Teachers College, Columbia. At present she is a member of the Student Club Advisory Committee of the American Home Economics Association. Miss Jessie W. Harris was chosen as Con Ida Adelaide Anders, Iowa Jessie TV. Harris, Tennessee A </p>
      <pb ref="arr5930289_0004" seq="04" n="294-295  "/>
       <p>294 THE MARCH ARROW vention initiate at Asheville in 1938 because she had won national recognition in her field and because she had rendered invaluable service to our Settlement School project over a period of years. Miss Harris is professor and director of the School of Home Economics, University of Tennessee, A.B., B.S., A.M. She was formerly State Home Demonstration Agent for the State of Texas, associate professor at the University of Nebraska, state director of Home Economics in Texas. A member of 0 N and (I K I), Miss Harris is president of the American Home Economics Association, which she has served in various executive capacities. Miss Marion G. Heard, although not a Pi Beta Phi, has been intensely interested in the work being done at Gatlinburg. She has a B.S. in Ceramic Art from Alfred University, Alfred, N.Y., and an M.A. in Fine Arts from Teachers College, Columbia. She is now an associate professor of Craft Design at the University of Tennessee. Marion G. Heard Pi Beta Phi Magazine Subscription Blank (Send to Pi Beta Phi Magazine Agency, Marshall, 111.) Date Subscriber's Name: Address Magazines Requested Price $ Price $ Price $ (Indicate if new or renewal, when to begin, and how long to send) Total amount of money order or check made out to Pi Beta Phi Magazine Agency, Marshall, Illinois $ Credit the subscription to (Give name of alum= club, active chapter) Signed: Address hat a Fraternity Girl Thinks NOTE : These articles were selected by the Editor of this section, Mrs. Armstrong, and the Editor of the ARROW as being most representative and most interesting of those which came in. This year the percentage of chapters contributing increased, and so did the general quality of the contributions. Of Leadership It seemed irrational that one should be sitting in a public park of a busy city while humanity about her gushed toward busses and cars. Our work day was ended. Eight hours of materialistic phrases Priorities, Al-location, War Production had warped my spirit. Then I saw the two fountains. From identical bases the columns of water spurted upward six feet. Here each tube deviated into a spray as fountains do. A second glance assured me that one was more appealing to contemplate than its sister. The latter was functioning perfectly, achieving symmetry of action and design. The former, part of whose column was above the planned level of the spray and the remainder of which behaved independently of expectation, evoked inspiration. Is it not true that we are too often followers ? We're content to pursue a planned course and willing to wait for another to tell us what to do. Such a life is uninspiring in normal times, and now is selfishly un-American. How much beauty there is in that life which is independent of the average! Today there is necessity for leaders who possess individuality of thought and can transmit their foresight to others. The fraternity girl should be such an initiator. She has the advantages f an organization which fosters leaders. Her potentialities can be exercised by first advancing the worth of her chapter. When these become stronger she is prepared to assume the responsibilities of a chaotic world. Let us be women who need no prodding, individuals who are ahead of the field. Then we attain truth and beauty. Remember this challenge: there are two fountains! MADALYN BORN, Michigan B Fraternity Enthusiasm Fraternity enthusiasm is one of those things not quite tangible and yet so conspicuously present among each of our chapters. The necessity of making a speech about fraternity enthusiasm never arises, for it is ever pres ent. It is indoctrinated as a spirit, something instilled in each of our hearts as our fraternity associations grow in richness and in knowledge. The little, trivial things about fraternity enthusiasm are what make it so important. The feeling we have when we sing a fraternity song that brings tears to our eyes, the sincere feeling of sisterhood we have toward each girl in our group, the proud tone we may rightfully use when we say "I'm a Pi Phi." These little things go to make fraternity enthusiasm. This spirit, this enthusiasm is essential to our continuance. There can be no cooperation, no truly good times, no success in any undertaking without it. Now more than ever before, we must keep this burning in our hearts. There are so many things, if we will permit them, to take away the true joy of living, but it is our duty to overcome them. The enthusiasm of Pi Beta Phi is some-thing big and not easily overcome, for upon this rests the foundation of our fraternity, the life-cord, not to be sacrificed for a worth-less cause. CHARLENE BAGGETT, Missouri r National Sisterhood Frequently a girl feels that all Pi Phi tradition and feeling is ' centered in her chapter alone for, with the exception of brief visits from grand officers and province executives, it is the only active instrument that can mold a girl, or have great influence toward making her a true Pi Beta Phi. So often we Pi Phis find that we are thinking only in terms of chapters, and are too tied up in our little house projects to realize that we are just a few among many that Pi Beta Phi is a national fraternity, and that we have sisters all across this far-flung nation who wear and love the arrow in exactly the same way as we. But the war has already brought a great change to Pi Phi, and will undoubtedly bring many more. For the first time some of us are realizing the true meaning and warm feeling of national sisterhood. We see, with a glow 295 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



