<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr5410023_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Settlement School Reports </title>
                        <author><name> Holton, Lillian Beck</name></author>
                        <author><name>Weaver, Eunice S.</name></author>
                        <author><name>Snow, Ethel M.</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>September 1937</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr5410023_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">September 1937</date>, Settlement School Reports </title>
                        <author><name> Holton, Lillian Beck</name></author>
                        <author><name>Weaver, Eunice S.</name></author>
                        <author><name>Snow, Ethel M.</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 23-39</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">39</note>
                        <note type="Folder">2</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 54, Number 1 (September 1937), Pages 23-39.</note>
			<note type="document">arr5410023_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Chairman of the Settlement School Committee July 1, 1936 to June 1, 1937; Pi Beta Phi Settlement School- Report on Audit Treasurer's Accounts Year Ended June 30, 1937; Director of the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, 1936-37; Arrow Craft Report, 1936-37; Weaving Report- June 30, 1936 to June 1, 1937; Jennie Nicol Health Center; Home Economics Department Term- 1936-1937; Report on Dormitory, 1936-1937; Principal's Annual Report, 1936-193</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Staff</item>
                                <item>Curriculum</item>
                                <item>Health care</item>
                                <item>Funding</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr5410023_0001" seq="01" n="22-23  "/>
       <p>T H SEPTEMBER ARROW a complete inventory of the supplies nt of the Central Office is given to This year the Central Office was purchase a new file for the geotion of the card file which greatly filing of that section. al Office has been fortunate in having Pi Beta Phi national officers as visar: Lois Franklin Stoolman, Grand :arianne Reid Wild, Assistant to the President; Florence Hunt Webster, Assistant to the Grand President; Helen Glessner Scott, Delta Province President; Agnes Hildebrand Daniel, Epsilon Province President. In closing, the Director of the Central Office wishes to thank the members of the Grand Council and the national officers for their assistance and loyalty; and the chapters, clubs, and individuals for their kind cooperation. Respectfully submitted, BEATRICE S. PURDUNN Director, Pi Beta Phi Central Office STANDA IZATION AND SU VEY RECEIVING EXCEPTIONALLY HIGH Cooperation with Central Office GRADES (5% out of a possible 5%) Cooperation Virginia r Indiana r .age from eight to nine grades) Missouri B Kentucky A Tennessee A Illinois Z 9.90 Iowa Z Kansas B 8.91 Louisiana B California 21 9.91 Arizona A a A 9.73 9.87 9.96 Financial Responsibility (an average from two to four grades) 9.94 9.99 5% out of a possible 5%) 9.82 Wisconsin B Vermont B 9.80 Illinois B-O Pennsylvania B Illinois B D.C. A Minnesota A Virginia A Michigan A Missouri B ixtra-Curricular Activities Kansas A Texas B Vermont A Montana A % out of a possible 20%) A Illinois B-ZS,, CHAPTERS RECEIVING EXCEPTIONALLY LOW Wyoming A GRADES s A Oklahoma A Texas A Louisiana A Montana A California T Internal Organization Illinois H Nebraska B Kansas A North Carolina A South Carolina A Florida I' Extra-Curricular Activities Wisconsin A Nebraska B Internal Organization Kansas B Idaho A % out of a possible 15%) California B D.C. A Virginia A Maryland A Illinois B-Li North Carolina A North Carolina B Indiana Missouri T Indiana A Michigan A Michigan B Cooperation with Central Office Ohio B Pennsylvania B Louisiana A Ontario A South Carolina A California A Vermont A South Dakota A Nebraska B H[AIRMAN ENDOWMENT FUND COMMITTEE year has been a busy one for the of the Endowment Fund Committee. thought and careful planning the i.RE OFF TO THE RACES" contest ted and the idea was presented to the the May ARROW. On October 1 go out to_the entire membership giving )f the contest. Province presidents and Province vice-presidents were contacted to ask their help in presenting this contest to their groups and to urge them to see that the Endowment Fund was given a place on all Province Conference programs. The Committee was most fortunate to be able to have Margaret Tasher Smith, publicity chairman for the Fund, present the interest idea to Pi Phis in twenty THE SEPTEMBER ARROW cities while she was on a trip in the South and East. Key Pi Phis in these cities were previously contacted in order that arrangements could be made for her visit. With the beginning of this new year the contest will be begun in earnest. Every Pi Phi will be given the opportunity to credit her pledge or contribution either to her own chapter or to her nearest alumnm club. By wholeheartedly entering into this "race," which will be equally fair to groups of all sizes, clubs and chapters will not only fill the treasury of the Endowment Fund but they will benefit from it as groups if they are among the three winning chapters and the three winning clubs. This is true because of the awards that are to be given, the winning club and the winning chapter each to be awarded the opportunity of sending a member to the 1938 Convention. The club and chapter thus rewarded should benefit because of the opportunity afforded them to have Convention "taken back" to them by one of their own members. It should benefit the Fraternity generally by creating a certain amount of Convention enthusiasm. Other awards will be fifty dollars and twenty-five dollars to clubs and chapters in second and third places. The progress of the contest will be presented in each ARROW until the 1938 Convention. It has been a real pleasure to work out the plans for this contest with the members of the Committee and Grand Council. The plan is submitted to the membership of the Fraternity with the earnest hope that it will create the required amount of interest and enthusiasm in clubs, chapters and individuals to bring into the Fund $12,000-the amount required to complete the desired $50.000. Every Pi Phi should wish a part in establishing this Fund which means so much to the development, both present and future, of the Fraternity. Respectfully submitted, LOIS SNYDER FINGER MAN OF THE SETTLEMENT SCHOOL COMM][TT July 1, 1936 to June 1, 1937 On October 1 an important letter will a out to every Pi Phi from the Endowmei Fund Committee. Be sure to note its conten and be one of 28,000-(or whatever membership is at present) to respond to iappeal. Your interest and cooperation in th project will make possible both the preset and future development of Pi Beta Phi. There are only three things which dui and chapters should bear in mind if the wish to win the greatest number of points i the Endowment Fund Contest. 1. The larger the per cent of the men bership contributing, the more points tit club or chapter will receive. 2. The more donations it can get from il members or from alumnae unaffiliated wit a club, the more points it will receive. 3. The more money it can send in, th more points it will receive, Every one of Pi Beta Phi's eighty activ chapters has at some time contributed to Endowment Fund. During the years 193 and 1937 all but three of the eighty sent in contribution. Was YOUR chapter one of th three that failed the Fraternity? Will yo see that it contributes this year? All one hundred and eighty-eight alumni clubs of Pi Beta Phi have at some time cor tributed to the Endowment Fund. The Ian est total amount sent in by any club is $93( contributed by the Kansas City AlumrL Club. What do you think your club's cor tribution should be this year? la CHAI THE fine condition in which my predecessor, Frankie Cochran Hill, turned over the affairs of the Settlement School when her term of office ended has made my work as chairman much easier than it might otherwise have been. Another thing which helped was the fact that I had had one year's experience as a member of the Committee and so was familiar with the School and with the Committee work. Now at the end of my first year as chairman, I can report a year of satisfactory work with progress along many lines. I took over the chairmanship immediately following the 1936 Convention, and my first work was arranging for and presiding at the 1936 Committee meeting which was held in Gatlinburg, June 19 to 26, 1936. A complete report of that meeting was sent to you immediately following, and a short report was printed in the September ARROW. The work of the Committee has been divided as follows: Josephine McCleverty continued as treasurer and her watchful attention to expenditures and her efficient work as an accountant have been great factors in enabling the School and Arrow Craft to be managed most economi and at the same time most efficiently. It is nc easy task to make a budget when certain expo tures must be covered by an uncertain incon: is the case of our School. The budget of $21 was made as carefully as possible and the ca. supervision of Mrs. Weaver has kept various i within their estimated cost. Our alumnae cont tions have come up to the anticipated total so we are able to close the year with a Bala budget. Charlotte Cropley Brown has edited the I from Little Pigeon and has made that depart not only readable and informative but has g. it real literary value. She expended much time effort in collecting and editing material for twenty-fifth anniversary number which, with twenty-five contributors, was a valuable add. to the history of Gatlinburg and the School. Marie Bacon Hagee, a new member of Committee, has been a most efficient secretary. minutes of the 1936 meeting were carefully and were copied and sent to the member! Grand Council and the Committee in an unusl </p>
      <pb ref="arr5410023_0002" seq="02" n="24-25  "/>
       <p>THE SEPTEMBER ARROW time. She is cooperating with the Grand President in revising the list of "Ways of rig Money" for Alumni Clubs. ifries Green Pace, the other new member on :ommittee, was not able to attend the annual ng, but visited the School in the fall and up her work on programs for clubs with enthusiasm. She has put many new ideas into vork and has helped many clubs with films ,they material for Settlement School programs. addition to the individual accomplishments crated above, each member has been faithful ,rrespondence with the chairman, has given al consideration to all problems, and has helped aide all questions which have come up. chairman of the Committee, I have given at tiles my closest attention to the affairs of the )1. The difficulties of distance have been over-by telegraph, air mail, and special delivery quick communication was necessary. Regular hly letters and many others have been sent to ::ommittee and to Miss Onken. Weekly and times daily communication with Mrs. Weaver teen kept up. Correspondence with other staff aers and much general correspondence has carried on. have tried to keep the officers, the active, and tlumnx members of the Fraternity informed t the School. Instead of the annual letter, marily sent out by the chairman, I sent out a s Letter, gotten up in newspaper form. I edited numbers, one in November and one in April, Mrs. Weaver edited one in January, letting take the place of her annual letter. Copies sent to all clubs, province, and national officers. )ugh the News Letter lacks the personal touch letter, we feel that the news is presented in ,re striking and readable way. Another change made in sending a letter directly to chapters Lg of vacancies in the School staff, instead of rovince Presidents as was formerly done. This which not only listed vacancies but described type of community work that our teachers fit into, brought many applications. We only t that there are not enough positions for all his who are so earnestly interested. made my mid-year trip to visit the School ' in November. As we had made quite a change ving the teaching of agriculture and the super-,n of the farm to the principal, the Committee Director thought it advisable for me to make visit in the fall. I stayed ten days, a length of sufficient for me to get the feeling of belong-there, and time enough to get acquainted with 7 phase of the School and community work. I ed a class of every high school teacher and 7 grade room. I spent some time at the weavbuilding and at the shops. I went over the L with Mr. King. With Mrs. Weaver, I visited )us shops and many people in the community. ether we were able to make decisions on many ,1ems. I made a complete report of this visit e Committee and Grand Council. )n my way home from attending the national .U.W. meeting in Savannah in March, I was to stop for a short time at the School and gad the opportunity of talking over a number ^roblems with Mrs. Weaver. This was a great in making several decisions. )ne new teacher in the high school and three he grades were the only changes in the staff until April when the resignation of Mrs. Mary Ella McDonald was accepted, and Mrs. Ben Fleming was elected to take her place as house manager. Mrs. McDonald's service to the School as super-visor of the boarding department and house mother for the dormitory girls and boys has been greatly appreciated. All other members of the staff have worked ably and much has been accomplished by them. Mrs. Eunice Weaver has completed her third year as director. A charming personality, executive ability, and untiring effort to be of service have made her work increasingly successful. All branches of our work have shown improvement. A detailed report of these activities will be given you by Mrs. Weaver. The greatest change that was made in the school was the addition of the fourth year to the high school, making a regular standard high school. This required an enrollment of 75 pupils in the high school. The county paid for the extra teacher required and we equipped a chemistry laboratory for the additional science necessary. The enrollment came up to the required number and the fine graduating class of twenty-two certainly justified the additional effort and expense involved. Mr. William King, principal, has taught agriculture and managed the farm during the past year, which arrangement was very successful but cannot be continued on account of a change in the state ruling. Mr. King is a good administrator and his work in the community is most valuable. He will continue as principal and will teach in the high school. A teacher of vocational agriculture will be employed to take that work in the high school. The Committee voted to retain Stella Huff Cox in the high school. Stella has been a valuable member of the staff, not only because of her fine teaching ability but because of her help in the community. We are glad that Ben Fleming is to continue in his position, for he is a fine teacher and his work with the young people is most valuable. The seventh and eighth grades have been taught by Pauline Torley who will return. The grade school has had a good year with Roger Ward teaching the sixth grade and supervising the discipline. Mr. Ward has coached the girls' basket-ball team, but he has failed to fit into the staff so will not be retained another year. Rosemary Moor-head, Illinois H, completed her second year as a grade teacher. It is with regret that her resignation has been accepted, for, in addition to her teaching, she has been a great help with the music and with the entertainments. Mary Durkee, Nevada A, is another Pi Phi who has successfully completed her second year in the grade school. She will continue her work in the grades and heir, with the music in the high school. Mary Glenn Walker, Tennessee A, taught the second grade and her pleasing personality and conscientious work meant much to the School. Elinor Brabson, who has been with us a number of years, continued her fine work as primary teacher. Arrow Craft has had the most successful year in its history. Not only have 105 families been benefited by the work but the profit has now risen to such a figure that the Committee feels that a sum can be used to decrease the debt to the endowment and still leave enough reserve to carry on the increased business. Last year Grand Council accepted the recommendation that this should be THE SEPTEMBER ARROW done when the Grand Treasurer and Settlement School Treasurer agreed upon the amount and the advisability. In January of this year our treasurer put $2,500 of Arrow Craft profit into a savings account to be used for this purpose. This has now been turned over to the Endowment. Arrow Craft has expanded greatly in volume of business done without increasing the number of employees, and consequently without increasing the cost of production. Wholesale costs of materials have advanced, but this has been met by buying in large quantities and whenever possible before advances came. The use of the Woodcraft building, although entailing some extra expense in heat, light, and upkeep, has greatly facilitated the weaving work. In fact, I do not believe that this increased business could have been carried on without the increased space thus made available. This also released some space in the high school which was needed for laboratories required for the fourth year high school course. Mrs. Snow has worked very hard and very successfully in managing the sales end and Gene Redding has been most efficient in managing the production end of Arrow Craft. Pauline Requarth, Illinois H, has been a faithful and efficient bookkeeper and has been a great help to Mrs. Weaver as well. She has fitted into the staff and into the community life, and it is with regret that her resignation has been accepted. Frances Brown, Missouri r, has been elected to take her place. The work of the Jennie Nichol Health Center has been carried on by Mrs. Marjorie Chalmers who has completed one full year and part of another in the work. She has most ably carried on the work which has increased in proportion to the increase in the size of the community and the school enrollment. She has cooperated with the county health officers and has done as much work as possible in outlying districts. The Committee consulted with the county health physician in regard to her work and secured all county assistance possible. I began my report by saying that we have completed the year with a balanced budget. This has been made possible by the care and economy of everyone on the staff, by the efficient planning and constant supervision of the Committee, especially the treasurer, and by the generous response of the alumnm and actives in donations. Our Settlement School cannot continue without the continued interest and help of all Pi Phis. Our work in Gatlinburg is not finished. As the county is able to support the School we are not only taking what support it can give but urging it to do all it can. In the village, we are getting all the cooperation and help that the people are able to give. We are helping a community to help them-selves. There is no one on relief in Gatlinburg. The Committee feels deeply grateful to Edith ARE YOU transferring to another college this year ? If so, please n the Committee on Transfers, the address of whose chairman appears ire Directory at the front of this issue. Updegraff Stephenson and her assist Newberry Motycka, Sarah Huston Ruth Rose Postal for the efficient r the Magazine Agency. The year's pr( highest amount in the history of th hope that all alumnle will read the work as given by Mrs. Stephenso: gain enthusiasm to make next yea greater. The Pi Beta Phi Cook Book, the Los Angeles Club, has already of $700 for the School. This proje Nita Day Carman, has been promot Clubs all over the country, so hear not only to Mrs. Carman and her cc Los Angeles Club but to all who sale. The Los Angeles Club not only nation-wide project but kept up the making activities, giving, beside tl money, $1,001.44, which was the h received from any club. The Clevel Kansas City, North Shore Chicag( contributions ranked next in size. clubs have done as well in prop( size and the Committee is most for their fine work and generous gi chapters have also been most get] contributions. Just at the end of the year come alumna of Illinois B are giving $1 ment bonds to the Settlement Scho, This is a fund which Illinois B h chapter was combined with thin( Settlement School Endowment fur place where all Lombard Pi Phis vs to put the money. We are certain to receive this gift and appreciate and the interest that Illinois Beta always given to the School. I wish to extend to all meml Council the grateful appreciation mittee for the consideration and a recommendations we made at our r 1936. The Grand Vice-President, Smith, was most helpful as our Co that meeting and has continued w during the year, for which we an Grand President, Amy B. Onken, h Grand Council Adviser to the Corr wide knowledge of the past and pr the School, her willingness to give times, and her unfailing good i been of inestimable value to me and of the Committee. Thus all forces have combine( year most successful in every way that the continued interest and N Phis will make the School of even in future years. LILLIAN B </p>
      <pb ref="arr5410023_0003" seq="03" n="26-27  "/>
       <p>THE SEPTEMBER ARROW BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL REPORT ON AUDIT EASUREI 'S ACCOUNTS YEA ENDED JUNE 30, 1937 ID; July 23, 1937 Josephine McCleverty, Treasurer eta Phi Settlement School le, Washington R. MISS MCCLEVERTY: ,t your request we have audited your account-:ecords as Treasurer of the Pi Beta Phi Settle-: School for the year ended June 30, 1937. We received a copy of the report of Homer K. s and Co., Certified Public Accountants of cville, Tennessee, covering the operations of Settlement School and Arrow Craft Shop for rear as reflected by the accounts that are kept atlinburg. We have given effect to the figures Lined in this report in your books, and have ared therefrom and submit herewith the fiial statements showing the results of your ations for the year. FIXED ASSETS fixed Assets, $72,456,96, are stated at cost depreciated values. Live stock is included at story value as reported from Gatlinburg. he mortgage was paid off during the year, ng the Settlement School entirely free of debt. NET WORTH General Surplus, Exhibit 2, amounted to $100,265.84 after being credited with net income and charged with allocations to the Endowment Fund. Total Net Worth, including the Reserve for Endowment Fund, amounted to $138,108.21. ARROW CRAFT SHOP INCOME and EXPENSE The business activities of the Arrow Craft Shop resulted in a net income of $6,702.86 which is carried to Surplus, Exhibit 2. Further analysis of the operations of the Arrow Craft Shop is given in the report of Homer K. Jones and Co. CONTRIBUTIONS Contributions from Alumnae Clubs and Active Chapters are summarized in Exhibit 8, with accompanying detailed lists. We found the books and records well kept, and have made all necessary adjusting and closing en-tries to bring them into agreement with this report and to close the books as of June 30, 1937. Respectfully submitted, R. C. MOUNSEY Certified Public Accountant BALANCE SHEET June 30, 1937 ASSETS nt Assets: ;h on Hand and at Banks $ 11,573.87 :ounts Receivable Arrow Craft Shop 5,357.84 entories: otel Shop $ 751.50 .1-row Craft Shop 10,646.07 Weaving Supplies 5,036.95 16,434.52 Total Current Assets $ 33,366.23 'meets: tool Endowment Fund Exhibit 5 $28,824.27 posits in Closed Bank 1,570.77 Assets: Id, Buildings, Equipment and Live Stock Exhibit 6 red Charges: expired Insurance Exhibit 7 1,889.98 Total Assets $138,108.21 LIABILITIES AND NET WORTH Vorth: ;erve for School Endowment Fund* $ 37,842.37 neral Surplus Exhibit 2 100,265.84 Total Liabilities and Net Worth $138,108.21 mount due School Endowment Fund: Leserve $37,842.37 und Principal 28,745.51 due Fund $ 9,096,86 ANALYSIS OF GENERAL SURPLUS June 30, 1937 cc', June 30, 1936, per Audit Report Profits for Year Ended June 30, 1937: Lool Treasurer Exhibit 3 1,737.92 low Craft Shop Exhibit 4 6,702.86 30,395.04 72,456.96 !ities: ne $ 93,741.10 $102,181.88 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW Deduct: Adjustment, Endowment Fund Income $ 20 Three-fourths Active Chapter Contributions, to Endowment Fund 1,71 Balance General Surplus, to Exhibit 1 INCOME AND EXPENSE STATEMENT Year Ended June 30, 1937 School Treas Income: $ 2,21 Contributions--Active Chapters, Exhibit 8 Contributions-Alumnae Club, Exhibit 8 12,0 Contributions-Individuals 2 Magazine Agency 2,3 Interest Earned 8 Interest Alumnae Fund 9 Commission-European Tour $ 11.30 Smith-Hughes Agriculture Smith-Hughes Home Economics 219.00 Hospital 102.25 Farm (including products for living $1,914.19) 2,446.94 Inventory Decrease, Livestock 5 Living 3,333.77 Picture Show 621.89 Rent-Photo Shop 39.00 Miscellaneous 14.85 Total Income $6,789.00 $18,3 Expenses: $ 134.96 $ 1 Administration Auto Expense 56.37 Community Service 6.25 Convention Expense 6.74 Depreciation 2,4 Farm Expense 1,367.85 1,0 Fuel 724.74 Furnishings 346.28 Health Unit 123.88 1,6 Insurance 9 Interest 283.77 Laundry Lights 594.71 Living 1,914.19 3,5 Miscellaneous 27.08 1 Office 35.61 2 Publicity 110.78 Repairs and Upkeep 500.82 Replacements and Improvements 235.82 2 Salaries 31 School Expense 402.20 Smith-Hughes Agriculture 8.98 1,4 Smith-Hughes Economics 90.68 1 Telephone and Telegraph 99.29 Travel S Truck Expense 204.69 Total Expenses $7,275.69 $16.1 Balance Being Net Income, to Exhibit 2 $ 486.69 $ 2, 2 ARROW CRAFT SHOP, INCOME AND EXPENSE STATEMENT Year Ended June 30, 1937 Income Baskets Weaving Chairs, Stools, etc Hooked and Tufted Articles Miscellaneous Items Mountain View Hotel Shop Total Expenses Commissions-Mt. View Hotel Sales $ 5 Rent-Mt. View Hotel Shop 2 Transportation Cost (net) 1 Industrial ErPense Industrial Salaries 4,8 Industrial Publicity Industrial Miscellaneous 2 Lights Fuel 1 Office Expense Telephone and Telegraph Repairs and Upkeep Sutit'lies 2 Convention Expense Car Expense Truck Expense Total Expenses Profit from Operations </p>
      <pb ref="arr5410023_0004" seq="04" n="28-29  "/>
       <p>THE SEPTEMBER ARROW Income: e of Tennessee Weaving 500 0 rest on Savings Account ' ' ' ' ' 8.33 PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL FIXED ASSETS June 30, 1937 Estate $ 7,900.00 n~~d ~~~~'~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~"~'~~ "~'~". $64,021.06 nent ' . . .' ' . . ' ' . ' ' ' ' . ' . . ' 14,318u6 ' ngs and Equipment, net " .' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " . ' ' ' ' ' ' . . . .' e3,456.96 .~ Inventory 1,100.00 CONTRIBUTIONS, YEAR ENDED JUNE Alumna Active Clubs Chapters "."."."."."."."."$ 1,068.45 $ 145.39 '' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' '' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' '' ' ' ' ' ' ' 1,910.28 206.00 ''''''''''''''''''''''' 296.51 93.07 685.27 252.00 " 1,268.18 235.00 ''''''''''''''''''''''''''' 277.24 1,786.10 784.36 131.03 927.54 249.00 ' ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~ ~~ ~ ~ ~~ ~ ~ ~~ ~ ~ ~ 997.38 225.00 la ".".".".".'.'.."." 1,679.06 230.00 Us, to exhibit 3 $1z,0a9.94 $2,289.04 Beta Province , Ohio $ 138.75 )rd, Pa. "."." ...".' ".' 3.89 ston, W.Va. mad, Ohio ~~~~~~~~~'~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 135.00 e20.00 thus, Ohio 58.75 ` Ohio 64.00 'are, Ohio 7.25 burg-Carlisle 100.00 aing Valley 40.00 ...................... .ntown, W.Va. 10.00 Valley 10.00 lelphia, Pa 320.64 Irgh, Pa.. . 35.00 !rn New jersey 55.00 Hills, Pa. .~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 37.00 D, Ohio 75.00 $1,910.28 ALUMN./E CLUBS ACTIVE CHAPTERS Alpha Province Maine A $ 2.50 Vermont A Vermont B ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 20.00 Massachusetts A 5.00 10u0 Nova Scotia A 10.00 123.00 Ontario A $ 25.00 Ontario B 5.00 New York A N ~ York r ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 1040.00 .00 New York A 25.00 West $105 /m 42.80 50.00 Pennsylvania B $ 25x00 Pennsylvania r '''''''''''' '''''' ''''''' Ohio A 71.00 Ohio B Ohio ~~ ~ ~ ~ ' ' ~' ~ ' ~' ' ~' ~~ ~~ ~ ~~~ ~ ' ~~ ~ ~~ ~~~ ' ~ I85 ~~ r~~ Virginia ~' ~ .~~ .~ ' ' ~ . . . . ' . . .~ . 10.00 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW Gamma Province Baltimore, Md. " .' ' " . " . " .' ' ' ' ' " . " .o 60.76 Chapel Hill, N.C 10~~ Columbia, S.C. Richmond, Va. ~~ ~~ ~ ~ ~~~ ~ ~~ ~~ ~ ~ ~ ~~ ~~ ~ ~ ~~ ~~ ~~ 3.75 Virginia A Virginia r ~ ~~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~. . ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ Washington, D.C 182.00 North Carolina A North Carolina B South Carolina A $ 296.51 Delta Province Ann Arbor, Mich. ".' "."."."."."m 125.17 Mich 50o0 Bloomington, Ind. ' ''' '''' '' '' '''' '' ' '' 25.00 Detroit, Mich. Calumet Regional Mich 6.00 Ft. Wayne, Ind ' 20.00 Franklin, Ind 15.00 Gary, Ind. ' '' ' ' ' ' '' '' ' '' ' '' '' ' 2.00 Grand Rapids, Mich 15.00 Hillsdale, 1\Cch 2.50 Southwestern Indiana. ' '. ' ' .' " .' 15.00 T Southwestern Michigan erre Haute, ~~~'~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 3.50 Epsilon Province Chattanooga, Tenn * 35.00 Columbia, Mo 32.18 Kansas City, 506.00 Louisville, Kv 50.00 Memphis, Tenn 15.00 Nashville, Tenn 5.00 St. Jose-ph, Mo. 20.00 St. Louis, Mo. ~ ~~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ 600.00 ' 600.00 Zeta Province Atlanta, Ga. ".".".".".".' "."m 100.00 Birmingham, Ala 5.00 Daytona Beach, Fla 10.00 Deland, Fla 30.00 lacksonville, Fla 22.24 akeland, Fla. 5.00 Miami, Fla. ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 15.00 Fla 60.00 St. Petersburg, Fla. Palm Beach, Fla Tampa, Fla 25.00 Eta Province Avon, $ 11.00 Beloit, Wis. ' '' ' ' ' ' '' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' 10.00 Carthage, ''''''''''''''''''' 17.00 Champaign-Urbana 103.60 Chicago Business Women 145.00 Chicago North Club Chicago South Club ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 2350.00 Chicago West Suburban 75z0 Decatur, Du Page, 19.00 Elgin, ' ' ' ' ' '' '' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' '' Galesburg, 30.00 Madison, Wis 50.00 Milwaukee, Wis. '' ' ' ' ' '' ' ' ' ' '' ' ' ' ' '' '' 215.00 Monmouth, 7.50 North Shore Club ..^ 425 5.00 Oak Park-River Forest 5.00 Rockford, 10.00 Michigan A Michigan 13 Indiana A Indiana B Indiana r ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ Indiana A Missouri A .. . Missouri B .. . Missouri . . . Kentucky A Te ~~~~~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ Alabama A Florida A Florida B .~ ~~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ Florida r Wisconsin A Wisconsin B Illinois A Illinois B-A Illinois E Illinois Z .~ ~~ ~ ~~~ ~ ~ ~ ~~~ ~ ~ ~~ ~~ ~ ~~~ ~ Illinois H ..' </p>
      <pb ref="arr5410023_0005" seq="05" n="30-31  "/>
       <p>THE SEPTEMBER ARROW Iowa # ;ton, Iowa Rapids, Iowa 1 Bluffs, Iowa :oines, Iowa L, Minn Forks, N.D Dla, Iowa ay, Iowa ''' ' ' ' ' '' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' '' ' !polls, Minn tasant, Iowa al, Minn )eg,2ity,MaIowa Theta Province 12.69 SPecial 46.00 Manitoba A 70.00 North Dakota ~' ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ $10.03 5.00 $ 3~0 19.42 Minnesota A ' ' ' ''' ''' '' ' ' ' '' ' ' '' '' 25.105.00 Iowa A 00 75.00 Iowa B 5.00 10.00 5.00 20.00 Iowa r 15.00 3.00 15/0 Iowa Z 25.010.00 70.00 150.00 70.00 110.00 6.25 15.00 Iota Province r, Colo ^ 40.00 50.00 50.00 . ... ... .. .... . .. .. ... Coin 25.00 _ ht., Wyo 30.00 ce, Kan 38.50 L, Neb 30.00 ttan, Kan 125.00 .. .. . .. . .. . . .. . .. . . .. . . , Neb. 68.80 Vallev. Colo 10.00 Colo ' 25.00 ~ KKan a. .~~~ ~~ ~ ~~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~ ~ ~ ~~ ~~ ~~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ 2~00 on, S.D 5.24 KaPPa Province Okla $ 6.40 .__ . --_ louge, La 2.00 Christi, Tex 19.44 Tex 200.00 ville, Ark 5,00 :th, Ark 25.00 1rth, Tex. Tex 10.00 a, Tex 200.00 tock, Ark 15.49 ;ee, Okla 10.00 ,rleans, La 50.00 a, Okla 40.00 ma City, Okla 125.00 ee, Okla 15.00 District 97.30 Itonio, Tex. ~ ~~~ ~ ~~ ~~~ ~ ~~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~ z~ )ort, La. . 00 ter, Okla " ' 10.00 Okla. Tex. ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 30.75 ana, Tex 5.00 ^~^ Lambda Province 40o0 Alberta A ' ' . . ' ' ' ' ' ".$ 5.00 2.00 Montana A 5.00 25.00 ~0 Idaho A Washington ~.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 25.00 10.00 Washington B 10o0 5.00 Oregon A ".".".' "."."."." . ' ".' 7.50 150.00 Oregon u 20.00 5.00 103.57 2.00 50.00 7.00 5.00 South Dakota A $ 10.00 Nebraska B 10.00 Kansas A 25.00 Kansas B 44.00 Colorado B 40.00 Colorado ~ ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 100.00 Wyoming A 20.00 A $ 50.00 Oklahoma B 25.00 Arkansas A 15.00 Texas A 50.00 Texas B 25.00 Louisiana A 50.00 Louisiana B 10.00 Idaho v r, Alta . . . . . . . . . . . .. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . ,is, Ore. ton, Alta , Ore !a, Wash d, Ore Ore Wash e, Wash Wash THE SEPTEMBER ARROW California A California B California California ,A Nevada A Arizona A Utah A $1,679.06 MAGAZINE AGENCY District 1 $ 571.32 District 1t2 1,006.73 District $ 3 546.60 District t4 241.83 $2,366.48 INDIVIDUAL CONTRIBUTIONS National $ 250.00 Individual (Misc.) 45.00 The rapid multiplication and extension of a wide variety of honorary, p semi-professional societies in colleges have been a matter of concern to colleg and officials of the general fraternities and many of the outstanding and long orary societies. The National Association of Deans and Advisers of Men, at Philadelphia last year, heard a report on this subject presented by a committ, J. A. Park, dean of men at Ohio State University, is chairman. He said in part : "Assuming for the moment that scholarly endeavor or extra-curricular at thered by recognition such as is accorded by membership in the various soci sideration, we are faced with a question for which we must immediately admit an answer, namely, exactly what standards or skills deserve recognition of thi! the older and best known societies recognize achievement in a general or pro: course. Such recognition is usually highly valued and seldom questioned, bu are formed not only for individual subjects of study but these subjects are ag we reach a reduction to the point of absurdity. . . "Something is to be said for any device which will unite students of co= a relationship which will be mutually stimulating. Some of the professional though necessarily in a circumscribed area. Honorary groups are in many case admiration societies. Having been elected their sole duty is to elect their succes ly, the line dividing honorary from professional groups is a very shadowy so-called `honorary' organizations are satisfied to elect to membership almost at work of average quality. . ." Mu Province Albuquerque, N.M $ 20.00 Berkeley, Calif 150.00 El Paso, Tex 10.00 Fresno, Calif 15.00 Glendale, Calif 50.00 Hawaii, T.H 50.00 Long Beach, Calif 50.00 Los Angeles, Calif 1,001.44 Nevada Alumn 5.00 Palo Alto, Calif 5.00 Pasadena, Calif 50.00 Phoenix, Ariz 22.02 San Diego, Calif 100.00 San Francisco, Calif 35.00 San Jose, Calif 30.00 Santa Barbara. and Ventura Santa Monica, Calif 21.60 Tucson, Ariz 14.00 Utah Alumni 50.00 </p>
      <pb ref="arr5410023_0006" seq="06" n="32-33  "/>
       <p>THE SEPTEMBER ARROW CTC) OF THE PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL, 1936.37 school children. Those who were not able to attend because of the distance or illness were remembered in the distribution of Christmas baskets from the school. Both boys' and girls' basketball teams, coached by Ben Fleming and Roger Ward, did excellent work. Games drew crowds too large to seat around the sides of the gymnasium. Both teams played in the district tournament and one boy was named on the all tournament team. A very great help was the twenty-four dollar ($24.00) monthly allowance from the N.Y.A., which was used to pay students for taking care of the library, washing dishes in the lunch room, cleaning up the campus, or helping in the office. Care was taken in hiring those who most needed the money. Dormitory Community ire our community takes on the of the real summer resort. I appear at first glance that the Its have been tourist cabins, there substantial new homes, a Swiss rrge hotel, and some tea rooms, beauty of the west section. Duryears the Business Men's Club ff ort to improve Gatlinburg and rden Club is just beginning. n of our high school is still the it is kept so busy and crowded h for a public community center. ainments, class plays, picture games of both local and school neetings, so fill the season that d bleachers are in a constant state i moving out. of school and community we had n February a recreational leader, ion, sponsored by the Conference untain Workers and partly iippa Delta Phis, the service of this .der was available for a number rs. With the cooperation of Mr. 3, a room for Mr. Seaman at the )oard at the school, we managed ks instruction in singing, games, rvision, and the singing of folk troup was organized, having for Ian Walker and Pauline Torley, :hool. achers Association has not failed provide the hot lunches for the y means of rummage sales and School undergone more drastic changes ay of the previous ten years and e changes were necessary. With the fourth year class our high etc,. One of the class rooms was laboratory for general science ad economics, American history, French were added to the other re twenty-two graduates. Five of definite arrangements to attend ended with baccalaureate sermon :lurch, class day and commence-=slum. and eighth grades were moved aol building. Ceilings and upper ae grade school building were bring more light into the rooms. !e still crowded. The enrollment ;even of these were high school was made in certain extra-curplay production especially. The plays would have been a credit to Christmas entertainment was ay and evening performance so Eildren could conveniently take as usual the real thrill for the There were twelve boys and eight girls in the dormitories when school opened. After the first of the year, three of the girls found homes in the Burg with families who were relatives. It was arranged that a number of students could in turn spend week ends at home, leaving enough at school to carry on the work. During the winter months, because the dormitory was much too crowded, two boys roomed in the weaving building. An epidemic of flu and measles in February was a noticeable hindrance to school attendance. "They appreciate all that is being done for them to make possible their education," said Mrs. McDonald, who has had supervision of the dormitories for five years, "and while many will not express themselves, you will find that all do realize and appreciate the advantages you are giving them." A great improvement was made in the girl's dormitory, in moving the furnace from the dining room into an outside addition built to protect it. Hardwood floors were put in the dining room and kitchen. An April 9, Mrs. McDonald gave up her position to go to the Riverside Hotel as dietitian. Mrs. Josephine Fleming then filled the position in the dormitory as manager and housekeeper, with Bess McCarter as cook. Home Economics The Home Economics classes under Anne Bell had an interesting year. The first year class numbering eleven, had the usual program beginning with food's, then home courtesies and personal grooming, clothing, making toys, and ending with child care, which lasted for a month. The second year class of twelve followed the same basic plan in a more advanced way, the clothing unit ending with the making of very pretty evening dresses by the seniors for class day, and voiles and linens for the others. The annual dinner for the staff, planned, pre-pared, and served by the seniors was as usual one of the most enjoyable events of the year. The favors and decorations were original and made by the freshmen. For two weeks in April, there was an exchange of students between the freshman home economics THE SEPTEMBER ARROW standards. Their discussions on how to keep with the demands of increasing tourist bus are helpful. As yet, we have not benefited ga by membership in Southern Highlanders Inc. includes the majority of Guild members, b has made possible the experimenting with w saling, cooperative buying and styling. through its three markets, the shop at Norris the shop at Chattanooga, and the one at R feller Center, New York, we have taken in d the past year an average of $135 per month. the shops take a twenty-five (25) percent dis and we pay the express, very little of this is Spring vacationers and people returning Florida are good customers and boosted the of the hotel branch shop to nearly $900 fo month.. Clubs have made remarkable sales year. No matter how much stock we plar we seem to be low at inopportune times. Sin( prices of materials have advanced, in all probs the selling price will change accordingly. Mrs. Snow, manager of Arrow Craft Shop 1 the best free advertising the shop has had i the past year was the article in the mad section of the Nashville Tennessean. The exciting was the visit paid us by Mrs. Roo: and the most far reaching was the picture c garden basket in Better Homes and Gard( would add the reference to our school i Geographic, in Laura Thornborough's new "The Great Smoky Mountains," and also an from the White House for Arrow Craft goo, Ten prizes were taken on articles exhibi state and county fairs. The Weavers' Guild gave the first act of play of last year in the University of Ten gymnasium, during the Southern Mountain er's conference. They will repeat it in 31 the school and also present a new play. Out of the efforts of the Weavers' Gu beautify their own homes has grown the C Club with a membership extending from C burg to Roaring Fork in the Glades. Until February, a class in veaving, of juni^ senior girls was taught by Miss Redding. VI was found that this course could not be acct it was discontinued and outside classes were Hospital "It is surprising to note," says Marjorie mers, our nurse, "how health conscious otu munity is growing. It has been a gradual bI up through the years." As the community , so does the health tabulation, as follows: 1936 7 Field visits 1380 Office Calls I831 Individual Pupil Inspections 1343 Class Room Inspections 67 Class Room Health Talks 166 Blue Ribbon Children 248 Surgical Dressings 1909 Total Typhoid Shots 1408 Completed Typhoid Inoculations 404 Diphtheria Immunizations 59 Small Pox Vaccinations 242 Schick Tests for Diphtheria Immunity 129 Our school children are always interested Blue Ribbon contest carried on every year County Health Department, for they like to in the parade and carry the Pi Beta Phi Sett School banner. This year we won first pr larger schools---a silver cup, our percentage Agriculture Wm. King, Agriculture Arlie . Watson, Gardner Ambers Ogle, Stock manager Farm management was taken over by Mr. King this. year. Having lived on the place for seven years during school terms, he was familiar with conditions and routine of the school farm and being qualified to teach agriculture, carried on the farm work and taught the course. This was done as successfully as under the Smith-Hughes vocational agriculture plan of last year, though not at much time could be spent on outside classes. There were twenty-one boys in the argriculture classes. They attended state and county fairs. At the county fair they took six first, and two second prizes on their shop work. Other prizes were taken on farm products. They also visited large creameries, dairies, and hatcheries. The class of home economics girls exchanging with the argriculture class was taught garden making and chicken raising for two weeks. Student labor on the farm was more staisfactory this year due to the fact that the boys were older and more experienced. They built all of the new fencing and cut all of the wood. Larger vegetable gardens have been made in order to supply C.C.C. camps and hotels. Perhaps the most attractive scene on the farm to visitors is the wonderful jersey herd which this season produced 125 lbs. of milk per day. The F,F.T.'s entertained the home ec girls with a party. They also sponsored a show. Arrow Craft Ethel Snow, Iowa r, Arrow Craft Manager Gene Redding, Weaving Supervisor Georgia Duffield, Hotel Shop Veatress Parton, Shop Assistant Lura Owenby, Weaving Assistant Every spring when I see new handicraft and gift shops appearing along the highway, I fear a reduction in our sales, but thus far, they have not been a serious drawback. Fine workmanship and lovely new designs seem to appeal to the discriminating. Through our membership in the Southern High-land Handicraft Guild, which has become one of the foremost organizations of its kind in the country, we are informed of the progress handicrafts have made in the south and the importance of high and agriculture classes. It is interesting to find that boys are anxious for instruction in some of the home ec subjects and they were allowed to express a preference. Eating properly, setting the table, and pressing a suit and making candy was requested by all. All were taught to make biscuits, to darn, and to make beds. A monthly meeting was conducted for outside classes by Cornelia Bell, County Home Demonstration agent. A better homes campaign was organized by this group with Mrs. Newt Clabo as chairman. This meant the improvement of twenty-five homes in Catlinburg. A new sewing machine was bought and the old ones mended, making in all four Singer ma-chines. The Home Ec. Club entertained F. F. T.'s with a party. </p>
      <pb ref="arr5410023_0007" seq="07" n="34-35  "/>
       <p>THE SEPTEMBER ARROW as being 78.1 percent, an increase over 71.2 t year. The nurse visited six mountain schools spections and inoculations. telephone was put in the hospital in March. was decided upon after an emergency case re injured people brought in at one time. was great difficulty of communication with rs and relatives. Night calls may now be Ted more quickly. Our nurse has her living 1-s in the hospital and her big white dog s the place. tudent assisted with the office work and was by the National Youth Administration. m "Friends of the Mountain Children" we ed our yearly allowance of fifty dollars 00) to be used for medical treatment of en. Office dine Requarth has for the past two years he accounts for all departments of the school efficiently and we deeply regret that she t be with us longer. It seems logical for the :eeper to handle the funds for ogranizations as P.T.A., the movies, and local benefits of ads, and these have received the same careful ion as the regular business. Old Arrow Craft tits have been cleared up satisfactorily and ame system of accounting has been carried closing, I want the members of Committee :ouncil to know how deeply grateful I feel m for their patience and kindness to me in Torts to carry out their wishes in directing -ork of the school. The interest and support icers and clubs have been constant and it is ncere desire to have the opportunity of exng our appreciation in person as they visit re at the school. Respectfully submitted, EUNICE S. WEAVERRecommendations for 1937 1. An agreement with the county board as to how many county teachers we are to have in our school, might prevent many difficulties. I do not think we can employ teachers who are neither county residents nor Pi Phis after this year. 2. Unless we can afford two bookkeepers I do not advise moving our office to the shop. The farm men, nurse, housekeeper and director have business with the bookkeeper so much of the time that it would be inconvenient for all to go to the shop. Giving the director an assistant would hardly solve the problem and we do not have room for another person. 3. We have been warned by the sanitary officer that our drain at the front gate should be done away with. We can not be forced to do this but it might be a very good example to do so. We might have underground disposal. The officer has offered to help us plan, whenever convenient, a better arrangement. 4. It does not seem wise to put as many boys in the dormitory as we had this year. With Mr. King occupying one room and possibly an agriculture teacher another, only two rooms are left for boys. We can easily put a shower in the basement and with very little expense. In this way all could bathe before supper time. 5. Under building repair Walk from teacher's cottage to weaving building. New gutters on grade school and hospital. New steps and other mending on boys dorm. Roof on farm shop. Screens on grade school ($10 given by alumnae) . Extra garage space (2). Porch (boys dorm). 6. Painting Girl's dormitory, Boy's dormitory Grade School, gables on high school, walls in gym, at least lower portion, dining room and up-per hallway (girl's dorm). 7. Purchase Folding chairs or seats of substantial construction for gymnasium. Trade in Ford car on new one if this is best time for trade. 8. Salaries raised Cook. Farm and stock men. ROW CRAFT EPO T, 1936.37 1* \ \ A 'E ARE all happy over records broken in the year just past. That part has already been told times so I will not dwell on it. The figures July 1, 1936, to June 1, 1937 may be found separate sheet, as May first, when this is writ-s a little early for that part of it. This is to be a listing of problems so that they may be hi out wherever possible. ere were many advantages in packing the club orders in the stock room at the weaving [tag. Figures show that we shipped more, but s so much easier that it did not seem so. It lice to fill up the boxes from the fresh stock le shelves. The girls did almost as much ng, except that it was the other way; from hop to the weaving building. There were a nore mistakes made as Miss Redding had no for direct supervision and some one has to the shop. Two San Jose boxes were sent to !lice, Kansas, which was sad. But, there are i to be some mistakes during that hectic time e Christmas. There were times when we were f certain things so that we either had to hold -dens or send without. That, also, will always happen I fear, because having the shelves where Jean could check did not solve it. It goes back to more stock which is a hazard in more ways than one. The loss from a financial point would be greater and the moth situation begins to loom large. There have been more holes than at any time since I came. The only way to be at all sure of that situation is to spray every bit of wool weaving that comes in, and keep it where moths would not enter. A great many of the smaller clubs were more thoughtful, and a great deal better about the re-turns. The balance of the large returns comes from the clubs which hold large sales each year. They want a large display and they usually do sell a great deal. I feel that also, will have to be borne with as long as they still sell sixty percent (60%) of our goods. Club problems are bound to come up with the various types of chairmen. This is more or less a repetition of past years, but by repeating my problems, I am always in hope there will be some happy solution suggested for some of them. I am proud of the way Pauline has cleared up THE SEPTEMBER ARROW many old accounts. Having the correspondence at the shop and most of the other records at the office still creates difficulties. Some of both Pauline's and my time is wasted, which is only the least important. I feel the only way to correct this is to give Mrs. Weaver a helper at the cottage, and Arrow Craft a bookkeeper who could also act as a checker on the new and old costs, and many other details. I started to say, "petty details," and it has gotten to the place where it almost needs one person to check every tag that goes into the orders, and recheck everyone that returns. Even so, when tags are missing, as they often are on returning, it is hard to say if it should read, Nu, NB, or Bi. One sometimes wonders if we are not inconsistent in our business, paying attention to small details and allowing larger things to remain the same. We have found that the reason some clubs have not cleared up their accounts is because they have held to the rule of "NOT RETURNABLE." A former chairman may have fancied baskets and then been unable to sell them. One club so in-formed me. I would suggest that the total cost prices of the baskets might be added and sent, and that much received from them, rather than have a lot of baskets returned. That, however, would start a precedent. No matter how it is handled, baskets are a problem. At that certain time of year it is impossible to fill the demand, and if we had all the baskets, to find cartons to send them in would be difficult. If we have to pay for cartons, which will have to be done if we fill even the orders received last year, it would take away that little profit we now get. Finding boxes to ship in slows us up as it is, and grows harder each year. Letters of inquiry came from many states in the Union, and also Honolulu. There were not manydirect orders from the twenty-fiv( answered, but I do know there v contacts made, such as other purl from clubs in their vicinity. Answering a letter from Hor our club there. Mrs. Denison, th wrote that my letter bore fruit, number of things from them be basket for a friend to be shippet I also received a note of appre lady herself. And speaking of fi our old lady dolls went to Vie long ago. Competition, as you all know, Some in the Burg have realizeC selling too low and there is a tei prices. They are still able and baskets at less and pay less for tl by their own people. But unless the baskets and all the chairs out by these people, there is nc about it, because, there are time: that little bit in order to eat. If the customers take time to of various shops, they all agree as a whole. But there are a goo their purchases before turning road near the Post Office. There not venture in just because o higher class, just as there are Ta buy from a second class depar wonders if it is not time to r little shop at the turn of the roa space, adequate heat, and close Hotel might solve various prof tinue to harass at present. Respectfully submit E' WEAVING REPORT-JUNE 30, 1936 TO JUNE THIS year, although the work has gone very smoothly, has not been without its problems. One great concern of mine from the producing end is how much stock it is wise and necessary to keep on hand in order to allow the clubs the privilege of returning 50 per cent of all the weaving they take. We found last fall that it was necessary to keep invested in stock about 33 per cent more than would be required if we were doing a cash business. I realize that a cash business is impossible under our conditions but would it not help to keep down the amount of returned goods if the percentage were raised? It would help from Mrs. Snow's end as well as from mine. Then of course it is impossible to predict the vagaries of the public. Last fall I thought I had an ample supply to fill orders only to find that some of the least expected articles went better than we thought possible, thus causing a shortage. I also had difficulty in getting some satisfactorily dyed threads that took weeks to adjust which meant a shortage in a few cases. This brings me to the point of buying weaving materials in larger and larger quantities, I have had to run over my allotment figure in order to get some materials at all as the factories demanded large wholesale orders before shipment. Also the market prices have continued to advance so I have bought staple warps in cotton and linen to lastat least a year. This not only ho our products but will help to k( more stable for some months to portant item. In dyed threads tl sideration as it is much easier lots separated when they are Fz The stock room for the fini been one of the biggest helps had. We use it for tagging, s weaving, and in the fall, for shi need more shelf space and I w moth proof closet for the woolt One of our greatest worries curred from the cost prices. No. ever due to the rise in the cost same article in many instances N under three cost prices; those m material, those of part old and and those of all new material. keep a balance between the phy: inventories. The bookkeeping we fear it will be impossible t Tags will get lost and removed no way of telling which cost pi article. The selling prices will hav result of this advance in the prh We have no articles in our stock touched by the rise. </p>
      <pb ref="arr5410023_0008" seq="08" n="36-37  "/>
       <p>THE SEPTEMBER ARROW eaving meetings continue to be a lives of the weavers. We have a lighter nature this year as I f the opportunity to play that so rers have. The play the weavers so successful they have written are preparing to give this June. )eing used as an emergency fund id are administered by them. Garden Club was started this auspices of the Weavers' Guild. !ndid and enthusiastic start. The 2d to weavers only, but is open of Gatlinburg. It meets once a h school auditorium. wing class was much more sucird and fourth year age group of te eighth grade. The girls were .nd were sorry to give it up. The :ountered from having the class time to do my regular work, ng, which resulted. I do my call-)ons and having the class every akes it hard to work with the yes, especially in the winter when the days are short. Previous to this year, the assistant has taken more time with the class than was possible this year. If this course is put in a school department in order to receive credit, it would be necessary to have Lura undertake some of the teaching to leave me free for my routine work. When the school class was discontinued, I started two classes for the women. They received one lesson a week for eight weeks during the spring. We had a total of 106 weavers this year, our record number. The greatest number working at one time was 97 in December. A rotating system is used so that they will all get an equal chance to work. In the time between July 1, 1936 and May 30, 1937, there were 2153 calls at the weaving building, 145 calls made in the homes, and we had an average attendance of 70 at the weaving meetings. Lura Ownby has continued to render her faithful and efficient service. I sincerely recommend that her pay be increased from $45.00 a month to $50.00 a month. Respectfully submitted, WINOGENE REDDING JENNIE NICOL HEALTH CENTER aas been one of improvement in er the year that went before. In of endeavor, there has been an that shows how large a place n the life of the community. en a large number of sick and he usual rush at recess time for urns and bruises, cuts and sores, ,r advice on baby care. School inoculations have been made, ;t clinics have been arranged, and, is time, routine calls in the homes school children. the county officers, the district atage of immunization for diphi. It is much easier to give small-than the year before. In only a find that the children have been vaccination done. me Hygiene were taught by the 7, with a few demonstrations by rt talk was given to the science Aid, and the boys and girls d bandaging themselves and each Ln a week, one of the bandages hospital as a First Aid dressing The bandaging was well done, e interest aroused by that demon )nomics class had a demonstration ad each boy took his turn at the Room. Some of them were quite in the Dormitory, and those who the tourist camps, did very credit-Eon of the dormitory rooms show alk, and the request of house-)oms be left in good order before is in the district showed intense le Ribbon Contest, and nearly all their percentage over the prero of them won cups this year, Elkmont won the gold cup in the small school class with 87.2 per cent, and Gatlinburg, with 176 Blue Ribboners, won the first in the large school class. Their percentage was 78.1, a good increase over last year's 71.2. Dentist days continue to be extremely busy, and it may be that Dr. Mayberry will find it necessary to give the community two days a month instead of one. People as a rule, do not delay calling the doctor in extreme cases, as they used to do. In fact, many of them call him quite often. But there are those who wait until the nurse insists on his advice and aid. It seems presumptuous, in a way, this ordering of peoples' lives, just because one assumes more knowledge of life as it should be. Too deep a contemplation of one's responsibility would cause a faltering that might impair usefulness. The days seem to pass rapidly, each with its series of problems that must be met with as much wisdom as one possesses. In spite of a decrease in population, there is an increase in work. More people are taking advantage of office hours, some because of illness, and some merely to discuss the bettering of living conditions, diet, and the like. The new outside telephone in the hospital has proved a friend indeed. Calls may be answered more quickly, or a direct call may save miles of travel. In time of emergency, the benefits are immeasurable. I wonder, now, how we managed without it. The friendliness of the people for the Health Center seems to increase month by month. This is a great cause for satisfaction, for antagonism would surely end our usefulness. It is surprising to note how health conscious is this community. One would have to search far and wide to find any district, rural or urban, to equal it. It has been a slow and gradual building up, one that has grown through the years, until now, the closing of the Health Center would be catastrophe, indeed. THE SEPTEMBER ARROW We are always grateful for the cooperation of the doctors with whom we come in contact. Their helpfulness smooths rough going many times. Al-though we greatly miss Dr. Kash, who resigned his County office in November to take a position in New York City, Dr. Sauberli has shown himself to be a worthy successor. We are grateful, too, for the interest of the community, and of the members of the Fraternity. They have helped in so many ways since I came here. Because of the spirit of unity that exists ar the members of the staff, we are assured of pr and willing aid in any emergency. But, above we are grateful for the sympathy and understar of our resident director. Firm, of course, wher duties require it, she is always just and kindly her solicitousness about our welfare, and the of the school has endeared her to us all. MARJORIE CHALMERS, R. HOME ECONOMICS DEPA TMENT TE M 1936493'61 I* \ First Year IN THE first year Home Economics class there was an enrollment of fourteen eleven first year girls and three second year girls. The first week of school a short unit on food preservation was studied. The girls canned vegetables by two methods; the use of the pressure cooker and by the intermittent process without the cooker. The next month there was a combination of two units, home courtesies and personal grooming. In those units we tried to establish standards for the betterment of habits of courtesy and good grooming. The next unit was clothing-selection, construction and care of clothing. The problem was the construction of a uniform smock to be used in the unit on foods. It took six weeks to complete this unit. The girls did fine work and had neat looking smocks. The next unit was foods planning, preparing, and serving breakfast. In this unit the girls studied menu planning, cooked, served and ate a breakfast. The week before Christmas there was a special unit on toys for children and presents for the family. The freshman girls made favors and helped decorate for the Christmas dinner given to the staff. The child care unit covered one month. In this study we tried to get a better understanding of the needs of the pre-school child, the use of various methods in guiding the child toward desirable habits and giving them the right diet for proper growth. Mrs. Chalmers demonstrated bathing the baby by using a doll. The next unit clothing, the selection, cutting and construction of a school dress. All the girls showed great improvement and speed in their sewing. The dresses were completed in a month. The girls did excellent work and were really proud of their dresses. The food unit for the second semester dealt with luncheons, school lunches, suppers, and teas. The girls cooked meats, vegetables, breads, and desserts. The class as a whole cooked and served a luncheon. The girls had a tea for the adult class of women. The unit on health of the family was next studied. Mrs. Chalmers gave a demonstration on bed making and bathing a patient in bed. In the last unit, the house, the bedroom was studied and each girl tried to to improve her own room in some way. Second Year In the second year class there was an enroll-ment of twelve six sophomore girls, one j girl and five senior girls. The first unit, the preserving of vegetable fruits, the newest methods of canning was pleted in two weeks. In the clothing unit the girls planned a b to follow throughout the year. They planne, lected and constructed a tailored wool dress, of the girls made over wool garments. Om made a beautiful tailored silk dress. This corn project took seven weeks. The foods unit, planning, preparing, and se dinners lasted until Christmas holidays. They pleted their study by preparing and serv. dinner to the staff. In the house planning and furnishing un girls studied the arranging and decorating ( house, floor plans, and period furniture. The were very interested and made some excellent books. We also visited some homes in Gatli and saw some of the principles we had studio into use. The study of the child in the second y different from the first in that the girls stuc prenatal stage, the diet of the mother-to-b the care of the young baby. The unit deal with hereditary, environment, and family re] ships. Mrs. Ralph Lawson bathed her bat the second year class. In the last half of unit on Child Care, the all made some garment for the baby or pre child. Three girls made some wraps for the tal. The others made clothes for some child family. One girl made a beautiful tacked a for a baby bed. In the clothing unit the senior girls mad ning dresses and slips for class night and the girls made voile and linen dresses. The! studied the principles of sewing and textiles Mr. King taught the first year girls gar( for two weeks and I taught the boys. Th( were so very interested in all the lessons dealt with etiquette, setting the table, cook biscuits and candy, darning, the pressing of and making beds. The Home Economics Club had fifteen me We sold candy to pay our state and nation dues. The club belongs to the State and N Home Economics Student Club Associatior club entertained the F. F. T.'s during the Besides the Home Economics classes, taught one class in Chemistry, planned the for the school lunch and did eighty hours 1 side adult teaching. Respectfully submitted, ANNE </p>
      <pb ref="arr5410023_0009" seq="09" n="38-39  "/>
       <p>THE SEPTEMBER ARROW E 0 T ON DO MITO Y, 1936.1937 !d August 24, 1936, with eight elve boys in the dormitories. Four )oys were seniors, four girls and Iniors, and two boys were fresh :ottage were Mr. King and the i Cottage were Mrs. McDonald, iss Torley, Bess McCarter, and the rter and her sister, Kate, have been [ertie Ogle has been the laundress, rom the girls, have included new floors laid in 1g room and in the kitchen, and a for the heating plant the furnace house built back of the student I girls' basketball team, six dormi-All of the dormitory boys played on either the first or second boys' team in the School. A few students were left at Christmas to help with the work all seemed delighted to return to School after the holidays. The boys have done all kinds of farm work they have taken care of the stock, gotten in wood, and many other things. The girls have waited tables, washed dishes, worked in the laundry, and done house cleaning. The dormitory student grades have on the whole been good, some making outstanding grades and only a few poor ones. With their work and activities, it is remarkable the good grades they do make. The general atmosphere of the dormitory life has been good and all have been happy together. MARY ELLA MCDONALD R][NC]IPAL'S ANNUAL 18' EPOR T, 1936-1937 'd on August 19, 1936 with the aching staff: William King, Prine, History; Ben Fleming, Science, telly Huff, English, History; Anne omits, Chemistry; Pauline Torley, th grades ; Roger Ward, Fifth and ary Durkee, Fourth grade; Rose-d, Third grade; Mary Glenn grade; Eleanor Brabson, First .ry school enrollment on opening less than last year, but the high .t was 78 the first day. The enroll-Eons by grades are as follows: MENT ELEMENTARY SCHOOL Boys Girls Total 43 32 75 16 19 35 15 14 29 22 25 47 10 14 24 10 12 22 13 13 26 10 10 20 139 139 278 DLLMENT HIGH SCHOOL 15 31 .............. 1.6 .............. 5 11 16 .............. 6 10 16 .............. 11 13 24 .............. 38 49 87 177 188 365 IONS ELEMENTARY SCHOOL 60 .............. 35 25 .............. 12 11 23 .............. 13 8 21 .............. 18 22 40 .............. 6 10 16 .............. 10 11 21 .............. 8 10 18 ............. . 6 . 6 12 108 113 221 MOTIONS HIGH SCHOOL 12 23 11 5 9 14 4 10 14 9 13 22 29 44 73 dance Elernen 200 .............. tendance High 78 .............. Elementary School. Although the elementary school enrollment dropped from 300. last year to 278 this year, the attendance was much more regular this year due to the open winter. The placing of a man in charge of the elementary school worked well. The general discipline in that building improved greatly. The building is still very crowded and an assembly room for chapel exercises is badly needed. The basement room under the hall was cleaned out to be used as a playroom for bad weather, but no floor has been put in yet. The walls and ceilings of the classrooms were painted a light color, which makes lighting much better in that building. The textbooks were changed this year. The new books are a great improvement over the old ones and should' be helpful in improving instruction. High School. The fourth year of high school was added to the school this year. Twenty-four seniors were enrolled, twenty-two of whom were graduated. A laboratory was installed to teach chemistry and general science. The smallest room in the high school building was used for the laboratory room. Enough equipment was purchased to meet the minimum state requirements. Chemistry, General Science, American History, Economics, and fourth year French were added to the high school curriculum this year. Non-vocational agriculture was taught in the place of vocational agriculture. Special emphasis was placed on practical agriculture for this section. The attitude of the high school students towards their work improved throughout the year. Most of them are serious minded and in earnest about their work. Extra-Curricular Activities. Both the boys' and girls' basketball teams had successful seasons. The boys' team won all their games but two, and the girls won more than half their games. The boys went to the semi-finals in the district tournament. More people attended the home games than we could well accommodate. Mr. Fleming coached the boys' team and Mr. Ward the girls' team. The local chapter of the Future Farmers of America held their regular bi-monthly meetings. They initiated sixteen new members this year, making a total of thirty members in the organization. Besides their regular meetings they had two THE SEPTEMBER ARROW socials a weiner roast in the fall and spring, having the home-economics girls as their guests. They sponsored a program "The Crazy Tennesseans," from Knoxville to make money to pay their club dues. The Christmas programs went off nicely. The larger pupils presented their program on Thursday evening, and the primary group had theirs on Friday morning, after which the stockings were given out. The Junior class gave the play "Don't Darken My Door," in March, and the Seniors presented the three act comedy "Redheaded Step-child," during commencement week. Both plays were well received by large crowds. The pupils enjoyed Mr. Richard Seamen's work with us. He taught folk songs and games to the pupils. He also led songs and games at community parties, which were enjoyed by old and young. Student Aid. Ten students received $216 from the National Youth Administration for work at school. Two girls had charge of the library, two others washed dishes for the school lunch room, one boy worked on the campus, and others did various jobs about the school. Commencement. Rev. O. E. Tumor from the First Baptist Church of Knoxville, preached the baccalaureate sermon, and Prof. B. O. Duggan, from the University of Tennessee, delivered the graduating address. Class night and' the senior play were also part of the commencement activities. Agriculture. Twenty-one boys were enrolled in the agriculture class this year. Eighteen of these finished the year and received credit for course. The work was divided into six units of six weeks each. These units were: 1. Horticulture, 2. Live-stock and Poultry, 3. Field Crops, 4. Home Orchards, 5. Cattle enterprise, 6. Farm Management. Shop Work. Eighteen class periods were de-voted to shop work. This time was divided between familiarizing the boys with carpenter and black-smith tools and doing useful repair work about the place. A shopwork exhibit at the County fair won six first prizes and three second prizes. Field Trips. The agriculture class made numerous field trips during the year. Visits were made to the Sevier County, and East Tennessee fairs. Other trips included visits to packing companies, woolen mills, dairies, creamery, hatchery, lime quarry, and fertilizer factory. Community Work. The agriculture coma work had to be worked into an otherwis program. A class for the seventh and eighth boys was held at Wearwood school last fal. work consisted of rope and leather work little carpenter work. The chief value of this is in interesting these boys in high school. ous visits were made to farms to doctor animals. Farm Report. Financial report by month; Month Disbursements Cash Receipts Products ti 182.43 $ 4.65 $ 184. July Aug. ... 86.72 23.23 175. Sept. 174.62 35.58 180. Oct 93.06 89.85 136. Nov. ... 78.08 38.70 108 Dec. ... 6.00 7.25 118 an. 51.45 82.00 134 eb. 12.56 9.00 146 March .. 190.40 .00 191 April .. 222.85 87.32 186 Paid by S. 421.29 S. Treas. Total ...$1,519.45 $398.29 $1,562 Total income first ten months $1 Total expense first ten months 1 Net income Farm Improvements and Changes. The ch provements on the farm this year were the bl of new fences around all the poultry yards, new line fence between the school and Mr. land. The sheep have been disposed of at will be a great help to the pastures, as the ate the grass so short that the steep lan beginning to wash in some places. Two Jersey gilts were purchased for breeding The vegetable garden is being consideral creased this year with the hope that the ; can be sold to the hotels and CCC Camps Student Labor. Student labor has beer satisfactory this year. The older and me perienced boys required less supervision, an done better work than could be expectec younger boys. All the wood used by the Craft Shop and the school was cut by them also built the new fences. Ambers and Arlie have been agreeable t with. Both work hard at their jobs and he interest of the school at heart. Respectfully submitted WILLIAM COMMITTEE ON EXTENSION y OUR Committee on Extension has tried hard, since last Convention, to discover new fields that seemed to have possibilities for extension for Pi Beta Phi. Correspondence with Alumnae clubs, scattered alumnae, and national officers has been very helpful. A few inquiries were received from local groups at universities and colleges where there is not a chapter of our organization. Inquiries as to our policy of extension were received from groups at Akron University, Berea College, Kent College, Lake Forest College, Toledo University, and Miami University. Alumnae have written this Committee in the interests of local sororities on the campuses of the University of British Columbia, Creighton University, University of Kansas City, and Willamette University. This Committee has sent out letters to regarding possibilities on the following can Florida Southern, University of Georgia, University, Queen's University, Mississipt versity, North Carolina, Storrs, University ( nesse, University of New Mexico, and Was] College in Maryland. We feel Willamette University at Saler gon, furnishes a field that may prove quite i ing as soon as National groups are permitter campus by the Board of Trustees of the The merits of the three local sororities campus have been investigated and alumna vicinity will soon report on the possibilities school. We are grateful to all Pi Beta Phis wl answered our inquiries so promptly and ful </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



