<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr5130873_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Pattengill, Emma </name></author>
                        <author><name>Duffield, Georgie M.</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>February 1935</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr5130873_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">February 1935</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Pattengill, Emma </name></author>
                        <author><name>Duffield, Georgie M.</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 872-877</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">38</note>
                        <note type="Folder">14</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 51, Number 3 (February 1935), Pages 872-877.</note>
			<note type="document">arr5130873_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">The Staff 1934-1935; Summary of the Work Done at the Settlement School Committee Meeting; My Guest Book; Notes from Mrs. Weaver's Letters; Odd Items from the Settlement School</note>
                        <note type="Additional Information">Issue titled Convention News, February 1935.</note>
	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Staff</item>
                                <item>Facilities</item>
                                <item>Tourism</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr5130873_0001" seq="01" n="872-873  "/>
       <p>ROM LITTLE PIGEON 111111111 1111111 11111.111111.11111.1111111,11.111.1. 1111.111.11111.111111.1111.11111IM111111181111A.I.1111,11.111.1.11111111111I 1111I 111111 I THE STAFF 1934 35 pool Committee takes Mrs. Eunice Weaver, of the School for the reaver has been house for the past few years, ias endeared herself to graduate of the Uni AVER, DIRECTOR rs. Weaver's daughter Robert) also a memhbors to the West Sub-^f Chicago. ived the resignation of ee during convention. to be relieved of her re-Id had gone to Yellow-return to Gatlinburg, the committee accepted her resignation. Mrs. Weaver was one of the personnel of convention, and on the last day four of the committee who were also present at convention talked with her about the directorship of the School. After some consideration, she consented to serve as head resident until definite arrange-merits could be made, and after a few weeks at Gatlinburg, accepted the definite appointment as director. The committee sincerely appreciates the efforts she is making in behalf of the work in Gatlinburg. Mrs. Emma Pattengill, whose Arrow Craft exhibit was of absorbing interest to visitors at Old Faithful, also made many friends at convention. In December Mrs. Pattengill closed a year of devoted service as manager of Arrow Craft. At this time the death of a member of her family called her home, and she returned to the school for only long enough to fill Christmas orders and close her books. She is once more in her home in Ames, Iowa, where her daughter is an active member of Iowa Gamma. Mrs. Pattengill under-took her work at Gatlinburg at a very difficult time. A letter from her, printed else-where in this department, shows her appreciation of the mountain people she dealt with and of the worth of the school. As her successor, comes another Ames Pi Phi; Mrs. Esther Weaver Snow. For a number of years Mrs. Snow's home has been in Los Angeles where she has been an enthusiastic member of the alumna club, often handling Settlement School goods. She has had exceptional preparation for the managership of Arrow Craft, for she was trained under Mrs. Mary Atwater, one of the foremost weaving teachers in the country. In addition she has had teaching and commercial experience. With her daughter, Jane, who is in the second year of high school, she motored from California to Tennessee in time for the New Year. From Iowa comes Ethel Irene Mitchell, the new supervisor of weaving. Mrs. Mitchell has her B.S. and M.S. degrees from Iowa THE FEBRUARY ARROW State College, but she had completed the normal training course for elementary school teachers at Illinois Teachers' College at Ma-comb, Illinois, and had taught school six years before going to Ames. Her time will be largely spent in supervising the weavers who work for Arrow Craft and in planning with its manager articles to be sold in the shop. Mrs. Mitchell has written enthusiastically of the mountain women and of her interest in the school and the beauty of its surroundings. William King is back as principal of the school and teacher in the high school. In addition, he has charge of the boys' athletics, training the teams and taking charge on trips. Much of the life and spirit of any school depends on sports, and in. Gatlinburg the interest in games not only fills this need and helps to keep up school attendance, but it furnishes wholesome school and community entertainment. The news of Mr. King's re-turn was received with great enthusiasm in Gatlinburg. Highly recommended from among the 1934 graduates at the University of Tennessee comes Mary Elizabeth Spencer. She is teaching home economics. Missouri r again has sent a teacher to theSettlement School. This year it is I Douthit, who has second and third Dorothy comes with two years' exper teaching in Oklahoma and a very g interest in her work. Along with these new members o. Phi family in Gatlinburg, there ar( who have been at the School for son Mr. King would not consider himsc nor would jean Handley, although sl new position. Jean is doing high scho now, filling the position made vacant 1 ine Whaling's marriage to jack Hu Duffield has charge of the shop in the tain View Hotel. Veatress Patton at the main shop. Maggie Parton and Alice McCarter weave special Mrs. McDonald heads the household ment. Lucy Field, Texas A, ren bookkeeper, and Virginia Moore a Don Smith teaches agriculture and the farm. After a summer term at t versity of Tennessee, Eleanor Brab Miriam Swann are back teaching th( class and the first grades, respective].) Huff, Iowa r, continues in the four and her sister, Stella, has fifth and six Watson and Ambrose Ogle look stock and grounds. SUMMA Y OF THE WORK DONE AT THE SETTLE1 SCHOOL COMMITTEE MEETING The Settlement School Committee, meeting at Gatlinburg, Tennessee July 16-23, 1934, 1. Reviewed the year just past and found it good in spite of the changes in the staff and the closing of the dormitories ; 2. Learned, upon examination of the treasurer's books, that the school was in a slightly stronger position financially than it had been in July, 1933, the time of the previous meeting; 3. Arranged to reopen the dormitories; 4. Filled vacancies on the staff; 5. Inspected the School properties and planned the necessary repairs and replacements; 6. Discussed the School and Gatlinburg community with the members of the local committee Mrs. Steve Whaley, Mrs. Newt Clabo, Mr. Harve Reagan, and Mr. Charley Clabo and received their assurances of appreciation and continued cooperation ; 7. Accepted with gratitude interest moneyvoted by the Alumnae Department at don to be applied on the School ind( and used the $575.00 received this the mortgage rather than on the de Settlement School Endowment (t: gage is now $3,325.00) ; 8. Attended a special meeting of linburg Weavers' Guild at which harp and ballad singing and husban( 9. Received assurance from count of money to pay the regularly allow for a junior high school principal; 10. Formulated manuals for the of Arrow Craft and the supervisor ing; 11. Planned for the year of 193 12. Felt deeply touched by the fa of the staff at Gatlinburg and of the of Pi Beta Phi throughout the c, maintaining the Settlement School cient a level during a year of trial a tainty; </p>
      <pb ref="arr5130873_0002" seq="02" n="874-875  "/>
       <p>THE FEBRUARY ARROW surely upon every concontinuance of the Settlement School and its people the need for the many human services. MY GUEST B OK By GEORGIE M. DUFFIELD charge of the shop in the Mountain View Hotel where Arrow craft goods are sold, is a ly and a most enthusiastic supporter of Pi Beta Phi in Gatlinburg. In her own inimitable the visitors to her shop.) 3 of my guest book with )ver and its pages filled es and pleasant memo-; son of a Pi Phi mother l kept him from buying he found we had noth-;ouvenir for small boys. me to the door and sing )p where there's nothing Lily, in desperation, he cheapest thing in the him, he pulled fifteen et and handed it to me Lis mat. I'll give it to when we get home." I Beet little voice, as he el lobby, chanting, "So there's nothing for lit ;e after page of names, of our country's best it is to be thrown with Charles D. Walcott of fore her marriage was [elphia! She is seventy-major general, doesn't uses no make-up, yet eshest complexion and .e, they are so dear and igent. Her gray hair and twisted in a small ply but always in good lture and breeding who !rtained by members of country and moves as a the scientific circles of lis lifetime, her husband charge of the Smithsonshington, of which she relates many interesting gether. She has painted I flowers, Rockies and which were printed by tution. The deluxe ediolume. Hers was a laborof love and took her twenty years to paint. She paints the flowers life size and while they are fresh. She never draws an outline, but with her brush and magic skill, paints them as they are, all the time talking to you in the most entertaining way. A very decided character, no patience with some of the present day doings. One thing she absolutely tells you most emphatically, "You are' welcome to come and talk with me but no cigarette smoke is to be puffed over .me or in the room where I am working." She first came to our mountains at the request of Horace Albright, who at that time was director of all the national parks. Mr. Albright thought she might find some specimens in the Great Smokies that were not among the ones in her collection. She rises fairly early and if the morning is fair, she goes for her ride through the woods and off the beaten path, taking a guide with her. The afternoon is spent in painting. Oftentimes the entire day is spent at her work. She is not only an artist but a very practical business woman who has managed large farming interests. She always travels in her own car with her trusted chauffeur. On her last visit Mrs. Walcott brought Mrs. Ickes with her for her first visit to the Park. Here is another personage whom I wish I could describe with her simple, unaffected manner, she is a real person, who accomplishes things, and always has, gracious and cordial to everyone, with a zest for life. She's an inspiration to be with. Both she and Mrs. Walcott had a thoroughly enjoyable time, going to the church one Sunday afternoon to hear "my mountain folks" sing hymns. They stayed until it was over, were introduced to all the singers, and thanked them for the mu-sic. Mrs. Walcott is very, very fond of Mrs. Herbert Hoover and visits the Hoovers in their California home. She gave me an order to make one of my afghans for Mrs. Hoover. I have it ready. I tried to make it look like California gold and sunshine. Hope she will like it. THE FEBRUARY ARROW Another very charming person is Mrs. Josephus Daniels. Just one of the lovely, sweet, motherly sort of persons, with no effort at being stylish but a personage one instinctively felt, was just a very devoted grandmother who came into the shop to get something to send to her little grandsons. Again I had to confess that I had nothing for little boys. She had waited for me to get back from dinner and open the shop. Once previous to this time, she and her husband were brought to our shop by one of my friends. It was Sunday, and sohe would just have to count it up f( said, "Isn't it wonderful to have such keeper" and my generous custom "What about the customers ?" and "Oh, I'll tell you that when you have Imagine my telling them to please ste the lobby while I wrapped up the (my shop is too small for my stock tomers at the same time) . I dug th Book out of a corner, for I haven't a put it, and asked them to write thei in it. You know men don't fuss aroi HIGH SCHOOL BOY I unlocked the door and let them in. Mr. Daniels stayed the courteous length of time and departed. She, while busy picking up things here and there, said, "I just hope he will stay out, because he doesn't want me to buy things on Sunday and I'm going to do it anyway." Another time just lately while I was waiting on some customers, Major Eakin came to the door, with three awfully good looking men and introduced them. I didn't catch the names at first, but found out mighty quickly they wanted to buy. I got so excited that I pulled things out right and left and when one of them began walking around and picking five-dollar coverlet squares off the line and pewter plates off the tables and scarfs out of the drawers, I just turned to Major Eakin and handed him a paper and pencil and told himwomen, when they pay they do it in After they had gone and I had the and saw inscribed there, "R. G. Tu; went dizzy and thought to myself, t dent's is not the only "brain" th "trusters." Mr. Tugwell really has a ally charming personality and is v looking indeed. Doesn't look a thin world like the pictures I've seen of : only ones I've seen looked like Dil some other cut throat. He was only i burg about half an hour and spent that time to come into our little shot generously. Thank you, Mr. Tugwel A few nights ago I was tempte home and not go back to the shop not feeling up to par and there s few guests in the hotel. But the there's a kind providence that wat. </p>
      <pb ref="arr5130873_0003" seq="03" n="876-877  "/>
       <p>THE FEBRUARY ARROW fools, and so I came back. And I was! I had only been here for es, when my attention was atittle man coming down the line, very good looking younger man. the shop, and there followed one woman. The little man was somebody the lady was from They, with the other members were a group of famous people the housing question and had 1gland, Germany, and the States ith a T.V.A. group at Norris. generously. Sir Evin was very laughingly showed the others a pstick towel he had purchased ad a use for it but just for the ,r. ooking forward to the 17 to the !r when the American Forestry eaded by the Secretary of Inte-[ckes ; the Secretary of Agricul-A. Wallace; the Chairman of T.V.A., A. W. Morgan ; and E. B. Cammerer, Director of National Parks (who by the way is not only a very delightful man but a good customer of ours) meets. This meeting is to be held in Knoxville, but they will pay a visit to the Smokies and, as this is Park Headquarters, I'm expecting a visit from them. October the 8 is to be a great day for Gatlinburg. The Great Smoky Mountains National Park stamp is to go on sale. First Day cover, only in Washington and Gatlinburg. Already there are great piles of letters and requests to the postmaster for first day stamps. One collector that I know of has sent in re-quest for 10,000. We expect a crowd in that day. Numbers and numbers of Pi Phis have visited the shop and school this season. My tongue is hanging and my brain is fagged from the constant telling of the School and the work the Pi Phis are doing in this community. (The second installment of "My Guest Books* will appear in the May ARROW.) FOURTH GRADERS NOTES F OM MRS. WEAVE 9S LETTERS )rtly before the ARROW went to Teaver said: itory boys and girls (there are em) came home from the state Tille drenched but saying that )nderful time. Virgil Ogle and Elmer Helton took first prize for a self-feeder that they made for hogs. Earl Reagan took second for sharpening a hand saw. He and Bruce Whaley made a chicken coop which took third prize. Arrow Craft did not enter anything this year. THE FEBRUARY ARROW "The boys are now working on the stone walks and getting the gardens in shape for winter. Previously, they studied cement mixing preparatory to flooring the barn under Don Smith's supervision. "Last week a man came from Knoxville and arranged to give us a drop curtain and a set of stage scenery for the assembly hall. Space for advertising on the curtain will be sold, and the proceeds will pay for the 0 D ITEMS FROM THE The Settlement School nurse, Virginia Moore, last year had eleven schools under her supervision. She inspected 1544 children and visited 371 of them in their homes, while 654 called on her for professional services. At the Jennie Nichol Memorial Hospital at the Settlement School, typhoid innoculations were given to 210 persons; 47 children took toxoid for diphtheria; 52 youngsters had Schick tests to determine their diphtheria immunity; 134 were vaccinated for small pox. Dressings were done for 513 school children " and members of the community. LETTER FROM MRS. PATTENGILL Mrs. Pattengill wrote in July: "There are about sixty-five women doing our weaving, besides the following specialized workers contributing to Arrow Craft: Mary L. Ownby makes our chairs and stools, using a crude foot lathe and turning out works of art. The fobt lathe, called boom and treddle, is the most antique in existence, and is used in the Orient. Arlena McCarter takes great pride in bringing in several dozen colored split fans each week. Mrs. Ogle's contfibution is rye straw fans. Harrison McCarter makes the best baskets in Gatlinburg and can make `All you'ns can use.' Aunt Sally makes the "Aunt Sallies" and brings them in when it rains. Mertie Bales makes good willow trays and coasters. Mrs. Hatcher makes our beautiful quilts. All our Number 1 hooking, which included hooked rugs, is done by Mrs. Armstrong ; and gift. It will be ready to use for "Gatlinburg is to have a little the year. Squire Maples is to bu the post office and his house. Tl be there and perhaps dancini come next spring, you will find tain in the log cabin beyond th "There are 292 children in sc year." SETTLEMENT SCHC the Number 2 hooking, by Mrs Both women do superior work design. Lizzie Lemons does fine tuft Elmer Kear makes our al brooms. Penland Weavers and Potts with the beautiful hand hamme which we not only make a 35 which enhances the beauty of o. Mr. Lamb makes for us han wax candles and honey jugs fil mountain honey. Wood carvers make reprodu( American furniture from nati' walnut which adds a great deal this beautiful furniture. A careful survey shows fift: entirely dependent on us for a 1 families are supported in a n-school." "I believe our fraternity is d trial work that is about ten yea scope. T.V.A. has ahead of it a similar to ours. Some of their have interviewed us and in g ideas show that they are planni: thing that our fraternity has dl years. The influence of the Mountains National Park ha$ village. We have an opportunil tensiveness of which few reali trade is four times as great a5 ago to keep abreast of it all N large vision. One of the big pr.( ticipate what is ahead and to b^ whatever is required of us." EmmA ' </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



