<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr5820159_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Think on These Things</title>
                        <author><name>Copp, Ethel Hogan</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>December 1941</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr5820159_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">December 1941</date>, Think on These Things</title>
                        <author><name>Copp, Ethel Hogan</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 158-159</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">39</note>
                        <note type="Folder">10</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 58, Number 2 (December 1941), Pages 158-159.</note>
			<note type="document">arr5820159_0000</note>


	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Philanthropy</item>
                                <item>Education</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr5820159_0001" seq="01" n="158-159  "/>
       <p>"Think on These Things" You and I hold in trust a monument to our Founders. Long ago we dedicated to their memory a Settlement School. Our wish was to perpetuate the ideals of friendship and service which prompted the founding of our Fraternity, We have grown strong while nurturing it. Upon this occasion, the members of your Settlement School Committee feel a truly great responsibility. For today we must re-dedicate ourselves to renewed effort in our service to humanity, if we are to remain a strong organization of educated women. We are convinced that a national philanthropy is vital to our growth and strength. Maintaining a high degree of enthusiasm for it is essential. This comes only from understanding of the needs and belief in them. In view of changing world conditions your committee does not pretend to know all that the future has in store for our service, nor do we attempt to predict accurately ; but we have a feeling that our sincere effort to make the right decisions today, plus a faith in the tomorrow, will combine to make our future right. Your service has been unselfish, unstinted, and devoted. Upon no other basis could there be reflected this living memorial to our loved Founders a contribution to human betterment which far exceeds our fondest hopes and dreams of thirty-two years ago. In the fraternity world there is no comparison. In the world of philanthropy it is noteworthy. Grateful, always, have been our members that wise planning gave us the opportunity to develop a national welfare project whose support is based upon service and not assessment. In terms of hours of labor, many of you claim a sizable investment. In terms of actual money from your own pocketbooks, how very little you have been called upon to give! Most often your financial investment was returned in immediate recreational relaxation. Regardless of the medium of ex-change, Pi Phi has given generously, and to Pi Phi has been returned in abundance! Our next phase of usefulness beckons with a firm hand and, if followed, will lead us into a greater contribution to human uplift than even our colorful pioneer days have shown. Our past has been a development. Our future will be a development toward a richer field of experience for the large community of which, long ago, we became self elected sponsors a richer experience even for our-selves. Battling against ignorance, starvation, and superstititon was a stimulating challenge the results so obvious! It will continue to be a soul-satisfying challenge to supplement the bare essentials of county education with every possible field of influence to enrich further the lives of a great people. There is much to be done, if we are to develop to capacity this truly pure blood Anglo-Saxon people and prepare them to take their rightful place among the prideful, strong, and worthy people, whose power and stability our nation so desperately needs. And we must redouble our efforts. This is no time to become satisfied. We have a long way to go. And the gratifying part of all this is, it can be accomplished in our own plant in the Smokies. Radiating from this area, our influence will be far reaching indeed. There is no form of service that is educational, humanitarian, or helpful to mankind which cannot be cared for in Gatlinburg. Our School can expand and transform itself into any field that intelligent thinking and national viewpoint may determine. Never should we impoverish ourselves by giving materially of our physical assets and never should we surrender that precious portion of our capital investment our prestige in a region where our roots are strong and far reaching. With our integrity safeguarded, in a community where our good name is firmly established, the forces of our national unity can and will assure success in whatever field we choose to develop within the physical plant already owned by us. In fact no individual Pi Phi dream of service, however remote or far fatched, is out of the realm of possibility. Possessing more than the usual advantages in scenic wonders, with lavish beauty displayed in seasonal changes, a moderate climate, and great accessibility few geographic locations offer more. Right there in the Smokies will continue to be Pi Phi's source of strength, providing both inspiration and steadfast -purpose combined with unity in determining our trends. It is fortunate that the intensive study of trends which your committees have been making for years is clearing itself and beginning to take definite direction at this 158 THE DECEMBER ARROW 159 time. It is with much satisfaction that the committee brings certain assurances to you of their findings as they review the Settlement School in this memorial issue of the ARROW. In following closely the Settlement School history, you will know that always there has been the accepted fact that our service was not static. We have been experiencing changes for years. Do not be misled by neon signs or the influx of the traveling public in 'Gatlinburg. All this has stimulated certain obvious relinquishments of our service, such as the recent decision to turn over to the county the Elementary School in 1943. Do not forget that the county has been paying for years, a substantial sum toward the expense of the Elementary School, including salaries and rent and a considerable sum on the High School. But do not forget, too, that Pi Phi's ad-ministration of this school has supplemented the county support by supplying school room supplies and equipment, that it has given proper maintenance of buildings, and that by careful selection of the teachers it has offered a curriculum which far exceeds the demands of the State of Tennessee. In planning for our future, it is highly desirable that Pi Phi maintain certain contacts and continue certain responsibilities in both the Elementary and High Schools that will provide education, guidance, and inspiration in fields not other-wise possible in this county. Do not think when we make certain changes in our service that there is no further need in Gatlinburg. We are just beginning. Pi Beta Phi's philanthropy is a very live issue a very active interest. You will be interested to know that your committee has been making a record of every constructive question from alert Pi Phis everywhere while thinking up far harder ones themselves, as they completed an exhaustive survey of trends with arguments for and against each phase of our service. With committee's evaluation complete, arrangements were made several months ago to secure an authoritative outside survey from the best possible source for unquestioned opinions and advice. With the decision to turn back the Elementary School came the logical time for the Fraternity to profit most from a professional survey. Welcomed was a thorough evaluation of every department with relation to the quality of its past service, present value, and future need. An analysis of administration will help determine our future course and the advice of experts will assist us as we together direct the planning of all future supplementary service. Especially pleased is the Settlement School Committee to present to the Fraternity the first word from the survey which is just being brought to conclusion by Dr. William S. Taylor, of Lexington, Dean of Education at the University of Kentucky. We believe that enough factual serious study has been made, over a period of many years by the Fraternity through its national officers, its Settlement School Committee and through previous surveys by others whose experience has made their judgment reliable and highly valued, to justify us in accepting the present summing up as a sound basis upon which to formulate future plans. Accordingly, a highly qualified but completely unbiased and unprejudiced stranger was invited to make a critical evaluation. To the best of our knowledge both Dr. Taylor and Professor Seay, his assistant, were unknown to any member of Council or Committee and possessed no advance knowledge of the School or the Fraternity. Upon the assistance of the present report by Dr. Taylor, plus the findings of long Fraternity study and experience, and the ac-cumulation of recommendations from ever-changing committees and previous surveys, a plan will be based for an expanded program which we can conscientiously recommend and in which we sincerely believe. From this sum total of experience will evolve a path so straight, a plan so logical that it will be self-evidently right. It will be just what you have expected and wished for all the time a vision of an enlarged circle of worthy influence radiating from our Settlement School. The Settlement School Committee will give earnest consideration to the report of Dr. Taylor, and to his supplementary suggestions which lack of time has kept out of this issue of the ARROW, and will make re-port of their recommendations at Convention next June. ETHEL HOGAN COPP, California r Chairman, Settlement School Committee </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



