<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr5320199_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Brown, Charlotte Cropley</name></author>
                        <author><name>Johnson, Paul</name></author>
                        <author><name>Bishop, Evelyn</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>November 1936</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr5320199_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">November 1936</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Brown, Charlotte Cropley</name></author>
                        <author><name>Johnson, Paul</name></author>
                        <author><name>Bishop, Evelyn</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 199-204</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">38</note>
                        <note type="Folder">17</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 53, Number 2 (November 1936), Pages 199-204.</note>
			<note type="document">arr5320199_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Ten Years of Arrow Craft; Arrow Crafters Suggest Some Anniversary Trading Possibilities; The Southern Highlands; The Weavers' Guild Play; Report of the 1936 Settlement School Committee Meeting</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>
                                <item>Handicraft</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr5320199_0001" seq="01" n="198-199  "/>
       <p>THE NovEMBER ARROW Dcker, artist, of Los Angeles, province officer of the fraternity to be chosen ar managed the Art Exhibit at from the west Coast, and that she was reles County Fair, as she has done sponsible for the fine display of articles from access for many years. It is of the Settlement School at Bullocks in Los Miss Horlocker was the first Angeles. MAGAZINES`' FOR THE UNUSUAL GIFTS )ck, knock." o's there ?" vard." vard who?" vard you like to receive a gift subscription this Christmas ?" the busy season now in full swing it is especially important that Pi Phis friends keep in mind that we have a Magazine Agency. are magazine minded, which I am sure most Pi Phis are, we can not only 'hers in solving the Christmas Gift problem, but avoid the wild scramble st of us have about a week before Christmas. special bulletin of Christmas Gift offers will be sent any Pi Phi upon from your District Chairman. If you are already selling our subscriptions w what a fine project we are carrying on. If you are not using our Magaency for your friends and yourself we urge you to start at once. nissions vary rom 5c to $1.50 on all magazine subscriptions. These corn-are sent at different intervals to the Settlement School Treasurer, Miss erty. The School depends upon this income for a part of its budget. lew set-up of having the agency divided into four districts should make c more efficient as well as add to our volume of business. esses of District Chairmen appear in the Directory pages of this number. )rget the Pi Beta Phi Magazine Agency. EDITH U. STEPHENSON NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON Edited by CHARLOTTE CROPLEY BROWN, Vermont B ARROW CRAFT SHOP TEN YEARS OF ARROW CRAFT THE current Pi Beta Phi year seems to be one significant for Settlement School anniversaries. First to appear is the tenth anniversary of Arrow Craft Shop later months will bring the School's own twenty-fifth anniversary. Arrow Craft's rise to a preeminent position among American handicraft centers is the result of an ever-increasing loyalty on the part of Pi Beta Phi's members throughout the country and Pi Beta Phi's workers throughout the 'Burg. Then, too, a number of handicraft experts have given to the Shop the benefit of their special training. Small wonder that the present weaving-teacher encouraged our weavers this past spring to prepare a special anniversary towel with a motif of ten lighted candles. In a report to the Convention preceding 1926 Miss Evelyn Bishop said, "The baskets and weaving we have for sale are in Mrs. Dowell's room in the attic. Not the least of our troubles is to find a place to store and pack, as well as to sell, the baskets. The business has grown until it really would keep one person busy all the time if it were handled as it should be." Today the Shop is attractively housed in the School's first building, the remodeled schoolhouse. The weaving department is set up nearby in the stone building which earlier housed the woodcraft dc ment. Their staffs include four full workers and many assistants. Besides, is a branch shop in the lobby of the l tain View Hotel with an extremely able ager there. And in 1936 all of these we are busy all of the time. Twelve months' industrial income it pre-1926 year had amounted to $4,981 the twelve months preceding the 1936 vention net sales were reported $25,830.72. Edgewater Beach sales alon largest in Convention history, amount $1,456.77. Since then Arrow Craft's ma. has reported August, 1936, the best ri in local retail history, with over $1,6i cash sales. That the development of Arrow Cra: remained altruistically worth while in tl years of its rapidly expanding busing perhaps best illustrated by quoting an o of the Southern Highlanders in Norris said in September of this year, "Rece asked a member of the Pi Beta Phi st Gatlinburg what proportion of her w( were at or near the relief level. She i nantly declared that none of them which brought to me forceful recogniti the value of Pi Beta Phi work in that 1 </p>
      <pb ref="arr5320199_0002" seq="02" n="200-201  "/>
       <p>THE NOVEMBER ARROW 201 \ OW C AFTE S Suggest Some Anniversary Tradin Possibilities 1. Pi Beta Phi Cook Book compiled by the Los Angeles Alumni Club, 50c. 2. Cellophane evening bag satin-lined, white and pastels, $1.50. 3. Cellophane sport purse blue, green, red, white or yellow, $1.50. 4. Arrow Craft Anniversary towel all linen, blue, green, yell ow with white candles; white with wine and blue candles, $1.25. 5. Pi Beta Phi towel all linen, silver blue with wine red letters, $1.25. 6. Beverage napkins oblong, fringed, small stripes in mixed colors, 4 for 85c. 7. Cellophane mat with marvelous Christmas decorqting possibilities, white, green or red, 16 by 12 inches. 60c. Pewter bowl a product of Penland Weavers and Potters, 10 inches in diameter, $3.50. 9. Candles the familiar long-lived hand dipped beeswax variety, natural, red or green, 7 inch ones, 25c a pair, 12 inch ones, 50c a pair. 10. Streamline towels all linen, white with black, brown, green, gold or red, $1.00. 11. Shoulder shawl soft wool in pastel colors, one of the Shop's loveliest creations, 27 by 54 inches, $3.50. 12. Etching "In Tennessee," colored, the product of Leon Pescheret who is a Pi Phi husband, $7.50. Special Emphasis THE ANNIVERSARY TOWELS. They will be especially treasured in years to come. THE CELLOPHANE ARTICLES. They are a startlingly modernistic product from the South's oldtime looms. Have You Sent for Your Copy of the New Arrow Craft Shop Price List? </p>
      <pb ref="arr5320199_0003" seq="03" n="202-203  "/>
       <p>THE NOVEMBER ARROW SOUTHERN HIGHLANDERS' SHOP, NORRIS DAM The Southern Hi hianders By PAUL JOHNSON 931 that the Southern Highland 't Guild was formed. A volun-)n of producers of fine handitrea of the Southern Highlands, ion dedicated itself to the mainghest quality in handicraft pro-Guild has since 1931 operated re retail shop, the Allanstand ;tries, in Asheville, North Caroafts of all the members of the ced for display and sale in this )fits from which are employed )f the Guild, as determined by 935, an organization of equal as formed. The Southern High-)perative corporation organized 's of the state of Tennessee, has . Its purposes include marketing of Southern Highland handin tourist shops and in metro.-; creation of a design counsel ans of which styling, designing 1formation may be made avail-:raft producers providing a re-for the solution of production d increasing the economic well producers of handicrafts in the outhern Highlands. )p of the Southern Highlanders is operated at the Norris Dam of the Tennessee Valley Authority, and there is also one near Chattanooga, Tennessee. Here the handicraft products of the region have been presented to thousands of tourists and visitors. Weavings, woodcarvings, pottery, and other fine handicrafts have been carried to all parts of the country. On May 1, 1936, Southern Highlanders opened its shop unit on the lower concourse of the International Building, Rockefeller Center, New York City. Handicrafts are here assembled in wider range than has ever be-fore been possible. Their use in modern home decoration schemes has been emphasized. This display is realizing one of the foremost dreams of handicraft producers, in proving that Southern handicrafts embody both the tradition of finest workmanship and the character which makes them possess a modern, living beauty and usefulness. Numbered among the membership of Southern Highlanders are almost all of the members of the Southern Highland Handicraft Guild* schools, workshops, individuals, cooperative groups. * Arrow Craft Shop belongs to both the South-ern Highland Handicraft Guild and the Southern Highlanders, Incorporated. THE NOVEMBER ARROW The Weavers' Guild Play By EVELYN BISHOP NEWS came to me, "The Weavers' Guild is writing a play, rehearsals are about to begin, the play will' be given early in July." There was no need to add that the women were having a grand time writing it and that we must be sure to go. I had seen two original productions that Homemakers classes had put on in years past and knew well that this one would be worth the trip from Norris to Gatlinburg. The program, when the gala night finally arrived, read as follows: LIGHTENING THE LOAD An Original Three Act Play Presented By The Gatlinburg Weavers' Guild Act I. October, 1898 Scene: Home of Mrs. Nancy Burns on Lone-some Creek where her neighbors have come to a workin'. Act II. Spring of 1930 Scene: Living-room in the home of Mr. and Mrs. Joe Arnold in Gatlinburg. Act III. Spring of 1938 Scene I. College room of Jewel Hamilton. Scene II. September, 1938. Living-room of a home in Gatlinburg, where Jewel lives. The cast of characters is too long to bear reprinting, but the names, chosen by the ac-tresses for themselves, were particularly interesting. A deep plot was not necessary. There wasjust the story of the changes that had to individual families and to the comm since the School had come, and the changes when the Park had given em ment to the men. The first act was the that created the most interest. It is ha say which of the women wrote it. Miss ding had to keep pruning it down, f each rehearsal the women would thir more to add bits of old mountain s stition or philosophy, sayings which an them as much as the audience. The women had really experienced many o things related in this act of the play, a: true to the times were the stage setting the loom, wheel, dye pots, and costume been in use by the actresses or their r bors in years past. The second and thin seemed to follow real happenings so c and were done so naturally that the: peared to be merely the recounting o story of the past few years. Personally, my greatest enjoyment Ns seeing the thoroughly good time the act and the audience were having. Old young paid little attention to the terrific of the room that evening. The audit, was packed and it was indeed a Gatli] audience. The play was full of humo local color, and I think we all hope weavers were really sincere when the] as soon as the curtain went down on last act, "Let's do another one next yea Report of the 1936 Settlement School Committee Meeting By LILLIAN BECK HOLTON, Chairman THE Settlement School Committee spent the week of July 7 to 14 at the School for the annual Committee meeting. Lillian Beck Holton (Mrs. E. L.) , the new chair-man, presided and Marie Bacon Hagee (Mrs. G. M.) was made secretary. Josephine Mc-Cleverty continues as treasurer. Charlotte Brown was made editor of News from Little Pigeon and Jeffries Green Pace (Mrs. E. M.) was put in charge of publicity and club programs. Mrs. Hagee and Mrs. Pace are new members of the Committee. Reports given by the director, prix Arrow Craft director, nurse, and other bers of the staff showed that the pas was one of great accomplishment. C ences with people of the community sl that our work is still greatly neede, greatly appreciated. Conferences with and state officials brought out the co tion of the School with these officia: their intent to continue to help in ft ing our work. The addition of the fourth year </p>
      <pb ref="arr5320199_0004" seq="04" n="204-205  "/>
       <p>THE NOVEMBER ARROW as decided upon and that ne-!quipment of. a chemistry lab-high school building. The ad-r will be paid by the Dosition, as well as three vaby resignations, was filled. .cient plan of production for presented by the weaving suadopted. Needed repairs were The management of the farm of production were discussed who will have charge of the tddition to being principal this contacts with the Magazine 3-rand Vice-President, and the Presidents were planned. Miss ;ain made Grand Council ad-:ommittee. An inspection trip to the Southern Highlanders' Shop at Norris Dam was made. The Committee greatly enjoyed the Weavers' play which the weavers wrote and presented for us under the direction of Gene Redding. The tea given by the Gatlinburg Alumnae Club was another delightful event, as was the dinner given by Stella Huff at the Hotel. On each of these occasions, as well as in regular sessions, the Grand Vice-President joined the Committee. After adopting budgets for both the School and the Arrow Craft Shop, the Committee adjourned with the feeling that, with the plans made and the excellent staff to carry them out, the coming year should be most successful. 300D USE OF THE FELLOWSHIP! Miss Onken from Frances Mc--4d the Pi Beta Phi Fellowship you might be interested to rn to teach English at Hollins ar. Of course, the work would !en open to me if I had not Master's Degree, and I could that without the help of the hip. I cannot possibly tell you rand Council, in words, how rience of studying at Columbia ow, five years later, I am still discovering what an inspiration it was to be! Not only to help me to find congenial work, but in many ways which do not show on the outside; acquaintance with interesting people, books and music, and countless ideas for teaching. "I haven't written much lately except some verse in the Lyric, the New York Times, and the junior League Magazine. I took a fascinating writing course this year at Bread Loaf (Middlebury's summer English School in the Green Mountains) ." SUCCESS ECOMES A T ITION Iit A 11 chapter does not pledge anybody muse. The group has learned that a large number must be discarded ightful drag while affiliated. Pledge cipline are definitely related to iniinitiation class means a large active rrespondingly large number returnich fall. ecently discussed with a traveling .son for the unusually long period -ed by a chapter of his Fraternity, zgesting that success had become a chapter. Of course, it takes some thing to create a tradition and to keep it alive. The real answer is that the members of this chapter are so keen about the Fraternity that they work diligently to maintain its high standard of performance; they know how to entertain; they subject their pledges to rigid, but wise, discipline and give them a thorough training; they initiate a large percentage of each pledge class, and, above all, the active chapter provides the pledges with a living example of what a good chapter is like. C. H. Freeark, Sigma Phi Epsilon in Fraternity Month EXCHANGES AND COLLEGE NOTE Edited by NITA DAY CARMAN, Minnesota A Approximately 200 of young college women writers, members of Theta Sigma Pi, national honorary and professional journal-ism society for women, went to Texas for the biennial national convention of that organization. They were guests of the University of Texas chapter and the Austin Alumna chapter, June 18, 19 and 20. It is interesting to recall that there are men who are members of sororities and women who are members of fraternities. Dr. Richardson of the University of Arkansas is listed as a founder of Chi Omega while General John J. Pershing is a full fledged member (in good standing, too) of Delta Delta Delta ; George Banta Sr. helped found Delta Gamma (and wrote the first constitution) and was made a member of that sorority; Eleanor Payne's father is a member of Alpha Delta Theta. Lucy Pattee of beloved Sig Alph memory was an initiated member of Sigma Alpha Epsilon in token of her services in saving valuable Sigma Alpha Epsilon documents during the Civil War, and Betty Locke, founder of Kappa Alpha Theta, was offered membership in Phi Delta Theta. Are there others ? The Fraternity Month VALUE OF A DELTA GAMMA MOTHERS' CLUB 1. It is a means of securing home cooperation in promoting the rules and policies of the Fraternity. 2. It affords an opportunity for the mothers to become acquainted with each other and with the members of the chapter, and provides a reliable means of giving mothers information concerning the chapter and the Fraternity. 3. It secures the interest and assistance of mature minds in the welfare of the chapter. 4. An organized mothers' club is in a position to be of great financial assistance to the chapter. 5. It can assist in entertaining and rushing. 6. An enthusiastic interested Gamma mother is the finest kind of Gamma "publicity." The Anchora of Gamma. Margaret Flint Jacobs, Alpha Omicrc mother of six children and wife of 1 bridge supervisor, won the Pictorial R $10,000 prize for a novel entitled "Th( Ashburn House." Mary Ellen Chase, formerly won the Pictorial Review $ short story prize, is also an Alpha On Pi. How Do WE RATE? By Louise Leonard, A r A, National Pad, Delegate Last spring, when fall rushing plans already in the air, there came to my d( chance one of the prevailing booklets are prepared for the information and cation of the presumably uninformed ees who invade the campuses each fall sons will disagree concerning the (let what should go into such booklets, has always seemed to me that fraternity taste is as valuable a requisite as pe good taste. Therefore it was with a d shock that I read among the "Do you k of this booklet prepared by a chapte: fraternity other than my own the st query "that fraternity ranks all the N.P.C. fraternities becau! ." The reasons, which could be refuted by one with a Panhellenic ground, I omit since the identity of tl ternity in question is not pertinent i present discussion. A universal besetting sin of the I race is talking too much. Most of u to talk and it is impossible to talk a deal and not have a goodly amount c talk worthless. With some of us a st. designation must be used, dubbing our harmful or even vicious. This is esp true in any superficial discussion of th tive rating of the N.P.C. groups. Supp we have all long since put away cl </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



