<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr5030275_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Frost, Mary Cooper</name></author>
                        <author><name>Whiting, Philippa Gerry</name></author>
                        <author><name>Moore, Virginia</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>February 1934</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr5030275_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">February 1934</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Frost, Mary Cooper</name></author>
                        <author><name>Whiting, Philippa Gerry</name></author>
                        <author><name>Moore, Virginia</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 275-280</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">38</note>
                        <note type="Folder">12</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 50, Number 3 (February 1934), Pages 275-280.</note>
			<note type="document">arr5030275_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Christmas at Gatlinburg; The Staff; Arrow Crafters Present A Dress to Mrs. Roosevelt; Southern Mountain Handicrafts Exhibit; The Blue Ribbon Health Program</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Holidays</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>
                                <item>Handicraft</item>
                                <item>Health care</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr5030275_0001" seq="01" n="274-275  "/>
       <p>274 THE FEBRUARY ARROW publicity), and the thrill when we received by special delivery the authentic pictures of "Lindy's" bride-to-be. In those days we were proud to announce forty-eight hour service on pictures from New York to our Iowa readers. Now we are disappointed when Tuesday's happenings in the eastern coast can not be pictured in the Des Moines Tribune in less than twenty-four hours. We used to boast of "telephoto" service which brought pictures by wireless on a special machine despite the fact that the picture might be only a mass of blurred objects. Nowadays a telephoto can be distinguished from a posed photograph only by an expert in many cases. Always there's something doing for the picture editor. A fire, a train or auto wreck, a noted citizen being honored, an inauguration, a wedding of notables, athletic events of all kinds, a cute baby winning a health contest photographers all over the country are busy taking hundreds of thousands of pictures daily of such things, and the picture editor has the job of selecting the ones most interesting to the readers of that particular paper. Once it was an event to have a picture as well as a story of a news event. Nowadays it is a necessity, for the readers demand to see, as well as hear about, what is going on. Psychologists say that a picture is worth a thousand words of description. If so, the job of picture editing would make one equal to a very prolific writer. A survey taken recently shows that the Tribune is running about six times as much art as it did five years ago. I believed it even before the survey was taken! There's something insidious about newspaper work. I've sat in sessions with dozens of newspaper men and women, and never once did I hear it defended as a profession. I take that back, I've heard a few reporters of a couple of months' experience on a small paper attempt, rather weakly, to argue that it is a "grand game." BUT and this is the funny part all the ones who attack it, work hardest at getting the news. They hate to be accused of thinking cr it a "romantic" business, but just the same we all do. Else why stick to it? And to me, the business of getting pictures from China, from London, from Paris, New York, and Cuba, from Podunkville or even from the corner across the street is the most interesting part of it all. MARY TREE WATSON PRESENTS DANCE RECITAL By RUTH SURPRENANT, North Dakota Alpha MARY TREE WATSON, Oklahoma B and now instructor in physical training for women at the University of North Dakota, presented a dance recital at Still-water, Oklahoma, her former home on January 6. Upon her graduation from the Oklahoma Agricultural and Mechanical College, she went to London where she took advanced work in dancing at the London Academy of Choreographic Art, studying under Ninette de Valois. After returning to the United States,she studied under Adolph Bolm in Chicago and for three summers danced with the Denishawn dancers in New York. Mary Tree appeared in fifteen dances on her program in Stillwater. While at-tending college she was president of her chapter and interested in all n B (I) activities. She has been teaching at the University of North Dakota for four years and during that time she has been very much interested in the activities at North Dakota A. .111,111111111111.11111 1 I I Malt i II NEWS F OM LITTLE PIGEON Edited by MARY COOPER FROST CHRISTMAS AT GATLIN I U \ G Christmas is over once more in Gatlinburg, save as memory of it lingers in the hearts of children whose happiness depended upon the loving interest of members of II B (b. In groups, the one hundred ninety children in the first six grades participated in three Christmas plays written by Jean Handley, Miriam Swann, and Eleanor Brabson. Jean's mother sent the music for them. The youngsters were dressed as little teddy bears, bunnies, candy canes, old rag dolls with their faces blacked. Each group sang nursery rimes corresponding to their dress and part in the performance. Maryalice Chaffee writes, "The teachers worked very hard to make the program a success, and Mrs. Duffield did her full share with the music. Jessie Brannan's class with the assistance of the P.T.A. took charge of all costumes. They made over a good many from other years, and SEVEN LITTLE DUTCHMEN we bought some new material too. Lucy and I think that the clubs sent enough money to cover expenses, also to pay for the candy and nuts used to fill three hundred eighty stockings. I never real ized before that there are so many children here that don't have any Christmas except what the Pi Phis provide. Mrs. McDonald bought the candy, fruit, and nuts at wholesale; these cost us $23. UPON THE THRONE That isn't so bad when you think of the number of stockings we filled." Every child in the school participated. An innovation to teach the pleasure of giving was started this year by having the children draw names to exchange ten-cent gifts. Secretly using their little store of left-over toys, the teachers provided for a gift from any youngster who couldn't afford to buy something for the child whose name he had drawn. Miss Chaffee took several group pictures for publication in "News from Little Pigeon," but as in most cases a number of youngsters moved and spoiled the effect, only a few photo-graphs can be reproduced. However, those that are printed will delight members of II B for the children look like any other groups of normal happy </p>
      <pb ref="arr5030275_0002" seq="02" n="276-277  "/>
       <p>276 THE FEBRUARY ARROW A FESTIVE STAGE AND AUDIENCE -TEDDY BEARS, BUNNIES, AND CANDY CANES" THE FEBRUARY ARROW 277 children. Part of a letter written by Miss Chaffee on December 21 may be of interest to ARROW readers: About fifteen boxes from Pi Phis came with toys and infant wear. The children drew names for gifts. In a few cases we had to fill in because some children could not afford gifts, and so we used toys that were sent. We have seventeen boxes ready for delivery to families where we are sure that the children will not have any toys for Christmas. Into these we put a toy and may-be a pair of stockings (which were sent by some of the clubs) a big Christmas stocking filled with nuts, candy, and an orange for each child in the family. I have taken two boxes out, and the people are very happy with them. As all but three members of the staff went away for all or part of Christmas, only the Director, Mrs. Pattengill, and Pauline Whaling were left at the School. Miss Chaffee continues: We have a little Christmas tree up in the living room, and we have some lights on the two pine trees in front of the house which look very beautiful at night. How the people in the Burg enjoy them! I think they said it is the first time anyone has had lights on a tree outdoors,. . I am planning to visit some of the neigh-boring schools for the programs next week. On December 28 we shall have about one hundred adults in for a visit, to play games, and to hear some mountain music. We thought it would be a good time for us to get better acquainted. The local committee, composed of Mrs. Steve Whaley, Mrs. Newt Clabo, Harve Reagan and others, are helping. They think this party will be very nice, because the local people have never had any-thing like it. We who stay want something to look forward to at holiday time. I think it will help take the place of going home. THE STAFF THE NEW MANAGER OF ARROW CRAFT Another Iowa U has come to Gatlinburg to take her place on the Settlement School staff. Mrs. E. A. Pattengill, Iowa r and a graduate of Iowa State College, arrived on December 5 to become manager of the Arrow Craft Shop in the place of LaDelle Allen. Mrs. Pattengill has been president of the Ames Alumnae Club and also chair-man of its Settlement School Commit-tee. For ten years she was treasurer of the Pi Beta Phi Investment Company which manages the affairs of the local chapter house. Such a history of interest in both active and alumnae problems proves Mrs. Pattengill's real interest in the fraternity. Since her husband's death in 1930 Mrs. Pattengill has been hostess at Margaret Hall, a house for graduate women at Iowa State. She writes of herself, "My hobby iscollecting old furniture and textiles. The happiest years of my life were spent in decorating my Colonial home, in finding and refinishing Early American furniture for it." Mrs. Pattengill's daughter Louise is a member of her mother's chapter of II B 4 at Iowa State College. THE NEW WEAVING TEACHER The Settlement School is very fortunate in being able to welcome to its staff Veva Narcisse Carr as weaving teacher to take the place of Winogene B. Redding who resigned recently. Miss Carr is a pupil of the same teacher, Mrs. Mary Atwater, a writer and an authority on weaving. Miss Carr, who has come to Gatlinburg from Florida, is not only an experienced weaver but through her own shop understands the commercial problems which the Arrow Craft Shop must meet. </p>
      <pb ref="arr5030275_0003" seq="03" n="278-279  "/>
       <p>278 THE FEBRUARY ARROW OW CRAFTERS ESENT ESS O M Again can Arrow Crafters say that the First Lady has a dress woven in the Arrow Craft Shop! Mrs. Roosevelt's well known interest in handicrafts and a desire to show her a product of the section of the South in which the President won back his health and for which he has done so many generous things were the reasons for the gift. A precedent was the material sent to Mrs. Cal-vin Coolidge when she was in the White House. Maggie Parton, a graduate of the Settlement School, wove the dress for Mrs. Roosevelt last summer. THE PRESENTATION By MARIE WINSOR STEBBINS, Assistant to the Grand President When I arrived in Washington, on November 14, to speak before the Washington Alumna: Club, my thoughts were far from meeting the First Lady of the land. One may imagine my surprise when, upon being greeted by Mrs. Reginald Geare, the club president, I was informed that a dress from the Settlement School, especially woven for Mrs. Roosevelt, was to be presented to her on the following afternoon, and that the officers of the club wished me to make the presentation. It was a pleasure to accept the invitation; and at the appointed time on the next afternoon Mrs. Geare, Mrs. Clark Ober, vice-president of the alumnx club ; Mary Katharine Lutz, ARROW Editor, Jean Kirkwood, president of District of Columbia A, and I drove up to the beautiful pillared entrance to the White House. We were greeted by the head usher who asked us to wait a few moments in the Green Room. In a moment he returned, and ushered us into the Blue Room where Mrs. Roosevelt was standing by a lovely crackly OOSEVELT open fire to receive us. After the introductions, we were seated, and Mrs. Roosevelt said, "Do tell me about your school." She wished to know where it was located and all details and when we spoke of the weaving she was re-minded that she'd learned to weave when she established a class in weaving at her school. Then I took from Mrs. Geare the lovely silver-blue box tied with a gorgeous bow of wine and silver blue ribbons and presented it to Mrs. Roosevelt telling her that Maggie Parton, a graduate of our school, had woven especially for her the beautiful white dress goods, edged with its three-inch band of white Angora. Mrs. Roosevelt asked permission to open the box at once and worked feverishly at the bow, which Mrs. Geare assured her would slip right off. But, "No, indeed !" our First Lady quickly remarked, "I was reared by a thrifty grandmother, who taught me to save string, so I know how to untie knots." And she did and was so pleased and surprised at the fine, beautiful cloth within, that she wanted to know Maggie's name and address and promised to write to her. A bit more conversation, then Mrs. Roosevelt stood and so did we all, saying our adieus. The last words I heard this very tall, charming lady say in her soft, cultured voice were, "It is very lovely!" This present was given to Mrs. Roosevelt from Pi Beta Phi Fraternity as a sign of recognition of the very genuine interest she has taken in the Exhibit of Southern Mountain Crafts which opened at the Corcoran Gallery of Art in Washington last November. This exhibit included many handsome pieces of work from our Settlement School. * Maggie is now a proud girl, for she has a letter from Mrs. Roosevelt. I\\ S. THE FEBRUARY ARROW 279 SOUTHERN MOUNTAIN HANDIC AFTS EXIiI k~i IT By PHILIPPA GERRY WHITING (MRS. F. A., JR.) District of Columbia Alpha As Pi Phis we have for years concentrated our energies upon the Settlement School, quite justifiably limiting our interest in social work to the particular job that we were able to do. But occasionally it is worthwhile to look beyond our own problem to the things that others are doing in the same field. There are, of course, many settlements throughout the Southern Mountains which are engaged in teaching the crafts, developing home industries, and otherwise improving the economic and social conditions of mountain people. To unite these agencies and further their common purpose, the Southern Highlands Handicraft Guild has been formed, a cooperating organization to which all craftsmen and handicraft producing centers are eligible whose work measures up to Guild standards in quality, design, and workmanship. The Pi Beta Phi Settlement School is one of its members. An exhibition of mountain handicrafts by members of the Guild, including a group from Gatlinburg, is now being circulated throughout the country under the auspices of the American Federation of Arts, scheduled for showing in a number of great art museums. This exhibition is of the greatest significance for various reasons: it is, in a sense, official recognition of the high artistic quality of the work of mountain people; it may prove a spur to the whole handicraft movement, which is growing all over the country; it is in-valuable publicity; it proves the existence of an extensive market. In a practical sense, the last is most important. In the six weeks that the show was on view at the Corcoran Gallery in Washington, orders were placedthrough the Federation amounting to nearly $1,400, which would be an amazing record in straight sales, but is more amazing since the articles had to be ordered always a disadvantage. By the time the exhibition finishes its circuit several thousand dollars worth of crafts will have been sold, and hundreds of thousands of people will have been interested in mountain products who previously had not known of their existence. This new interest and this wide market should be capitalized. A traveling exhibition is an excellent de-vice for introducing the crafts, but for their permanent benefit there should be salesrooms in every city of any size. Since the Guild is poor and probably will not be able to organize these itself, it should establish an adequate whole-sale department so that the crafts articles can be handled by suitable shops al-ready in existence. At present, some centers sell at wholesale and some do not, and the lack of a perfectly definite policy and of an efficient system is discouraging to the prospective retailer. The Great Smoky Mountains National Park offers an increased market for the goods, and it is hoped that the products of the Southern Highlands Handicraft Guild may have the exclusive field there some time. Pi Phis will undoubtedly be interested in the series of articles on mountain crafts that are appearing month by month in The American Magazine of Art. Several things from the Settlement School have been used to illustrate these, and more will be used in the future. Copies may be obtained from The American Federation of Arts, Barr Building, Farragut Square, Washing-ton, D.C. </p>
      <pb ref="arr5030275_0004" seq="04" n="280-281  "/>
       <p>280 THE FEBRUARY ARROW THE LUE ON HEALTH P fa, I OG AM By VIRGINIA MOORE, Public Health Nurse at the Settlement School The work in the health department has been very interesting this fall, be-cause we have been pushing the Blue Ribbon Program. On the academic side a child must be making satisfactory progress in school to qualify for a Blue Ribbon Award. On the physical side, he must be free from such defects as bad tonsils and teeth and poor vision, he must weigh within ten per cent of the average normal weight; he must take the inoculations for typhoid fever and diphtheria and be vaccinated for small-pox; and he must have kept for at least a month the ten health habits prescribed by the Tennessee State Department of Health. Last year we had seventy-eight wearers of the Blue Ribbon in the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, and this year we expect many more. For the first time we are planning a county program with a parade and with prizes for the school having the highest percentage of Blue Ribbon children. The children are eager and excited and have had defects corrected that otherwise would have been uncared for. Vaccination for smallpox seems to be the thing they dread most, but during the month of November I vaccinated about eighty, and so it seems that even the fear of a bad arm will not keepthem from wearing a Blue Ribbon this year. This program has been used by the state health department since 1930, and every year the number of schools participating and of children receiving rib-bons increases. With almost forty thou-sand children in Tennessee schools last year receiving ribbons and with a large number that are working to come up to the standard this year, the general health of the population will be raised. Not only will the health of the individual be better, but he will understand better how to guard against poor health in his children. The dentist has already been busy on dental corrections. When school re-opened in January every child was weighed again, and those underweight received extra milk at the noon meal.* The ones that had filled all requirements received a Blue Ribbon early in February. They are cherished possessions. Before that I hardly could go down the road without being stopped by some youngster who wanted to know when the awards were to be given out. *Money for the hot dish at the noon lunch is given by the P.T.A. which holds rummage sales and sells candy at the weekly movie in the high school building to raise funds for its valuable work. MR. FENN PASSES It is with sincere regret that members of II B ,(b have learned of the death of Prosper Dalien Fenn, father of Margaretta Fenn Putman. Mr. Fenn was a wonderful man and al-ways displayed great interest in the Fraternity. Mr. Fenn, publisher, printer, and binder, died in December, in Brookline, Massachusetts, while visiting his daughter, Margaretta Fenn Putman, over the holidays. Identified with the publishing business in Chicago, Mr. Fenn was president of the Metropolitan Syndicate Press for nearly 30 years. He was also vice-president of the W. B. Conkey Company, publishers in Hammond, Indiana. His father, Theophilus Fenn, was founder of the Telegraph, a newspaper at Harrisburg, Pennsylvania. Margaretta Fenn Putman (Mrs. Redding) was president of Epsilon Province before it was divided, and served afterwards as Assistant to the Grand President. The Fraternity extends to her, deep sympathy in her bereavement. FROM Y'd PHI PENS Edited by MERCEDES BAKER JORGULESCO (MRS. JONEL) YESTERDAY'S PROMISE The woods seems to be full of books about the depression. But try to find a book about our hard times as entertaining and as readable as Mary Badger Wilson's Yesterday's Promise (Penn Publishing) . The search will be long and probably unrewarded. Miss Wilson, New York B and District of Columbia A, has no axe to grind, no theories to expound and happily no "I told you so" attitudes. How-ever, the latest of her novels, while having the appearances of being written for mere enjoyment, has a basic theme of significance underlying its story structure. The book opens with four women gathered around the bridge table. Sue Page, the sweet type who detests women who lose their tempers even over bridge, has as her partner Leila Somers who has a "perfectly deadly knack of going soft and helpless the minute a man appears on her scene." There is Pauline Kinsey who supplies courage to a charming but spineless husband and Olivia Hirst who knows what it is to be engaged but not married. After the game, the four go their separate ways, little realizing that soon their separate ways were to be inextricably twisted together. That fateful after-noon in 1929 the four women read a headline: "Panic in Wall Street as Stocks Crash." That headline proves to be a yardstick by which the four bridge players are to measure their lives during the next three years. To trace the story farther would detract from the very real pleasure that will be the reader's. The author is exceptionally clever in writing witticisms. One always has theurge to write them down. Too, her method of introducing characters, her inimitable chapter headings and her ever youthful viewpoints contribute much to her books. Interesting indeed are Miss Wilson's comments upon women's fraternities. MARY BADGER WILSON To quote from Yesterday's Promise: "These organizations had ceased to be loosely-bound social clubs with a snobbish slant. Guided by their alumnae associations, women's fraternities have changed amazingly in the past two decades. They had become purposeful groups whose good times were balanced by some definite altruistic work. Their national conclaves set up high social and moral standards to which individual members must conform. In the college world which has naturally felt the post-war laziness of the greater world outside, women's fraternities had been an effective balance wheel." In conclusion, may we say, that </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



