<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr5640319_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name> Pace, Jeffries Green </name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>May 1940</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr5640319_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">May 1940</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name> Pace, Jeffries Green </name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 319-320</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">39</note>
                        <note type="Folder">8</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 56, Number 4 (May 1940), Pages 319-320.</note>
			<note type="document">arr5640319_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Christmas Celebration at Settlement School</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Tourism</item>
                                <item>Holidays</item>
                                <item>Southern Appalachian culture</item>
                                <item>Plays</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr5640319_0001" seq="01" n="318-319  "/>
       <p>OM PI PHI PENS Edited by MERCEDES BAKER JORGULESCO, Afassact5usetts A F lllll ..11.1.11111111116.1111.11t llllll Please note the request that appears in Editorial in this issue that review )s o all works of Pi Phi authors be sent to the editor of this section. No books were received for review in this issue. CAMPING DO (EDITOR'S NOTE: We are indebted to a certain Pi Beta Phi for the following excellent resume of Camping Down to Highgate by Hildreth Tyler Wriston, Vermont B. We regret that the writer of this article will not allow us to use her name, but may she herewith accept our thanks.) Hildreth Tyler Wriston's books grow with her own children. John and Cynthia were four years younger when Downstreet With Edith appeared. Now at fourteen and twelve respectively they have inspired Camping Down at Highgate and all the delightful children who play through it Theodore with the superiority that one additional year gives; baby Joan; exciting Harry whose father could own in 1905 an automobile and a motor launch; the cousins Mark and Arabella ; and finally Emily, brave, imaginative, responsible, a truly charming little girl. The plot is kept simple. A family goes with high heart to the scene of its annual vacation, a camp site in Highgate, Vermont. There they spend two weeks in midsummer, 1905. No villain mars the bliss unless it be the bull, but he for the most part con-fines his bellowings to the barnyard. The central figure Emily not overlooked is an Indian arrow head, the "tribe talisman" every child has to have. Taking into account her readers' interest-span, Mrs. Wriston does not postpone her highpoint to the book's end. Instead, each day brings its climax: a tent afire, a lake storm, the discovery of a cave and a river to explore. Highgate was the Tyler family's camping ground; hence the book has the authenticity of first-hand experience. It will delight children, but it will have a charm for grown-ups, too, especially for those who were young in 1905. They will feel nostalgic twinges as the sights and sounds they once N AT HIGHGATE .. knew are recreated: tasting the first roasted sweet-corn of the season, waiting for the train to flatten a nail laid on the rail, walking up and down a heavy wagon tongue a hundred others. Even oldtime tunes like Lair. Dooley are ready to do their conjuring tricks. And what a reminiscent smile greets Papa's Temperance Club with its torchlight parades and the pledge never to drink "any you-know-what-sort-of-thing." When the swift passing of the days has brought the last time the family would eat o supper looking out over the lake, the reader shares Emily's sorrow. "She looked as hard as she could, hoping to remember forever just how nice it was," And we close the book knowing that we shall long remember it, too. THE AUTHOR: Hildreth Tyler Wriston received her Ph.D. degree from the University of Vermont. Her first book Down,rtred 11"ith Edith. published in 1935, was a story of the everyday like of a little girl in a Vermont village in the early 1900's. Asked how she came to write her latest book, she said "Camping Down at Highgate is based on the things 1 did in my childhood while camping in Vermont. The two weeks which 1 spent at High-gate each summer, with my family, were the high spots of my life, and the amusing little incidents of camp life never failed to interest my own children, when recounted to them verbally. The natural result was to write them down, but the story did not become crystallized until my husband and 1, with my brother and his wife as partners, purchased most of the original Lakeshore farm traversed by Emily and Theodore in Camping Down to Highgate. Since then 1 have had the pleasure of seeing my own children, John, now fourteen, and Cynthia, twelve, enjoy Highgate as did." The Wristons are now making Highgate their year-round home. As she puts it, "just another Vermonter come home." WHAT THE REVIEWERS SAY: "Hildreth Wriston proved in Downstreet With Edith that she could capture a little girl's outlook on everyday experi (Continued on page 324) 318 NEWS F OM LITTLE PIGEON Edited by JEFFRIES GREEN PACE, Virginia A k.1111111IIIII1118811.111IIIISOI1.11.1,1111111IIIIIIIIIII 11111 aaaaaaaaa 11111.11.1 aaaaa lllll 11.1113tItIll.0.111 CHRISTMAS CELEBRATION AT SETTLEMENT SCHOOL Christmas at the Settlement School this time outdid any other during my time in this office. Our program for the entertainment was more simple than usual, but the shipment of Christmas boxes simply filled the office to the doors. Some boxes were huge and in some cases there were two boxes from the same club. Everything was beautifully wrapped up and on most gifts was written the name of the article and the age for which it was intended. Three boxes arrived after Christmas but it didn't matter. We used the things in the baskets for the hospital to give out to sick children during the year. Senders were: Cincinnati club, athletic goods for boys; Springfield, Missouri, club, big box of toys; Indiana A chapter, baby clothes. Every year this chapter sends baby clothes and we have come to depend on them. Harrisburg, Pennsylvania, club^, lovely big box of toys; Elizabeth Kates, Goochland, Virginia, packages of papers, quantities of pencils and note-books; Wichita club, large box of toys and canned fruits. The Wichita club never fails us. Mrs. Maud Stanton Western, Washington, D.C., large box of pictures, Christmas cards and ribbons for primary grades. Des Moines club, big box of toys; Bellevue, Pennsylvania, club, box of toys; St. Paul club, box of toys; Mothers club, St. Louis, check for $10, this they send every year. Santa Monica club, box of gifts and toys; St. Louis Alumnae Club, check for $5.80. Syracuse Junior Red Cross, box of gifts; Syracuse club, box of gifts; Sigma Phi Gamma Sorority, Muncie, Indiana, chapter, huge box of clothing. Chicago Business Women, two boxes of gifts; Chicago North club, two boxes of toys; Asheville club, box of toys ; Peoria club, box of toys; Wisconsin B chapter, box of unique toys; Du Page club, two boxes of gifts; Burlington, Iowa, club, used clothing; Kansas City, check for $3.65. You can see that the teachers had no trouble in selecting at least two nice gifts for each child. The boy who was to take the part of Santa in the play, got chicken-pox and didn't show up, but outside of that, everything went off beautifully. The Weavers' Guild Christmas dinner was quite elaborate. All were seated at a table that went around three sides of the room. A group of weavers, assisted by Lura, Bess, and Edna, and directed by Gene, prepared the dinner in the Home Ec Room and the Dorm kitchen. Some of the high school girls helped with the serving. There were presents for all under the Christmas tree. These were purchased as well as most of the food, with prize money from the Knoxville Fair. Lovely trimmings were donated by Mrs. Voorheis; and fancy candies by an interested Arrowcraft customer staying at the hotel, Mrs. Sandberg. Jerry McCutcheon showed colored movies of the mountains, Mrs. Voorheis' gardens, and Gene Redding's garden at Hebron. (Signed) EUNICE WEAVER Director of the School FIRST MOVE TO PRESENT MOUNTAIN LIFE TO VISITORS WEAVERS' PLAY TO RUN THROUGH SUMMER Sponsored by Miss Redding and directed by Mr. Palmer, the weavers are to put on their play this summer for the benefit of tourists. Great effort has been made to pre-serve the mountain atmosphere in staging and plot, which will give many outsiders their first glimpse of mountain life as it has been lived for generations. Those who at-tended the Convention two years ago in Asheville will not forget the colorful presentation of Settlement School day and it is hoped that many more may have the opportunity of viewing this summer's production. The play will be given once each week 319 </p>
      <pb ref="arr5640319_0002" seq="02" n="320-321  "/>
       <p>320 THE MAY ARRt'tv throughout the summer season. With the proper response, it may become an institution so that the old way of life may not be lost. The subject matter was compiled by and the cast made up from the list of those women weaving for the school and for that reason has accented interest for all Pi Phis. ATTENTION ALL SOCIALITES Before outfitting yourselves with new evening bags, see the lovely ones that Gene Redding has made up to make their debut at Convention. Handwoven of metal cloth and reasonably priced, they cannot fail to appeal. ELEMENTARY SCHOOL ASSUMES 100% SANITARY RATING Years of effort and money have been expended to bring our elementary school to a perfect rating and it is now the proud achievement of Mr. Price, the principal of the elementary school. He has worked continuously to that end for the three years since his arrival in Gatlinburg, but each year some unforeseen obstacle would prevent the goal being reached. This year he is proud to announce his success; the rating having risen from 71 to 100% during his incumbency. THE GIRL SCOUTS ANNUAL TEA The last week of February saw the annual celebration of the Girl Scouts their silver tea at the Teacher's Cottage. It is a very popular occasion and the attendance was t,00d. Each girl exerted herself to see that the guests were properly entertained and they are so well organized that when things seemed to stagnate somewhat, the word "shift" went around and each guest found himself with a new and eager entertainer. A large picture of George Washington hung in the hall and a big flag above the living room davenport. Coffee and little cakes with hatchets on top were served. RECENT ARRIVALS FOR LIBRARY USE Miriam Herron of Illinois Tr from Flint, Michigan, sent in a shipment of lovely books foi children. They had been samples for a library and so were quite new. looking. The teachers were delighted. Also a set of ency clopedias and a set of Shakespeare donated . by Miss Fleming, chaperon at Illinois Z chapter house, were placed on a shelf in the dining room where the dorm students study at night. All such thoughtful gifts are most acceptable and of great service to the proper conduct of the school. NEW ARROW CRAFT BUILDING GROWS APACE Although there has been a great deal of bitter weather with deep snows through the mountains, progress can be seen on the new Arrow Craft building, which now has its foundation in and has carpenters busy on the upper section. By the time the tourist season begins in earnest, we should be ready to serve with improved facility and renewed enthusiasm. Come to Gatlinburg and See the Changes the Years Have Wrought You Will Find It Worth Your While HAPPINESS Like a lone star at eventide It shone forth in adolescence, Then gradually in the twilight of middle age A few more stars appeared, The clouds drifted away, The sky was brilliant with stars. But soon these were overshadowed By the warmth of a glowing moon Of peace, quiet then happiness. ELLEN MORRISON, New York OVE THE WORLD Dr. Icie Macy, Virginia A and Colorado A, one time holder of the 11 B cl, Fellowship, whose distinction has many times been noted in the ARROW, was last year given the Norlin Achievement Medal, awarded each year by the alumnx of the University of Colorado. She received it in absentia, her place being taken that day by Ida Loyd Swayne, Colorado A, since on that day she was being married to Dr. B. Raymond Hoobler, of Detroit, Michigan. Mary Alice Jones, Tennessee A, was signally honored by Yale University when she was asked to become visiting professor on the Divinity Faculty for the last term of last year, the first woman ever to be so honored. Of her experience there, she writes, "I have never seen a grander group of persons together. I shall cherish the memory of it for-ever !" Honor Easton Webster, California B, and her husband, are doing unusual and interesting work in architecture and interior decorating. Mae Wynne McFarland (Mrs. I. B.), Texas A, of Houston, Texas, has been made chairman of a state-wide committee for high-way beautification in Texas. Her work has been influential in having passed the recent bill for the protection of wild flowers and plants along the highways of her state. Margaret Bancroft Griffin, charter member of New York Gamma, has the distinction of having three daughters who are members of B K--Margaret Griffin, also New York Gamma, and Dorothy and Louise Griffin, who are twins, and who were among only four who were given the distinction. Janet Marie Mason, Ohio B, is secretary to the merchandise staff of the R. H. White department store in Boston. Laura White Russell, Indiana A, is a landscape architect in Los Angeles. Minnie Freeman Penny, Nebraska A, (Mrs. Edgar B.) , was president of the Chicago Branch of the League of American Pen-women last year. Olga Ross Hannon, Montana A, head of the Fine Arts Department at Montana State at Bozeman, had a painting, "Nevadaville," selected for showing at the New York World's Fair. Neil Dyer Fitch, Oklahoma A, has a shop-ping service in New York City. Pauline Berg Graves, California r, is doing advertising work in the offices of Barker Brothers, in Los Angeles. Marie Grimes Knowles, Ohio B, has a unique hobby she collects minerals and fossils which has taken her recently to Central America, to visit the Mayan ruins at Uxmal and Chichen-Itza. Peggy Senneff Percival, Iowa Z, is on the air in the General Mills Program, over WHO, Des Moines. Mrs. Percival was last year's president of the Des Moines Alumna Club. Colonel John R. White, U.S.A., husband of Fay Kincaid White, Texas A, has recently been made chief of operations for all national parks, with headquarters in Washing-ton, D.C. Dean of Law A. J. Harno, of Washington University, St. Louis, father of Michie Harno, Illinois Z, is national president of Order of Coif, which honors high character and scholarship in students of the law. Joan Stealey, Missouri B, is assistant publicity director of Washington University in St. Louis. Dorothy McCleary, D.C. A, is represented by a short story in the Edward J.O'Brien collection for 1938. Louise Cuddy, Idaho A, is serving as State Chairman of Welfare for the state of Idaho. Dorothy Burg Cassut, Washington A, is Dean of Girls at the Chemawa, Ore., Indian School. Ida May Born, Louisiana A, is Director of Personnel Work at the Girl Scout Camp Edith Macey, Pleasantville, N.Y. Charlotte Cropley Brown, Vermont B, former member of the Settlement School Committee, is Assistant Dean of Women at Grove City College, Grove City, Pennsylvania. Arthur Bestor of New York City, whose wife is Jeanette Lemon Bestor, Indiana A, is president of National Chautauqua. Edna, Bassler Neely, Illinois E, gives a series of book reviews to both afternoon and evening audiences in Fresno, California. 321 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



