<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr5730285_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Scene on Little Pigeon River</title>

                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>March 1941</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr5730285_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">March 1941</date>, Scene on Little Pigeon River</title>

                        <extent>Page 284</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">39</note>
                        <note type="Folder">9</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 57, Number 3 (March 1941), Page 284.</note>
			<note type="document">arr5730285_0000</note>


	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Land</item>
                                <item>Rivers</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr5730285_0001" seq="01" n="284-285  "/>
       <p>inimu.181.11III.I.I.O.111.111alil...00.0010I 1511111.1111.11...S.M1111111.11111.1.01101011.1.1.1.11111.110.4010118III.B.11811^1110,1111011I.M 1110.11S.1glell0ae.e.e.60.11.1111000111.1111.1 MARCH, 1941 THE A ROW OF Volume 57 ETA PHI Number 3 s UM ..O .1111.1.111I. I I 1.01.1.11.11111810110111111111.1111.111.1.101.1.11101111.1111.11.111111. 1.111111.11.111.111s isgisolIeslils to 1$1118.. O^B.IIIIII 9 1 11.1 10 0.111.1101.1.1101111. EDIT IAL$ Apologies First THE PICTURE on the cover of the December ARRow is that of the remodeled house of Michigan B we regret that the name was omitted. In 'Ti Phi Personalities," Lynn Wainwright is mentioned as a member of Louisiana B we were wrong. Lynn was pledged by that chapter, but was initiated into Indiana B as the special initiate of the Delta Province Conference in 1939. OE Province Conferences As we go to press the list of provinces holding Spring conferences this year is not complete, and only Alpha West and Theta province have sent in notices of their coming meeting. We hear that Beta, Delta, Kappa, Lambda, are also planning their meetings, and there will doubtless be several more. Plan now to include your province conference in your spring travels, or to attend any one of them if you will be in its vicinity. You will find them second only in interest to the national conventions. You will meet charming Pi Phis, and make lasting friends ; you will take part in intelligent discussions ; you will improve your knowledge of fraternity affairs, and your appreciation of the work that is being done by active chapters and alumnae clubs. The conferences have, of course, no legislative power, yet they do furnish a cross-section view of fraternity opinion which is of great value. Here is a chance for informal meetings, for worthwhile exchange of ideas, for fair and unprejudiced discussion of fraternity affairs. Programs are carefully planned by the province officers and the local commit-tees, and much hard work goes into preparation for them. Their subjects for discussion must be thoughtfully chosen, their events well-planned, if they are to have significance. Your part is to attend one of them if possible, ready to contribute your ideas and thus aid in the planning of fraternity progress. Go once and we promise you that you will want to go again! Holt House Progress Elsewhere in this issue we devote some space to the Holt House in Monmouth, founding . place of Pi Beta Phi. The committee authorized by the last Convention has spent a busy fall and winter of planning and supervision. The restoration of the house is practically complete, as you will see in the exterior view taken in January, and lacking only window shutters and the planting of shrubbery to show the finished appearance of the house. The successful placing of the house in as nearly as possible its original condition, is proof that its apparent ruin was an external matter only, that the. builders of that early day really built for many generations, and also that a splendid piece of work has been done by the committee, the architect, and the builders. The structural rebirth of the house is complete: there remains the task of replacing the furnishings of the house as nearly as possible as they were in the sixties, and the responsibility of insuring that the house will be so maintained that it will be a lasting source of pride 285 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



