<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr5240217_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Holton, Lillian Beck</name></author>
                        <author><name>Ogle, Van</name></author>
                        <author><name>Beck, Martha M.</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>May 1936</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr5240217_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">May 1936</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Holton, Lillian Beck</name></author>
                        <author><name>Ogle, Van</name></author>
                        <author><name>Beck, Martha M.</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 217-220</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">38</note>
                        <note type="Folder">16</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 52, Number 4 (May 1936), Pages 217-220.</note>
			<note type="document">arr5240217_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Our New Nurse; Aunt Sophie Passes Away; A Log Cabin; An Easter Tour; We Go South for the Summer; President Emeritus Visits Gatlinburg; Our School; An Appreciation</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Nurses</item>
                                <item>Teachers</item>
                                <item>Southern Appalachian culture</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr5240217_0001" seq="01" n="216-217  "/>
       <p>Yaniz 9 tions Sirn.il r to Mortar oard 10' .LSIP Eta HELEN RUTH CHODAT Illinois Eta MARY FRANCES WOOD Illinois Eta DOROTHY JEAN ARMOR Colorado Beta BAKER Beta HELEN MULLENDORE Oklahoma Beta ELIZABETH DEAN California Gamma EVELYN SEMENZA Nevada Alpha Girls whose pictures are also among those of dele gates: DOROTHY MANWARING, Florida Gamma, delegate Zeta Province, MARIAN CARLISLE, Virginia Alpha, delegate Gamma Province, ADRIAN JOHN-SON, California Alpha, delegate Mu Province. WALSH A.1pha BARBARA STEINBECK California Alpha RUTH GOODAN California Alpha NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEO Edited by LILLIAN BECK HOLTON OUR NEW NURSE Mrs. Marjorie Chalmers, Galesburg, Illinois, our new public health nurse, came to us December 1. She received her training at Eitel Hospital, Minneapolis, Minnesota, MARJORIE CHALMERS, Nurse and later was medical and surgical nurse there. She was floor supervisor at Cottage Hospital, Galesburg, and has had experience in family relief, child welfare, and rehabilitation for the American Legion Auxiliary. She also has had teacher and kindergarten training. The community is pleased with her work and the household has found her a con-genial member. Virginia Moore, who for the past four years has been our public health nurse, will take up county public health work in Tennessee, when she has recovered from an illness of nearly two months. AUNT SOPHIE PASSES AWAY From Mrs. Weaver's letter "Sunday morning we heard that Uncle Tom Campbell and Aunt Sophie were very ill. Aunt Sophie is the old lady who made clay pipes in her home on the mountain. As soon as they could find high boots warm clothing, Mrs. Chalmers, Mrs. S and Mary Durkee made the trip throug snow up the mountain to see if there anything we could do for them. They f members of the family there doing all could be done. "Aunt Sophie died Sunday night and cle Tom requested that our nurse `lay out.' Mrs. Chalmers with Bess and Ka helpers gladly complied with this rec They left the little string of red beads ar her neck that Mrs. McDonald gave her ago. I never can describe to you the 1 chill of the scene as coming out of the cl we waited until the nails were driven int lid of the home-made casket then it carried on to the cemetery on the hill. I the coldest day we have had." A LOG CABIN By VAN OGLE, Sixth Grade Upon a hill where the trees are ver) stands a little log cabin. The trees silo from the sun, and the moon shines bri on the trees at night. At the left side c house is a small rock chimney. It and the are covered with green moss where build their nests. On the porch are flow, boxes and cans. Next to the door lies a hound dog with her puppies playing her. In the doorway sits an old woman ing her cob pipe. AN EASTER TOUR A southern Easter tour conducted by Mabel Kirk, 4301 Atlantic Avenue, At City, New Jersey, left New York, Apr After a weekend in Asheville and stc Chattanooga, Knoxville, and Bryson Cit party arrived at Gatlinburg. According itinerary, "The afternoon is left open visit to the Pi Beta Phi School and nun quaint shops and museums at Gatlir Luncheon, dinner and over-night acco dations at the Mountain View Hotel.' </p>
      <pb ref="arr5240217_0002" seq="02" n="218-219  "/>
       <p>THE MAY ARROW 70 SOUTH FOR THE SUMMER )n of an article by Martha M. Beck, tourist who visited Gatlinburg last swnmer re here in the little mountain town the bend of the Little Pigeon river, .art of the beautiful green mountains overed by a purplish haze which are kies. This is almost the center of the the "Mountain Whites" who for ndred years have preserved their pure 'Dlood, the purest strain in America. mountain homes they have lived and lost untouched by the outside world. ms almost unbelievably primitive still :heir homes. They eke out what seems xistence on their hillside farms. s to such a community that the Pi Fraternity brought their Settlement bout twenty years ago. In the years e passed since then it is impossible ate the influence that has been ex-L the lives of the boys and girls of ement. From a small beginning the s grown to a considerable size. They re than a hundred acres of land which d for the benefit of the school. A fine Jersey cows is housed in a modern, barn. Chickens are equally fortunate quarters. High school and grade uildings, teachers' cottage, boys' and ,rmitories, a small but well equipped and a shop for selling the products krrow Craft industry, have all been through the efforts of the college o wear the arrow of Pi Beta Phi. The :hool is now run with the aid and ion of the local school district. The finances the two-year high school. s are taught agriculture and the girls :onomics. An auditorium is provided for school activities, but for the :ture show and for other community ;. weaving is the major industry of nen here. Nearly every mountain has her own hand loom and the art tiful weaving has been taught by to daughters for generations. So the has made this art the major activity, it in the school and through its chapughout the country provides a market finished product. At least seventy-five n women bring their work to the :o be sent to the market provided a, adding materially to their meagerincomes. The object of the school is to make the pupils dissatisfied only with conditions which can be bettered. In elevating their traditional occupation to an art they have in-creased their self respect and helped them to appreciate their heritage from the past, which is perhaps even more important than the learning they acquire from books. A full time nurse is provided by the sorority and the good that has been accomplished is inestimable. No night is too dark or stormy for her to respond to a call for help. Health instruction is given. Mothers are taught to care for their babies and to brinc, b them to the nurse to be weighed and examined and inoculated. In one day since we have been here she gave SO typhoid inoculations to children and adults at two remote school houses. If she can, she drives the school car. If the car can't make it, she goes horseback. Where the horse can't climb she walks. She always gets there, and she is doing a great deal toward eliminating the diseases which sap the lives of the mountain people. PRESIDENT EMERITUS VISITS GATLINBURG It was a delightful experience to return to the Settlement School after a number of years and really see for oneself the great changes that have taken place both in the people themselves and in the actual material equipment of the school. We arrived late one evening, a party of three Pi Phis and ` a friend, after having driven for hours over those marvelous new mountain roads. Mr. Huff received us at his hotel, and, when we had retired to our rooms, the finding of private baths attached to each room was almost too much, especially for the one who on an earlier visit had laboriously drawn up a quart can of water from the well and carried it to her room to wash. Everywhere it was the same, the new building with its large auditorium and weaving room; the Arrow Craft Shop from which we could hardly tear ourselves away; and the new barn with the well-caredfor stock was all a matter of surprise and pleasure. Mrs. Weaver graciously showed us over the whole establishment, and although the heavens opened and the rain descended for the entire period of our visit, it did not pre-vent the inspection of all the main points of interest. We were greatly amused over the THE MAY ARROW friendly rivalry between the Arrow Craft Shop proper and the auxiliary one in the hotel. In the evening we spent most of our time in the hotel shop, which is just a corner partitioned off from the main lobby of the hotel, and felt very proud when the other guests admired the furniture, shawls, quilts, etc., all done by our people. The next day in the rain we set out to see some of the home weaving, especially the rainbow shawls. We missed some familiar faces, but after climbing to Aunt Lizzie's cabin and visiting with her awhile, the government road was forgotten as were the new houses and other improvements, and in spirit we were once more back in the teachers' cottage in the days when Aunt Lizzie kept house and Miss Evelyn ran the school. Mr. Huff has very sensibly kept the surroundings of the hotel rustic, and it was delightful to see the bank by the hotel covered with ferns and tiny plants from the woods. Gatlinburg has become known through the opening of that region as a National Park, but that does not mean that the school is not needed. It is a splendid and vital center for that entire section of the country. A third year has been added to the high school, and eventually a fourth will follow. A Parent Teachers' Association has already been formed and is bringing to many of the mothers a real interest in the progress of their children in the school. It is still the community center and more and more the fraternity will have to enlarge the boarding department in order to accommodate the boys and girls from the isolated districts, who are longing for a share in the good things the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School has to offer our mountain friends." MAY L. KELLER MESSAGES FROM TWO TEACHERS The school is most fortunate this year in having two of our graduates back as teachers. After completing their college courses elsewhere Stella Huff and Ben Fleming are both teaching in our high school. Their knowledge of conditions in our mountain community and their sympathy with the people are a great help to them in their work. The following articles by Stella and Ben show their appreciation of what the school has done for them and their desire to give to the school and community their best work. OUR SCHOOL By BEN FLEMING It was more than eight years a first became acquainted with Pi through the extension work in 1 munities. These community org were gathering and developing th BEN FLEMING terests and abilities of a large n school children, as well as adults. In the fall of '27 I entered Pi School. Those two years of stud spent here are memorable ones tt atmosphere of the entire school be that of an ideal home just one The instructors showed a warm an interest in each student, and th challenged us to be bigger and fine girls. This new experience gav( broader, a brighter, and a sound on life. I wish you people out t: just know what this institution to me and to numerous fellow stue The spring of '29 found a clan boys and girls reluctant to depart school they liked so well. They re could never find another Pi Beta the road of education. Thoreau once said, "Arnbiti plans, determination carries them leaving Pi Beta Phi, I asked a ques I come back some day?" It is a great and long anticipat( to be back here today as an instruc I shall be able to help these boy as some instructors have helped r </p>
      <pb ref="arr5240217_0003" seq="03" n="220-221  "/>
       <p>THE MAY ARROW is who are reaching out and knowledge, and who are willing commendable efforts is one of oys of a teacher's life. Ind girls of our mountains still Phi a happy, convenient and de-in which to carry on their eduyear brings an increased en roll more conscious than ever be-7alue of this pioneer school of behalf of our local people, take ity to express my deepest grad-)ne who has helped to make our ty and a success? \T APPRECIATION ' STELLA SUE HUFF ended Pi Beta Phi School the of my school life and inciden STELLA HUFF ten years in the history of the ,eing now in the midst of my fourth year of teaching here, makes me feel as "Aunt Lizzie Reagan" would say, "might nigh like being one of them Pi Phis." I shall never forget the first time I heard the mention of the name Pi Phi. My father was talking and laughing with my mother one night about a misunderstanding that had taken place between two of the pioneer Pi Phi teachers concerning their pets, a cat and a dog. I believe I was about four years of age at the time, and every day since that time Pi Phi has meant more and more to me. I have and always will have an indescribable feeling of appreciation and admiration toward the many Pi Phis I have known. When I am reminiscent of the past four years of my teaching, the first morning I at-tended chapel is my most outstanding memory. Miss Evelyn Bishop asked me to direct the children while we sang "We're Loyal to You, Pi Phi Dear." I did as Miss Evelyn asked, but I fear that I sang very little be-cause of the huge lump in my throat. It sounds very sentimental, but I tell you this, dear Pi Phis, to illustrate not only my feelings toward our school and Pi Beta Phi, but the feelings of every boy and girl who has gone to the school. My work this year, which brings me into contact with high school pupils, has made me realize more than ever before the need of more of the good influence that our Pi Phis have radiated throughout these years. Our boys and girls are truly fine, and they are eater to learn. When we know that the training they receive while under our care completes their school training in most cases, we know that our task is an important one, and one that requires the best of everything that we can give as teachers. My wish is that every Pi Phi will some-time be able to visit in Gatlinburg and see that we are working with you to make the Pi Beta Phi School worthy of the name that it bears. Attu l.1111111.1.1.1,111.11I.I.I.I I..I.11111111.11.11111.111.111110,1AIIN11.11.111.11111111.111.111.111IIIIIIIIIIIIII.I.111111.11111.11111111111111.1111111.111M.11.11.3. IN MEMO \ 1AM THE editor announces a new policy for this department. Hereafter, only brief notices, ing chapter, date of initiation, date and place of birth and death, and offices held i; national organization, will be used. Exceptions to this rule will be made only in the ca active officers of the fraternity, former Grand officers, and members of I.C. Deaths of erally known members of the families of Pi Beta Phis, will appear in the personal sectit the chapter concerned. MARY ANN BROOK PEARCE (Mrs. George T.) , I.C., Illinois A, died in Davis County, Iowa, December 3, 1935. She was initiated into Alpha chapter at Monmouth College the year after it was founded, and later organized the chapter at Lombard College. She was graduated from Monmouth in 1872 with a B.S. degree. Mrs. Pearce was a sister of Libbie Brook Gaddis, Founder. JENNIE GRUBB FOWLER (Mrs. Frank Hamilton) , Illinois B, died in Tucson, Arizona, January, 1936. An ever active and de-voted member, she served on the advisory board of her own chapter while she lived in Galesburg; after her family moved to Salt Lake City she worked with the petitioning group there in their early days, and during her residence in Tucson she had been active in the alumnae club and in close touch with Arizona A chapter. The fiftieth anniversary of her membership in Pi Beta Phi was celebrated by the Tucson Alumnae Club last October, and her friendship and fine Pi Phi spirit will be greatly missed. She had many Pi Phi relatives her sister, Mrs. E. M. Han-son, Illinois B; two daughters, Mrs. D. W. Albert and Mrs. J. A. Magee, both Arizona A ; four cousins, Mrs. Ella G. Simmons, Mrs. Charles L. Miller, Mrs. Percy Hale, and Mrs. B. E. Gilmore, all of Illinois B a niece, Mrs. J. R. Thorpe, Illinois B ; and a grand niece, Ellen Thorpe, was pledged to Illinois A this year. ELLA AMELIA PENN, Iowa A, I.C., died at Tucson, Arizona, December, 1935. She was a sister of Lulu Penn Ingersoll, also of Iowa A. MAY COPELAND REYNOLDS DRYBREAD (Mrs. Charles Harvey), I.C. Michigan A; charter member, died in the summer of 1935. A former Grand Vice-president of Pi Beta Phi, Mrs. Drybread had served the fraternity in many prominent positions. She was instrumental in obtaining a chapter hous, her own chapter, and helped to install IV gan B. She was the mother of Marthena bread, Indiana B. ELLA MAY MARTIN WHITAKER Charles H.) , I.C., Illinois A, charter met died at Clinton, Missouri, Septembet 1934. LOUISE CARITHERS MORRISON (Mrs. H.) , I.C., A, initiated 1868, first recorde itiate into Monmouth chapter, died D ber 9, 1935, at Las Cruces, New M( where she made her home with her son I W. Morrison, Grand Trustee of Sigma An account of Mrs. Morrison's connc with the fraternity appeared in the H number of the ARROW, in connection the Convention of 1872, Greencastle, ana, where she presided. ELVA PLANK, I.C., Iowa E, charter . ber, of Kansas City, died November 1935. A devoted Pi Psi, she had serve fraternity in many ways, and was v known. She was Grand Secretary in I.C. and was presiding officer of the Law: Kansas, Convention, in 1885. For two she taught at the Settlement School. REBECCA HEFTY CHAPSKY (Mrs. Ma I.C., initiated into the Chicago chapter vember 1881, died April 15, 1931. LIZZIE FISHER ROBINSON (wife of E J. W. Robinson), I.C., Iowa ,B, ini 1887, died at Delhi, India, June 17, 1S MARY MEGRUE VAN KEUREN Henry S.), I.C., Colorado B, initiated died July 11, 1935. ALICE JOHNSON STEELE (Mrs. S H.), I.C., Iowa A, Iowa E, initiated died in September 1934. BLANCHE SMITH VREELAND (Mrs. J.), I.C., Illinois A, initiated 1880, die 22, 1935. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



