<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr5920179_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Sale, Mildred Odell</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>December 1942</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr5920179_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">December 1942</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Sale, Mildred Odell</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 178-183</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">39</note>
                        <note type="Folder">11</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 59, Number 2 (December 1942), Pages 178-183.</note>
			<note type="document">arr5920179_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">A Study In Contrasts; The Boston Handicraft Show</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Handicraft</item>
                                <item>Tourism</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr5920179_0001" seq="01" n="178-179  "/>
       <p>NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON Edited by MILDRED ODELL SALE, North Dakota A Spring in the Great Smokes A Study in Contrasts In February, 1912, Miss Martha Hill of Nashville, Tenn., was at Sevierville. It was two-thirty in the afternoon, on a snowstormy day when, "The `rig' came no-top buggy, wraps, mule, boy, snowstorm. The journey of fifteen miles (to Gatlinburg) was very enjoyable, the scenery grand, and the boy bright and entertaining. The air was delightful, the mule a fine traveler, and the novel trip was over in four hours and I was sitting by a great wood fire with savory odors coming from the kitchen." Here Miss Hill found that Gatlinburg, in the center of "wildly beautiful country" was "not a town but a community (some seven houses) along the big road, served by rural mail carriers; has a public school house that has not been re-roofed in 30 years; school furniture home made and 20 years old. About 200 children are within school influence of this point and many needy outlying coves are accessible from it. The public school term usually begins in August and closes at Christmas, teacher's salary, $30.00.." She rented living accommodations a three-room house made of rough, overlap-ping boards, with porches front and back, outbuildings, and well. "Inside the walls, ceiling and floor are of native woods with no paint and no varnish. The only treatment it has had was a generous drenching and scrubbing with a strong solution of lye and hot 178 THE DECEMBER ARROW 179 water when Miss Hill took possession." With the aid of a nurse from Madison, Tenn., Miss Hill opened school in an abandoned Methodist church, enrolling fourteen pupils. Five months later when it closed on June 29, thirty-three pupils presented closing day exercises, with demonstrations of actual class methods and equipment, exhibits of sewing done, and most enthusiastically received of all, music from the prized portable reed organ, donated by the Washington and Baltimore Pi Beta Phis, who denied them-selves a banquet on Founders' Day order to help start the musical education of the Gatlinburg children. 1912 "CLoSES" The following fall Miss Hill and the first Pi Beta Phi ever to teach at the School, Della W. Gillette, Illinois Zeta, taught along with the county teacher for the regular four months of public school, until on November 30, when "closes" were attended by parents who came afoot over "devious mountain trails and rocky, muddy mountain roads of so modest a nature that they were often difficult to find." "The closes" themselves stand out in the memory of at least one of the visitors (Kate B. Miller, Iowa B) as unique. The large room, sided with boards, was dimly lighted with the lamps and lanterns which the audience had brought. A small wood stove and its stovepipe burned red in the center of the room. A profusion of holly branches heavily laden with red berries decorated the windows and the low platform stretching across the front of the room. Just off the platform, at the left, stood a small reed organ. The desks were of all ages, from new ones just placed to old, scarred ones showing intimate relations with the jack knives of boyish occupants. "The audience itself baffles satisfying description. . . Unlike the thousands of illiterate foreign men and women in our cities, these mountain men and women of purest English ancestry, deprived of educational opportunities, do not wear their hearts upon their sleeves or show their thoughts in their faces for the casual observer to read." The program itself consisted primarily of speeches by visiting guests, and drills and music by the students. "Forty-five boys and girls from seven to twenty years of age marched proudly to the platform as Miss Hill played. At least they thought that they were marching, but unison of step was too new, and too difficult for them to learn in their short training. Undisturbed by their mistakes,. however, they stood swayingly happy in their places, the big ones ranged against the wall, and the littler ones ranged in steps down to the front row. Arid how they sana! Loudly and mechanically and in Mildred Odell Sale, North Dakota A, new editor of News /thin Little Pigeon. dependently, each one sang as seemed to him best." "CLosEs" 1942 Years of toil and devotion have passed since then untiring enthusiasm and love for the mountain people on the part of those who taught there, and years of hard-earned contributions from Pi Phis all over the country. Truly an age of progress has intervened between those first public appearances of the sad-faced children, and the day late last spring when the Settlement School Commit-tee adjourned its business session to interview the poised, self-reliant boys of our Pi Beta Phi Senior High School class, who presented us with an opportunity to advertise in the program of their Senior play. And it was a Senior play well worthy of any average American community. There was no lack of unison of step, either, when the twenty-five graduates of 1942, in cap and gown, marched down the aisle of the Baptist church for Baccalaureate, </p>
      <pb ref="arr5920179_0002" seq="02" n="180-181  "/>
       <p>180 THE DECEMBER ARROW the white-robed girl? Chorus already on the stage with the Director and the High School faculty. Nor was there any lack of assurance at Class Day exercises, with the seniors in complete charge. The girls in dainty pastel evening dresses and the boys in dark coats and light trousers singing "Speed Thee My Arrow" were shining examples of how far the Arrow has sped these mountain children Georgia Marrs Barber, Colorado B, Denver Club Magazine Chairman (her work was mentioned in the September ARROW). along the path of progress, education and character-development. And Wiley Ward, Jr., valedictorian, and Dot Fox, salutatorian (one of our dormitory boys) presented ad-dresses of real merit proof that they had used their native intelligence to acquire a splendid educational background for future life. Tuesday of that week was the Junior-Senior banquet at the Mountain View Hotel, with mimeographed programs whose paper lace covers held tiny clusters of pink laurel, and with Dr. Ruth Stevens, faculty member from the University of Tennessee, speaking on "This War of Today." Friday came the grand finale Commencement itself, with Dean Thackston of the University of Tennessee delivering the ova tion twenty-five more "dividends" from our Pi Beta Phi dollars ready to meet the challenge of the rapidly changing scene around them. THEN AND NOW-MATERIALLY Yet the boys and girls are not the only changes to be seen. Gatlinburg has grown from its seven houses to a community, running now along a beautiful paved highway, its electric and neon signs calling upon the tourist to tarry, and to buy. Result of a newly developed national park in the Smokies, Gatlinburg has blossomed; yet the amazing fact is not that it did blossom, but that, because Pi Beta Phi had prepared the citizens by giving them education and developing their latent abilities, these citizens were able to meet the demands of increasing tourist trade and became, themselves, the proprietors of the new business establishments. Had Pi Beta Phi not stayed in Gatlin-burg, "furriness" would have come in to establish hotels and souvenir shops, and the deserving natives, unable to cope with their progressive ideas, would have retreated farther into those Smoky Mountain depths where time seems not to move. DIVIDENDS OF BRICK AND STONE And the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School has it remained as pictured in 1914 by Miss Pollard, head-resident ? "Imagine twelve wriggling boys and girls, from eight to twelve years old, all sitting at one small table about the size of an ordinary kitchen table. There is not a table that has less than eight at it, and if there were a chair for me to sit on, there is no place to put it. Miss Stock at her end of the room sits on the organ stool, and during the one period of the day when I can sit down, I use the edge of the platform or the back of a bench. I happen to teach the arithmetic classes, and so I occupy the front of the room where the blackboard is. We have about thirty feet of blackboard space, and with thirty in one class, it is some-times rather crowded. But the children do not mind it, and so far as I can see, are learning their multiplication tables almost as rapidly as though they had all the room in the world to scribble on. . . Miss Wilson has the small children through the second grade in the old store building, which Mr. Ogle vacated the first of December. During the Christmas holidays the old school house was thoroughly repaired and made tight and THE DECEMBER ARROW 181 warm, and the old store was thoroughly cleaned and windows put in. In that building we have an enrollment of about thirty, making a total enrollment of one hundred." No, indeed. Now the buildings stretch from the Health Center, near the tulip tree, up the side of the hill to where, nestled together, stand Teachers' Cottage and the Stuart and Pollard dormitories; on back to the barns in the "back lot" ; then sweeping on to the right again at the level of Teachers' Cottage to the grade school building (that joy and pride of the 1914-15 faculty) , the high school building and back down the hill to the road again, past the Arts and Crafts Building, where metal wear and pottery are being designed and made, to the new Arrow-craft Shop, with its inviting show-windows and its busy weavers. Yes, there are material dividends to show, also! A CENTER OF COMMUNITY LIFE Pi Beta Phi has, through all the years and in all its plans, kept to its original decision to make the Settlement School a community, cooperative venture. From the days when Mrs. Helmick informed the leading citizens of Gatlinburg that if Pi Phi's school stayed there, they would have to donate more than half toward a site for it, the community has felt its obligations and assisted to the utmost of its ability. From its original $1,200 gift toward the site (Pi Phi at that time gave only $600) the community has assumed more and more financial responsibility, Pi Beta Phi retaining always the supervision and direction. The community respects and reveres Pi Beta Phi, but it also accepts us and our School as a fostering mother or helpful big sister. The mountain weavers still prefer to meet under our friendly roof than at any other public place in the community. To make its surgical dressing classes successful, the Red Cross requested the use of the "old loom room" at the School, and a group of women work there each day. The Scrap Metal Drive used part of the school ground as a collection point; a "Country Social" for the benefit of the Gatlinburg Library included booths, hot dogs, games and prizes, and a square dance; and once again our Gene Redding presented the weavers in their original play "Store Britches" each week. This summer the Chamber of Commerce promoted a series of weekly Community Sings, held on the school playground. With roaring bonfires built and supervised by forest rangers, with the smoke wafting up-wards among the pines on the side of "Pi Phi Hill," with the quaint strains of the old mountain songs drifting towards you small wonder that the tourist passing by joined the group and learned of Pi Beta Phi's helping hand extended only enough to guide, direct and encourage, bringing out the talents that would remain hidden beneath a "bushel" of ignorance and poverty were it not for their generosity. Many tourists have expressed their congratulations and appreciation of what the Settlement School has done to our director and staff, but Marjorie Avery told the readers of the Detroit Free Press about it in her column, "Detroit Dairy": PI BETA PHI SCHOOL COMES UP TO EXPECTATIONS By MARJORIE AVERY The bus stopped and the bus driver said . ... "There's the hotel you want and there's the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School.. . ." "Pi Phi Settlement School," I said to myself as the years rolled back to college days . . "then I'm really in Gatlin-burg. . . ." In Ann Arbor the mountains seemed so far away... . All my life I've had to hear of Pi Phi's mountain. school. . . . You can't be around a Pi Phi for five minutes without hearing about it. . . We used to listen with a jealous resentment when they talked the way you do when some other group than your own tells about its good works. . . . But we all pitched in to help raise the money and we all had a healthy respect for what the sorority was doing. . . . And here I was suddenly dumped down in front of the real thing.. Eighty-four and Still Weaves Mrs. Elizabeth Peck, director, took me through the school the next morning, a morning of burning sunshine, deep shadows and haze hanging on the mountain tops. . . So that's why they're called "the Smokies." She told me about Aunt Lizzie Reagan, 84, who still weaves for the school a certain striped pattern called after her "the Aunt Lizzie." She told about the weavers who had their pictures taken for House and Garden last spring and how unimpressed they were when the magazine was passed around. . . One man said when shown a gorgeous picture of his wife winding warp, an old quilt forming a back-ground, "She do look old, don't she?" The out-side world means so little to them and when I think of the mountains .. . . well, who knows? Maybe they're right. Came Back to Teach Ben Fleming is principal. . . . A few yeafs ago he was a student. From Pi Phi School he </p>
      <pb ref="arr5920179_0003" seq="03" n="182-183  "/>
       <p>182 THE DECEMBER ARROW went to college and then back again to teach. . . . A man from the village came home while I was there. He'd been in a nearby city making big money in , a factory. He was asked why he gave up such a good job. "Ah just think ah'd rather live here," he said. Pi Beta Phi started the Gatlinburg School in 1912, the only school in the neighborhood to bring education to the isolated, mountain people. . The effect has been almost revolutionary. . . Now there are 415 pupils every year . . . 25 in June's graduating class of which 12 are going to college . . an excellent record. The shop connected with the school employs 130 people, makes it possible for women in the mountain districts to be self-supporting. Mrs. Ethel Snow is direCtor of the shop, Miss Gene Redding is weaving supervisor. "We aren't trying to change the mountain people," Mrs. Peck said, "you can't do that whether you want to or not. . . . And they're a self-respecting, fine type of people. But we know they can't remain isolated much longer and our education has helped to soften the blow of sudden exposure to the world. We're making it possible for them to meet changing conditions without getting the worst of the deal." No "Furriners" W'anter. . She cited Gatlinburg as an example. . . It was a tiny village when Pi Phi came there.. . . Now it's a thriving tourist town, the gateway to the Smokies. All the hotels, the stores, the tourist attractions are owned and run by the mountain people. If there must be a hotel, a local man will run it. They don't welcome "furriners" in those parts. But the interesting thing is that, the school had to revive weaving ... taught the mountain women fine craftsmanship, supervised patterns, made weaving into an industry and art from which it had fallen. There were tomatoes ripening in the sun. . . "It was hard to get them to accept new vegetables," Mrs. Peck said, "but they're coming around to it gradually. .. . And so the last of the great Individualists are being modernized. Pi Beta Phi's task is not yet complete. Should we forget this Memorial to our Founders in the stress of our busy wartime lives, the fog which Mrs. Andy Huff, in 1914, dreamt was rolling down the mountains to envelop her children and those of her neighbors, would again roll out from the mountain fastness where it has been pushed back by the searching light of the Settlement School influence, overpowering those community leaders who would wish to keep ignorance within bounds but are handicapped by lack of funds. Gatlinburg is a thriving tourist community when you drive through it on your vacation (and will be if gasoline rationing and the war do not prevent) but the children from "main street" are only a small share of the 434 now enrolled. Many come from primitive homes on rocky mountain farms where Pi Phi's Arrowcraft continues to be the main source of income. We must continue to invest if we wish to continue to receive dividends strong, well-educated graduates, and grateful thanks from the best exponents of our American Southern Highlands crafts. "From these homes in the Smokies, with a heritage of pioneer 'Grandmothers and Grandfathers, have come these children, This boy, this girl to be educated by Pi Beta Phi In old skills, in the three R's, in ways of health, and in ways of beauty, That they may make their contribution to a growing, changing community life." The Boston Handicraft Show It was early Monday morning, October 5, and Ethel Snow, Director of Arrowcraft, Edna McCarter and Mary L. Ownby, all from Gatlinburg, with Beth LeRoy, Boston member of the Settlement School Committee, arrived at the Boston Garden, to arrange the Pi Beta Phi Arrowcraft Booth at the first Handicraft Show to be held there. But circus animals, including lions and elephants, still called the Garden "home," since freight cars to take them elsewhere had been commandeered by the Army for other purposes. Rushing back at intervals all day to see the progress being made in clearing and cleaning, the Tennessee visitors managed to see some of the historical scenes of Boston. And well it was they were able to sightsee that day, for from Tuesday morning until the following Saturday evening (or Sunday morning, to be exact) all hands were busy: Mary L. and Edna entertaining visitors by making baskets and weaving ; Ethel Adams, Mildred Wildes and Emily McWade of the Boston Alumnae Club working with Ethel Snow to interest and sell all who came by; and Beth LeRoy speaking over radio stations WMEX and WEEI and exhibiting the new Settlement School film two or three times daily in conjunction with a film made by Allen Eaton showing the government's work with handicraft in the Southern Highlands. This was a splendid opportunity to display Arrowcraft beside handicraft from all over the Americas, before the foremost handicraft authorities and buyers of the United THE DECEMBER ARROW 183 At the Garden Show: Mary Owenby and Edna McCarter. Mrs. Snow in the background. States. And once again Gatlinburg and Pi Beta Phi won at Boston, not only financially, but also artistically, since one noted handi craft authority expressed his opinion that our Arrowcraft weaving was the finest in the entire Craft Show! Institute of World Affairs From June 27 to August 1, thirty students representing fifteen nations met at Hillcrest School, near Salisbury, Connecticut, under the auspices of the Institute of World Affairs. The University of Manitoba sent as its delegate Helen Aikenhead, active Manitoba A, and an economics major. The purpose of the conference was to discuss current world problems and to deter-mine how the students, as citizens, could play a useful part in the functioning of their respective democracies. Representatives came not only from Canada and the United States, but also from such widely scattered nations as Belgium, Brazil, Switzerland, Argentina, Great Britain, Bulgaria, Spain, and Greece. Representatives of France, China, and Holland, were weekend guests, and gave short talks about their countries. Seminars were held on alternate mornings, when Sir Norman Angell, noted economist and writer, led the discussion of various topics of current interest. The problems dwelt on were: causes of the war ; post-war reconstruction; Anglo-American relations; problems of imperialism; and public education. The last topic was one of which Sir Norman dwelt at great length. He stressed the absolute necessity of a new system of education in which the public would be </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



