<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr5210031_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Settlement School Reports </title>
                        <author><name>Hill, Frankie C. </name></author>
                        <author><name>McCleverty, Josephine</name></author>
                        <author><name>Weaver, Eunice</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>September 1935</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr5210031_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">September 1935</date>, Settlement School Reports </title>
                        <author><name>Hill, Frankie C. </name></author>
                        <author><name>McCleverty, Josephine</name></author>
                        <author><name>Weaver, Eunice</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 30-38</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">38</note>
                        <note type="Folder">15</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 52, Number 1 (September 1935), Pages 30-38.</note>
			<note type="document">arr5210031_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Settlement School Committee; Pi Beta Phi Settlement School Report on Audit Treasurer's Accounts Year Ended June 30, 1935; Director of the Settlement School</note>
                        <note type="Additional Information"> Page 39-40 of this volume is missing. </note>
	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Curriculum</item>
                                <item>Funding</item>
                                <item>Budget</item>
                                <item>Staff</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr5210031_0001" seq="01" n="30-31  "/>
       <p>THE SEPTEMBER ARROW PAID PAID 5.00 Glendale Alumni Club 25.00 50.00 San Diego Alumna Club 10.00 43.35 Albuquerque Alumnae Club 5.00 5.00 Salt Lake City Alumnae Club 12.50 5.00 California 25.00 5.00 Mrs. Warren T. Smith 5.00 10.00 Mrs. W. H. Montague 10.00 10.00 Long Beach Alumni Club 10.00 50.00 Santa Barbara Alumnae Club 5.00 5.00 Tucson Alumna: Club 7.50 1.50 San Francisco Alum= Club 5.00 10.00 5.00 $252.00 "hat" Collection in at convention $ 46.36 $254.35 Club of convention 40 $ 46.76 $ 50.00 Total $3,747.81. 17.00 50.00 5.00 MARY CAMPBELL GREGORY 10.00 Treasurer SETTLEMENT .SCHOOL COMMITTEE ............................. .......... . .... . ......... . . . . ............................. ......................... oule (Convention) [ace Club (Salem, Oregon) ............ . ............... Club Club ............... . ............. e Club ub b nx Club nover ........................... ub .. . mn~e Club "-SECOND year in the life of the ,chool has closed, and in some re-a an outstanding year. Nothing has but there has been continued progng our School with those of like Committee thinks the Fraternity to have been able to maintain ion with very little retrenchment. iormitories were opened, and about l girls took advantage of the optter schooling. The enrollment in he largest in its history. ig returned to be Principal of the 1. an able .corps of teachers had a year. Mr. King and Jean Handley :hool teachers of the regular sub-Smith taught agriculture and Miss Spencer had charge of home ecoiith has been a member of our mber of years and we regret his :h becomes effective July 1. Mr. to assume management of his LI classes for the seventh through were held in the high school rammar school was over-crowded least one grade will have to be mother building. The grammar ght by Eleanor Brabson, Miriam uff Lawson, Dorothy Douthat, and of these teachers were most con-s work in the schoolroom as well .pity. We are losing Mattie Huff, othy Douthat, Missouri r, as they ung men in Government service. les are living in attractive cottages Gatlinburg. Weaver, Illinois Z, has been the the . year, and she has endeared immunity and the staff. Virginia e, has continued her constructive r a radius of ten miles, and the ve been conducted throughout the gives full details of her effort living conditions. She has been the boxes which have been sent th needed supplies, such as band-. Lucy Field, Texas A, has com pleted her second year as bookkeeper and her work has been very efficiently executed. Mrs. Mc-Donald, housemother for the dormitories, has been most faithful, and her supervision of the house-keeping department reached the usual high mark of past years. The entire Staff has served the School in a very capable manner, and to them the Committee extends its sincerest words of praise and gratitude. Arrow Craft has shown a splendid year of progress. Its managers have been Mrs. Emma Pattengill and Mrs. Ethel Snow, both of Iowa T. Due to their fine efforts the Shop has closed its busiest year. During the fall the peak of shipping was reached; the months of November and December equalled the total of previous years up to '33. Mrs. Mitchell was Weaving Supervisor; the Shop assist-ant was our faithful Veatress Parton; and Lura Ownby has assisted in the Weaving Room. We have added Mrs. Duffield to our Staff, continuing her duties as manager of the Shop in the Mountain View Hotel. She weaves the handsome afghans which are popular sellers in many clubs. Her articles in the ARROW are very interesting, as she recounts the many important visitors whose names are in her Scrapbook. Community activities are continuing under school guidance. Mr. King has had a splendid basketball team which brought visitors for the games. The P.T.A. and Weavers' Guild are thriving and both groups have had many interesting meetings. The Staff assisted in community gatherings, in the Church and its activities, the Old Timers' Day, and in every way possible has tried to promote a community spirit and civic responsibility. We are hoping in the coming year to provide a recreational Director, as such a worker is greatly needed. The Committee is delighted that the clubs and chapters have been enthusiastic in their support of the school. We have outlined no brilliant plans for the future, but we are happy in that the school has not lost step in its forward progress. With an indebtedness still upon us, we deemed it best to reduce it as quickly as possible. Should the state of Tennessee pass impending educational legislation regarding the two year high school, some important changes may be forced upon us. THE SEPTEMBER ARROW This has been a year for many visitors to the school. The Great Smokies are attracting many tourists, and we are delighted that so many avail them-selves of the opportunity to see our plant. There is a real need for a guide, but the members of the Staff add this task of guidance to their already full day's work. The Chairman cannot close this report without expressing her deepest appreciation to Grand Coun-cil in particular for their sympathetic guidan, constant interest in the work. To the meml the Committee she extends her appreciation cooperation given during the year. To the St: acknowledges with pride their efforts and i in their work. With heartfelt gratitude she the fraternity one and all for the untiring loyalty, and financial support given to SCHOOL. FRANKIE C. I PI ETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL EPO T REASU T ON AUDIT ER'S ACCOUNTS YEA ENDED JUNE 30, 1935 1 \ August 21, 1935 Miss Josephine McCleverty, Treasurer Pi Beta Phi Settlement School Seattle, Washington Dear Miss McCleverty: At your request we have made an audit of your accounting records as Treasurer of the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School for the year ended June 30, 1935. We have received a copy of the audit report of Messrs. Homer K. Tones and Co., Certified Public Accountants of Knoxville, Tennessee, covering the Settlement School books and Arrow Craft Shop books that are kept in Gatlinburg, for the fiscal year; also a report from the Magazine Agency at Wichita, Kansas, for the period beginning September 25, 1934, and ending May 21, 1935. We present herewith the Financial Statements prepared from your books after giving effect to the figures contained in these reports, showing the results of your operations for the year. BALANCE SHEET-EXHIBIT 1 Cash on deposit at the Metropolitan Branch, First National Bank of Seattle, $6,615.65, was verified by checking in detail and reconciling with the bank's statements. For confirmation of the remaining current assets you are referred to the report of Homer K. Jones and Co. The amount due the School Endowment Fund is shown separately on the Balance Sheet. This represents cash paid into the Endowment Fund which was expended for school purposes prior to June, 1929. It has been reduced from $16,573.41 to $12,842.45 contributions of $200.00 having been applied against this account during the current year. Fixed Assets are shown in detail in Exhibit 6, showing the reserve for depreciation deducted. Live Stock is stated at inventory value as reported from Gatlinburg. The Mortgage has been reduced from $3,900.00 at June 30, 1934, to a balance of $1,825.00. Interest was paid in full to June 30, 1935. NET WORTH The General Surplus has been chargeC the loss of the Settlement School and credite the net income of the Arrow Craft Shop. which the amount of $1,306.40 has been all ated for the School Endowment Fund, lea' balance of $82,963.83 at June 30, 1935. Net Worth, including the General Surpi $126,199.85. Contributions received durir year for the Endowment Fund totaled $2 These amounts together with the above app Lion of $1,306.40 were forwarded in cash ti National Treasurer for investment. SETTLEMENT SCHOOL INCOME AND ExP: The expenses of the Settlement School ex the income by the amount of $1,457.78, as by Exhibit 2, which combines the figures by your books with those taken from your burg accounts by Homer K. Jones and Co. ARROW CRAFT SHOP INCOME AND EXPE: Exhibit 3 is a condensed statement of the , and expenses of the Arrow Craft Shop, are presented in greater detail in the re; Homer K. Jones and Co. MAGAZINE AGENCY EARNINGS Exhibit 4 is taken from the report sul by the Magazine Agency for the period Sep 25, 1934, to May 21, 1935. As no report ceived covering the periods from June 30 1 tember 25, 1934, and from May 21 to Ju 1935, we have incorporated the figures as sh this report in closing the books for the fist; All necessary adjusting and closing entrio been made on your books to bring them intc ment with this report and to close the be of June 30, 1935. Respectfully submitted, R. C. MOUNSEY Certified Public Accou </p>
      <pb ref="arr5210031_0002" seq="02" n="32-33  "/>
       <p>THE SEPTEMBER ARROW PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL BALANCE SHEET June 30, 1935 ASSETS It Assets: h on Hand and at Banks $ 8,696.90 ounts Receivable Arrow Craft Shop 5,314.36 ount Receivable Cash Advance 25.00 ntories: ate! Shop $ 597.07 rrow Craft Shop 6,874.06 leaving Supplies 2,928.53 10,399.66 AL CURRENT ASSETS $ 24,435.92 ments: ?ol Endowment Fund Exhibit 5 $ 21,552.50 ificates of Deposit 1,181.82 ,osits in Closed Bank 1,570.77 AL INVESTMENTS 24,305.09 Assets Land, Buildings, Equipment and Live Stock Exhibit 6 78,127.30 eel Charges Unexpired Insurance 1,597.85 nt Due School Endowment Fund 12,842.45 TOTAL ASSETS $141,308.61 LIABILITIES AND NET WORTH it Liabilities: ounts Payable Arrow Craft Shop $ 44131 Liabilities: .tgage Payable $ 1,825.00 School Endowment Fund 12,842.45 'AL FIXED LIABILITIES 14,667.45 7orth: :rve for School Endowment Fund $ 34,350.15 Voorhees Donation Woodcraft Shop 8,885.87 Feral Surplus June 30, 1934 $ 82,735.97 ins: Loss, School Operations Exhibit 2 1,457.78 $ 81,278.19 dd: Profit, Arrow Craft Shop Exhibit 3 2,992.04 d Surplus June 30, 1935 $ 84,270.23 educt: Three-fourths Active Chapter Contributions, to Endowment Fund 1,306.40 nce General Surplus 82,963.83 AL NET WORTH 126,199.85 TOTAL LIABILITIES AND NET WORTH $141,308.61 PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL INCOME AND EXPENSE STATEMENT Year Ended June 30, 1935 School Books ributions Active Chapter ributions Alumnm Clubs ributions Individuals ributions Endowment azine Agency, Net Exhibit 4 est Earned h-Hughes Agriculture $ 3.50 h-Hughes Home Economics 56.19 ^ital 148.38 1 (includes products for living $1,400.81) 1,660.45 g 2,865.01 ol 89.45 ellaneous 469.43 i.L INCOME $ 5,292.41, Treasurer's Total Books $ 1,824.86 $ 1,824.86 11,335.01 11,335.01 331.00 331.00 200.00 200.00 1,940.49 1,940.49 813.21 813.21 3.50 56.19 148.38 1,660.45 2,865.01 89.45 575.00 1,044.43 $17,019.57 $22,311.98 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW Expenses: Administration ' ' ' ' ' " . ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " . ' ' " w 60.18 $ Auto Expense 130.18 Community Service 31.78 Convention Expense 16u7 Depreciation 2 Exchange Farm 1,522.77 Fuel Furnishings ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 4922.60 04.90 Health Unit 17.16 z Insurance Interest Laundry '''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''' 22Lights 4.15 551.04 Living 4,655.81 Miscellaneous 25.61 Office Publicity ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 6.562 Repairs and Upkeep ' ' .' ' " . ' ' " . ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " . " ." .' ' ' ' ' " . " . 741/35 Salaries '''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''' ~ School Expense .. : Smith-Hughes Agriculture ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 551.67 56.90 ' Smith-Huighes Home Economics Tax on Checks 26I Telephone and Telegraph 119.02 TOTAL EXPENSE $10,664 .03, $13 Balance Being Net Income, to Exhibit 1 ".'.".".".'..".". $ 5,371.62 $ 3 PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL ARROW CRAFT SHOP INCOME AND EXPENSE STATEMENT Year Ended June 30, 1935 Sales Goo Finished Furniture 32.02 Chairs, Stools, etc. Hooked and Tufted ~~~~'~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ ~~~j Mountain View Hotel Shop '."."....'.".".".".'. 4,313.79 Expenses: Commissions Mt. View Hotel Sales Rent Mt. View Hotel Shop Transportation Costs Industrial Expense Industrial Salaries Industrial Publicity Industrial Miscellaneous Lights Fuel Office Expense Telephone and Telegraph Repairs and Upkeep Ta~. on Checks Expense Car Expense TOTAL EXPENSES Other Income: Bad Accounts Recovered State of Tennessee Weaving Net Income, to Exhibit 1 '.."."." ." .' ' ' " . ' N. B. The above figures are taken from the report of Homer K. Jones and Co. Please see further details. _ </p>
      <pb ref="arr5210031_0003" seq="03" n="34-35  "/>
       <p>THE SEPTEMBER ARROW PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL MAGAZINE AGENCY OPERATIONS September 21, 1934, to May 21, 1935 September z5.zp4 $ 75.15 ".".^"."." u 1.872.20 " '' ' ' ' ''' ' ''' ' ' ' ' ''' ' '' '' ' ' ''' ' ' ' ' '' ' ' '' '' ' '' '' ' 88.25 19.70 lblishers ~ . ~ ~ ~ . ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~.~ ~ ~ ~ ~~ ~ ~~~ ~~ ~~~ ~ ~ ~ ~ 15.20 ~ "."."."."` ". " .' ".' "."." . ' $ 2o72.13 ' . . ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' 'w 38.00 33.05 ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ''' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' '' ' ' ' ' '' '' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' '' ' ' ' ' 16.95 SC ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " . ' ' ' ' ' " . " . " . ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' 1434.00 !rises ' ' ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~ ~~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~ ~' ~ ' ~~ ' ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ 90.00 iptions SEMENTS ' "." .' ' " ." .' ' " . " . ' ' " . ' ' " . " . ' 352.25 $ 2,019.88 School Treasurer $ 2,000.00 on Hand 19.88 $ 2,019.88 hool Treasurer ' ' . ' . ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' . ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " . Stationery $ 13.10 et-dement School '. " .' 37.84 :ash Balance e.57 59.51 above figures are taken from the report of the Magazine Agency for the peri.od September 25, vlay 21, 1935, without audit or verification on our part. No report was had ot the periods July r 25, 1934, or May 22-June 30, 1935. PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL FIXED ASSETS Pine 30, 1935 ' .. ' . ' . .' ' " $ 7,900.00 ~~~' $ 1,028.34 ~.~~~~~~~.~~~~~~~....~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 633.07 734.59 3,384.49 2,000.00 hop 2,400.00 2ottage J~~~.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 4,437.73 _ 25,006.57 . . .. ... . . . . . . . . . . . . ... . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Plant '' ' ' ' ' '' ' ' ' ''' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' 114.91 6,743.85 2,011.02 vge 6,727.71 ;p.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ '~~~3 = ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " . ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' . . $ 1,003.00 ling ' " . ' ' ' " .' ' " .' " .' ". ". ' ' ' ' '.~'~ ~' ' ' ' ~ ~' ~~ ~ . ~ ~ ~~~ 3,405.03 2,500.00 ~e 2,083.03 otta= 1,655.00 ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 500.00 500.00 1,300.00 .~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 650.00 ~ 1,485.10 _ "u Equipment . . . . . Reserve ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' $ 2,000.00 15,331.16 $80,014.31 o.0m/u 68,982.30 ` tor' `mz to Exhibit ' o76ya/m 1,245.00 $78,127.30 THE SEPTEMBE.R. ARROW PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL CHAPTER CONTRIBUTIONS AND MAGAZINE EARNINGS Year Ended June 30, 1935 ACTIVE CHAPTERS Magazine Earnings Contributions CLUBS Contributions Alpha $ 753.13 Beta 1,993.40 Gamma 402.70 Delta 739.78 Epsilon 1,407.92 Zeta 145.00 Eta 1,694.00 Theta 633.82 Iota 834.92 Kappa 820.39 Lambda 480.50 Mu 1,429.45 $ 177.95 Alpha $ 138.85 Beta 89.85 Gamma 240.70 Delta 309.80 Epsilon 27.55 Zeta 219.20 Eta 71.15 Theta 316.35 Iota 103.25 Kappa 59.35 Lambda 118.20 Mu 120.00 178.86 155.00 215.00 75.00 64.00 235.00 130.00 270.00 193.75 95.75 92.50 TOTAL $11,335.01 $1,872.20 TOTAL $ 1,824.86 Alpha Contributions Albany, N.Y $ Boston, Mass 60.00 Buffalo, N.Y 50.00 Burlington, Vt Hartford, Conn 115.00 New Haven, Conn 30.00 New York, N.Y 249.70 Rochester, N.Y 75.00 Toronto, N.Y 100.00 oronto, Ont 31.03 Westchester, N.Y 42.40 Magazine Earnings $ 3.00 26.00 3.85 15.15 43.75 59.05 8.05 11.25 1.65 6.20 Alpha Contributions Ontario A $ 25.00 Maine A Vermont A 35.00 Vermont B 20.00 Massachusetts A 5.00 New York A New York F 10.00 New York A 25.00 120.00 $ 753.13 $ 177.95 Beta Contributions Akron, Ohio $ 100.00 Athens, Ohio Central Pennsylvania 8.00 Cincinnati, Ohio 100.00 Cleveland, Ohio 700.00 Columbus, Ohio 64.36 Da3ton, Ohio 35.00 Delaware, Ohio 5.00 Harrisburg-Lancaster 125.00 Mahoning Va4ey, Ohio 30.84 Morgantown, W.Va 25.00 Northern New jersey 162.50 Ohio Valley 15.00 Philadelphia 375.00 Pittsburgh 60.00 Southern New jersey 77.70 South Hills, Pa 10.00 Toledo, Ohio 100.00Magazine Earnings $ 2.00 5.50 16.05 24.15 3.00 2.75 .85 4.50 1.25 12.30 7.85 27.80 3.15 23.75 .25 3.70 Beta Contributions Pennsylvania A $ Pennsylvania B 35.00 Pennsylvania P 20.00 Ohio A 25.00 Ohio B 70.00 Ohio A 20.00 West Virginia A 5.00 Ontario B 3.86 178.86 $ 1,993.40 $ 138.85 Magazine Earnings Gamma Contributions $ 19.50 Maryland A $ 25.00 3.25 Dist. of Columbia A 25.00 Virginia A 15.00 Virginia F 10.00 3.95 North Carolina A 50.00 63.15 North Carolina B 25.00 South Carolina A 5.00 402.70 $ 89.85 155.00 Gamma Contributions Baltimore, Md $ 82.70 Chapel Hill, N. C 10.00 Columbia, S.C 5.00 North Carolina Richmond, Va 40.00 Washington, D.C 265.00 Delta Contributions Ann Arbor, Mich $ 112.00 Birmingham, Mich Bloomfield Hills, Mich 49.06 Bloomington, Ind 40.00 Calumet City Club 3.00 Detroit, Mich 150.00 Evansville, Ind Flint, Mich 1.00 Fort Wayne, Ind 20.00 Franklin, Ind 50.00 Grand Rapids, Mich 6.00Magazine Earnings Delta Contributions Michigan A $ 6.00 Michigan B 126.00 Indiana A 10.00 1.90 Indiana B 30.00 Indiana 25.00 145.50 Indiana A 18.00 4.35 9.50 5.75 7.80 $ 13.40 8.70 215.00 </p>
      <pb ref="arr5210031_0004" seq="04" n="36-37  "/>
       <p>THE SEPTEMBER ARROW ALUMN/E CLUBS ich 5.00 Ind 225.67 50.00 Indiana 26.05 Ida 2.00 ACTIVE CHAPTERS 1.45 31.35 8.65 2.35 ............. .............. .............. .............. ............ Ll $ 739.78 $ 240.70 Magazine Earnings Epsilon Contributions Earnings $ 11.55 Missouri A $ 10.00 $ 21.90 Missouri B 15.00 96.90 Missouri 15.00 .60 9.85 Kentucky A 35.00 5.40 Tennessee A 85 2.15 155.45 75.00 1.45 6.60 $ 1,407.92 $ 309.80 Magazine Magazine Earnings Zeta Contributions Earnings $ 13.55 Alabama A $ 15.00 1.25 Florida A 5.85 Florida B 25.00 Florida P 24.00 1.20 64.00 3.55 2.15 27.55 Magazine Magazine Earnings Eta Contributions Earnings Wisconsin A $ 50.00 $ 1.05 Wisconsin B 10.00 .85 Illinois A 10.00 10.75 Illinois B-A 35.00 24.85 Illinois E 10.00 2.75 Illinois Z 100.00 4.85 Illinois U 20.00 8.30 16.95 87.75 3.85 6.85 7.15 14.10 7.70 21.40 1.00 1.25 3.60 2.50 $ 1,694.00 $ 219.20 Contributions Tenn $ 22.00 D 69.61 Mo 500.00 7 50.00 no 25.00 !an 5.00 lo 10.00 ) 673.81 io 52.50 Magazine Contributions ' $ 50.00 Ala L 35.00 Fla 5.00 5.00 .............. 50.00 $ 145.00 Contributions $ 10.00 12.00 9.00 :bang, 120.00 h 280.00 200.00 aess Women 150.00 Suburban 101.00 5.00 8.30 235.00 ............. L 25.00 Ill s 50.00 iVis 205.00 Ll 25.00 Ill 400.00 er Forest 15.00 33.00 25.00 29.00 Magazine Earnings Contributions $ 125.00 Dwa 8.00 , Iowa 50.00 Iowa 105.00 1 20.00 N.D 5.00 wa 20.00 )wa 49.57 Minn 103.75 Iowa 50.00 gin 50.00 owa 30.00 anitoba 17.50 633.82 Contributions ) $ 50.00 40.00 ryo 25.00 Maazine Theta Contributions Eagrnings $ 2.25 Manitoba A $ 15.00 $ North Dakota A Minnesota A 25.00 1.85 Iowa A 10.00 5.50 Iowa B 10.00 Iowa P 20.00 .50 Iowa Z 50.00 1.40 1.10 13.85 15.00 1.65 71.15 Magazine Magazine Earnings Iota Contributions Earnings $ South Dakota A $ 5.00 $ 2.85 34.95 Nebraska B 15.00 12.40 Kansas A 30.00 23.10 2.50 .60 6.70 4.40 9.25 130.00 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW ALUMNA CLUBS Colorado Springs 5.50 Denver, Colo 350.00 Eldorado, Kan Laramie, Wyo 30.00 Lawrence, Kan 44.36 Lincoln, Neb 25.00 Manhattan, Kan 100.00 Omaha-Council Bluffs 100.00 Poudre Valley, Colo 5.00 Pueblo, Colo 25.00 Topeka, Kan 35.06 Wichita, Kan 834.92 Kappa Contributions Ardmore, Okla $ Austin, Tex 105.00 Beaumont, Tex Bryant, Tex Corpus Christi, Tex 15.23 Dallas, Tex 209.33 Fayetteville, Ark 10.00 Fort Smith, Ark 25.00 Forth Worth, Tex 50.80 Gainesville Tex Houston, Tex Little Rock, Ark 15.00 Muskogee, Okla 15.00 New Orleans, La 25.00 Norman, Okla 10.34 Oklahoma City, Okla 50.00 Okmulgee, Okla 25.00 Sabine District 93.79 San Antonio, Tex Shreveport, La 50.00 Stillwater, Okla 10.00 Tulsa, Okla 50.00 Tyler, Tex 35.90 Waco, Tex 25.00 820.39 $ 103.25 ACTIVE CHAPTERS 1.85 Kansas B 50.00 65.60 Colorado A 100.00 1.00 Colorado B 50.00 4.85 Wyoming A 20.00 6.60 34.25 18.60 10.75 2.65 270.00 6.05 116.80 $ 316.35 Magazine Earnings Kappa Contributions $ .60 Oklahoma A $ 25.00 Oklahoma B 25.00 25.15 Arkansas A 13.75 3.35 Texas A 50.00 Texas B 25.00 7.85 Louisiana A 55.00 5.75 193.75 .65 4.00 1.40 5.75 1.75 4.50 .15 14.65 1.25 26.45 $ Magazine Earnings $ 7.15 12.20 3.65 3.6) 10.80 Lambda Contributions Boise, Idaho $ 50.00 Calgary; Alberta 3.00 Corvallis, Ore 2.00 Edmonton, Alberta 10.00 Eugene, Ore, 25.00 Portland, Ore 90.00 Pullman, Wash Salem, Ore 5.00 Seattle, Wash 170.50 paokane, Wash 60.00 coma, Wash 50.00 Wenatchee, Wash 5.00 Yakima, Wash 10.00 $ 480.50 Mu Contributions Albuquerque, N.M $ Berkeley, Calif 200.00 El Paso, Tex Fresno, Calif 10.00 Glendale, Calif 75.00 Hawaii, T.H 50.00 Long Beach, Calif 50.00 Los Angeles, Calif 675.00 Palo Alto, Calif 25.00 Pasadena, Calif 65.00 Phoenix, Ariz 38.00 Riverside, Calif Salt Lake City, Utah 50.00 San Diego, Calif 75.00 San Francisco, Calif 41.45 San Jose, Calif 25.00 Santa Monica, Calif 30.00 Tucson, Ariz 20.00 Unidentified $ 1,429.45Lambda Contributions Alberta A $ 5.00 Montana A 5.00 Idaho A 5.00 Washington A 50.00 Washington B 5.00 2,25 Oregon A 5.00 4.40 Oregon B 20.75 10.25 2.30 2.70 59.35 Magazine Earnings Mu $ .40 California A $ 10.00 20.20 California B 5.75 California 75.00 .75 California Li .65 Nevada A 2.50 Arizona A 5.00 10.50 Utah A 19.05 4.25 7.60 2.25 1.40 23.00 5.05 $ 118.20 Due to original check having been lost in contribution of $85.00 from California A was after closing of books for fiscal year. TREASURER. $ 95.75 Contributions $ 92.50 II $ $ .90 .50 15.95 5.75 </p>
      <pb ref="arr5210031_0005" seq="05" n="38-39  "/>
       <p>THE SEPTEMBER ARROW DI I)A ECTO OF THE SETTLEMENT SCHOOL School On August 13, the school opened with 282 pupils present. This number grew rapidly in the next two months, and we had difficulty in finding desks for the pupils. In some of the rooms, the rows of seats extended almost to the teacher's table. Everett Trentham brought two bus loads of children every morning, one from Cherokee at seven o'clock and one from Forks of the River at seven thirty; then took them back in the afternoon. This was paid for by the County with the exception of the ninth month, as were the grade teachers' salaries. All were glad to have Mr. King back not only for his work as principal and teacher, but because of the interest in athletics which we knew would be forthcoming. Vivian Blair Reagan, a former teacher living near the school, offered her services as a substitute in teaching and other things during the year, and was a great help. There were a number of very popular and beneficial extra-curricular activities during the school year. An operetta, Paints and Patches, under the direction of Miss Handley and Miss Douthat, was presented in October. The basketball season, while not successful in the number of games won, was excellent from the standpoint of community support and the high type of sportsmanship exhibited by both players and spectators. The Christmas program was presented by the first six grades on December 20 and 21. This program attracts probably the largest crowds of the year. The seniors, under the direction of Miss Handley, presented a play, Hobgoblin House, on March 18th and gave a fine performance. The moving picture shows were discontinued for a few weeks during the basketball season, but there have been two shows a week since April 1st. In addition to the school basketball team, we had a very successful community team. This type of activity in the community seems distinctly worthwhile. The games and other community activities were so well attended, that it was necessary to erect two rows of temporary bleachers in the gym ; and to place guard posts along the edge of the driveway in order to keep the increasing number of cars from injuring the grass in front of the high school building. The dilapidated toilets for the grammar school building were removed and replaced by new and sanitary ones constructed by T.E.R.A. labor under the supervision of the County Health Department. The Parent Teacher's Association worked hard to keep their basement lunch room going, furnishing a hot drink or dish for the noon lunch, and deserve much credit. They held three rummage sales and one benefit bridge party, raising over $210.00. A stage setting was furnished the auditorium through advertising on a drop curtain by merchants in the vicinity. School closed with the Commencement program May 2nd. The graduating address was delivered by Dr. Ralph Waldo Lloyd, President of 1aryville College. Seven eighth grade and eleven tenth grade pupils received diplomas. HE YEAR 1934-35 at the Settlement School does not show any great changes except that the )llment of the school was increased, being 342, largest we ever had, the dormitories were re-led, and a larger business was done by Arrow 't. le staff for this year has been: . Eunice Weaver, Illinois Z, director. Liam King, principal, mathematics and history. t Handley, Missouri F, English and geography. ). Smith, agriculture. y Elizabeth Spencer, home economics. la Huff, 5th and 6th grades. tie Huff Lawson, Iowa r, 4th grade. othy Douthat Manley, Missouri r, 2nd and 3rd grades. [am Swann, 1st and 2nd grades. nor Brabson, primer. . Irene Mitchell, weaving. . Ethel Snow, Iowa F, Arrow Craft manager. . Georgie Duffield, Mt. View Hotel Shop. 7 E. Field, Texas A, bookkeeper. inia. Moore, nurse. . Mary Ella McDonald, dormitory and house manager. e McCarter and Lura Ownby, weaving assist-ants. :ress Parton, Arrow Craft assistant. )ers Ogle, farm. ! Watson, farm. McCarter, cook. le Ownby, cook. Community ;-atlinburg is now the largest town in Sevier ray, population fifteen hundred. With an in-3e in the number of tourists and visitors, quite t of friendly rivalry is being started between inburg and Sevierville, the County seat. A help le community is the construction, by the Gov-lent, of the road in the Smoky Mountain Park irds Newfound Gap, employing local labor. other construction in the Park development ed on by the Bureau of Public Roads, the Nail Park Service, and the C.C.C. camps is a 621 help to the people in this section. ,s one of the T.E.R.A. measures, an adult class !ading was conducted by Mrs. Sharp in one of school rooms in the evenings. This was a derful opportunity for those middle-aged ntaineers who had never learned to read. ie Oakley, "The Roaming Man of the Moun was a most enthusiastic pupil, and later .ed his home for the class. ,t the little post office almost at our front gate, the first-day sale on October 10th, of the new ky Mountain National Park stamp. This ght. a big crowd and over sixty thousand ps were sold. he usual County Fair was not held this year, after inquiring among the neighbors and our committee, it was thought that not enough ey could be raised to finance it properly. Old !l.'s Day was celebrated June 22. he movies have been held in the school all and have provided well conducted entertain-. THE SEPTEMBER ARROW Annual of Com itte S S P0 I'.'`IlITTEE ON EXTENSION C OUR COMMITTEE on Extension seems to have followed the principle of laissez-faire this year since we have no specific recommendations to make to the fraternity. We have continued the contact with Gamma Sigma at Connecticut State College. To date the college has not received the educational recognition required by Pi Beta Phi, however both Gamma Sigma and the college offer possibilities and are deserving of our attention. The alumnae club in Shreveport has continued its interest in Louisiana State University located at Baton Rouge. A group, Pi Beta, has made official inquiry of Pi Beta Phi. The Grand Secretary, who has made an unofficial visit to this campus, feels that the university and Pi Beta present unusual possibilities for strengthening our position. The Atlanta, Georgia, alumnae have been interested in the University of Georgia at Athens, having approached this committee last year. Early in 1934-35 Alpha Theta sent an inquiry to Pi Beta Phi. Although the University of Georgia offers us a field for increasing our strength in that section of the country, the committee awaits the report COMMITTEE ON SCHOLARS IP THE PRINCIPAL problem facing the scholarship committee during the last year was its own reorganization in order to make it more sensitive to the needs of and fluctuations of scholarship in the chapters. Scholarship Blanks Nos. 1 and 2 were revised to obtain more information. Scholarship Form A was formulated to assist individual girls encountering difficulties in scholarship. A pamphlet, "Study Aids," was compiled to assist individual students in their methods of study. The committee manual was rewritten, requiring a monthly series of reports and answering suggestions between the chapter scholarship chairmen and the province scholarship supervisor, the supervisors and the national chairman, and the national chairman and the Grand Secretary. It is designed to keep the committee in close touch with the problems of the chapters and to enable an exchange of suggestions that all chapters may benefit by the experiences of each. Included in the manual are complete calendars for each member of the committee to insure prompt reports. A new method of grading the chapters in scholarship for the Standardization and Survey re-port was adopted by Grand Council as was ex from Miss Onken, who has mad, visit to Alpha Theta recently. We have continued our corres Sigma Delta Theta at the Univei located at Akron, Ohio. Alumnae their interest in McGill at Mor Other members of Pi Beta Phi haN possibility of establishing a chapte tlement School, suggesting Vander at Nashville, Tennessee. In addition to the above the had inquiries from Our Lady of tF at San Antonio, Texas ; Beta Chi University in Salem, Oregon; Ga Washington College in Chesterto Psi Chi at the University of Tol Ohio. After thoughtful consideration to the inquiries and proposals ma mittee, we will have some definii tions to make for strengthening a our position as the outstanding it ternity for women. MILDRED Tm plained in the last issue of the ARI Grand Council has made the of ring, heretofore used for varyi awards, a special award. It may awarded only to the girl attaini scholarship in her chapter for the Despite the lack of organization, proceeded upon their own initia formulated and passed on many \ tions, accomplished fine pieces of chapters. With but few exceptior cooperated wholeheartedly. Those low scholarship have, with but shown definite improvement. The committee's effort for 1935 toward raising chapters in the love respective campuses to the middle that the fraternity shall have no com chapters. The committee welcomes and tions for the improvement of sch confident that the girls will make standing year in scholarships. MARGARET </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



