<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr6240393_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Smith, Eugenia Brooks</name></author>
                        <author><name>Chalmers, R.N., Marjorie</name></author>
                        <author><name>Donohoe, Mrs. J.B.</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>May 1946</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr6240393_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">May 1946</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Smith, Eugenia Brooks</name></author>
                        <author><name>Chalmers, R.N., Marjorie</name></author>
                        <author><name>Donohoe, Mrs. J.B.</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 393-400</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">39</note>
                        <note type="Folder">14</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 62, Number 4 (May 1946), Pages 393-400.</note>
			<note type="document">arr6240393_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">The Settlement School Health Center; Marjorie Chalmers, R.N.; The Health Center Serves; The P.T.A. President; A Settlement School Graduate; A Gatlinburg Pi Phi; The Last of the Granny Women</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Changing Mission of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity for Women in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1944-1964</item>
                                <item>Health care</item>
                                <item>Well-Baby</item>
                                <item>Nurses</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr6240393_0001" seq="01" n="392-393  "/>
       <p>,,,,,, NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON Edited by EUGENIA BROOKS SMITH, Indiana *11, IseummulasteogIssomosl uslo.a.1 The Settlement School Health Center By MARJORIE CHALMERS, R.N. It is a wild night. The mountain wind is raging down the valley, twisting the trees and flinging branches ahead of its fury. The tin roof dances a noisy fandango, and I wonder, a bit apprehensively, if this time, it really will go sailing of across the pasture. Last wind storm, most of the boards at the west end of the porch were torn loose. I pause in my mop-ping to look, but we are still holding together. The rain lashes the windows, and water pours in around the ill-fitting casings. The bathroom window jars loose from its lock, and has to be secured with a nail for the emergency. Great flakes of soot drift over the furniture through big cracks in the siding, as the little cottage trembles with each furious blast. I move my work into the bedroom, and set the logs in the fireplace ablaze. The steam heat makes little headway against the drafts. Yes, we do need-a new building. The termites and rot have weakened the floor dangerously though it has been braced and repaired. Water stands in the basement much of the time, and the almost new furnace is badly rusted. Equipment, instruments, books, and clothing must be guarded carefully from rust and mold. It is a discouraging task trying to keep things clean and attractive. The Health Center was started after the first World War, and was converted from a dwelling house. It has served us well for almost thirty years though it was none too convenient in the beginning. Now it is pathetically outmoded and inadequate. Needs of the community have changed with the changing years. No longer is it necessary to provide hospital facilities for patients. Now there are small hospitals in the country, and if a patient can be moved at all, another fifteen minutes will get him to a regular hospital. Two beds in the class room will provide for emergency. The class room in the old building is much too small for lectures and demonstrations. Cup-boards and storages are woefully inadequate. It will not be necessary to increase much the sizeof the building, but the space could be used to better advantage. We are making good use of the services of available physicians. But there is much that doctors cannot do. Baths and bedside nursing, instruction and supervision of home care, lie in the province of the nurse. Classes for school children and adults so important in community health, lie in her realm, also. Compare, if you will, the health service offered here, with that of your own community. You have, in all probability, a unit of the U.S. Department of Health. Be it a city or a county unit, the service is essentially the same. Sevier County is large and very poor. There is but one cement road, and very few "black-top" or macadam. There are about 80 elementary schools mostly one or two room rural schools. well scattered in areas difficult to reach save in fair weather. One public health nurse could hardly take care of that territory, if she did nothing else. The Public Health Service, as you know, has many departments. There are Prenatal and Infant Welfare; Inoculations and Prevention of Disease; School inspection of children, buildings and grounds Cancer, Tuberculosis, Venereal Disease, Well Baby, Crippled Children's, Dental and Nutritional Clinics. It is concerned with a man nine months before his birth until his death his life, his home, his community, his water and sanitary facilities, his food, his garbage, his diseases. He must be kept healthy, not only for his own sake, but for the good of the community. Illness is expensive for an individual and for a nation. Any service offered by the U.S. Department of Health is obtainable through the local Health Center. And in addition, there are services comparable to your own city Visiting Nurse Service. We are as modern as Streptomycin and allergens. We pore over medical journals and investigate new theories. We study psychology and make use of the latest in visual education equipment. We are looked upon as mentors 393 </p>
      <pb ref="arr6240393_0002" seq="02" n="394-395  "/>
       <p>\~\ \ J\/d$/'.} . . t/e ro~ e .SL// and ~ ' c S.t. . ~ a, ~ ~ t THE MAY ARROW 395 and we must develop, or be left behind by those whom we seek to guide. Our students of yesterday are the leaders of today. Our role is always, guidance and cooperation. Times change and we change with them or stagnate. Yet babies are as old fashioned as linseywoolsey. Mothers need advice. Boys fall out of trees. Young folk go a courtin'. "Ailments" come in spite of penicillin and atabrine. But we meet our problems in the newer, better ways. The lanky red-head, shuttling back and forth from Tokyo, walks today, because years ago, a nurse worked day after day, with muscles that were warped and twisted. A plump little mother cares for her lively brood of four, because there was trained help in that long and fearful hour before the doctor could reach that mountain cabin. A black eyed little chap has but a faint white scar to show for the scalding of both legs. There will be another doctor before long, because of the prompt first aid that helped to save a badly mangled hand. And there are a few more nurses in the world because of the instruction and inspiration gained at Pi Beta Phi. Is it all worth while? Is there still a need? Look at the figures for the past year, and judge for yourself. Home Calls 1020 Office Calls 2622 First Aid 2221 Small Pox Vaccinations 155 Diphtheria Immunizations 86 Typhoid Inoculations 476 Whooping Cough Inoculations 53 Health Talks 120 Health Examinations and Inspections 3813 We do not measure assistance and influence by the use of numbers, of course. But consider that many have been fitted with glasses, had dental corrections, referred to specialists, outfitted with braces and corrective appliances, and in several cases, surgery was done before serious trouble developed. This is the work of the Fraternity. No wonder it has an honored place in the community. In any journey, it is well to pause and evaluate progress now and then. We look back to the starting point and visualize the' road we have come. We have done well, and we have not deviated from the path. We are going in the right direction, but our journey is not ended. There is work to be done good, honest necessary work for our hands and for our hearts. Work that may help the dim of eye to see, the lame to walk, and children to grow healthy andhappy. Work that finds its reward in the hearts of a grateful people. They still need us for a while. We will not fail them. Marjorie Chalmers, ''\ , .N. In December 1936, Marjorie Chalmers came to Pi Beta Phi and Gatlinburg as the new Public Health Nurse. She brought with her a wide field of experience having received her training at the Eitel Hospital, Minneapolis, Minnesota. She was later medical and surgical nurse there. She had experience in family re-lief and child welfare work. Her training in Marjorie Chalmers kindergarten and teacher work has better equipped her for the splendid service she has rendered to Gatlinburg and the surrounding community. Marjorie, as we all know her, is beloved by all. She has a remarkable knack with people. Her patience, tact and tirelessness have paved the way to trust and love. She is constantly on the go administering aid to the school personnel as well as those of the community which extends for miles around up the "cricks and hollers." She has faithfully carried on the work for ten years and knows most of the mountain folk and their troubles. All phases of her work are important. In addition to ministering to the sick, she has made tremendous strides in preventive measures. A well baby clinic held weekly has improved in</p>
      <pb ref="arr6240393_0003" seq="03" n="396-397  "/>
       <p>THE MAY ARROW 397 f ant health. She makes periodic school inspections,'not only in Gatlinburg, but in thirteen rural schools as well. She conducts classes in First-Aid, Home Nursing, Bedside Nursing, Prenatal Care, Infant Welfare and gives advice and instructions. For many years "Miz Chalmers" has felt the need of a new health center in order to carry on more efficiently the work she is doing for us. Her accompanying article reveals the need for the new building. The Health Center Serves No group of people are in a position to speak more authoritatively on the work of our Health Center than the residents of Gatlinburg and the mountain folk from the surrounding territory, to whom the Health Center and its staff have been physician, hospital, medical guide, training school and first aid center. Gatlinburg people have come to depend on the service we have provided for them. A series of their own letters not only express their appreciation but also provide an interest-. ., , .... "If we can be of any assistance to you at any time, please do not hesitate to call upon us." Very truly yours, MRs. J. B. DONOHOE, President Gatlinburg P.T.A. A Settlement School Graduate Mrs. Grace Huff has lived in Gatlinburg all her life as have her parents and her grand-parents before her. As a child she was enrolled in the Settlement School and is one of our graduates. Her knowledge of the Health Center comes from long association and personal benefit. "I am very proud to have this opportunity to express my gratitude for what the Health Center has done for our small town. "To me the Health Center has always stood for dependability in case of sickness, accident and other emergencies. Beginning with my birth when the nearest Doctor was fifteen miles away and had no means of transportation except by horseback, it was the nurse from the Health Center who arrived before the Doctor nt1fl 11C.kPt'Ptl rn. ;n+'n +41. T'rrn,l,l 4444, </p>
      <pb ref="arr6240393_0004" seq="04" n="398-399  "/>
       <p>~~ ~ .. . Oitnce  . ~ /9ievention " THE MAY ARROW 399 Church. She and her family spend the summers on top of Mt. Le Conte, running the famous Le Conte Lodge. Mrs. Huff tells us what the Health Center has meant to the entire community: . "It's so different looking from the outside into a room, than sitting in that room looking at the same things. You see so much more from the inside especially the little things that can make a world of difference in the picture. "That's the way we who live in Gatlinburg feel about the Health Center. There's so much in the day-to-day contact with the "Nurse" and the "Hospital" that any one away from here could not know or feel. To all of us who have small children, or any illness in the home, she represents a "friend in need" at all times. If the illness is small, her suggestions counsel us. If large, her helpfulness and assurance tide us over until a doctor can come. "The Home Nursing courses are invaluable. Every home-maker needs to know how to care for sick members of her family at home. Where else, here, could such courses be available except through the Health Center? There's still so much to be done in Preventive Medicine that no one else has time to do, or can do as well. Personally, I wish that the nurse had an assist-ant or two to do the office routine, while she concentrates on teaching, visiting, and school work. "This is a large county, with a small income. Much of the taxable land has been taken into the Park, and because of indefinite plans for a State Highway, businesses that would have been a source of income have not been built. This leaves only a small amount of money to spread a long way. The number of people who are engaged in business in Gatlinburg are a very small minority of the people served by the Health Center. "The need for a new building is very apparent. The work to be done in all the highways and byways is manifold, and the lives reached and helped are many. "Looking from the inside, and feeling our need, we, the beneficiaries of such good work done in the past, pray for its continuance in the future." PAULINE WHALING HUFF (MRS. JACK HUFF) The Last of the Granny Women Large families are common in the Tennessee Mountain area, and when a new baby comes it often must be introduced to the world with-out the assistance of a doctor. This was true, even in a greater degree twenty years ago when roads near Gatlinburg were unimproved and doctors were as scarce and overworked as they now are. At that time, Miss Phyllis Higinbotham, our first nurse, trained a class of mid-wives to assist her in obstetrical cases. Etta Brown is the last of these "Granny Women" trained by Miss Phyllis. During her long years of service, she was faithful and most helpful. Her patients were never known to develop an infection. Her work is now ended and her pleasant ways in the sick room are being missed but she continues loyal and interested in the work of the Health Center. She writes: "Dearest Nurse. If I have given you any-thing that will help, take it, please. If you copy any of this, copy it right I can't write letters like they should be. "When I was a little girl, I started out to make my way by staying with people, and minding babies, was sometimes my job. So I started off minding them like this. They told me if they cried to give them .a sugar-tit. The way I made them was, I got a white cloth and tied up a lump of sugar, and dipped the end of it in water to get them to nursing. So that is the way I minded them. When they were born they would give them milk and coffee mixed, till . their mother could furnish them milk. "While they were in bed some mothers were afraid to take a bath. and put on clean clothes. Some women would have me smoke their clothes with corn meal bran before they put them on. "Later on, I started out with my own family not knowing how and got part of my family on the way. Miss Phyllis came in to Gatlinburg to help in the school. She started us all out the right way on her plans, so we got along much better, with our little ones. So I will never forget her. "She planned a class for us women (midwives) and got doctors to come to the hospital and help her with our lessons, on how to take care of women and babies. So then I started out helping doctors. And sometimes it was just me to do the best I knew how. I have been helping in this work. for several years. "Now I am getting old, and my health is bad. I can't help no more. I hope the good work will go on for the younger people. Will you please help our good nurse to carry on the good work for the sake of our little ones that are still coming on? "I have been one of the school weavers for many years, till the doctors told me to quit it </p>
      <pb ref="arr6240393_0005" seq="05" n="400-401  "/>
       <p>t evenin,g t nh . io hard for me. I am the mother of seven get a new hospital. She needs more room and 11. and live near the Gatlinburg school. help to take care of us here." spent a lot of my time giving baths to MRS. W. C. BROWN i and babies, and have caught sixty-three Pictures used in this department are by or more. I wish our good nurse could Dorothy McLean, Gatlinburg, Tenn. In the very near future, our dreams and those of our friends will come true with the )nstruction of the new Health Center. The Committee and Grand Council are now udying plans for the new structure and as soon as these are agreed upon and workmen Id materials are available for construction, the building will be started. 400 Holt House News formed at the Second United Presbyterian church at three o'clock in the afternoon on October 4, 1945. Connie was the second Holt House bride. As the daughter of Mrs. C. C. Carey, popular Holt House receptionist, the House was her home throughout the four years during which she at-tended Monmouth college. As a student she brought many honors to Illinois Alpha chapter. A Fine Arts major, and the possessor of a lovely soprano voice, she took part in many local programs. Last spring she was chosen "Miss America" in "The Scan-Dolls of 1945." LIEUTENANT AND MRS. DANIEL 'C. PELTON (CONNIE CAREY), Illinois A. (A portion of one of the Holt portraits is visible in the background.) Connie Carey a The old House was aglow shaded lights, flickering candles, lovely flowers, soft music, and the gay voices of two hundred guests. The one-hundred-and-seven-year-old Holt portraits smiled their blessing upon the attractive couple standing near the bride's table with its tiered cake, white roses and chrysanthemums. The occasion was the reception which followed the marriage of Connie Carey (Illinois Alpha) to Lieutenant Daniel C. Felton of Monticello, New York. The ceremony was per i. ride 401 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



