<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr6030267_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>LeRoy, Beth Brainard</name></author>
                        <author><name>Munn, Ann Leichliter</name></author>
                        <author><name>Chalmers, R.N., Marjorie</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>March 1944</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr6030267_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">March 1944</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>LeRoy, Beth Brainard</name></author>
                        <author><name>Munn, Ann Leichliter</name></author>
                        <author><name>Chalmers, R.N., Marjorie</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 267-270</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">39</note>
                        <note type="Folder">12</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 60, Number 3 (March 1944), Pages 267-270.</note>
			<note type="document">arr6030267_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Do You Know These Facts About Our Settlement School?; Mrs. Munn Introduces Ruth Dyer; Health Service; Word Pictures of the Health Center Service</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Changing Mission of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity for Women in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1944-1964</item>
                                <item>Staff</item>
                                <item>Health care</item>
                                <item>Nurses</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr6030267_0001" seq="01" n="266-267  "/>
       <p>NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON Edited by BETH BRAINARD LEROY, Massachusetts A ssssss ssssss littst.swisa versation about a farm and its problems. Ruth understands these problems and can intelligently ask questions when outside guidance is needed. This knowledge is going to be especially helpful since we have been without a Smith-Hughes farm teacher in our school the past two years. For the past year and a half Ruth has been on the campus at Iowa State College as housemother to a rather new sorority. There, besides her duties as chaperone, she had charge of the meal planning, the buying and of all the problems relative to food stamps and ration books. They hated to lose Ruth and I did feel guilty in being partly responsible for their loss. So that you may have the reaction from someone who has just met Ruth, may I quote from Mildred Sale's recent letter to committee, where she tells of the open house held in Teachers' Cottage on December 21, when the townspeople were invited to meet our new Director. "Ruth has lovely poise, meets people easily, and carries a conversation along with no difficulty, if it happens to be one that doesn't carry itself." Ruth is interested in old glass and is really quite an authority on the subject. She has taken some of her things to the School so when you collectors of old glass meet her you can have fun chatting about an interesting subject. Many of you know Ruth, but for those of you who do not, I hope that I have made you feel close to her. The job of Director of the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School is a big one. Won't you continue to give Ruth the loyal support and splendid help you have given all directors in the past? Our School is such a wonderful project! You should see the light on Ruth's face when she speaks of it oh I just know we have a wonderful new Director! Best wishes to all Pi Phis for a New Year of peace and happiness. ANN LEICHLITER MUNN Health Service By MARJORIE CHALMERS, R.N. Sometimes it seems as though the Health Center gathered within its slightly warped walls all the problems of living of the entire community. That will be so as long as we continue e to Miss Ruth Dyer, the new Director of the Phi Settlement School at Gatlinburg, Tennessee. Munn Introduces Ruth Dyer ?l PHIS: I tell you about the new Director of our Settlement School ? She is Ruth Dyer, , graduate of the science division of the ^tate College. is well qualified in many ways to take e direction of our project. She has had experience, so that she understands blems and can "speak the language" of :hers, the superintendent, and the county !w years ago Ruth managed a lovely shop in Evanston, Illinois. This ex-2. qualifies her as an appreciative and anding helper to Ethel Snow at Arrowuth and Ethel are friends of long stand.-i they are both very happy over the t of working together at the school. here in Iowa she owns a farm and you )er down in Gatlinburg we all own a ^Tow many of us may know all about ag a farm, but I imagine lots of us aerely carry on. a rather one-sided con 266 THE MARCH ARROW 267 to serve, for birth and death, health and illness, the stark, unadorned struggle for life, and the love and beauty of living these are the things that pass. through the little white cottage day after day. These are the things that bring a few more gray hairs, as well as a wealth of affection. Folk cannot face together dream's fulfillment or the tragedy of despair, without trust and understanding. One cannot measure the accomplishments of this Health Center by statistics. If that could be so, we should say there had been so many lives started, so many stilled, some bodies saved from disfigurement or fatal disease, fear conquered, superstition erased, and faith and confidence strengthened. Lessons have been taught, in theory and in reality. Perhaps we shall never see the evidence of knowledge gained. We can but hope that day by day, there is progress. We can hope that by living together, playing together, working together yes even "Miz Chalmers" "Miz Chalmers," our nurse at the Settlement School, has seen all phases of life in Gatlinburg and in a personal letter to me she writes, "I've watched over them before birth, patched them together, and told them stories. I've pulled them through measles, heartache and love affairs, helped them with their lessons and married them off. I've spanked them and played with them, scolded them and laughed with them, washed their faces and held them in my arms till death took them away. I am very humble. How could I ever fail them in their hour of need ?" And then she adds, "We are having the wartime epidemic of babies, bless 'em, and fine, hearty babies they are!" The changing needs and the trends of Health Service she has outlined in the accompanying article.singing the same songs, we may, together, make our lives a little easier and safer. We discussed, at the last Red Cross Work Shop, the evaluation of our several jobs to set a goal, and to take stock, now and then, lest we stray too far from the path. Difficult it is to state in raw, blunt terms, our goal for Beulah Moore and her children the future. Our watchword has ever been "Service." Not blind, unreasoning servitude. Not merely working for people, but working with them to attain happier and more helpful environment. Each baby bath, each school inspection, each conference with a mother-to-be, has behind the need of the moment, the building for the future. We have been trying for years to teach illness and accident prevention. We have upheld the value of inoculation, of nutrition and hygiene. We have stressed the importance of early diagnosis and treatment of disease. We have advocated regularity and early training and intelligent care of our children and our sick folk. And there has been progress. Lessons learned in the class room or in a log cabin are being applied many times. The "anticky" youngster of yesterday is the proud daddy of today, and the woman who stood by him through the measles or the first love affair, is naturally the one to help him pin the first "hippen" on the first baby. And the girl who learned to give a sponge bath in class, will find it easy to follow directions for making formulas or improvising a croup tent. </p>
      <pb ref="arr6030267_0002" seq="02" n="268-269  "/>
       <p>THE MARCH ARROW .t should we ever continue to lead, our Tship would be seriously at fault. We are Ming for advancement for independence. we are advancing is evidenced in many With the Health. Center as a clearing Three boys on Bearskin !, the churches and the community are g care of the needy. We have formed an icial sharing corporation where clothes )a'thinettes, nursery chairs and galoshes are Lnged. We share the rides, and we also the things that are increasingly hard to And we, in emergencies, care for one ler's families. Those who know how, help who would learn inter-dependence of the th Center and with one another. It may )e easy to sing at the final service for one e hand you held during the last long or the baby you helped "A-horning," t is part payment on the debt of affection trust-evidence, indeed of interdependence. erretta, our film-baby-in-the-scales, came the office the other day, all bright smiles, ual. She pulled out the little, chair, and yd and sang to herself, while mother and I d. Healthy and active from the perky bow le wisp of shining hair to the spotless little ;, every stage of her development has been ssed. Nelle was in the grades when I and Ernest was in High School. They re-to listen to Granny tales and follow di-)ns to the letter. And this is but one ace of how our young folk put training practice. Major and Gladys have a son one week old today. Major is off to the war, but Gladys is sending for Bundeson's Baby Book, even as you have done and is preparing to put up a good fight on the home front. Graduates from the Home Nursing Classes are now using in their homes, knowledge gained from their lessons. One of the boys who took First Aid in high school is now doing good work in an Air Evacuation Unit in the South Seas, and two of our girls have entered Nurses' Training this year. In the rural schools it is great fun to be sent to the car for the Nurse's bag, and to gather around with the others, while things are spread on the fresh towel, ready for what-ever first aid seems necessary. The whys and wherefores of various medicines, the packaging of sterile dressings, healing processes, and prevention of infection, remedies used in the home are topics of infinite absorption. And judging from the carefully bandaged cuts so proudly shown, some homes are profiting by the lessons. Many times parents come into the office, for themselves or with children, stating that some school child had insisted on the boundless ability of "The Nurse" to make all things right. Now they will accept unquestioningly, the occasional statement, "I am not sure enough. Let's go to the doctor and find out what to do." The sound commonsense underlying the theory of the book, the reason for balanced meals, for inoculations, for rules of hygiene are exemplified again and again. No contact is void of teaching nor should it ever be. But such teaching should not be dogmatic. No good will ever come from the "Holier-than-thou" approach. After all, here are many times when the teacher has gained more than she gave. I have never yet completed a course of teaching without learning almost as many things as I have taught. Perhaps they were not the same as "stood in the book," but they are workable things, adapted to the situation. And above all things, she who would work in rural areas particularly with mountain folk must learn to be flexible and to improvise. And, when, together, we work out the solutions to our problems whether it be the proper training of the pre-school child, or the application of the rules of hygiene from a text book, we are laying a firm foundation for better living. "Service," then, is not now the goal for which we strive. For what we are trying to do has more of guidance of cooperation than that. Education is progress, not so much the actual learning as the increasing ability of adap THE MARCH ARROW 269 tation to changing circumstances. 'Could we inculcate inspiration and confidence into our educational development, then we would be achieving progress. Hard as it is to express our de-sires in tangible words, perhaps as good a phrase as any would be "Health Guidance." Now, how far toward the goal have we come ? He who is swimming in the river, with head close to the tide, cannot mark his progress as well as the man on the shore. But there have been advancements. So we are becoming firmly established in the new phase of existence at the Health Center. Gradually, that there be no abrupt change, with its resultant confusion and possible resentment, we are taking on the habiliments of an educator a health mentor, if you will. Our business is prevention a positive role. Our business is with living safe and sane. We are banded together the community and I, to banish, as far as humanly possible, filth and disease, fear andsuperstitution. There are still heart aches and discouragements, but we have started in the right direction. What do we want for the future? First and above all, a mobile dental unit. One so constructed that we can get to the isolated areas at least once each month. One that would be independent of power lines and financial worries. I firmly believe, that within a short time, such a unit could pay for its running expenses. Stop to think that there is but one dentist in the whole of Sevier County, ,an elderly man swamped with emergencies, that there are no bus lines reaching into rural areas, that cars and trucks are few, and used for business only. Dental corrections seem almost impossible, in the majority of cases, and are our biggest problem. Next in importance comes the corporation of a definite health education program in the schools. There is need for an authorized teacher acceptable to the State Board of Education, so that the students may get their credits. But fully as important is the selection of a teacher who knows her subject, one who is qualified in theory and experience to handle the course. Last of all on our list for wishful thinking, is a Health Center. Sentiment and familiarity must not blind us to the fact that the picturesque, homey little cottage is not practical. A unit with firm foundations and level floors, with walls that exclude daylight and rain, and windows that fit tightly; an office, light and cheery, a workroom that can be kept clean and convenient, a clinic room large enough to care for classes and demonstrations, a power line that will handle more than one burner at a time, and a dry heat sterilizer for dressings. These are in our dreams for the future. They are practical wishes and in time will be a reality. There is much to be accomplished wonderful, vital things. It is our privilege to have Pearl Gray and her son had a little part in the preparation for the things to come. You, who have been so loyal through long years of service to the community, who have brought light into the shadows, have created a living monument to the honor of the Fraternity. May you see, in the not too distant future, Health Guidance developing; surely and wisely, into the next stage of growth, perhaps, who knows, into a Council of Health in which we may all have our share of responsibility for life and happiness. Agnes Wright Spring gave rich inspiration and dynamic leadership last fall as Director of the Settlement School. From her facile pen comes the following inimitable interpretation. Word Pictures of the Health Center Service By AGNES WRIGHT SPRING Whether you hurry up the cobblestones to the front porch of the Health Center, or whether you come along the concrete walk from the Teachers' Cottage and enter through the back door, you will always find sympathetic aid from the skillful hands of "Miss Marjorie," our Nurse. Or, if it is only a word of cheer </p>
      <pb ref="arr6030267_0003" seq="03" n="270-271  "/>
       <p>0 THE MARCH ARROW homesickness that you need, you'll find that, For suddenly Nurse Chalmers remembers .t she must make a call in the Glades or up mont way, and tells you to hop in the car and along. And after the drive with her through the ,okies no matter how long or how short ]. come back refreshed in mind and spirit. the shiny bottles and instruments in the .rte cabinets, the neat card files, the shelves little blankets and "hippens," even the clean ell of those rooms over which the Nurse !sides instill confidence. N'o one is better known up and down the Llers, in the coves, in the Burg, or in the DOI rooms than "Miz Chalmers." A proud young mother stops the Nurse Charlie Ogle's store with this greeting, 'ou should see Elmer now. He's grown a then" Then she leads the way to a baby riage in which an infant sleeps. Another mother with tears of gratitude in r eyes, brings her child to the Health Center or to show that his little feet that are still rased in braces are "a sight better." Little muddy handprints on car fenders at-t how children group around the Nurse's car she prepares to drive away after taking care a sick 'un up in Turkey's Nest. And how eagerly those little folk wait their in the schoolroom when the Nurse gives various "shots" for whooping-cough or )htheria or typhoid. And there is never a limper, except, of course, from the wee es in their mother's arms, who are too small realize what is happening. When you drop into the Nurse's living quar ters for a chat and watch the firelight play across the dulcimer strings, or on the gay chintz curtains and lovely pictures, books and rugs you forget that this is the oldest building on the School grounds, that is, next to the original Ogle cabin. You are quite unaware that the large rocks near the doors are used to prop the warped doors shut or open, as desired. You are not conscious of the fact that the basement is moldy and the foundations are wobbly from the constant attack of termites. Every time I crossed the School grounds during my stay at the School last autumn, I could see in my mind's eye a lovely, new substantial Health Center, with adequate equipment to take care of the tremendous needs of the community. It seemed to me that through our Health work and through our Nurse we have the most direct contact with the homelife of those who live back of the main paved high-way. Believe it or not, that homelife in many, many ways is still two generations behind that which you and I enjoy and which many know who live in the Burg. With men coming back from the war, many of whom will be broken in body, but still able to take their places in the old home community our opportunity. for service undoubtedly will be doubled. How soon can we make the dream of a New Health Center come true? Do you know the answer? Just as soon as the "quality of contact" of 38,419 Pi Beta Phi women makes it possible. Let's start now! -4 ver the World ANN FEILD, Oklahoma A, was recently honored at presentation of a University of Oklahoma Service .g. Ann is chairman of the University War Service uncil, and the award was for purchase of war mps by more than 90% of the student body. MARJORIE HENDRICKS, Wisconsin A, manager for past twelve years of Normandie Farms, her restau-Lt in the country outside of Washington, D.C., and re recently also of the Water Gate Inn on the tomac River in Washington, has placed her experi-:e at the disposal of the American Red Cross. She s first in temporary charge of a large Officers' Club New Caledonia; then she became a food supervisor Australia. Later, she will make a tour of Red Cross revising menus and recipes, and making any Lnges necessary. Her work has received special emendation from the War Department. She is a :er of GENEVIEVE HENDRICKS, also Wisconsin A, tinguished interior decorator in Washington. Wayman Adams, husband of MARGARGET BORGHS ADAMS, Texas A and Louisiana A, was hon ored with first prize of $1,000 at the Pittsburgh "Painting In the United States" show held under the auspices of the Carnegie Institute. The picture was a portrait of Gregor Piatigorsky, renowned cellist, and had previously been featured in the "Arts For Victory" in the Metropolitan in New York a year ago. National Chairman of the War Products Committee of the Daughters of the American Revolution is MRS. HANSEL DWIGHT WILSON (FLORENCE PORTER GATLING, Missouri 1') . GLADYS KIRCHNER BUNTEN, Kansas B, is salvage chairman for Laramie County, Wyoming, which has recently held a drive which netted a ton of unusually good garments, to be distributed to the needy in war torn countries through the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration. HELEN GLEASON, Ohio A, is in charge of the University of Michigan Extension Service in Grand Rapids. IIIIsn.l.11.1.11IIIIII.I.11101111.10111101011111,1111111111111111I.11111.1111111101111118101110.111.0te..S.111111.110A.AIIIIIIIIII0.11.83.11.111.11.1.11IIIIII1.1.11111.1.11081111.101.11a.11MO.I.I.I.IM.11.1.1 I PHI PENS Edited by MARJORIE BRIGHT SHARPE, Texas A 0 M FR HAMILTON HOWARD, Kentucky A, has emerged a full-fledged columnist. Her journalistic efforts, "Maid in Manhattan," appear in the Louisville Courier journal. She describes with youthful effervescence what is going on in New York ; Kentucky friends who visit wartime Gotham; and the still exciting, though partially dimmed Great White Way. A sample column includes the following items, "Most out of towners think of New York as Broadway, Grand Central and the -Pennsylvania Station, Rockefeller Center and a few other best-known landmarks. They never get uptown as far as 86th. But that's quite a neighborhood. The street itself, wider than Louisville's Broadway, is the main artery of Yorkville, New York's German section. The Bund as everybody knows, used to thrive there. Now big red, white and blue banners fly over the middle of the street to say, "For God and Our Country" or something like that and tell how many boys from the neighborhood are serving Uncle Sam. It's a goodly number, too." "The Movers Warehousemen's Association of Greater New York estimates it moved 60,000 families in and around Manhattan during September alone. We were among the movers but we did it in easy stages by taxis and crowded double-decker 5th Avenue buses. Be-fore the war nobody could stand on 5th Avenue buses. Now they shout "standing only" and pack people in like the subways. Gas rationing has thrown a terrific burden onto the public transportation systems. These days there are practically no cars on the streets outside of taxis and New York is a pedestrian's holiday. You still have to be on your toes when you cross against the traffic lights which everybody does but the only time you're in real danger is during the dim-out at night." Author Sidelights Miss Howard carries on in her chatty style to sum up her biography, "I surprised my ma one October night twenty-five years ago and it would be nice phrase-turning if I could say I've been full of surprises ever since. But it wouldn't be true. I went through the usual Louisville growing up. Went to University of Louisville for a year and joined the Pi Beta Phis. Left immediately for New York to work in my uncle's advertising agency. Came home on a vacation and sold the Courier lour-nal on hiring me as a copywriter, in spite the fact I'd never written any copy. After thr years came into the promised land in Ne York on the best gamble anybody ever took Miss Howard shares an apartment with thr other girls, one a singer looking for a bre: and the other two rival copywriters. ETHEL CHAMBERLAIN PORTER, Illinois a prolific article-writer, is by-lined in the lat( issue of Travel Magazine. This particular artit is one in a series resulting from several sat mers' sojourn in the Balkans with the author husband and two sons. It is illustrated by a of these sons, Ensign C. L. Porter, and is e titled "Jugoslavian Undercurrents." Mrs. Port evidences a close study of the countries, ticularly from an ethnographic point of vie' She begins: "This is the story of a summ spent in Jugoslavia. Here West meets East, at civilization as old as Greece and as young tomorrow passed daily before our eyes. Ov( lying this is the story of a country crucifie racked by pain, 'scarred and ruined in may of its parts. Some of its inhabitants are deg others are hiding in caves and forests, sufferit but brave. Jugoslavia will not die nor w the other Balkan countries, but in the fie crucible of war they may lose their interr hates and be fused into a United States of t: Balkans, able to stand in that brave new wor of which we dream." With pertinent word-pictures Mrs. Chas berlain escorts the reader through Jugoslavia-a hodge-podge of , conflicting peoples, belie and customs. She contrasts with conviction t country's status before and after the prese global war. "Now the Adriatic waters mined the pirates' deep turquoise caves ho guerilla bands; Slays fight the Germans ha] to hand in the narrow streets of cities whi were old at the time of the Crusades" s. writes. The Balkans, long the focal point of E rope's seething political and racial cauldrc are graphically described. Jugoslavia, a count approximately the size of New York and Pen sylvania, is depicted as a land of infinite .'s riety. Its climate is varied too. High in t snowy reaches of the Alps, the weather is p( petually cold, while in the languid southe 271 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



