<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr6840291_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>To the Fortieth Anniversary of the Settlement School</title>
                        <author><name>Rauch, Harriet Goodsell</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>May 1952</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr6840291_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">May 1952</date>, To the Fortieth Anniversary of the Settlement School</title>
                        <author><name>Rauch, Harriet Goodsell</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 290-294</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">40</note>
                        <note type="Folder">4</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 68, Number 4 (May 1952), Pages 290-294.</note>
			<note type="document">arr6840291_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">A Skit for Carnicus</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Changing Mission of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity for Women in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1944-1964</item>
                                <item>Plays</item>
                                <item>People</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr6840291_0001" seq="01" n="290-291  "/>
       <p>%at' in/ q!nq aq ()I 'loom /uguoy"as act/ iv as ~aprsa s,Aaq.7r.aL ,naN T1/al's .rpaqq,4v 1 0 II *MI II S I 1 II II THE A I OW OF PI BETA PHI MAY, 1952 VOLUME 68 ',mum /I g.1$1111 To the Fortieth Anniversary of ttllL~c~ Settlement School A Skit for Carnicus By HARRIET GOODSELL RAUCH, Iowa B SETTING: Pi Beta Phi chapter room at the University of Tennessee. CHARACTERS: Committee of four to plan skit: Lois Boop, President, JEAN DEVAULT, EUDELL RIPPETOE, BARBARA HUFF. ACT ONE jean and Eudell are seated on sofa in room looking at book. Enter Lois. EUDELL: Hi-ya, Lois. What are you going to do after committee meeting tonight? Lois: Study, My Dea'. Study! (Puts down books, turns) Why, do you have something better to offer? EUDELL : I'm tired of cramming. Jean and I are trying to get up a four-some of bridge. Lois: Perish the thought! No time in my life for frivolity! EUDELL: Well, we probably won't be out of here until all hours anyway. So skip it. JEAN: Why, what do we have to do? EUDELL: It's easy like that. Just plan the winning skit for Carnicus. JEAN: Oh, Oh, another assessment. Lois: Well, we can't afford to take any money out of the treasury. Taking money out of the treasury is out. EUDELL: What chance have we then? (Enter Barbara) JEAN: Say, Barbara, what d'ja' draw in that Poll Sci quiz? BARBARA: B plus. JEAN: Wonderful. It certainly was a toughie. Lois: C'mon girls, C'mon. Back to the mines. Back to the mines. We must have a skit for Carnicus. EUDELL: I say, what chance have we? The Betas have jack Strong. His dad is in the lumber business. They even get lumber fo sets for nothing. JEAN: Well, look at the Chi Omegas of rich alums right in town. EUDELL : Oh, the 2 A Es are really crowd. Fanciest house on campus. the limit. They'll get all their stuff and then turn in the smallest bill. Lois: Girls, this catty chit-chat isn't with our problem. We aren't he' plans for the other organizations ( BARBARA: O.K. Lois, what does it to Lois: Eye appeal. Snappy script. ( Colorful costumes. EUDELL: Is THAT all? Lois: Girls! Down to business. Hasr a real sharp idea that won't cost us Remember, no money. JEAN: (aside) Same song. Second N BARBARA: We've got trunks full of up in Gatlinburg that they use in th play. JEAN: Why couldn't we put on at: play of the early days in Gatlinbur; EUDELL: Frankly, I'm not much imp that idea. That stuff's been done JEAN: Well, you can bet your bot that no one else on campus will timey play. BARBARA: Well, Girls, no other hot] pus has a Settlement School in i Tennessee, either. EUDELL : You have got something i BARBARA: Of course I have I hav Phis have. JEAN: I know that everybody know Settlement School. EUDELL: I wouldn't be too sure. Pe know about the school as it is nova 291 </p>
      <pb ref="arr6840291_0002" seq="02" n="292-293  "/>
       <p>THE MAY ARROW since the University of Tennessee is working with Pi Phi at Gatlinburg in the summers on the Summer Work-shop. Say, by the way, did you see the perfectly stunning jewelry that Marion Heard's classes turned out last summer? ]UDELL: No. Where'd you see it? At their open house at the end of the summer school. It's TERRIFIC! 3ARBARA: You know they even gave pottery this last summer, too. EUDELL: Yea. So I heard. Lois: Just think what Little Pigeon has turned into since 1912! [EAN: That's not so long ago. Lois: Not so long. Why I wasn't even born then. Lois: Go 'way! I'm going to be twenty-one this summer. EUDELL: Say, you know, Barbara, come to think of it, we all have pretty hazy ideas about the Settlement School. Whether we win the prize or not, it certainly wouldn't do us any harm to work on it in dead earnest. BARBARA: It certainly wouldn't. Lois: Just what's been done since 1912? Just a minute I'll get my notebook. (Gets note-book) Let's see the first little school was started in 1912 with 14 pupils. There are two school buildings now with about 500 pupils. EUDELL: Well, that's something to brag about but there's no drama in that. Just good steady day-by-day work for the Pi Phis and the people in Gatlinburg. Lois: All-right, then, We'll take the health pro-gram. (Reading) In 1920 our first nurse, Phyllis Higginbotham, started with nothing but a horse, a saddle-bag and a lot of sick people. Now we have a new modern health center and nurse Chalmers is busy with all of the latest in health work. BARBARA: Gee, she's proud of her babies, as she calls them. You should go up some time and just visit one of her well-baby clinics. I swear you never saw lovelier babies any-place. EuDELL: I'm sure there's plenty of drama in the health program but we can't just use the health center. Somebody'd be sure to think that was all Pi Phi did in Gatlinburg. We mustn't give the wrong impression. It'd take the Settlement School Committee all winter to straighten that one out. Lois: Then, there's Arrow Craft Shop. New building built in 1940 by Pi Beta Phi. (Reading) Outgrowth of sale of baskets made by local people through the alumnae clubs in 1915. Now through the weaving Arrowcraft helps an average of over one hundred families a year. E UDELL : There've been too many weaver's plays, I think. The early costumes and expressions are fun, though. Lois: (continuing reading) U. of T. and Pi Beta Phi started Summer Work-shop eight years ago as an experimental summer crafts-recreation school. It has now moved beyond the experimental period (ends reading), It's a wonderfully interesting hand-craft development. But it is still such a small part of our work there. JEAN: Well, what'll we do ? It's getting late and none of this is going to make the skit. BARBARA: I'll tell you what. I'll go up to the Mountain View hotel in Gatlinburg this weekend and talk to my grandfather Huff . If he's not too busy with the park tourists, he'll give me a story! EUDELL: It'll be authentic, at least. JEAN: Authentic! 'STOO bad Prof. Smith isn't one of the judges. He certainly like things authentic! Speaking of authenticity, I simply must get going and bone up on history for tomorrow. Can we be on our way, Lois? Lois: Sure. Run along. Thanks for coming. See you tomorrow. (Exit lean with waves or what ever) EUDELL: Say, who mentioned bridge? It couldn't have been I? So long. (Lois picks up books, etc.) Lois: Coming, Barbara? Exit Together. ACT Two SETTING: Interior of Aunt Lydia Whaley's cabin. CHARACTERS: AUNT LYDIA WHALEY, AUNT LIZZIE, MIZ HUFF AND MIZ WHALEY (When curtain goes up, two of Pi Phis in first act fixing set) (Girls move quickly. Aunt Lydia and Lizzie speak slowly until climax, lots of pauses). Lois: Guess, it's all fixed, Barbara. BARBARA: Yes, we'd better skip. It's about time for our stunt. Curtain goes down long enough to seat Aunt Lizzie at a loom. Enter Aunt Lydia. AUNT LIZZIE : Lawsy. Aunt Lydia, you shore do get up early of a morning. I figger in winter effen you don't get up early, you an't got no time to set and enjoy the day. AUNT LIZZIE: I don't like to milk so early. Hev to feel to see where the cow is. THE MAY ARROW 293 A UNT LYDIA: Hev you et this morning. Come, sit and hev a bite. Hit eats good. (go to the table) AUNT LIZZIE: (eating) Hit shore does. You ain't fraid up here, Aunt Lydia? AUNT LYDIA: Nope. Ain't never seed but one fraid in my life. That was one night when I seed somethin' black out in the yard. AUNT LIZZIE: Wha'd ya do? AUNT LYDIA: Went out to it, give it a hard kick (starts chuck/in') and it was my own little black kittle. (Both laugh together) (Aunt Lydia walks to loom) AUNT LIZZIE: What you loomin' today? AUNT LYDIA: A county-pin. Gentleman's Fancy little bo-knot pattern. AUNT LIZZIE: I'M all tied up with the misery today. AUNT LYDIA: You shore do look peaked. AUNT LIZZIE: I ought to do chair-bottomin'. Chair bottomin' is easy settin' down work. (Pause) But this house sets mighty easy. (Pause while Lydia works and Lizzie sits) AUNT LYDIA: Effen hit's the Lord's will, reckon' it'll be. AUNT LIZZIE: Now what'd you say, Aunt Lydia? AUNT LYDIA: I'M sayin' reckon effen it's the Lord's will, reckon it'll be. I'm talkin' about them Pi Phi wimmen that came down here to set up a school. AUNT LIZZIE : I'm thinkin' Lord heps them as heps themsevs. We got to get 'em some land to build on to do our part. Miz Helmick, one of them Pi Phi wimmen, said most places the people hed to hep so they'd know they wanted sumpin' like a school. AUNT LYDIA: I didn't set no store by them wimmen when they first come down here but I reckon they's comin' to hep a needy people. AUNT LIZZIE : We don't confidence furriners much. AUNT LYDIA: No, but I'd like my least 'uns to have some larnin'. AUNT LIZZIE : Yes, but I don't want 'em rottenin"em up wi' spilin'. AUNT LYDIA: No. Reckon not (long pause). But they need more larnin' now. AUNT LIZZIE: Them Pi Phi wimmen hez shore got us all back at our looms and baskets. AUNT LYDIA: Hit had been a tolable long spell sence I'd set at my loom. AUNT LIZZIE: I been making kiver lids. Been makin' ooze out o' barks agin', too. AUNT LYDIA: I been turnin' out baskets fast as ever I kin'. (Both chuckle pause)AUNT LIZZIE : I heered if them wimmen stay, they're goin' to git a man to teach tools. AUNT LYDIA: Just esackly, why been't they stay ing? AUNT LIZZIE : 'Cause they ain't got no land fer a buildin' school buildin'. (Sit or work quietly for a bit) AUNT LYDIA: Effen they go now after sech a good start, our young 'uns '11 feel in a sorry plight. AUNT LIZZIE: 'Specially after last Christmas when they fotched up them dolls and play-pretties and lamed 'em them new Christmas stories. AUNT LYDIA: 'N how the least 'uns liked them new games. AUNT LIZZIE: What games? AUNT LYDIA: You know, that `farmer in the dell' and `Button, Button.' AUNT LIZZIE: Yes. They's havin' all this fun and a larnin', too. (Work and/or sit and rock) AUNT LYDIA: You say, they been't goin' to stay? AUNT LIZZIE: No'm. Miz Helmick says we've been too long gettin' a piece to build on. (Pause) AUNT LYDIA: Reckon them wimmen is begin nin' to think we ain't a wantin' of a school. AUNT LI771E: Andy Huff's that proud of the school. AUNT LYDIA: So's Uncle Steve Whaley and Charlie Ogle. AUNT LIZZIE : There's the Maples and the Huskies and the Reagans. AUNT LYDIA: I heered that Andy Huff is a totin' his four year old Mattie every day so they's one more pupil and she'll be a larnin'. (Aunt Lydia goes to window and looks out) AUNT LYDIA: Well hep my time. Here comes Miz Huff and Miz Whaley now. (Aunt Lydia goes to the door) AUNT LYDIA: Come right in. Glad to see ya'. What brings ya here at this hour? MIZ HUFF: We're a sight worried about our school. AUNT LYDIA: Well set down and cotch yore breath. Miz WHALEY: We ain't got more time fer foolin"round. AUNT LIZZIE: What's that, you say? MIZ WHALEY: We ain't got more time fer foolin"round. Miz Helmick says. Miz HUFF : They'se been awaitin"round fer long, long spell for a piece to build on anc now it's most too late. Miz Helmick say: effen we don't do our part in gettin' the lanC </p>
      <pb ref="arr6840291_0003" seq="03" n="294-295  "/>
       <p>294 THE MAY ARROW by after-noon they's goin' to pick up and go some-'eres else. AUNT LYDIA: Miz Huff, what kin we do? Miz HUFF: I've sent a boy to clean up to the lumber camp to fetch Andy. He should be a comin' most any time now. MIZ WHALEY: I'll jest be a goin' along to talk to Steve. We don't hev no time fer foolin'. (Exit Miz Whaley) AUNT LYDIA: No more time? MIZ HUFF: No. Miz Helmick's ordered a hack from Sevierville to come and fetch the school things away effen we don't hev some land by eveni'. (Pause) AUNT LYDIA (Go to chair and sit) : Well, we're certainly in the middle of a fix! AUNT LIZZIE: That's jest the way hit hits me. (Re-enter Miz Whaley) MIZ WHALEY: I run plum into Steve. He sez E. E. Ogle'l give his tract reasonable effen the money kin be raised. AUNT LIZZIE : He could git $2000 fer that tract. MIZ WHALEY: Well, he'll give $250 hissef and them Pi Phi wirnmen'll give $600. MIZ HUFF: Andy and Steve'll give $250 apiece. (Pause disturbance of voices off stage) (Aunt Lydia runs to the window) AUNT LYDIA: There's the hack from Sevierville, now. (Aunt Lizzie runs to the window, too) AUNT LIZZIE: What's Charlie Ogle doin' ? (All run to the window) AUNT LYDIA: Land sakes, he's gathered up a heap of fire crackers. Like en ez eff it's the Christmas. Miz HUFF : I recollect I did hear Charlie had rounded up all of the firecrackers in the Burg. AUNT LYDIA: What's he aiming to do wi' those? MIZ HUFF: He's aimin' to set 'em off all to once effen them wimmen gets a piece to build on. AUNT LYDIA: Men are crowded all around the store and hack now. AUNT LIZZIE: There come the Pi Phi wimmen. MIZ WHALEY: I'm goin' to run out and hear what's goin' on. I'll be back. AUNT LYDIA (going back to sit down) : Land sakes. Most excitin' as the Rebellion. AUNT LIZZIE: I'm goin' to set too. I'd plumb forgot about my misery (Chuckles). (Miz Huf f stays at window, Other two sit. Voices off stage) MIZ HUFF: Here she comes. MIZ WHALEY (very excitedly) : They got it. They got it. Eph Ogle said he'd rether hev the school than the land effen he could get a fair price. Andy and Uncle Steve headed the money. The Pi Phis gave theirs. Some others helped. Then Andy and Mr. Maple said they'd make up any difference. MIZ HUFF: Then them Pi Phi wimmen is down to sign the deed. (All run to the window) (Excitedly all): There's goes the hack back to Sevierville. (Noise of the firecrackers off stage cap pistol will do) That's it. That's it. (Dance around excitedly and finally all go off except Aunt Lydia) (Noise off -stage gradually subsides and Aunt Lydia goes to her chair where she can look out of window. Sits down and picks up Bible. Reads aloud, very slowly and laboriously) I will lift up mine eyes unto the hills from whence cometh my help. My help cometh from the Lord which made Heaven and Earth. He will not suffer thy foot to be moved ... to be moved ... to be moved ... pope 'twon't move ... 'twon't move ... school won't move . . (Drops book. Falls asleep in chair. Curtain) Curtain goes up and girls in first act come on stage in set of Act Two EUDELL: Lois, Girls, we won the cup! We won the Cup! Pi Phis won the cup! Lois: Barbara, I'm so thrilled that you went up to Gatlinburg to get a story for us. EUDELL: I was afraid that it just wasn't enough story to win. BARBARA: But it won! Lois: Well, come on girls, we have to go and get the honors now. JEAN: Come to think about it, I've realized something while we've been working on this skit. GIRLS : What, Lois ? Lois: I've learned that our Pi Phi Settlement School is now giving the whole country the knowledge that it own folk art is good. JEAN: Well, I've realized we have to help raise money for our new staff house at the Settlement School. Lois, Let's give our skit on campus and charge admission. Then we could send the money for the new staff house. GIRLS : Wonderful. (Exit, talking excitedly about giving money for furnishings to new staf f house) CURTAIN Editorials Greek Letter Women Participate in Know Your America Week: an NPC .ARet How well do you know your America? Do you know what the American freedoms are and why we treasure them? In hundreds of cities and towns throughout the Nation on May 14 to 20, 1952 Fraternity Wc will participate in Know Your America Week. The benefits and opportunities of the free wo life are increasing in importance to more and more people in every American community. Citi will rededicate themselves to the preservation of the basic American principles which wit exemplified and dramatized through numerous and varied programs planned in the respe communities during Know Your America Week. What can you do? Fraternity women can plan programs within their chapters and Panhellenics, as well as volur their services to the local organizers, or if no organizers, can volunteer such leadership thems( to the civic authorities or broadcasting studios in their communities. In observing Know America Week, fraternity women can volunteer to present or take part in historical pagei college chapter houses can display the flag throughout the week (do our chapter houses own emblems ? They should!). Fraternity women can contribute choral groups ; they can offer to booths for the dissemination of information ; they can speak on radio and community progrl and they can offer organizational experience or the "know how" to get things done. Prate. members are among the most experienced and devoted group of volunteer workers in the Ur States_ Put the leadership training and organizational experience your fraternity helped to dev in you at work during Know Your America Week. All programs throughout the United States will highlight the story of our Nation; its laws liberties, its faiths and national origins; its schools and churches; its clubs and free associati its rights and responsibilities. We college women have responsibility as citizens because we enjoy the freedoms our forefat won for us. In recognition of this responsibility, the National Panhellenic Conference joins ,with 54 c national organizations representing approximately 800,000 citizens all associated in the All-A ican Conference in urging their memberships to observe and participate in Know Your Am' 'reek. At a called meeting of delegates of the National Panhellenic Conference on March 29, 195 Chicago, Illinois, the following resolution was unanimously adopted: "The National Panhellenic Conference becomes a member of the All-American Conferen( Combat Communism, as a demonstration by the college Greek letter societies for women of opposition to the philosophy and techniques of communism, and as evidence of their devotic American freedom." The All-American Conference whose present headquarters are located at Room 406, 1624 Street, N.W., Washington, D.C., is an informational, educational and advisory body. Each ticipating organization speaks for itself on matters of policy. It does not speak for the Confer( The Conference does not speak for it. Dr. Daniel A. Poling who serves as chairman of the All-American Conference in an ad^ on World Peace on June 27, 1951 before the Supreme Council Session of the United Comm( Travelers of America said among other things: "The price of freedom first of all is knowledge. We need to know these United Statc America. . . . We need to know what is going on in America. "Freedom is not free. Always freedom has its price. And that price has been paid. Freedc both an inheritance and an achievement. . .. We have it from those who went before us, in their time paid the price. . . . Theirs is a finished work. But in some sense, at least, this fre( must be re-born in me, it must become alive in me. I must make my contribution here and n Fraternity women have their opportunity to contribute here and now in Know Your Am Week, May 14-20, 1952. As Mrs. Fred Sharp, National President of Alpha Sigma Alpha editorialized in a recent of their publication: "In the security of friendship, we can review the basic values of fraternity and the ever-wid( boundaries for the application of the principles. In mutual reverence we can experrenc( 295 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



