<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr6540381_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Summer Workshop 1948</title>

                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>May 1949</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr6540381_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">May 1949</date>, Summer Workshop 1948</title>

                        <extent>Pages 380; 384-386</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">40</note>
                        <note type="Folder">1</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 65, Number 4 (May 1949), Pages 380; 384-386.</note>
			<note type="document">arr6540381_0000</note>


	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Changing Mission of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity for Women in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1944-1964</item>
                                <item>Summer crafts workshop</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr6540381_0001" seq="01" n="380-381  "/>
       <p>aeaereeaaaraeeerraaraaaeaaaruraeeerrrraarreeraeaaeaaeeearaeararaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaeraaaaaararaeaeaaaaeaeeaeaaaaeaeeaaeaeeaaateaaeaeeerereaareeraeeaeaeereaaeearaeeeaaeeeeaaaraereeeeeraraearreaaaau THE AR OW OF PI BETA P s' MAY, 1949 VOLUME 65 NUMBER 4 Editorials Of Extension An interesting phase of fraternity life today is the increasing attention being given to the subject of extension. Even fraternities, both men's and women's, hitherto ultra conservative in adding to their chapter rolls, are working in this field. Literally dozens of excellent opportunities for entering campuses old and new are presenting themselves, and many chapters are being founded; whether this is done by taking local groups or by colonization, fine members are being added to many fraternities. From this movement much good may come, with results which lead beyond the actual confines of the new chapters themselves, with all they mean of friendship and excellent influence for finer living standards. With each group is added not only the local strength of the active members and of the many alumn2e initiated, but from the public relations angle, every chapter added means an ever-growing circle of interest in and knowledge of the fraternity here is potentiality for good, new channels for making friends who will help counteract some of the bad publicity which has for years plagued the lives of fraternity officers. Here are new friends who can speak from personal experience in praise of college chapters and the fine young students in them whose quality out-weighs the unwise acts of the few, acts vicious at their worst, silly at the best. Here will be people who will say, "No, those stories cannot all be true---I know so many splendid fraternity members !" By making the most of such channels for new chapters as we are offered in the case of our colony at Alabama, and by possible new groups in California and elsewhere, we are taking a wise, forward-looking step along the road of maintaining present strength and guaranteeing the permanence of that strength. And besides, think of the joy to be found in those new groups ! Let's work to establish our new chapters, and to support them after they are installed. Through Bonds of Wine and Blue This year there came to our desk a copy of a speech made last year at the Initiation Banquet of Michigan B, by Margaret Martindale Griffith, Michigan B. We liked it so much that we yield some of our space here to extracts from it, only regretting that space forbids the use of it all. Speaking to new Pi Phis, Mrs. Griffith says, "Advantages are often accompanied by some opposition. One of your greatest responsibilities now will be to prove that women `tagged' by the selective methods in Panhellenic, are democratic. Each year you will be asked to help devise more modern and less hurtful approaches to rushing periods, and IN ORDER TO PRESERVE OUR GREEK LETTER HOMES, give it your best collective thinking. It will amaze you, when you are out of college and in your respective communities, to hear women going around getting paid for expressing thoughts about `selfish, undemocratic snobs these fraternity women are.' You will practice the poem `Outwitted' because in spite of your selectiveness, the situation is rather diabolically opposite from campus life in modern, industrial cities, Panhellenic women are distinctly minority. You recall the poem: "He drew a circle that let me out, Heretic, rebel, a thing to flout, But love and I had the wit to win WE drew a circle that let him IN. "And you will smile because you perhaps never classified yourself in that category. And you will also smile because your Pi Phi years prepared you for the responsibilities ahead. You will work together now to be prepared to go home and take your part on the Community Chest, Red 381 </p>
      <pb ref="arr6540381_0002" seq="02" n="384-385  "/>
       <p>\k~~""... f z a Dr. Allen Eaton Summer Workshop 1.948 OW TIME flies! And Ruth, Dyer, our Settle ment School Director, is more convinced of this than any Pi Phi working for or with Little Pigeon. September finds our Pi Beta Phi school buildings all set for the nine months school program. Then it's a running race with the required study courses, athletics, music, dramatics, craft-work, health program, Parent-Teachers Association, parties, holiday festivities to the graduation of another senior class. June finds Ruth and her faithful helpers transforming the elementary school building into the unbelievably livable dormitory again. The High School building becomes a building of work-rooms with screens, paints, stencils, yardage in the textile decoration room; unusual and carefully planned exhibitions of all hand-crafts in Mr. Eaton's lecture room; rows of looms set up for the weavers and rug-makers in the two largest rooms of the High School building; and the Voorhees building is made ready for the metal-crafters and jewelry-makers. The Pi Phi Settlement School again becomes a_ center for graduate, under-graduate or just-forfun study of the handicrafts for the six weeks Pi Beta Phi-University of Tennessee Work-shop. The 1948 Summer Workshop proved to be the most successful in all ways. It has now moved well beyond the experimental period showing a combined enrollment of 108 students for the two three-week (or six-week) sessions. Thirty states were represented and the quality and beauty of the work presented at the two open-house parties far surpassed that presented in the three previous summers. In the textile room (interior decoration or applied art as applied to textiles) the display included striking examples of batik work, stencils, and silk screen designs on materials of all kinds. The weaving classes exhibited examples of be-ginning and advanced weaving and rug-weaving. The weaving and rug-making and textile decoration were done under the guidance of Ingeborg Longbers, one of the founders of the famous Saterglantan weaving school in Sweden ; Mary Elizabeth Starr Sullivan, Washington Alpha Pi Phi, formerly of the University of Washington; 'and Jane Glass, assistant professor of craft design of the University of Tennessee. In the Voorhees building, under the direction of Miss Marion Heard, associate professor of Craft design, rural arts, and agricultural extension service of the University of Tennessee, the craftsmen turned out leather belts, bill-folds,and purses of superlative quality. The metal workers exhibited trays of all sizes, aluminum and copper bowls. There were silver rings, bracelets, pins and necklaces. And stunning buttons, ash-trays, pins, buckles and clips made of enamel on a copper base represented part -of the metal workers summer out-put. The students in the last Summer Workshop came from diversified professions: 36 teachers, 2 graduate assistants, 3 high school students, 6 housewives, 9 home demonstration agents, 2 craftsmen, 9 college students, 1 Red Cross worker, 3 occupational therapists, 1 librarian, 1 weaving designer, 1 sorority house-mother, 1 retired business man, 1 nurse and 1 companion. The studentshad competent assistance and were given ample freedom and time to create their own designs and finish their own articles. Even after dinner on the warm summer nights, lights were blazing in the school buildings and the noise of the hammers and the thuds of the beaters on the looms could be heard as the student craftsmen worked to complete their handiwork. The three occupational therapists took one warp and designed as many articles as they could which would answer hospital problems. The articles were interesting to make, colorful, inexpensive and required a short time for completion. Hannah Norwood, aged 16, came from Columbia, South Carolina, for weaving instruction. She and her mother weave professionally and Hannah, who joined the Handicraft Guild at age 15, plans to go to Sweden for advanced study when she finishes school. A Mr. and Mrs. Pease from Fort Lauderdale, Florida, joined the student group last summer after doing handiwork at Penland for three summers. After Mr. Pease retired from business, the Peases built a cabin near Gatlinburg in 1940 for summer living. So Mrs. Pease was busily making rugs for the cabin while Mr. Pease was making aluminum bowls and plates for their own use as well as two very decorative clips for Mrs. Pease. Huey Dell Mercier, ,a blind girl from Hazelhurst, Mississippi, was a student this summer. She learned to do simple weaving in the six-weeks session and planned to teach weaving in the school for the blind in Mississippi. Huey Dell lived in the dormitory and said, "I couldn't have had more fun or have wanted a better place to live." As this ARROW goes to press plans have been 385 </p>
      <pb ref="arr6540381_0003" seq="03" n="386-387  "/>
       <p>386 THE MAY ARROW made for an even finer summer Workshop for the 1949 summer. Workshop will open June 13th and close July 20th and students may register for the entire six weeks or for the first or second three weeks. Last November Ruth Barrett Smith (our Settlement School Chairman) went to Gatlin-burg and met with Ruth Dyer (Director of the Settlement School), Esther Mines (assistant to our Director), Jessie Harris (Vice-Dean of Home Economics of the University of Tennessee), Henrietta Sivyer (Head of the Department of Related Arts of the University of Tennessee), Ruth Buckley (Head of Department of Foods and Institution Management of the University of Tennessee) , and Marion Heard (Associate Professor of Related Art and Director of our Summer Workshop). Every-thing for the Summer Workshop was mapped out at this meeting and plans have matured during the winter months through much correspondence. Dr. Allan Eaton, outstanding authority on the crafts, will again lecture on aesthetic appreciation of crafts as well as the historic back-ground of crafts. Miss Marion Heard will continue to serve as Director of the Workshop and resume her place as instructor of beginning and advanced jewelry. Mr. Lynn Alexander, Head of Applied Art at the University of Oregon, is to head our weaving department for the summer. Miss Berta Frey of New York City will teach special weaving problems. Miss Harriet Adams, Assistant Professor of Applied Design from Iowa State College, will teach metal and recreational Crafts. Miss Helen Watson from the University of Tennessee will have charge of Community and Camp Leadership. Two new crafts have been added to our list: pottery will be taught by Mrs. Ken Mc-Donald of Gatlinburg, and a course in wood-working will be offered by Miss Ruth Transgrud of Cedar Rapids, Iowa. Pollard will again be transformed into dining-rooms and three institutional management majors will have charge of the preparation and serving of the meals. Pi Phis, actives and alumni, we of the Settlement School Committee urge you to follow the growth and development of the Summer Workshop as you have followed the growth and development of the Settlement School pro-gram through the years. Among the students last summer, there were 3 Pi Phi actives and one Pi Phi pledge, a Pi Phi daughter and a Pi Phi chaperon. Nancy Alexander, one of the graduate assistants, was also a Pi Phi from Iowa Gamma. When the Committee asked Nancy to return to the Workshop this coming summer, she wrote that since she plans to be married this June, she can't join our staff again. Nancy wrote: "If it were at all possible I would certainly enjoy returning to the Workshop in 1949. I had a most interesting and enjoyable time last summer. No one could ask for nicer people to work with. I certainly think Pi Phis are to be congratulated on their wonderful staff, both in the school and in the Workshop. Every minute was fun. "My one consolation is not being able to take the position is that some other active or young alumna will have the opportunity to see and know the Settlement School. There will then be another Pi Phi who will realize so much more clearly just what we are doing in Tennessee. "It's really too bad that each and every Pi Phi can't visit the school and Workshop. I was both humble and proud to be a member of the organization that has done so much and has come to mean so much to the people of Gatlin-burg." Mrs. Newman Sheets (Shirley de Spain), Colorado B, was soloist at the National X Convention in Seattle last August. Her husband was a national officer of the fraternity. Mrs. Charles W. Sitler (lone Goodnight), Colorado B, is in Madrid, Spain, where her husband is a labor attache in the State Department. Mrs. Frank J. Henry (Hilda Beggs, Colorado B and Maryland A), mother of Atlanta Alumnx Club president, Mrs. E. P. Granberry (Dor-othy Henry, North Carolina B), is Georgia State Chairman of United Nations Program for League of Women Voters. Mrs. Henry was sent to Lake Success in February to sit in on the United Nations meetings now in progress. Mrs. Henry gave a most interesting description of Lake Success and the meetings attended while there, at the February meeting of the Atlanta Alumnae Club, giving a fine inside view of the many goals which representatives from all over the world are endeavoring to achieve. Pi Beta Pai Mothers' Clubs By MARIE BACON HAGEE, Missouri B, Director of Extension NOT EVERY Pi Phi Chapter has a Mothers' Club, but how lucky are those which have! To receive help with their rush parties, in refurnishing their room or house, or in getting the luxuries which their budget just can-not provide this seems heavenly to the' chapters who are wholly on their own. While it is true that some clubs have started simply be-cause the mothers desired to know each other better, usually they have been organized in order to aid in some way the chapter to which the daughters belong. As the clubs vary in size and type, so does the help which they give. Some clubs are small, some are large; some never fail to get together each month, while others with many non-resident members find that it is possible to meet only. at the annual mothers and daughters luncheon. The few members of the small club may find all they can do is to prepare and serve the food at rush parties, while the large ones with too many members to meet comfortably in homes can raise astronomical amounts to buy amazing gifts for the chapter. And, perhaps because chapter memory is so short, the girls seem perpetually to be surprised at getting any help at all. Since gifts are not acquired by wishes alone, most clubs have to struggle with projects to raise money. These are varied and follow the same lines as do those of alumnae clubs rummage sales, style shows, Arrowcraft sales, bridge parties, lending libraries, bake sales, and re-selling of clothes. It is difficult to tell inquiring clubs how to organize, because only they them-selves can know how many officers they need, how often it is wise to meet, and what type of program will attract a large attendance. Usuallya successful club will evolve gradually a plan which fits its needs but which can be changed when necessary. Like all other groups, Mothers' Clubs have their problems, and perhaps for most of them membership ranks first. For many it is a question of how to attract new mothers and hold their interest, but just as troubling for others is the necessity of tactfully confining member-ship to the mothers of actives and pledges only, because of the difficulty of finding houses large enough to hold meetings. Programs which appeal to all are sometimes difficult to find, but usually this is no great problem. It is far-sighted to ask sometime during the year one of the deans or professors to tell of college policies and trends. Such a talk is informative and, if the choice of speaker a wise one, very enjoy-able. There is no attempt to require reports from the clubs, but each year an informal letter is sent out to them by the Director of Extension (their contact member on Grand Council) giving news of the fraternity, and restating some of its aims. In this letter there is always a hope-fully voiced hint that a reply from the clubs with a list of incoming officers for the next year would be appreciated, and it is encouraging that more and more clubs do answer with pleasant, chatty letters. As always when writing or thinking about Mothers' Clubs, I come back to that intangible but greatest of all their help the interest and affection which need not even be expressed to be felt by the chapter, but the warmth of which carries many through a difficult time. Would that every chapter .had a Mothers' Club! ----- Ruth Barrett Smith Scholarship given by the alumnae organization in accordance with the action of the last Convention, has been awarded to Peggy Baker, Kansas A. Applications for next year's scholarship should have been sent before May 1, 1949, to Mrs. Wild. 387 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



