<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr6610059_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Settlement School Reports</title>
                        <author><name>Smith, Ruth Barrett</name></author>
                        <author><name>Dyer, Ruth </name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>September 1949</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr6610059_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">September 1949</date>, Settlement School Reports</title>
                        <author><name>Smith, Ruth Barrett</name></author>
                        <author><name>Dyer, Ruth </name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 58-73</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">40</note>
                        <note type="Folder">2</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 66, Number 1 (September 1949), Pages 58-73.</note>
			<note type="document">arr6610059_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Report of Chairman of the Settlement School Committee 1949; Report of the Director of the Settlement School 1949; Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, Report on Audit, Year Ended June 30, 1949</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Changing Mission of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity for Women in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1944-1964</item>
                                <item>Budget</item>
                                <item>Education</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>
                                <item>Heath care</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr6610059_0001" seq="01" n="58-59  "/>
       <p>Settlement School Reports REPORT OF CHAIRMAN OF THE SETTLEMENT SCHOOL COMMITTEE 1949 LOVE the Smokies. Misty blue-ness, wooded slopes, wealth of flower and shrub, steep heights and sun-lit coves. The sheer breath-catching beauty of far horizons, melting into veiled sky tints, the contrast of cloud shadows on sunny hills; the strength and vigor of mountain winds, the rushing. torrent of running water; bird songs and the cry of the hounds racing fox. "I love the invigorating scent of dim pine woods, and spongy spring of dried needles underfoot; the pungent, hungry smell of wood smoke; the busy hum and the odor of a wood-crafters shop; the rhythmic thump of the loom, and the singing of the spinning wheel. "Time stands still, for though the days come and go, the sun shines and the rains fall; the mountains are ageless re-creating ever and again, their serene majesty." The Pi Phis who first saw this picture, beautifully described above by our Marjorie Chalmers, R.N., must have acquired therefrom the strength which persuaded Pi Beta Phi that in this majestic setting was the right place for a living memorial to the Founders living in its service for the Education and Health of a small section of early America, Gatlinburg, Tennessee. For the first time in many years at least, the Settlement School Committee has just concluded an annual meeting in May; we were privileged to see Gatlinburg and our School under normal conditions, the town without the influx of summer tourists to the Park and the school itself in regular session. Each has come away firmly convinced of the wisdom of the original choice of location and of the continued need for us there. Pi Beta Phi's service in Gatlinburg covers a wide and diversified field and the passage of time widens rather than narrows its scope. First, our new Health Center in its first year has proved to be worthily "dedicated to the service of mankind." There, with up to date equipment and proper space, preventive and corrective measures aiming toward, better health for young and old are possible. This past year a pre-school Round-up was first to take advantage of the new quarters when one of the local doctors and one of the dentists gave a day of their time to free examinations. Later in the year the State Department of Public Health's X-Ray Mobile Unit processed 567 persons over fifteen years of age in one day. This number equalled that of the preceding year when the unit had remained two days. Three women are now hospitalized for treatment of primary tuberculosis, one with six children whose welfare had to be carefully considered first. The State Department of Health also sent specialists for Dental and Nutritional Clinics. In addition to our own children, where some had their teeth cleaned each day, ten from one of the rural schools walked four miles into town for their check-up. Pi Beta Phi is particularly grateful to the Sigma Phi Gamma chapters who have so generously sent checks to assist us in dental correction and for badly needed eye attention. The little babies are always with us or about tobe ! While most deliveries are now made in the hospitals, the Health Center does much toward Pre-Natal care and the emergency arrivals. There were three premature babies this year, two of them twins weighing 3 and 3 pounds, respectively. All three are living though the twins, born in a drafty house in December barely pulled through pneumonia after hospitalization. At the school, besides the general run of cuts, bruises, and breaks, our "Marjorie" has given health talks and picture shows and various demonstrations. Sixteen High School girls under her tutelage passed the Home Nursing Course. Her service and what it means was best expressed in a note from a fifth grader: "Dear Miss Chalmers Thanks to you we will have a Merry Christmas and not be sick in bed, so a Merry Christmas to you." The pattern of our Health Center is indeed worth-while. Under the able direction of Ethel Snow on Sales and Mrs. McMorran on Designing, with weaving supervision, Arrowcraft has had another fine year. On May 1, 14 clubs had already sold over $1000 worth of Arrowcraft products; two, Peoria, Illinois and Albuquerque, New Mexico over $1500; Houston, Texas and Sacramento, California, over $2000, while Champaign, Illinois headed the list with $2500. Perhaps a word of explanation is due those clubs which do not always secure all articles ordered in the quantity they would wish; the Director of Arrowcraft is not wholly responsible. Already boxes and shelves are filled with finished weaving, ready for the fall ship-ping, though it is difficult to know what the orders will be. The running inventory is always high, both on the finished product and the weaving supplies. From the standpoint of the auditor and of insurance, this is a matter to question. Therefore, if at times, Arrowcraft is short of a particular article, it may be because they must hold a lower inventory on that article in order to increase production in another, likewise in demand by the purchasing public. It is nice to hear, "The designs are prettier than ever," while we still may retain some of the familiar pat-terns, so well liked. One of our greatest services in Gatlinburg is made possible through your Arrowcraft sales, for thus so many weavers benefit. Through the winter they work full speed but ease off at planting and canning time or when they can secure the extra tourist employment. It is surprising that sometimes these weavers, living far away, see only the pattern on which they themselves weave. At the spring weavers' party, Mrs. McMorran arranged a display of all things woven for Arrowcraft as well as those articles which the high school girls had woven in their class; the weavers truly appreciated this chance to see others' work. A nice recognition has come to Mrs. McMorran in that she has been asked to serve as one of two weaving teachers for the two week Workshop to be conducted this fall by the Southern Highlands Guild at the Penland School (North Carolina) . At the Pi Beta Phi School, the County continues to supply the faculty for teaching the basic subjects but as yet is unable, without our aid, to offer all the courses which would make the school fully accredited. 58 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 59 The universal problem of teacher-shortage is also evident but the staff has been at a high teaching level. All in the high school were college graduates, three with Master's degrees. The teaching experience varied from one teaching for the first time to another completing his forty-eighth year, this by special permit from the State. As Physical Education and Health Instructor, Mr. J. B. Johnson made his usual fine contribution to the academic program. In addition to a successful coaching season in basketball, he assumed many other responsibilities which added to the general well-being at school. He assisted Mr. Grim, new as principal, in his duties. He and Esther Mines took on the co-sponsorship of the Senior class and carried it through to a successful graduation; Mr. Johnson also took the class on its senior trip to Williamsburg, Jamestown, Yorktown and Virginia Beach, an outing, educational as well as pleasurable. It is with regret that we must accept Mr. Johnson's resignation. We would dislike losing his services alone but he will take with him as his wife, Esther Mines, the Assistant to the Director. He tells us that he owes much to Pi Beta Phi and we think he does, as we have observed the many fine attributes of the prize he is taking from us. Mrs. Alethea Armstrong has again contributed much in handling the music in the schools; she has taught music to the ten elementary grades, trained an elementary chorus and a High School glee club ; has provided the music for the High School assemblies and for the meetings of many civic organizations. The youngsters have become familiar with the negro spirituals, with the folk-songs and ballads of early day, and with the lives of the great musicians. The youngest have learned the use of the rhythm band instruments while the fifth graders have attained knowledge of part singing and note reading, with special emphasis on tone color. At Christmas time a Nativity play was given which introduced both ancient and rare carols. Those of you at the 1948 Convention who heard the sweet clear voices on the Settlement School program will be interested that Barbara Steele and Paul Clabo took the parts of "Mary" and the littlest Shepherd in this production. Two operettas were given as the year progressed, one of which the Committee had the privilege of seeing and hearing. As we observed the proud parents or other kin-folk watching the thespian grace of their favorites on stage, we thought to ourselves how very much Pi Beta Phi had contributed to the evening; with Mrs. Armstrong directing, other responsibilities such as stage sets, make-up, the accompanying, the publicity, even the lock-up duties were all handled by those whom Pi Beta Phi arranged to help the school program. New in the Arts and Crafts position this year Fay Van Roekel of Iowa has brought both training and talent to her classes together with an interest in all other phases of the school and community life. Her high school classes were taught Designing, Lettering, Sketching, Metal Work, Pottery and Weaving in sufficient amounts to acquire a working knowledge of them and an appreciation for Art as well. Work with the elementary grades was done in their rooms for the most part though a special after-school class was formed for those particularly interested or talented in the sixth, seventh and eighth grades. Regular classes worked on murals for their rooms, sketching, toy-making, finger painting and in clay while the special group could do that in which they had the greatest interest. Two special recognitions came to Miss Van Roekel this year, her first in teaching. By submitting samples of her own work and passing their Board of Review she became a member of the Southern Highlands Handicraft Guild. In January she was selected as one of fifteen from near-by states to receive a scholar-ship to a Workshop in Metals offered for two weeks by the University of Tennessee. The boys of the high school were given wood-working under Major Huskey, a young man from one of the shops near-by, who gave us part of his time. Small tables and book-cases were the popular articles made. The County Superintendent felt this a most practical offering by Pi Phi for a school elective since so many near-by wood-working shops could provide employment after graduation. As mentioned above, the County still does not seem able to assume full financial responsibility for its school in Gatlinburg. Its inability was again demonstrated this spring when after two years of seeking a school site for new buildings and an athletic field, it again turned to Pi Beta Phi. The only available acreage was finally appraised by a Board of Vue appointed by the Court at the figure of $8000 an acre, a prohibitive sum. The County Board of Education came to Miss Dyer, hoping that the offer made by the fraternity two years ago (See 1948 Information ARROW, Page 94.) or some similar one might be worked out. Miss Onken went to Gatlinburg and ably conferred with the County Superintendent, the School Board, and representatives of the various civic organizations. While she could make no renewal of previous Council or Committee commitments since there had been changes of personnel in both groups, she expressed a willingness to consult and to ascertain present feelings. Meantime each representative would confer with its own group for an opinion on whether it wished its school to remain in its present approximate location. The outcome was that all Gatlinburg organizations voted that plans go forward which would tie the school up with Pi Beta Phi permanently. Though still in negotiation it is probable that the County will be deeded the same 1.8 acres previously offered and that the fraternity will lease sufficient other land for playground purposes on a fity year (renewable) basis, together with leases as at present on the school buildings. The County will endeavor to purchase some property adjacent to the lot they now own, which is also next to the Settlement School property. The first six room unit of a modern grade school building would be started as soon as negotiations are satisfactorily completed. Changes in the school buildings have included an added recitation room in the High School building made possible by vacating the old Ag. shop, recently used for storage purposes. A group of mothers placed neon lights in one recitation room and Pi Beta Phi has just provided neon lights in those rooms which will be occupied by the weavers during the Summer Workshop. While the Committee enjoyed the privilege of meeting during the regular school year, we would also like to return for a glimpse of the Summer Workshop. This is no longer the trial balloon of four years ago sent up by the University of Tennessee and Pi Beta Phi, but a school of merit for six weeks of fun and/or credit. This year finds increased enrollment with representatives from many different states. The staff is outstanding, each in his own line, and is headed by Miss Marian Heard of U.T. and Miss Ruth Dyer of the Pi Beta Phi School </p>
      <pb ref="arr6610059_0002" seq="02" n="60-61  "/>
       <p>60 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW as Directors. The one hurdle still to overcome is an adequate housing plan. All seem to want both room and board right at the School. Some day their dream and ours may be realized. Last summer the first Craftsman's Fair, with over 6000 registered from 45 states and 8 foreign countries, held on the Pi Phi Green was so successful it is to be repeated again this summer in more pretentious fashion. The Governor of Tennessee will open the Fair and has invited four other Governors of the other near-by states where handicrafts are important to the economics of the area. This is a tremendous undertaking for the Southern Highlands Guild but the outstanding display of the crafts of that area brings splendid publicity. Pi Beta Phi is happy to have had a share in it. No two days are ever alike for our all-year staff, save that all are busy ones. There is, of course, the usual consultation over the running of the place as such and the daily over-sight of school routine by Miss Dyer; there are the community contacts to be maintained. The Pi Phi and other visitors are an entertaining break in the routine. This year there have been a number of foreign visitors sent as Fellows through the United Nations, to whom we have been hostess. Three were from China and so very much interested both in the Child Welfare and the Crafts, it was a joy to offer them Gatlinburg's best. One said, "How peaceful here in your valley !" which can readily be understood when one thinks to what these young women must return in Shanghai or Nanking, today. India and Uruguay have also provided visitors. If the length of stay permitted, these spoke to the school. For city school children this might not be unusual but to Gatlinburg it was an educational opportunity for the children to learn some of the customs of other countries. Esther Mines, as Assistant to the Director, has, in addition to the regular duties of her office, done all the accompanying for the musical programs and assemblies at school; directed the living of the dormitory girls at Stuart Cottage; sponsored the girls of the Beta club, national scholastic honorary, and has served as a co-sponsor of the 1949 class. Pi Beta Phi wishes her all happiness in her new home though it is with regret that we accept her resignation. The position of Assistant to the Director will be taken by Nancy R. Holmes, Illinois Zeta, but recently President of her chapter and in other respects, well qualified. Mr. Johnson's successor will be William J. Miracle of Oak Ridge, Tennessee, just graduated from the University of Tennessee and highly recommended by its Physical Education Department. We welcome both to our staff. As always the School is grateful for the special gifts which come each year in addition to the regular contributions from clubs and chapters. There have been wonderful books (small encyclopedias or text books) for both the elementary and high school libraries and one hundred dollars to be used for new shelves in the library. At Christmas time there were sufficient toys for each child in the first five grades (243) to have a small gift; for each room a special gift of athletic equipment or a particular book. The best books were placed in one or the other of the two libraries for all to enjoy. Boxes for six needy families were filled and even the heart's desire of one first grader could be gratified her very first doll. This coming Christmas we hope to distribute to the youngest children of the more isolated rural schools also. The real recompense for your generosity would be seeing the eyes of the youngsters as they accept their gifts but instead, here is the appreciation of a grateful Committee. An officer this year suggested that all fraternity reports be more factual. For this type of information, read the accounting audit in the Information ARROW. This message brings only an accounting of actual events, of interest to those of you who believe in the Settlement School and its reasons for being. We do appreciate all your splendid contributions for we know the real effort which always must go into the raising of funds. However, there is so much that could be accomplished toward a better Settlement School program, we cannot but ask for increased support next year. This report could not be rightly concluded with-out an expression ,of grateful appreciation to a wonderful committee. No task seemed too great though each member has carried heavy responsibilities of her own. The fraternity is indeed fortunate when busy people can find time to do volunteer work well in Pi Beta Phi. Again, gratitude is expressed to Miss Onken, the contact member from Grand Council, whose schedule is never too crowded to write a prompt reply on all discussion topics. Your Chairman appreciates the opportunity of working for Pi Beta Phi through serving the Settlement School. Respectfully submitted, RUTH BARRETT SMITH REPORT OF THE DIRECTOR OF THE SETTLEMENT SCHOOL 1949 somE of the older Pi Phis who made Settlement School visits in the early days should return to Gatlinburg I am sure that they could appreciate a newspaper quip that stated America is the land where in one generation you can go from a plain cabin to a cabin plane. We still have the "plain cabins" in the surrounding area but this particular corner of East Tennessee shows many evidences of the "cabin plane" era. Our once isolated village now has six hotels, two lodges, and fifty tourist courts. All up and down the street are eating houses, craft shops, and other attractions that pertain to the tourist trade. Since the opening of The Great Smoky Mountain National Park, located right at the end of our main street, the population of Gatlinburg has increased from 1700 to an estimated 2400 people exclusive ofthe tourists. This is a gain of more than 41 per cent. This growth has been so rapid that it has been difficult for the village to adjust to changed conditions. There is so much to be done in the way of public services such as sanitation, paving, street lighting etc., that the Fraternity is still needed though our help may be supplied in ways differing from those used when we too lived in a plain cabin, helping a backward people to enrich their lives. Community The most important thing that has happened in the village is that the water system is actually being built. An election in October 1948 authorized the sale of bonds, the contract was let in November 1948, and construction started in February of 1949. This THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 61 contract was for $480,925.00 and is to be completed in 500 days. The source is water from the Little Pigeon river and settling basins and other necessary installations are being made on land adjacent to the Park. Other important improvements include a lot of work that has been done on Baskins Creek Road which has been widened and improved with a hard surface. The dust on this road has been a positive menace for a number of years. A campaign of city wide spraying to kill insect pests has met with quite general co-operation on the part of the public. The County Sanitation officer and local committees have worked on this project. An addition to the Roaring Fork section of the village is the new Baptist Church built of native stone with wooden interior. The grounds about the Methodist Church have been beautifully landscaped and the interior is to be finished this year. A number of fine new residences have been built. Some new cabins, a swimming pool, and a drive-in restaurant will cater to the tourist trade. Just below us on the Squire's property a man from Newport is building a large movie house to seat 1012 people. Union services were held by several of the churches at Thanksgiving, Christmas, and Easter. The usual fund-raising patty for the Library was held on Valentine's Day at the Mountain View. Drives for the Red Cross, Polio, and Cancer Funds were all given local support. The children were entertained at the annual Easter egg hunt on the Whittle lawn and a sunrise service on the green of the Greystone hotel was an innovation of this year. The living Christmas tree in front of the Arrowcraft Shop was lighted during the holiday season through the efforts of the Garden Club. An office for the Gatlinburg Tourist Bureau was maintained for nine months. This has been a valuable thing for the town in that it serves as a clearing house for reservations from all the Motor Clubs in the Country and for individuals as well. When this service was first started, Knoxville supplied fifty per cent of the funds necessary for its operation, the next year one third of the amount and last year only a very small per cent. School Under Tennessee statutes we were entitled to an extra high school teacher this year, for we had in-creased enrollment over the year before. Mr. Mark Grim has served as Principal and has taught classes in Social Science and given one class in Spanish. This was a good addition to our rather limited curriculum. Mrs. Ann Lighter again had charge of the library and taught most of the English classes. Mr. Willard Conchin, who is the minister of the Christian Church in Sevierville, took the rest of the English work and taught History. Mrs. Ruth Owenby held her old position as teacher of Biology and Mathematics. Miss Ethel Womac was the Home Economics teacher. We have had difficulty all year with the other Science and Math position for it seemed impossible to secure a qualified teacher. Mr. Plez Atchley, a retired teacher from Sevierville, has done most of the teaching but many substitutes have had to be used. The special teachers supplied by the Fraternity, Mr. J. B. Johnson in. Physical Education, Fay Van Roekel and Major Huskey in Arts and Crafts, and Mrs. Armstrong in Music have all helped with the high school program. With the extra teacher we were faced with the problem of more classroom space. This was solved by the County fixing up the old ag room that we had used for storage into a classroom. This is a very unsatisfactory arrangement as the students have to use aback entrance and go outside the building in all sorts of weather to reach the room. This situation will be much improved when a new grade school building has been built by the County and the five grade school rooms now taking space in the high school building are moved to the new building. The students have been kept busy with their studies and the extra curricular activities such as their basket ball games, field day for sports, the Halloween Carnival, class plays well given by the Junior and Senior classes, Assembly programs and various parties and entertainments. Two very lovely banquets were high lights of the year. One was the basketball banquet given by the American Legion Auxiliary and the other was the annual affair given by the juniors in honor of the seniors. This year we have co-operated with the University of Tennessee in their teacher training work in Home Economics. For three different months we had two student teachers working in our department. Future Home Makers of America, the Home Economics Club, participated in the national project of Christmas gifts for overseas, making some of their gifts. They took part in a small radio skit over a Knoxville station and in a regional style show where they modeled garments they had made. A lovely tea was given in May with Mothers, faculty and friends as guests. Historic Williamsburg was chosen by the senior class of twenty as the destination of their class trip. The usual commencement events finished up the school year. In the Elementary School there were twenty-nine who graduated from the eighth grade and will be entering high school next fall. The five teachers in the small building have had an especially well organized unit and the work has gone on with almost no friction and with excellent results. Pi Phi Contributions With Sevier County now supplying the basic instruction in the schools the Fraternity has made its contribution to the curriculum by providing some very important extras such as Arts and Crafts, Music, and Physical Education. Our full time Arts and Crafts teacher is Fay Van Roekel, a 1948 graduate of Iowa State College, and the part time wood-working teacher, Major Huskey, is from a local family who operate the Jack Knife Shop. Fay is talented and has brought much enthusiasm to her work. She has been generous with her time in helping with all phases of school work. Under her direction many posters for plays and other events, stage settings, properties and costumes have all been worked out by her classes. Her high school class of girls learned to weave and following lessons in design used the designs they had made to block print curtains for the craft shop. She has held a special class for upper grade school students who are especially interested in art on two afternoons a week, after school hours. These children work on different projects that especially appeal to them. Some of the grades have made murals for their rooms, done sketching and figure drawing, a little work with clay and produce some clever toys from different sized cardboard boxes. Fay was honored by being given a scholarship to a Workshop in Metals which was held at the University of Tennessee for two weeks. She submitted samples of her work and was made a member of the Southern Highland Handicraft Guild. She also gave some lectures and demon.-stations in Camp Crafts at the Training School for Camp Leaders held at the Methodist Assembly Grounds in April. Major Huskey started his work three weeks late in the fall. His high school boys have made some very creditable looking small pieces </p>
      <pb ref="arr6610059_0003" seq="03" n="62-63  "/>
       <p>62 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW of furniture and have learned the use of the different machines we provide in the shop. There are a number of wood-working shops in town and a knowledge of this craft often leads to a good job. Mrs. Aletha Armstrong has again directed the work in Music. The special programs given by her department have all been well done. The Christmas program was in the nature of a Nativity Play that was beautifully done in the true spirit of the season. Two of the main parts were taken by the children who delighted Convention with their singing at French Lick. Two operettas were given this year in-stead of the usual one. The first one was "Hansel and Gretel." This was produced by a very youthful cast of children, mostly from the third grade. Later in the year a second operetta. "In Old Mexico," was given by the children of the five upper grades in the Elementary School. Both entertainments packed the gym with enthusiastic audiences of fond parents, small brothers and sisters and others who enjoyed the gay songs and dances. Children love "to be in things" and their parents love to see them perform. The Physical Education program has been very capably handled by Mr. J. B. Johnson. He coached the boys' and girls' basket ball teams through successful seasons again this year. In addition to these duties and his classes in Physical Education he has served as Co-sponsor of the Senior Class and has helped with most everything that has gone on at the school. His influence for fair play and sportsmanship in athletics, his unselfish interest in the students and willingness to accept extra duties will be missed next year. Though he announced at Convention that he was a bachelor, he is soon to become a benedict. He and Esther Mines plan to be married this summer and will live on the west coast. The school will greatly miss Esther too for she has been very helpful with her musical talents, playing for all the weekly chapel programs and doing the accompanying for Mrs. Armstrong's programs. She has been sponsor for the Beta Club and devoted much time to working with its members. Other contributions by the Fraternity include the cleaning and repairing of the stage curtains and a monthly check of fifteen dollars to supplement the salary of the school bus driver. This enables him to make a daily trip to Elkmont, in the borders of the Park, to bring eighteen children down to our school. The music teacher from Pigeon Forge has given piano lessons two days a week on the piano in Stuart Cottage. P.T.A. The weekly summer bingo games sponsored by this organization netted $ 1200.00. From this fund they financed a summer recreation program for the children of the town. Our Mr. Johnson directed this activity which was held at the American Legion Field. A piano for the music room was purchased from this same fund. An additional $100.00 was made at a rummage sale and this was used for the benefit of the elementary school library. The organization again operated the school lunch room in a very efficient manner. From last years funds they were able to purchase an electric dish washer for the kitchen. The table tops were covered with new linoleum and a telephone installed in the lunch room. To children who need the service, free lunches are supplied. Most of the meetings have been held in the evenings so that the fathers might participate. Interest has been good all year. One venture proved to be a financial loss but was a worth while effort to bring some goodentertainment to the School. This was a concert given by the James King Chorus of Knoxville. Farm The year has brought two changes in helpers at the school. Elvin Trentham resigned at the end of the summer and Neal Watson replaced him as assist-ant to Arlie. Our farm man, Carl Ogle, left in Dec-ember to accept a position where he works only with poultry. He was followed by another Watson Mr, n r. Richard. We sold the Jersey herd in December, , 1948 to Mr. Murray who is the manager of the Stokely Canning Company Farms at Newport, Tennessee. Several factors led to the decision to sell the herd. The animals were no longer needed for class work in agriculture since we have not had classes in that subject for a number of years. The University required that we serve and use only pasteurized milk during the Summer Workshop and as most of the eating places in town use no raw milk it was a problem to get rid of our milk. Pasteurized milk is now brought to our door at a cheaper figure than we could produce our own supply. We will raise more garden produce, selling any surplus to the Mountain View Hotel. They now take the eggs and poultry that we do not use for the table. Health Center Three clinics made use of our improved, modern facilities in the first year of use of the new building. A Pre-School Clinic was held in August, a Dental and Nutritional one in December and the State mobile T. B. X-Ray Unit spent a day in Gatlinburg in February. At the latter clinic 587 people were given free chest x-rays and it was found that three mothers of the community had active cases of the disease. These three cases are now all under treatment. The year has been the usual busy one for Marjorie. She helped the Home Economics teachers by giving with them a class in home nursing. Fifteen high school girls completed the course and received Red Cross pins for their effort. A number of children have been helped with eye corrections and been fitted to glasses through the generosity of the local Lion's Club and the money given to our project by Sigma Phi Gamma International Sorority. This organization has helped with health improvement in the mountain areas for a number of years. We are grateful that we are included in the list of schools and centers to receive their aid. It is impossible to enumerate all the services given to the community by our Pi Phi nurse for they are many and varied. The number of office visits and home calls adds up to an imposing number yet the work goes on day after day. The Health Center building itself fits into the plan of the grounds as if it had been there for a long time, now that some plantings have been placed around it. Arrowcraft To many Pi Phis the products from our weavers are their only link with the work of the Settlement School. They are proud of the articles that carry the familiar blue tag but perhaps they do not realize the full story back of the product. The material economic aid that our checks carry to one hundred weavers means much to many a family. Our Alurnnx pub sales form a very important part of our yearly business volume. In November Mrs. Snow and the girls shipped out $32,000.00 worth of goods to the Clubs. Some Clubs have spring sales and many small orders result from these Club sales. For sale next year there will be a number of new items. White baby blankets THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 63 and carriage robes, new baby material for the caps and jackets, more designs and colors in neckties, some new bags and some bridge squares in the Queen Ann design in natural and colored threads are just a few of these items. Tina and Lura planned two very nice Weavers parties for the weavers. The annual Christmas party is always a nice affair and one held in early spring proved to be a great success. At this affair there was an exhibit of the work done by all the weavers, some done by Fay's high school class, and interesting pieces from several local weavers. Harriet Gill from the University used some of her weavings to illustrate the talk that she gave to the group. Refreshments added to the party feeling. The hotel shop has been in charge of a good Pi Phi friend, Mrs. Edna McCutchean, mother of Mrs. Jim Huff who is a Pi Phi, and of Jerry who manages the Mountain View Hotel. Since she lives in a cottage near the hotel it is convenient for her to have the shop open during the hours when the most people are in the lobby. A very special Arrowcraft order was the powder blue dress material that the Washington D.C. Alumnae Club ordered and presented as a gift to Mrs. Truman. * * * During the past year some very necessary repairsand changes have been made in our buildings. The old shed back of the high school was enclosed and re-built to serve as a shop for Arlie, give us some storage space and a garage for the truck. Rather extensive work had to be done on the barn and minor repairs on other farm buildings. We built some fence and had the electric wiring for our three residence houses changed for more efficient service. At Teachers Cottage a new linoleum was laid in one of the bath rooms and the down stairs bed room porch and half bath of the large office were repainted at the time that Marjorie moved up from the old health center. Arlie and his family now occupy this building. I wish to close by expressing my deep appreciation for the many fine gifts sent to the School by the alumnae clubs, active chapters and individuals. We of the resident staff, try to the best of our abilities to work for the ideals that prompted the founding of the school in "plain cabin days." Each year brings changes in the type of service most needed but an alert Committee keeps the school functioning in "cabin plane days." I am grateful to them for their unselfish understanding help and especially so to Esther Mines who has been such a wonderful help to me in every way. Respectfully submitted RUTH DYER, Director PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL, GATLINBURG, TENNESSEE, REPORT ON AUDIT, YEAR ENDED JUNE 30, 1949 Little Rock, Arkansas Exhibit "A" Comparative Balance Sheet July 20, 1949 Exhibit "B" Statement of Operating Income and Expense Exhibit "B-I" General and Administrative Expense Exhibit "B-2" Instructional Expense Exhibit "B-3" Settlement School Operation Expense Exhibit "C" Endowment Fund Exhibit "D" Sinking Fund and Memorial Fund Exhibit "E" Statement of Profit and Loss Arrow-As directed by your committee, we have audited craft Fiscal Year Ended May 31, 1949 the books, records and supporting data of Schedule 1 Endowment Fund Securities Schedule 2 General and Sinking Fund Securities Schedule 3 Fixed Assets and Depreciation Charges Schedule 4 Comparative Summary of Contributions Received and submit our report of this audit as contained in Schedule 5 Comparative Statements of Club and the following Exhibits, Schedules and Comments: Chapter Contributions COMMENTS SCOPE OF EXAMINATION Our examination consisted of detail check of all transactions of the records of the treasurer as maintained at Texarkana, Texas, together with an examination of all records maintained by the Director of Settlement School at Gatlinburg, Tennessee. Our audit embraced the following procedures concerning verification of the assets: Cash on Hand: Verified by count. Cash on Deposit: Verified by our examination of all bank checks together with confirmation of balances furnished by the respective depositories. Securities: General and Sinking Fund Securities were verified by our physical count. Endowment Fund Securities were verified by confirmation received from the trust agent Harris Trust Company of Chicago. Accounts Receivable: Verified by examination of records at Gatlinburg, Tennessee by internal test checking and corre spondence where necessary. Inventories: Inventories were taken, priced, and extended by the personnel of Arrowcraft and were checked by us for mathematical accuracy, and by our physical examination of the inventories in the Shop and Warehouse. Fixed Assets: These assets consisting of property, buildings, and equipment owned by Pi Beta Phi Settlement School are stated at the cost at acquisition as reflected by the books with adjustment for the year under review for additions and retirements. We made no examination of these records beyond the audit report presented for the year ended June 30, 1948. GENERAL Our audit embraced all procedures considered necessary to establish the correctness of the items presented on the Balance Sheet and the accompanying Statements of Income and Expense. For the report of the treasurer for the year ending June 30, 1949, we have adjusted for the difference in fiscal year closing of May 31st as used by the Director at Gatlinburg and at Arrowcraft. In general, we find all records to be well kept and we wish to commend to your committee, all Settlement School and Arrowcraft personnel for their diligence. Very truly %Tours, McDuFFIE-CURRY AND CO. Certified Public Accountants Settlement School Committee Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Mrs. Henry Moore jr., Treasurer Texarkana, Texas DEAR MESDAMES: PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL GATLINBURG, TENNESSEE </p>
      <pb ref="arr6610059_0004" seq="04" n="64-65  "/>
       <p>64 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW; EXHIBIT "A" PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL, GATLINBURG, TENNESSEE COMPARATIVE BALANCE SHEET JUNE 30, 1949 ASSETS Current Assets 6/30/1948 Cash Funds Imprest Cash Fund $ Treasurer's Bank Balance Operating Bank Balances Savings Accounts Balances Items in Transit 60.00 15,370.44 7,251.52 8,042.99 6/30/1949 $ 60.00 29,584.03 9,955.71 3,740.76 , 4,088.83 Total Cash Funds 30,724.95 Investments Bonds held for Endowment Fund 52,458.41 U. S. Series F Bonds 30,155.00 U. S. Series G Bonds 18,000.00 Canadian Victory Loan Bonds 150.00 Cash Held for Investment in Bonds 1,761.59 Total Investments 102,525.00 Accounts Receivable Due from Arrowcraft Accounts 18,943.25 14,840.75 Inventories Arrowcraft Shop and Factory Inventories 68,958.17 78,956.85 Total Current Assets 221,151.37 236,669,75 Fixed Assets Real Estate 5,427.35 5,427.35 Buildings and Improvements 112,187.51 112,187.51 Equipment, Fixtures and Autos 31,066.86 31,377.10 148,681.72 148,991.96 Less: Reserve for Depreciation 47,800.27 52,022.35 Total Fixed Assets 100,881.45 96,969.61 Other Assets Prepaid Insurance 2,094.85 2,094.85 TOTAL ASSETS $324,127.67 $335,734.21 LIABILITIES Current Liabilities 6/30/1948 6/30/1949 Withheld Income Taxes $ 272.50 $ 240.70 Deferred Income 1949-1950 Contributions Paid in Advance 10.00 Total Liabilities 272,50 250.70 RESERVES 54,220.00 55,692.51 Endowment Fund Created by Annually Setting Aside 75% of Active Chapter Contributions Sinking Fund Special Reserve of Surplus for Additions to Buildings and Equipment 17,906.94 19,098.63 Memorial Fund Reserve of Funds Contributed for the Purchase of Music Supplies and Equipment 178.51 279.01 Total Reserves 72,305.45 75,070.15 NET WORTH 260,413.36 General Fund Surplus 251,549.72 ANALYSIS OF SURPLUS FUND Balance June 30, 1948 $251,549.72 Net Excess Operating Revenue over Operating Expense Exhibit "B" 11,363.64 Balance June 30, 1949 262,913.36 Less: Transferred to Sinking Fund 2,500.00 $260,413.36 47,429.33 54,072.60 19,055.00 20,545.31 150.00 1,619.91 95,442.82 TOTAL LIABIIJTTES, RESERVES AND NET WORTH $324,127.67 $335 734.21 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 65 EXHIBIT .B. STATEMENT OF OPERATING INCOME AND EXPENSE YEAR ENDED JUNE 30, 1949 Total Income General $5a,9a5., Income School Summer Session 1948 4,196.18 Fuel Sold '''''''''''''''''''''''''' '''''''''''''''''''' 300.00 Hospital Revenue 280.66 Farm Produce Sales Outside .~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 2,652,16 Farm Produce Sales Internal 2,841.49 Laundry 150.31 House Student Fees 432.38 Staff Fees Guest Fees ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ ~~~~ Gifts and Sundry ' " .' 170.02 TOTAL INCOME $74,y52.4z Expense General and Administrative Exhibit "B-z^ 11,455.30 Instructional Expense Exhibit "B-2" 16,868.81 Operation Expense Exhibit "B-3" 21,984.51 Summer Session 1948 '' '' ' ' '' '' ' ' ' ' '' ' ' '' ' ' ' ' '' '' '' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' '' ' ' Advances 3,100.00 Summer Session 1949 ~.. .~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 3,615.40 Provision for Depreciation Losses on Sale of Livestock 4,222.08 184.35 TOTAL EXPENSE e1,430.45 Excess Income $12,921.96, 75% Active Chapter Contributions to Endowment Fund ' 1,558o2 Balance to General Fund Surplus 11,363.64 ~2 921 96 , EXHIBIT "B-1" GENERAL AND ADMINISTRATIVE EXPENSE YEAR ENDED JUNE 30, 1949 *Convention '' $ 665.79 *Committee Expense 1,911.08 Auditing and Legal 321.88 General Office Expense 299.72 Printing Cook Books ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' '' ' '' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' '' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' 2,500.00 Miscellaneous ~, 29.25 Publicity 149.41 Travel 268.12 Insurance .~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 2,695.08 Repairs and Replacements Donations to Churches .' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " .' " .' " .' " . ' ' ' " .' " .' ^ ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " . ' ' " . " . ' ' ' ' . ' " ' 2,414.97 200.00 $11,455.30 * Convention Expense and Committee Expense charged in this fiscal year include the expense of both the 1948 and 1949 Committee Meetings. EXHIBIT "B-2" INSTRUCTIONAL EXPENSE YEAR ENDED JUNE 30, 1949 Salaries Director Assistant $ 3,370.00 ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' '' ' ' ' 2,131.00 Physical 2,500.00 1,830.00 Weaving 225.00 Health Nurse . . . . ' 591.21 2,678.56 Arts and Crafts 2,250.00 Auto Allowance Health Nurse Arts and Crafts Supplies 400.00 School ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' '' ' ' ' ' '' ' ' '' ' ' ' ' '' ' ' ' '' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' 313.81 Administrative 129.43 "~.~_ School ~~~~.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~..~~~~ 231.95 Music Contributions Income General Alumnx Clubs Active Chapters 2,239.40 Individual 50.00 Interest Earned on Investments 1,961.37 Cook Book Sales 1,920.45 Arrowcraft Na profit ' 33,130.91 $16,868.81 </p>
      <pb ref="arr6610059_0005" seq="05" n="66-67  "/>
       <p>66 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW EXHIBIT "B-3" StTT`EMENT SCHOOL OPERATION EXPENSE YEAR ENDED JUNE 30, 1949 Facility and Maintenance Lights Car Allowance o . .. . . . . . . . . . . .. . . . . . . . . . . .. . . . . . . . . . . . . .. . . . . . . . . . . . . .. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Office Supplies -''' '''''''''''''''''''''''' ''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''.... '............ Postage ~~~~ ' ^ru= Expense 4~ .... Fuel Used 1,074.22 Hospital " .' ' ' " . ' ' ' " . ' ' ' " .' ' ' " .' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " . ' ' ' ' ' ' " . ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " . ' ' " . " 248.20 Laundry ~~~~~ ~~~ ~~~~~ ~ ~~ ~~ ~ ~ ~~ ~~ ~ ~ ~~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~ ~~ ~~ ~~ ~~ ~ ~~~ ~~ ~ ~ ~~ ~~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~ ~ ~ ~ ~~~ ~~ ~ ~ ~~~ ~~~ ~~ 18.64 8,719.84 House and Farm Expense Produce from Own Farm Used 2,841.49 Farm Supplies Purchased 3,225.92 Food Purchased 3,349.67 House Supplies and Equipment 537,09 Service and Maintenance ^ 111.74 Laundry Service 17.31 Refunds Sundry Wages . . . . ~ ~ . ~~ ~ ~ ~ 100.86 EXHIBIT "C" ENDOWMENT FUND YEAR ENDED JUNE 30, 1949 Endowment Fund June 30, 1948 Bonds and Stocks ' ' . " . " . " . " . " . " . " ." .". ".". " .". " .".". " .'.' Uninvested Principal ~~ ~~~"' ' ' ' ' " .' " .' " . ' " .' " .' " .' ' ' " .' " .' " . ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " . ~ ~Zf61.59 Receipts and Revenue .54,220.00 Interest on U. S. Bonds Interest on Industrial Bonds ..~~~...~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 1,251.50 From Income Cash Balance Reduction 19.00 2,926.32 Disbursements and Expense 1 4 8 . 3 5 Loss on Bonds Called . Adjustment of Price of U.S.G. of 1958 ~..~~~..~.~...~.~~~ ~~...~ 8.03 Remitted to Lolita H. Prouty for Settlement School 1,219.65 _ 1,453.81 BmANcE Endowment Fund June 30, 1949 $55,692.51 SUMMARY JUNE 30, 1949 Uninvested Deposit in T~~~~"~~a~~~~~~~~~'~~~~~~~'~~~'~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 1,5561.59 8.32 EXHIBIT "D" SINKING FUND JUNE 30, 1949 Balance, Sinking Fund June 30, 1948 ... . $17,906.94 Additions to Fund: By Resolution of Committee Transfer from General Fund Surplus 2,500.00 20,406.94 Disbursements Chargeable to Sinking Fund: Architects Fees "."...".'.m26.6a 1,308.31 MEMORIAL FUND Balance, Memorial Fund June 30, 1948 178.51 Additions to Fund: Memorial Contributions ' "."-".'^".".".' 100.50 Balance, Memorial Fund June 30, 1949 =~~1 NoTE: Securities and Cash for these two funds are carried with General Fund Cash and Securities. 702.29 85.66 43.01 34.57 269.08 57,146.32 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW EXHIBIT "E" STATEMENT OF PROFIT AND LOSS FISCAL YEAR ENDED MAY 31, 1949 Wholesale and Shop Sales $146,496.99 100.00% Cost of Sales 68,949.21 47.07 Gross Profit Wholesale 77,547.78 52.93 Add Profit on Supply Sales 43.35 .03 Gross Profit 77,591.13 52.96 Deduct: Commissions Allowed to Sales Agencies and Clubs 27,511.26 18.78 Realized Gross Profit 50,079.87 34.18 Expense Salaries Manager 2,735.00 1.87 Designing and Purchasing 4,267.50 2.91 Selling and Shipping 4,255.45 2.90 Office 1,783.33 1.22 Utility 609.00 .42 Supplies Selling and Shipping 984.90 .67 Insurance 800.00 .55 Convention and Travel 339,44 .23 Fuel 224.25 .15 Lights 165.84 .11 Audit 215.62 .15 Memberships and Dues 95.30 .07 Taxes and Licenses 24.50 .02 Registration of Trade Mark 108.00 .07 Miscellaneous 34.91 .02 Car Expense 76.83 .05 Truck Expense 269.25 .18 Office Expense 100.88 .07 Publicity 343.04 .23 Postage 171.44 .12 Repairs and Maintenance 283.63 .19 Telephone and Telegraph 74.66 .05 Transportation 392.94 .27 Bad Debts and Adjustments 51.49 .04 Total Expense $ 18,407.20 12.56 Net Operating Profit 31,672.67 21.62 Other Income Retail Gross Profit $2,705.63 Less: Salary Expense $1,025.00 Rent Expense 240.00 1,265.00 $ 1,440.63 .98 Purchase Discount 283.80 .19 Interest Income on Savings Accounts 79.87 .05 State of Tennessee 820.75 .55 Total Other Income $ 2,625.05 1.79 Other Expense Cash Discounts $ 13.83 Loss on Charge-Off of Truck Account (Traded in Prior Year) 752.35 $ 766.18 .52 NET INCOME $ 33,531.54 22.89 NOTE: Arrowcraft Shop books are maintained on a May 31 fiscal year basis, this being the audited statement for that fiscal year. Net income has been adjusted for the period ended June 30, 1949 for use in the preparation of the Settlement School Treasurer's report. SCHEDULE 1 SCHEDULE OF ENDOWMENT FUND SECURITIES, JUNE 30, 1949 Par Value At Cost Yield ,Loss Year Ended nded AtCall June 30, 1949 Toledo and Ohio Central R.R. Refunding "A" 31/4's of 1960 $ 1,000.00 $ 1,042.50 $ 37.50 $ Wisconsin-Michigan Power First 3's of 1978 2,000.00 2,017.50 60.00 United States of America Treasury 2's 12/15/1950-48 Called 12-15-48 19.00 77.78 ............... 1,012.60 27.50 United States of America Treasury 2%'s 6/15/1963-58 1,000.00 United States Savings Bonds Series G 21/2's 8-1-53 2,000.00 2,000.00 50.00 United States Savings Bonds Series G 21/2's 1-1-54 2,400.00 2,400.00 60.00 United States Savings Bonds Series G 21/2's 8-1-54 1,300.00 1,300.00 United States Savings Bonds Series G 23/2's 8-1-55 1,100.00 1,100.00 2372:55o United States Savings Bonds Series G 21/2's 8-1-56 3,000.00 3,000.00 75.00 .................. 3,500.00 87.50 United States Savings Bonds Series G W2's 11-1-56 3,500.00 United States Savings Bonds Series G 21/2's 7-1-57 3,000.00 43,' Pog-.o" o 75.00 United States Savings Bonds Series G 2 's 8-1-57 4,600.00 115.00 67 Percent Net Sales </p>
      <pb ref="arr6610059_0006" seq="06" n="68-69  "/>
       <p>68 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW United States Savings Bonds Series G 2 's 11-1-57 3,000.00 3,000.00 75.00 United States Savings Bonds Series G 2 's 7-1-58 6,000.00 6,000.00 150.00 United States Savings Bonds Series G 21/2's 8-1-58 1,900.00 United States Savings Bonds Series G 2Y2's 9-1-58 5,200.00 5,200.00 130.00 United States Savings Bonds Series G 2Y2's 4-1-59 '' ' '' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' '' ' ' ' ' 3,000.00 3,000.00 75.00 United States Savings Bonds Series G _ 4,700.00 117.50 United States S~~~ Bonds Series G G 216's 3-1-60 21,/2's 7-1-60 ~~b~~ ~f~~G 21.25 United States Savings Bonds Series G 2 's 12-1-60 1,900.00 L900.00 23.75 $54,072.60 $ 1,349.00 $ 77.78 Deduct Trust Agents Fee ".".".".".".".".".".".".".".".".".".".". 148.35 SCHEDULE 2 SCHEDULE OF GENERAL AND SINKING FUND SECURITIES, JUNE 30, 1949 U. S. Series "F" Savings Bonds Maturity Number Issue Date Value 25.00 25.00 100.00 100.00 100.00 25.00 25.00 25.00 100.00 100.00 100.00 1,000.00 1,000.00 25.00 100.00 100.00 500.00 1,000.00 1,000.00 1,000.00 500.00 1,000.00 1,000.00 1,000.00 5,000.00 5,000.00 1,000.00 1,000.00 1,000.00 1,000.00 1,000.00 100.00 100.00 25.00 25.00 500.00 25.00 25.00 Cash Value Carried at 6-30-1949 Cost $ 20.55 $ 18.50 20.55 18.50 82.20 74.00 82 79.70 74.00 797.00 740.00 797.00 740.00 19.92 18.50 882.20 74.00 79.70 74.00 19.92 18.50 19.92 18.50 19.92 18.50 79.70 74.00 79,70 74.00 79.70 74.00 398.50 370.00 797.00 740.00 797.00 740.00 797.00 740.00 393.00 370.00 786.00 740.00 786.00 740.00 786.00 740.00 3,930.00 3,700.00 3,930.00 3,700.00 776.00 740.00 776.00 740.00 776.00 740.00 776.00 740.00 776.00 740.00 77.60 74.00 77.60 74.00 19.40 18.50 19.40 18.50 388.00 370.00 19.17 18.50 19.17 18.50 TOTAL "F" BoNDS $25,750.00 $20,260.72 $19,055.00 U. S. Series "G" Maturity Cash Value Carried at Number Issue Date Value 6-30~949 Cost M4881896G 8-1-46 v 1,000.00 1,000.00 w 1,000.00 M4881897G 8-1-46 1,000.00 1,000.00 8-1-46 ''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''' 5,000.00 ~~~".'~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ C~G~6 l~b.00n 15,000.00 ,000.00 _ U. S. Treasury Bonds 2% Due 6-15-54 35266 6-26-44 zR3584 w 500.00 $ 509o' 189087 6-26-44 zo35w 1,000u0 1,018.17 18e088 6-26-44 nR3584 1,000.00 1,018.17 TOTAL TREASURY BONDS $ 2,500.00 $ 2,545.41 $ 2,545.41 Dominion of Canada 3% Due 3-1-54 s418741 * 50.00 $ 50o0 ~~, ... .. .. . 50.00 50.00 ~ ..................................... $ 509.07 1,018.17 1,018.17 H538105 50.00 50.00 150.00 o 50.00 50.00 50.00 ____ $ 150.00 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 69 SCHEDULE 3 FIXED ASSETS AND DEPRECIATION CHARGES JUNE 30, 1949 School Balance Additions Balance Annual 6-30-1948 During Year 6-30-1949 Depreciation Provision 5,427'35 $ Land ".".".".".".".".".".".w $ 5,427.35 $ Buildings and Improvements 1,304.99 $ $ 1,304.99 $ 39.15 Fences, Walks and Roads * Water and Sewer System 1,516.51 1,516.51 45.50 Chicken and Brooder Houses 898.75 898.75 26.96 Barn 3,384.49 3,384.49 101.54 Hospital ''''''''''''''''''''-''''''''''''''''' 2,349.05 2,349.05 70.47 Mary F.)oIlard Cottage _ 4,634.60 4,634.60 139.04 Industrial Building 25,006.57 25,006.57 500.13 Log Cabin 160.18 160.18 4.80 School House 8,027.56 8,027.56 240.83 Stuart Dormitory 9,907.81 9,907.81 297.23 Teachers Cottage 6,870.38 6,870.38 206.11 Agricultural Shop 348.93 348.93 10.47 Small Buildings. .. . 566.98 566.98 17.01 Laboratory Addition 5,685.34 5,685.34 170.56 .~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 503.32 15.10 General Improvements New Health Center 19,685.04 19,685.04 590.55 520.00 Equipment and Fixtures Industrial Building 4,252.84 4,772.84 212.64 4,649.95 4,649.95 219.46 Teachers Cottage 2,083.03 2,083.03 Mary Pollard Cottage . Stuart Dormitory ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 2,929.15 2,929.15 116.17 2,703.12 2,703.12 77.69 Hospital 1,611.00 1,611.00 Autos and Trucks 2,012.05 1,326.00 650.00 650.00 32.50 Chicken and Brooder Houses 250.00 250.00 12.50 Stoker 485.00 485.00 24.25 90.75 90.75 4.53 Movie Equipment Farm Equipment 310.15 310.15 Miscellaneous 2,375.19 264.54 2,639.7* 118.76 Health Center 1,682.29 643.19 2o25,48 93.02 26,084.52 2,753.73 28,838.25 1,116.35 Livestock and Horses 1,840.50 1,840.50 zoTAL acHmoz 124,202.87 913.23 125.116.10 *,641.78 A=owcraft 2,661.57 2,661.57 79.85 Buildings and Improvements Arts and Crafts Arrowcraft Shop ".".'.".".'.'.'.'.' 10,792.57 10,792.57 215.85 Weaving Shop 7,882.87 7,88 2.87 157.6* 21,337.01 21,337.01 453.36 Equipment and Fixtures 1,196.89 149.36 1,346.25 67.31 Arts and Crafts 3,141.84 602.99 2,538.85 126.94 TOTAL ARROWCRAFT 24,478.85 602~9 23,875.86 580a0 913.23 125,116.10 3,641.78 $ 310~4, ~48~91.96, $~~~~ SCHEDULE 4 COMPARATIVE SUMMARY OF CONTRIBUTIONS RECEIVED JUNE 30, 1949 Alumna clubs Year Ended Year Ended Year Entded 6/30/1947 6/30/1948 6/30/1949 Alpha-East $ 206.00 $ 178.25 $ 171.55 Alpha-West 560.00 980.80 721.27 Beta Gamma 2,440.68 2,332.00 1,909.00 465.00 474.20 245.50 Delta 498.07 615.47 649.50 Epsilon 2,041.00 1,868.00 1,647.00 Zeta ^ 223.00 182.00 143.00 Eta 744.00 808.86 761.00 Theta ''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''' 270.80 242.00 289.03 Iota Kappa 813.00 943.91 935.50 Lambda 1,039.44 1,015.66 1,066.9 612.00 712.00 741.00 Mu 785.00 721.88 *28u0 zoTAL CLnBs 10,697.99 11,075.03 10,208.28 </p>
      <pb ref="arr6610059_0007" seq="07" n="70-71  "/>
       <p>70 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW Active Chapters Alpha East ''''''''''''''' ''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''' 81.26 Alpha West 45.00 Beta 258.80 138.94 Delta ~~~....~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~..~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 216 45.00 Zeta 11 5.00 Eta 285.00 Theta 60.00 ' ' '' ' ' '' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' 26 380.00 1.75 Kappa ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 116.50 Mu '...".." 89.86 $ 2,238.11 $ 2,206.26 $ 2,239.40 SCHEDULE 5 COMPARATIVE STATEMENT OF CLUB AND CHAPTER CONTRIBUTIONS YEAR ENDED JUNE 30, 1949 ALPHA-EAST Active 6/30/1948 6m0/1949 Maine A ' . .m 10.00 $ `mm Nova Scotia A 5.00 5.00 Vermont A 5.00 7.36 Massachusetts A 5.00 5.00 Connecticut A ~.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~. 5.00 Massachusetts 15.00 Vermont B 20.00 20.00 ' $ 45.00 $ 67.36 171.55 ALPHA-WEST Albany, N.Y. "."...".".m 20.00 $ 20.00 Buffalo, N.Y 75.00 75z0 N.Y 10.00 London, Ontario, Canada 5.00 5.00 Mohawk Valley 55.30 New York City 475.00 Poughkeepsie, N.Y. Northern New jersey .5.00 200.00 100.00 Rochester, N.Y 50.00 50 0 Ridgewood Glen Rock 10Toronto, Canada .50 15.00 15 0 980.80 $ 721.27 BETA 6/30/1948 6/301949 Boston, Mass. .. ' . ' ' ' ' . . ' . ' ' " .v Burlington, Vt Hartford, Conn. '''''''''''''' Montreal, Quebec New Haven, Conn Portland, Me. ''''' ''''''''' Stamford, Conn Eastern Maine H J~~~~~ ~~~'...~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 82.25 $ 81.55 2.50 50.00 50.00 7.50 10.00 25.00 15.00 10.00 10.00 1.00 3.00 2.00 New York A .. New York r ... New York A .. Ontario A . Ontario B . .. ... . .. . . . ............ ... ... . .. .. . ............ . . . . .. . . . .. ".".".'w .......... .......... .......... .......... $ 5.00 10.00 10.00 10.00 10.00 8.00 5.00 5.00 25.00 38.00 Pennsylvania B 35.00 $ 35.00 Pennsylvania I' 8.78 Ohio A 65.00 161.64 Ohio B 15.00 Ohio A West Virginia ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 10.5.00 ~45.40 Ohio E .'..'..' ' 10.00 10.00 Ohio x 15.00 15. $ 163.78 $ 287.04 150.00 10.00 25.00 10.00 100.00 Akron, Ohio $ 160o0 Athens, Ohio 5.00 Central Pennsvlvania Charlestown, W.Va. ~~~~~~~~~~~ 10.00 Cincinnati, Ohio 180.00 Clarksburg, W.Va Cleveland (East), Ohio 750.00 Cleveland (West), Ohio 250.00 Columbus, Ohio 100.00 Dayton, Ohio 75.00 Fairmont, 'W.Va. '''''''''''' 25.00 Harrisburg-Carlisle, Pa. '''''''''''' 100.00 Mahoning Valley-Yorktown Morgantown, W.Va. ~~~~~~~~~ ~~ .~~ 0 Ohio Valley 10.00 Pittsburgh. Pa 75.00 Southern New jersey South Hills-Pittsburgh, '~~'~~~~~~~~~~~ 25.00 Toledo, Ohio 40.0 Baltimore, Md ^ 100.00 $ 75,00 Chapel Hill 30,00 Charlotte, N.C. 3.50 Columbia, S.C. ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 2.00 2.00 Durham, N.C 5.00 5.00 Richmond, Va. Washington, D.C. ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 25.00 25.00 280.00 45.20 Wilmington, Del 23.70 1z0 Norfolk, Va. . .. . 5.00 5.00 $ 474.20 $ 245.50M=,u"a A ...' $ 5 . 0 0 South Carolina A North Carolina )3 30.00 North Carolina A 8.00 Virginia I' 5.00 Virginia District of Columbia ~'~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 140.17 0.00 5.00 S 103.17 100.00 10.00 5.00 30.00 15.00 o.D0 10.00 5.00 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW DELTA *30x948 6/30/1949 Ann Arbor, Mich * 35.00 Bloomfield Hills, Mich 100.00 Bloomington, Ind. ' ''` ' '' '' ' 25.00 Detroit, Mich. Fort Wayne, Ind. ~~~~~~~~~~ 125.00 0.00 Franklin, Ind 20.00 Gary, Ind 1.00 Grand Rapids, Mich 8.00 1.00 Indianapolis, Ind 200.00 LaFayette, Ind. Lansing-East Lansing, ~~~'~~~~~~~~~~ .47G Northern Indiana 2.00 Richmond, Ind ' ' 1.00 2.00 Shelbyville, Ind 1.00 3.00 Southwestern Indiana 40.00 40.00 Jackson, Mich. ..'.."...." xuo 2.00 $ 615.47 $ 649.50 $ 25u0 Michigan A 100/0 Michigan B 25u0 Indiana A 100o0 Indiana B 10.00 Indiana r 30.00 Indiana 4S, 25.00 Indiana E 8.00 Michigan r 1.00 247.50 25.00 5.00 ...... 71 .... 6/30/1948 6a0m949 60.00 5.00 5.00 34.40 30.00 5.00 10.00 10.00 20.00 5.00 5.00 48.30 10.00 $ 173.70 $ 150.00 ................... ................... ................... .. . ... ... .. .. . .. . . . ................... ................... ................... Chattanooga, Tenn o 5.00 Columbia, Mo. . ~~~~~. Jefferson City, Mo 2.00 Kansas City, Mo. .~~~.~~~~~~~ 500.00 Little Pigeon-Knoxville, 1.00 Louisville, Ky ' 25.00 St. Louis, Mo 1,200o0 ''' ''' ' ''' '' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' 15.00 .................... Blue Ridge, Tenn EnslLoN $ 5.00 Kentucky 20.00 $om 75.00 20.00 10.00 Missouri B 125.00 300.00 Missouri I' 5.00 Tennessee u 525.00 20.00 3.75 25.00 Tennessee B 30.00 130.00 5.00 10.00 Tennessee r 5.00 5.00 1,200.00 15.00 .500 2.00 $ 273.75 $ 210.00 $1,868.00 $1,647.00 Atlanta, Ga $ 50.00 Birmingham, Ala 15.00 Deland, Fla. '''''''''''''''' - Jacksonville, Fla 5.00 Lakeland, Fla 2.00 Miami, Fla '~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ z25.00 ~~~ Orlando, Fla. St. Petersburg, ~~ 0 Tampa, Fla 5.00 M~~.~~~~~~~~~~~..~~~~~~~~~~~~~ ZETA $ 35.00 ' ".'.." $ 30.00 $ 15.00 10.00 Florida A 10.00 10.00 -~~ Florida r ..~~~~~~~..~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 75.000 75.00 5.00 Georgia A 20.00 20.00 10.00 25.00 10.00 15 2.00 .00 1.00 $ 155.00 $ 120.00 $ 182.00 $ 143.00 Avon, Ill $ 7.00 Beloit, Wis 20.00 Carthage, 4.00 100.00 Chicago Business Women 5.00 Chicago North 25.00 Chicago South 50.00 Chicago West Suburban 5.00 Decatur, Dupage County-Nina Harris ]~~~'~~~~ 35.00 10.00 Elgin, 5.00 Fox River Valley, Wis 15^0 Illinois Fox River, Ill 5.00 Galesburg, ''''''''''''''' 15.00 Jacksonville, '''''''''''''' - Joliet, 5.00 Madison, Wis. Milwaukee, Wis 50.00 '''''''' '' 200.00 Monmouth, 5.00 North Shore, Oak Park River Forest, Peoria, Rockford, ....~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 102.86 250.00 25.00 5.00 $ 808.86 $ 761.00 ETA Wisconsin A $ 50.00 $ 50.00 Wisconsin B Wisconsin r ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 550.00 50.00 0.00 25.00 Illinois A 20.00 Illinois B-A 75.00 Illinois E 20.00 15o0 Illinois Z m oo 64.00 Illinois H ' 50.00 Illinois 0 ' 75o0 75.0 $ 378.00 $ 424.00 </p>
      <pb ref="arr6610059_0008" seq="08" n="72-73  "/>
       <p>72 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW THETA 6/30/1948 6/301949 Ames, Iowa w 20.00 $ 20.00 Burlington, Iowa 5.00 5.00 Cedar Rapids, Iowa Council Bluffs, Iowa ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 120.00 30.00 0.00 10.00 Des Moines, Iowa 15/00 5z0 Jr 75.00 100.00 Grand Forks, N.D 5^00 10.00 Indianola, Iowa, 5.00 5.00 Iowa City-, Iowa Minneapolis, Minn. .. 5.000 5.00 Mt. Pleasant, Iowa, 10.00 10u0 Tri-Cities 10.00 10.00 Minneapolis Afternoon Winnipeg, Manitoba 10.00 1.00 Minneapolis Evening 1.00 Fargo, N.D - $ 242.00 $ 289.03 ................ . .. .. ........ ................ .. . .. . .. ........ ..... ..... ..... ..... 6/30/1948 6/30/1949 10.00 10.00 10.00 5.00 10.00 10.00 10.00 5.00 $ 46.00 $ 40.00 Iowa A Iowa B Iowa r Iowa Z M anitoba A Minnesota A. . North Dakota A .... 85.00 25.00 25.00 50.00 400.00 35.00 50.00 20.00 1.00 28.50 25.00 100.00 10.00 25.00 10.00 10.00 10.00 1.00 25.00 Colorado A ".'.".".".'4 75o0 $ 75.00 Colorado B 50.00 50.00 Kansas A 20.00 20.00 ~~~~~~~.~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 100.00 100.00 Nebraska B South Dakota A ' ' ' ' ". ' ' ' ' " . " . ' ' 20.00 -~00 Utah A . 20uo 20.00 $ 333.86 $ 300.50 Boulder, Colo 50.00 Casper, Wyo. Cheyenne, Wyo. ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ ~~ Colorado Springs, Colo. 10.00 Denver, Colo. . .~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 400.00 Fort Collins, Colo 45.00 Hutchinson, Kan 25.00 Kansas City, Kan 20.00 Laramie, Wyo. Lawrence, Kan ~~ 25.00 Lincoln, Neb 25.00 Manhattan, Kan 100.00 Ogden, Utah 10.00 Omaha, Neb 65/65 Pueblo, Colo 10.00 Salt Lake City, Utah 10.00 Topeka, Kan. Vermillion, S.D. '~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 1.00 Wichita, K=n "."." 10.00 $ 943.91 $ 935.50 m 15.00 $ 15.00 Corpus Christi, Tex. 40.00 50o0 Tax 200x0 200.00 10.00 10.00 Little Rock, Ark 15.00 15o0 Tex ~~ 00 ~0 Muskogee, Okla 15z0 10.00 New Orleans, La ruo Nita Stark Beaumont, ~~'~~ 120.66 190.60 Norman, Okla 10.00 10.00 Oklahoma City, Okla 100.00 100.00 Okmulgee, Okla 40o0 15^00 Ponca City, Okla 5.0 Shreveport, La 25.00 25.00 Stillwater, Okla 10.00 10.00 Texarkana, Ark.-Tex 10o0 10.00 Tulsa, Okla 25o0 50.00 Tyler, Tex 50o0 50.00 Wichita Falls, Tex 5o0 Bartlesville, Okla 5.00 San Antonio, Tex 5.00 Waco, z= 5.00 $1,015.66 $1,066.93Texas A ^ 100.00 $ 100.00 Louisiana B 20.00 10.00 Texas B 50.00 Arkansas A ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 50.000 25.00 Louisiana A 100o0 100. Oklahoma A 50o0 50.00 Oklahoma B 30.00 25.00 $ 375.00 $ 360.00 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW LAMBDA 6/30/1948 6/30/1949 73 Alumna Boise, Idaho $ Bozeman, Mont Butte-Anaconda, Mont Calgary. Alberta, Canada Corvallis, Ore Edmonton, Alberta, Canada Eugene, Ore Everett, Wash Olympia, Wash Portland, Ore Pullman, Wash Salem, Ore Spokane, Wash Tacoma, Wash Vancouver, British Columbia Wenatchee, Wash Yakima, Wash Seattle, Wash Bellingham, Wash Walla Walla, Wash Medford, Ore $ 712.00 $ 741.00 Mu Albuquerque, N. M $ 5.00 $ 5.00 Arizona A $ 15.00 $ 7.50 Berkeley, Calif 2.50 250.00 California B 25.00 El Paso, Tex 5.00 5.00 California A 30.00 30.00 Fresno, Calif 20.00 25.00 California r Glendale, Calif 25.00 25.00 Nevada A 5.00 Honolulu, T.H 10.00(a) New Mexico A 15.00 15.00 Long Beach, Calif 20.00 20.00 Los Angeles, Calif 200.00 200.00 $ 65.00 $ 77.50 Marin County, Calif 10.00 15.00 Reno, Nev 10.00 10.00 New Mexico Alumnae Club 5.00 Palo Alto, Calif 25.00 25.00 Pasadena, Calif 25.00 25.00 Phoenix, Ariz 5.00 5.00 Sacramento, Calif 10.00 10.00 San Diego, Calif 100.00 100.00 San Francisco, Calif 75.00 75.00 San Fernando, Calif 10.00 10.00 San Jose, Calif. .. . 30.00 30.00 San Mateo County, Calif 15.00 15.00 Santa Barbara, Calif 5.00 5.00 San Bernardino, Calif 1.00 1.00 Santa Monica-Westwood 40.00 25.00 South Coast California 50.00 30.00 Tucson, Ariz 28.38 5.00 Contra Costa, Calif 2.00 $ 721.88 $ 928.00 (a) of $20.00 received, $10.00 is reserved for contribution credit in the following year. Come to Convention June 25-July 1, 1950, jasper National-Park, Alberta, Canada Active 50.00 $ 50.00 5.00 5.00 5.00 1.00 1.00 5.00 5.00 5.00 5.00 5.00 5.00 35.00 35.00 3.00 5.00 150.00 100.00 25.00 25.00 50.00 50.00 25.00 25.00 110:00 50.00 3.00 5.00 25.00 45.00 10.00 5.00 200.00 300.00 5.00 20.00 6/30/1948 6/30/1949 Alberta A $ 5.00 $ Idaho A Montana A .............. ....... 5.00 .. 00 105.0000 Oregon A 10.00 10.00 Oregon B 5.00 10.00 Washington A 15.00 5.00 Washington B 5.00 5.00 Oregon r 20.00 10.00 Washington I' 10.00 75.00 $ 65.00 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



