<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr6010039_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Settlement School Reports</title>
                        <author><name>Copp, Ethel H.</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>September 1943</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr6010039_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">September 1943</date>, Settlement School Reports</title>
                        <author><name>Copp, Ethel H.</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 38-52</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">39</note>
                        <note type="Folder">12</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 60, Number 1 (September 1943), Pages 38-52.</note>
			<note type="document">arr6010039_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Report of Chairman of Settlement School Committee; Pi Beta Phi Settlement School-- Report on Audit of Treasurer's Accounts, Year Ended June 30, 1943</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Expansion and Growth of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1928-1943</item>
                                <item>Teachers</item>
                                <item>Budget</item>
                                <item>School board</item>
                                <item>Curriculum</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr6010039_0001" seq="01" n="38-39  "/>
       <p>Settlement School Reports REPO T OF CHAI MAN OF SETTLEMENT SCHOOL COMMITTEE \ OUNTLESS loyal Pi Phis deserve much credit for their wise determination to protect their investnt in human betterment in spite of war and they re earned sincere praise for their perseverance in rying out this policy. Because of their continued 1 splendid support the Chairman of Settlement tool is able to report a balanced budget, with no rolvements or outstanding obligations. In spite teacher shortages, which caused disrupting changes personnel, Committee feels indebted to our loyal )up of teachers for completing successfully a very licult year. We report the completion of at least ! major achievement to record in Settlement School aals namely the acceptance, by Sevier County urt, of the financial responsibility of the basic protm of both the elementary and the secondary school. Committee's faith that the contribution of alumna Lbs and active chapters would remain constant has more than justified. The very slight decrease er the previous year has been offset by the in-!ased earnings from our Magazine Agency. We con s to having had some apprehension as we set the dget for 1942-1943 year, fully aware that there !re unpredictable emergencies ahead. We weighed ery item of expenditure to determine whether or t it was essential to the preservation of our in-;rity and the fulfillment of our self-assumed obligaes. We expressed the hope that the headlong rush :o the demands of war would not result in Pi Phis luffing off" permanent obligations which would !aken our structure when this temporary, though vastating, state of war is over. Now we know that Settlement School must have en double starred upon the preferred list of our Phi family's essential obligations. This indication enduring and steadfast purpose is pleasing proof at Pi Phi cherishes its privilege to serve humanity. 'ell do we know that maintaining Settlement School s been accomplished in addition to patriotic obliga-)ns which have been assumed by every club and apter and by Pi Phis as individuals. Because of such tselfish endeavors Pi Phis have attracted to them-Ives remuneration in bountiful measure, reminding again that "Faith is the brave endeavor, The splendid enterprise The strength to serve, whatever Conditions may arise !" The Settlement School Committee met at the School . late May, 1942, to plan for 1942-1943. The Chair-an went to the School in November and again in pril, 1943, to represent the Fraternity at the session the County Court and give all possible help in arifying Pi Phi's position in this all important after of transition of financial responsibility. This has not been an easy, carefree year for you or )r our school staff, or for Committee. If you asked !ttlement School's Director, she would be forced to port that shortages, teacher shortages, caused us le most concern. It has been anything but a smooth inning year with this ever recurring problem of ocher replacement. Sometimes it was the draft, then upid, and next the understandable lure of industry's high wages. Fortunately Elizabeth Comstock Peck possesses the fine state of mind in which happiness prevails in dark days as well as light. Both she and Superintendent Fleming should "feel contentment be-cause of deeds well done and joyousness in service at a time when the world needs the best we have to give." They closed the school term with flying colors with only an agriculture teacher short, though they would prefer not to be reminded of the struggle to keep positions filled. Some comfort was felt in the knowledge that rural schools throughout these United States were similarly afflicted and that Smith-Hughes Agriculture teachers are apparently choice morsels in every draft board's diet. Without this untiring and unselfish staff devotion, the substantial support and trust of Settlement School's donors would have gone for naught. Back of this front line has been a unified Committee who have met their responsibilities with unfailing promptness and a zealous determination that unsettled world conditions should not undermine Pi Phi's position, or jeopardize our future growth. To each of the following your appreciative chairman pays humble tribute: Beth Brainard LeRoy, Massachusetts A, Lolita Snell Prouty, Colorado A, Mildred Odell Sale, North Dakota A, Ann Leichliter Munn, Iowa T. Each has shown courage and wisdom in her prompt attention to Settlement School problems, a willingness to put self in the background and a spirit of devoted co-operation which has made the two year experience of serving as chairman a soul satisfying adventure. To serve with such an inspiring group is a privilege to remember for a life time. As a retiring chairman it is with fond admiration that I remind you also of those other wonderful Pi Phis who will continue to enrich my life because of having known them and having worked with them for something worthwhile. There is Lillian Beck Holton, Jeffries Green Pace, Marie Bacon Hagee, Irene Eldridge, and Agnes Wright Spring. For these dear friends, and many more, I am indebted to Settlement School. To Grand Council, as an official body, and to each member as a personal friend our Committee wishes to extend loving appreciation. You have given us all possible assistance and encouragement with generous evidence that you had faith in us. To the contact member, our Grand President, we extend warm greetings as we review the countless hours of added labor which our demands have caused her. Through her we have maintained a very close association with the national officers, in the 'belief that full knowledge of our activities and decisions would be of mutual benefit. If any progress has been made this year, add we sincerely hope that our decisions will prove constructive, it will be because of the Fraternity's faith in us which was expressed through Grand Council's friendly encouragement and their selfless whole-hearted cooperation. Lois Stoolman's regrettable misfortune has been cause for sadness as we have known her to be con-fined to her bed month after month. It is hoped that she will feel some happy consolation for her discomforts in the knowledge that her courage and continued usefulness to the Fraternity have won for her the 38 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 39 admiration which only personal sacrifice can inspire. Her uninterrupted constructive assistance has been a real inspiration. May she soon enjoy perfect health and freedom. Staff Personnel: With the exception of the October resignation of Pern Price, as principal of the elementary school, the personnel of the department heads was unchanged, until the last month of school, when Elizabeth Comstock Peck was forced to resign as Director, because of the serious illness of her sister. Mrs. Peck had completed two years of loyal, devoted service and had won the affectionate regard of staff, Committee, and community because of her consideration for the comfort and the interests of each individual. It is with regret, real appreciation, and sincere best wishes for her own and her family's welfare that we have accepted her resignation. Capable, generous Ethel Snow responded to our need by adding the heavy load of administrative duties to those of her own big job. This loyal and unselfish service is deeply appreciated by Committee. The Fraternity owes her devoted recognition. If there are to be jewels in Pi Phis' crown, Ethel deserves the honor. Last fall we were grateful to Miss Edith Bader, retired Assistant Superintendent of Schools of Ann Arbor, Michigan, for promptly offering her services to tide over until we were able to find a principal and teacher for the combined seventh and eighth grade. Miss Bader brought to our school a wealth of valued experience and inspiration. She was most valuable in assembling and cataloging our elementary school library and establishing a small reading room, the nucleus of an elementary department in our future hoped for unified school-community library. Settlement School Committee and the Fraternity are indebted to Miss Bader for her generous and patriotic efforts in our behalf. We are selfishly regretful that her health would not permit her to continue to serve our school. We are fortunate, however, that she is willing to advise with our staff. Those of you who are familiar with our teaching personnel will regret to learn that Eleanor Brabson resigned in May because of the death of both her parents. Eleanor taught the first grade for many years and is dearly loved by the community. We regret that Pi Phis Marylyn Abel and Mary Hayward and Flora Belle ,DeWit Poore will not re-turn next year. Each has given more than just a teacher's bit to her iob. Their original and charming ceremony for Little Pigeon Club's 1943 Founders' Day program was a sweet tribute and a real delight to the Pi Phis present. Your chairman was proud to be a guest in Flora Belle's lovely home with Jessie Harris, Asheville Convention initiate, and her associate friend, Ida Anders, and two other Knoxville Pi Phis to make the local group add up to sixteen. Special credit is due Pi Phis Pauline Huff, and Mary Hay-ward for the inspiring operetta which was the year's high light and the happy success of the elementary school. First grade teacher, Mrs. Howe, was equally enthusiastic in adding to the children's complete joy in this colorful production. In fact every teacher deserves much credit for a performance which de-lighted the parents. They love music and need it so badly. Superintendent Ben Fleming carried uncomplainingly a full day's teaching load in the high school in addition to his administrative duties. His fine under-standing of Pi Phi ideals and his devotion and loyalty to Settlement School is a prized asset. It is hoped that an additional teacher next year will relieve him of a part of his teaching load. Fortunate we are that he was given a six-month deferment. We hope that it may be extended to permit him to complete next year. I wish to include in this report a reminder that our Settlement School will be in constant need of Pi Phi teachers as long as the war lasts. Haven't you always wished you might teach at Pi Beta Phi Settlement School? Here is your chance. Tennessee teaching requirements are on file with every chapter president and with all Province Presidents and vice presidents. If you would enjoy the satisfaction of using your talents for the good of your country and Pi Phi and would thrill to the stimulus of a year's comfortable living in a natural woodland paradise, you cannot afford to miss this opportunity. Pi Phi needs you if we continue to make our School a model. Building: The School properties remain as reported last year, except that the obsolete and over crowded Health Center building, Pollard Cottage, which houses our girls and our dining room and kitchen facilities, and our elementary school, are more obsolete than ever. No new buildings have been added, no additions have been made. The three year old Arrowcraft Shop is still our pride and joy and brings us admiring comments from visitors. Stuart Dormitory, in its second year, is equally charming, corresponding in architecture and materials with Arrowcraft. In point of actual need it is difficult to state which is our number one building need. We have no favorite. Each need is number one, double starred. If a Pi Phi should feel a desire to make a lasting investment in human betterment, she could perpetuate her urge to serve by building a Health Center, or a Library, or a Dormitory for girls, or a Little Theatre, or building or buildings to house Arts and Crafts, or a Lodge for visiting Pi Phis. And if one of these fails to intrigue her she could winthe undying gratitude of the entire populace by erecting a community recreation center. Certain of these in-vestments would receive some support for upkeep from either the community or the county or the state. We believe that there is great joy and satisfaction in store for those fortunate Pi Phis who will accept the opportunity to provide buildings in which Pi Phis may work and serve. Health Center: Continuing under the able direction of registered nurse, Marjorie Chalmers, special emphasis has been placed upon health education. Be-cause there has been no County Health doctor for more than a year, all elementary school children of the district were given a complete phOical examination by our nurse. Inoculations for typhoid, diphtheria and smallpox were given the school and pre-school children and adults, either in the schools or during the Friday afternoon clinics at the Health Center. Crippled children's work goes on as necessary with satisfying results. Every day there are evidences that work of that sort is paying dividends in health and strength for many children. Well baby clinics are conducted as usual with conferences both in homes and the office. There was some whooping cough, a few cases of chicken-pox, more of pink eye, and a little pneumonia, but on the whole, health has been at a high level gratifying dividends from your investment in health education! A detailed report of our effort to stress health education would take you through six weeks of Home Nursing classes for adults, two classes of First Aid for freshman boys and girls, six weeks of First Aid </p>
      <pb ref="arr6010039_0002" seq="02" n="40-41  "/>
       <p>40 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW instruction for seniors by Dr. Mittleman, followed by two months of practical methods, taught by nurse Chalmers. The sophomore and junior classes studied, "Health and Human Welfare" for the entire year. Health education was carried on, as well, in the rural schools at weekly classes, including study of posture, nutrition, cleanliness, care of the teeth and hair, prevention of colds and other diseases, and the health and safety rules for daily living. None of this in-valuable education and assistance would be given in our area if we were not providing it. We have a long, long way to go in the field of health service. There is crying need for tuberculosis finding and prevention, for remedial dental attention and prevention through proper nutrition education, and for enlargement and continuation of our general health education program to serve a wider area. And none of these services would encroach upon the field of a county health doctor if there was one. Arrowcraft: Ethel Snow reports a surprisingly good year in Arrowcraft sales. Even without the usual great influx of tourists the local shop has had a very good year, perhaps because those who did come spent more money. The unusual showing of many clubs and the excellent results from most clubs has been proof that the American buying public has plenty of money and that they appreciate and want our high quality articles. Results have shown that personalized displays and enthusiastic prideful sales-women are responsible for increased sales. With foreign sources cut off, Mrs. Snow is overwhelmed with requests for our goods. Weaving supervisor, Winogene Redding, finds it difficult to get material and is concerned also with labor shortages. We appreciate the understanding and patience which our clubs have shown when their orders were not filled as desired. Miss Redding has been painstaking and punctilious in keeping detailed records throughout her years with us. She can tell us exactly how many utility doilies she has made and whether you like blue or pink baby blankets. A few facts are, worth remembering. In 1942 our weavers earned $14,959.57. In 1943 they earned $12,683.79. They have woven up approximately $100,000.00 worth of yarns since 1936. They live within a radius of ten miles, the majority within five miles. Their average earning is about $150.00 per year, earned during about eight months out of the twelve. Ninety-three is the least number, and one hundred and six the greatest number working in any one year in their spare time in their own homes. Two have opened weaving businesses of their own. Under Miss Red-ding's inspired leadership, one of our weavers wrote a play, Store Britches, in which she and her daughter and son each acted a part. Under Gene's direction the play was presented by our Weavers Guild for three consecutive summers, giving forty-two performances to enthusiastic tourist and local audiences. It is the hope of our present Committee that this dramatic interest may be revived after the war to. serve as a beginning for Pi Phi's Little Theatre of the Smokies. Farm: Since no amount of effort could produce a qualified teacher for Agriculture, our school pro-gram was readjusted to include civics. Smith-Hughes aid will be available later when an agriculture teacher is found. The responsibility for our live stock, farm, and garden produce was transferred to the farm man under supervision of our director. Because of the draft, which included seventeen year olds, we lost most of our farm boys to the Marines, the Navy, or the Army. This situation creates a real problem for next year. We may be forced to employ extra farm and maintenance labor. From present indications we will have more girls than we can accommodate. They have expressed a willingness to assume certain chores which the boys have previously done, such as feeding the chickens. This year marked the passing of Lady, twenty-six years old, our faithful farm horse. Home: It is nice to report that delicious, though economical meals satisfy our school family and still the cost is kept at thirty dollars per person for living. Where else in the United States could anyone live so economically? Under Miss Lena Hodgin's efficient supervision much garden produce has been canned, and some sold. The long wished for paper place mats became a pleasing reality this year. Director Elizabeth Peck made the original drawing of Settlement School's domain. From this Evelyn Prouty Lewis, Colorado A, made the whimsical sketch which will carry the Pi Phi legend to Pi Phis and prospective Pi Phis. We are indebted to these two Pi Phis and to Evelyn's father, Mr. Frank Prouty, who did the lettering and presented us with the first thousand place mats. The Denver Alumnae Club generously and enthusiastically volunteered to take the responsibility for the supplying of these mats to chapters and clubs. A lovely new color film was made under Beth LeRoy's direction. Those' clubs fortunate enough to write early for it have been delighted. We are proud of Beth's sincere enthusiasm which has brought her many flattering invitations to speak about our school to non-Pi Phi clubs, as well as churches and to civic groups. Hearing of their loved Pi Phi project over a nation wide radio hookup was a thrill to many a surprised Pi Phi last fall. It is a constant source of delight to Committee to hear and see evidences of the growing national regard for that which Pi Phis have wrought because of ideals and through lowly rummage sales. Policies: The march of events at Settlement School bring us to a long contemplated milestone. At an April session of the Sevier County Court the Squires voted to accept full financial responsibility for the basic program of both the elementary and the secondary school on a par with that provided by the county in their other schools. Our proposal to them was that we would allow them free use of our mod-ern, well equipped high school plant, with large playgrounds, for a period of twenty-five years for a rental of one dollar per year, in exchange for the continued privilege of directing, supervising the curricula, having equal voice with them in the choice of teachers, and of supplementing their meagre county program as we wish and as far as we are able, within the limits of our gift funds. They obligate themselves to erect a new elementary school building upon ground to be purchased by them, adjoining ours. In brief we have preserved the privilege of continuing to control the school standards in order to perpetuate and improve the quality of service to these mountain people which our Fraternity has rendered for thirty-two years, and at the same time we have allowed the community to shoulder its rightful financial load. With this important and long contemplated healthy step accomplished it becomes now our obligation to make this unified school system work harmoniously and to the advantage of both the community, the county and Pi Beta Phi, and, further, it is our signal to move forward in our entire program. It enables us THE SEPTEMBER ARROW to redirect our efforts to concentrate upon a finer type of scholastic service, an improved set-up in our community relations, an enlarged health program, the building of a unified School-Community Library, adjacent to our high school building, and the expansion of our Craft program to include diversified arts and crafts under guidance of master craftsmen. It is the sincere belief of the present Committee, and we think in harmony with the findings and avowed purposes of past Committee members, that this recent transition of responsibilities has proven the sincerity of Pi Phi's wish to make a sound contribution to human development by gradually educating a community to accept its own burdens. By so doing we have successfully completed our first cycle of usefulness to a once isolated community. It has been the responsibility of the present Committee to formulate the working plan for this new and close relationship of community and Pi Beta Phi and to clarify the idea and bring about complete accord and actual understanding. But the principle behind this balanced plan was in the hearts and minds of our early administrators. Only by the careful nourishing of this basic principle by each succeeding Committee has the final result been made possible. Sincerely do we hope that the final terms, which now stand as our Lease-Agreement, will express those idealistic plans and bear out the wishes of the many loyal Pi Phis who have contributed toward this accomplishment. It was three years ago that Committee, with the knowledge and approval of Grand Council, gave written notice to the School Board of Sevier County that they must assume full responsibility for the housing and maintenance of their elementary school at the close of the school year 1943. This brought to a climax the years of indecision on the part of -our Committee as to when this change could safely be made without endangering our school strength. By that time even the faint hearted and most sentimental were in perfect accord. The next two years were occupied in trying to work out a fair and logical plan to accomplish the desired end and still retain all the privileges which would protect our School. As a final means to this end we employed a school planning authority to advise with us, after studying our area and its natural restrictions and resources. Between the lines of Dr. William S. Taylor's survey we found the answer to our desires. He reassured us that our wish to keep control need not be wishful thinking, that a workable, fair plan could be worked out to retain supervision and influence, even though the County did assume the greater part of the financial load. He showed how we could keep a unified system by getting the County to purchase land and erect an elementary school building adjoining our high school. From this the terms of our present agreement were worked out. In 1938, Dr. Edwin Lee Holton had recommended the procedure which he felt was wise for us to follow as we encouraged the community to assume its own burden. Dr. Taylor's report confirmed again Dr. Holton's opinions. We felt doubly sure the right pattern had been set by these two educators. The actual amount of Pi Phi funds which will be set free will not be sizable, . since the County, for a period of years, has paid all the expenses of the gram-mar school and a part of the high school expense. It is hoped that the saving will be enough to provide supplementary enrichment such as music and art in which we have been sadly lacking throughout our training of a whole generation. If we are not spread too thinly with the three Rs we can surely awaken appreciation for things which make our lives lovely. In connection with current financial status of Sevier County, Tennessee, the recent lease agreement nei tiations with the County Court revealed some int esting, though rather pathetic facts. The only means meeting the expense for purchase of land and t requested new elementary building was to raise tax A raise from three dollars and fifty cents on the ht Bred to three dollars and sixty cents was voted. T total additional money that could be expected fr( this raise would be only thirty-six hundred dollars year. The additional money needed will have to co; through readjustments within the present Cow budget. Sevier County's meagre resources can be bet understood when we realize that the adjoining Kn County, though not a wealthy one, could collect much on an eleven cent levy as Sevier County can its $3.60 levy. It is difficult for us to believe that Southern states are still so limited in their abilities educate their children. Superintendent Hodges Sevier County Schools is President of Tennes Teacher's Association. He gives these figures wh. indicate that Pi Phi's help in education is more nee, in the Southern area than in any other part of i United States. Southern states have one-third the cl dren of the nation, one-sixth the income, and n eighth the wealth. When a load is shifted there is always a n pressure. It was not possible or wise for us to cc tinue to pull the load that had become uneven. 'I needed shift has been made in a way that v strengthen the structure upon which the commur is building its own economic and spiritual indep dente. We have taken inventory of our own stren and weaknesses as we analyse the part which we to play in these next few years. As soon as the p was understood the community and County Co accepted their share with full confidence in our cerity of purpose. Now we know that it will t; diplomatic, delicate, and thoughtful direction on 1 part to keep pleasant our relations with the Cour The success of our dreams to keep our School strc will depend almost entirely upon the quality of leaC ship at the School. For this reason it is understanda that our next Director shall have had training experience in the school administrative field wh will equip her for her new role of sponsor to a mo school. Her proven ability in this field will give the necessary "voice of authority" as she works v the County in spending their money. Never before this particular training been so essential. Each i director of our School has given valued and k service. Each has filled the need of the moment v devotion and sincerity of purpose. Each has brou some individual abilities which advanced the qua of Pi Phi service. In seeking a new Director at present moment when the current changes rap special qualifications we realize that only through quate preparation and experience can our next rector meet the problems which will confront from this day on. The way is now open to advance many fields. To do this our Director will find it advantage if she has had training in these fields. know that it is highly desirable that we have unbro continuity in direction as well as broad vision executive ability if we are to coordinate our visi, our fine national contacts, and combine these fo into a smooth running progressive, intelligently cht program. We are sure that there is a Pi Phi with tl needed past experiences and that we will be 61, entice her from some other interesting job, bec: we can offer her an opportunity to build a cente great and as important as her talents and labor </p>
      <pb ref="arr6010039_0003" seq="03" n="42-43  "/>
       <p>42 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW allow. Some Pi Phi with an urge to create will find a marvelous outlet right in Pi Phi's School in the heart of the Smokies. Futures: For many years national advisors and Pi Phi officials have reported to you the trends which indicate a challenging opportunity for Pi Phi to make a real contribution in the upbuilding of American handicrafts. Every Pi Phi will feel a thrill of pride to be a party to a greater educational development which later will offer them an opportunity to share in its benefits. There is no reason why our project cannot grow to be very nearly self-supporting in the fields of Arts and Crafts. It is the hope of this chairman that the Committee will continue the purposeful planning toward the ideals for a center which may be dedicated to the advancement of American handicraft. This may include many fine enterprises which can grow to be self-supporting. One essential stands out beyond everything else. We must set high standards and clearly define our aims and ultimate achievements before we make a move. We should know exactly where we are going before we start. The idea is to create a diversified craft center whose name, Arrow-craft, will continue to be synonomous with beauty, simplicity, perfection in design, and fine workmanship. We can create a pattern for all America to emulate. We can serve as a source of inspiration. The new chairman of Settlement School Committee accepts a challenging, though difficult, assignment as she assumes the direction of School affairs at the July, 1943, business session of Committee. A brilliant executive, a diplomatic coordinator, a radiant, happy personality, well grounded in Pi Phi traditions Mildred Odell Sale possesses the balanced judgment which makes her the ideal person to lead us through the next four years of thrilling opportunity. Pi Phi's School is growing up but it will never lose the sentimental appeal of its early days and Pi Phis will cherish forever the heart warming thrills which were experienced because of nourishing it during its infancy. Like youth, in general, Settlement School early showed a marked tendency toward deciding its own future. With maternal pride we claim credit for influencing its personality, though environment and opportunity have played important roles the while its personality achieved a very special pattern. No Pi Phi who is far sighted can ever regret outgrowing one period as we make the most of growing and greater opportunities. Settlement School has its own ideas. Our part is to nourish them, temper them with judgment, out them to work, and encourage the development of every potential urge for human betterment. At the moment Settlement School confesses to an urge to concentrate upon improving the quality of the School program, give adequate teacher supervision and assistance, enrich the program to make it a real credit to Pi Phi a model school. It confesses to a compelling urge to spread its wings to include several progressive fields which would materially improve the health of a larger number of people. It confesses to an urge to do something about the recreational leisure time pursuits of a restless, growing community. It is bursting with a will to serve and the way is clearly defined. All it needs is a loving pat on the back and the words, "Do your best, we will lend a hand." Respectfully submitted, ETHEL H. CoPP PI ETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL REPORT ON AUDIT OF TREASURER'S ACCOUNTS, YEAR ENDED JUNE 30, 1943 August 5, 1943 To the Settlement School Committee, Pi Beta Phi Fraternity, Office of Settlement School Treasurer, Denver, Colorado. DEAR MESDAMES: We have examined the books and records of account of the Treasurer of your Committee for the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School for the fiscal year ended June 30, 1943. Combining the data from these records with that furnished by Homer K. Jones and Company, public accountants, from the subsidiary records of the School and Arrowcraft Shop at Gatlinburg, Tennessee, we have prepared the attached financial and operating statements. In our opinion; subject to the limits of our verification as indicated by the following comments, the accompanying balance sheet and operating statements together with related schedules fairly reflect the financial condition at Tune 30, 1943 and the changes as a result of the fiscal year's operations. The following comments are an integral part of this report, and should be considered as such. Analyses are made of certain total figures and an attempt is made to clarify certain aspects of the report for the convenience of the reader, as well as stating the extent of your accountants' verification. COMMENTS Cash in Banks and on Hand $41,341.65 The total cash consists of balances as follows: Checking Accounts: Denver National Bank Settlement School Treasurer $10,707.70 Sevier County Bank School 582.26 Sevier County Bank Arrowcraft 6,633.92 Sevier County Bank Dormitory 72.08 Sevier County Bank House 229.01 Savings Accounts: Denver National Bank Settlement School Treasurer 5,000.00 Bank of Sevierville Arrowcraft 6,079.43 Morris Plan Bank Arrowcraft 4,848.30 Hamilton National Bank Arrowcraft 5,071.95 Bank of Canada Settlement School Treasurer (Untransferable) 62.00 Sevier County Bank School 2,005.00 Petty cash funds Arrowcraft 50.00 Total Cash on Hand and in Banks $41,341.65 The balance in the Denver National Bank was verified and reconciled by us and the deposits to the Bank THE SEPTEMBER ARROW of Canada for the current fiscal year were verified by direct communication with that bank. The answer from that bank led to the belief that Settlement School funds are not kept separate from other balances. It is suggested that the separation of present balances be made and future deposits kept separate for the various Pi Beta Phi accounts. The balance, $62.00, is only the current year's deposits and the amount thereof has been included in the income for the year. If there have been previous contributions deposited to this bank, they have not been included in income in previous years. Even though this money is not available for immediate use, it is believed preferable to include such contributions in current income. Other cash balances located in and near Gatlinburg were verified by the local accountants, the Homer K. Jones and Company of Knoxville, Tennessee. As with their verification of other local assets and operations, we have accepted their verification as satisfactory. Income Cash and Coupons with Endowment Trustee $292.76 The balance of this account is unchanged from that of the previous year as the entire income was disbursedas follows: Transfers to Settlement School Treasurer . .$1,182.94 Trustees' fees 137.81 Total Income $1,320.75 The balance is represented by cash and coupons verified by communication with Harris Trust and Savings Bank of Chicago as follows: Cash balance $ 86.51 Coupons on hand 206.25 Cash and coupons on hand $292.76 Accounts Receivable Arrowcraft Shop $7,741.68 The accounts receivable balances were not verified by either ourselves or the local accountants. The June 30, 1943 total represents an increase of $1,031.43 over the total of the previous year. It is understood that occasional reports from school authorities indicate that the individual accounts are for the most part current and collectible. It has just been disclosed, however, that in the case of one alumnae club the payment of the balance was erroneously sent to the Settlement School Treasurer and thereby included in income as a contribution. This occurred previous to the current year, and as the information was disclosed following the balance sheet date, no adjustment is included in this report. Inventories 124,764.70 The merchandise and supply inventories were verified to the extent of extensions and additions by Homer K. Jones and Company according to their re-port. Endowment Fund Assets $47,146.08 The securities, as shown in Exhibit "A," Schedule No. 2, were certified to be on hand by the Harris Trust and Savings Bank of Chicago. There has been no charge to expense for amortization of bond premiums amounting to $1,710.05. However, June 30, 1943 market value exceeds cost by $602.87. Changes in the Endowment Fund principal assets are she in Exhibit "A," Schedule No. 1. Fixed Assets S88,073.05 The fixed assets are itemized in Exhibit Schedule No. 3, and show a total cost of $118,745 Depreciation at recognized annual rates, consis' with previous years' practice, has been charged aga operations in the current year. No inventory of NI ment was submitted to us for verification. It is noted that the accountant preparing the pr ous year's report recommended correcting the be to inventory valuation. Since this was not done, wish to recommend the preparation of detailed list equipment together with depreciation reserves to d the presence of the individual items on hand anc verify that the adjusted cost is not greater than pre value. It is believed that the conservative "lower cost or present value" formula is a desirable posit especially in view of the decision to create a repl ment fund. Deferred Charges $2,012.61 The prepaid insurance amount was ascertained examination of the policies on hand and by comm cation with the holders in the case of Liability Fidelity Bond coverages. Other Assets-4999.00 The purchase of the United States Savings Bt was for the purpose of separating from other accounts the nearest amount of the previous y( contribution for the specific use in construction 1 health center. Surplus Reserves S48,231.08 The reserve for the Endowment Fund is equa the amount of the Endowment Fund principal bat, as shown in Exhibit "A," Schedule No. 1. The reserve for the Health Unit Building Fund transfered from General Surplus in order to s the specific nature of the amount contributed. The reserve for the Scholarship was credited rectly as the contributions were received as they i "ear-marked" for this specific purpose. It is belie preferable to separate these amounts from opera income so there will be no danger of losing sigh the nature of the contribution, even though amounts are insufficient currently to justify the ( Lion of a separate cash fund. Income and Expenses Settlement School The inclusion of contributions for specific purp, with the exception of the indeterminate amount w is transferred to the Endowment Fund, has not included in income, as noted above, as was done viously. Also, contrary to previous practices, amount of depreciation on certain assets definitely tinguishable as pertaining to the Arrowcraft Shop been charged against its profits. Another Chang presentation on the report is in the case of the charged by the Endowment Trustee. Instead of b shown as a deduction from income the amour herein treated as an administrative expense. In accompanying report comparative figures for the p ous year have been ad lusted to reflect these chat The Settlement School operations for the year e Tune 30, 1943 showed an excess of income over penses amounting to $558.53. Summarized, with partitive figures for the previous year, the result: as follows: </p>
      <pb ref="arr6010039_0004" seq="04" n="44-45  "/>
       <p>THE SEPTEMBER ARROW INCOME 1942-1943 Per Cent Amount of Total Income $17,303.65 60.32 onal 4,135.79 14.42 1,000.00 3.49 ry 6,246.49 21.77 tal Income (Forwarded) $28,685.93 100.00 EXPENSES strative $ 1,270.93 4.43 :ional 7,346.54 25.61 aance and Operation 5,008.82 17.46 ry 11,582.37 40.38 ation 2,918.74 10.17 tal Expenses $28,127.40 98.05 NCOME FOR THE YEAR $ 558.53 1.95 $ 5,565.05 20.45 Arrowcraft Shop operations for the year ended June 30, 1943 show a net income amounting to ..18, summarized as follows: , 1942-1943 1941-1942 Per Cent Per Cent Amount of Total Income Amount of Total Income gales $58,402.98 100.00 $54,651.28* 100.00 Sales 30,212.92 51.73 32,871.89 60.15 $28,190.06 48.27 $21,7f9.39 39.85 ats Allowed Alumnm Clubs 5,748.17 9.84 Profit $22,441.89 38.43 $21,779.39 39.85 ng Expenses 13,177.67 22.56 13,016.46 23.82 berating Income $ 9,264.22 15.87 $ 8,762.93 16.03 to Income 895.47 1.53 1,460.76 2.67 $10,159.69 17.40 $10,223.69 18.70 ions from Income 578.51 .99 57.71 .10 come for the Year 9,581.18 16.41 $10,165.98 18.60 ter deduction of discounts allowed alumna: clubs. aling the income from the Settlement School and the Arrowcraft Shop we have: rent School Net income for the year $ 558.53 'craft Shop Net income for the year 9,581.18 'otal income for the year $10,139.71 s amount is reflected in the balance sheet as follows: ASSETS June 30, 1943 June 30, 1942 %rreaseor ecrease ands and deposits $ 41,644.41 $ 28,166.27 $13,478.14 .ts receivable Arrowcraft Shop 7,741.68 6,710.25 1,031.43 .ndise and supply inventories 24,764.70' 28,915.07 4,150.37 "lent Fund princi pal 47,146.08 46,073.76 1,072.32 :ed assets Expenditures for new equipment less depreciation 88,073.05 90,134.47 2,061.42 1 insurance 2,012.61 2,068.40 55.79 ients 999.00 999.00 Ital. Assets (Forwarded) $212,381.53 . $202,068.22 $10,313.31 LIABILITIES AND RESERVES payable $ 88.60 $ 88.60 ship Fund 85.00 85.00 $ 173.60 173.60 rative Totals and Increase of Surplus $212,207.93 $202,068.22 $10,139.71 items of income and expenses recorded on the forwardings of books of original entry and the gen of the Settlement School were checked in detail eral ledger of the Settlement School subsidiary records. :eipts and vouchers. According to their report, A test check was also made of purchase and sales r K. Jones and Company proved footings and invoices. 1941-1942 Per Cent Amount of Total Income $14,879.27 54.68 4,592.86 16.88 1,000.00 3.67 6,739.54 24.77 $27,211.67 100.00 $ 2,936.91 10.79 8,276.37 30.41 5,791.17 21.28 13,015.12 47.83 2,757.15 10.14 $32,776.72 120.45 THE SEPTEMBER .ARROW 45 Recommendation has already been orally made by us to your Committee, through your Treasurer, to examine the advantages which may be gained during this period of uncertainty by carrying a monthly re-porting form of insurance for protection of your in.-ventories. We believe that an elastic coverage is desirable to prevent the overpayment of premiums when there is a shrinking inventory and avoid an undercoverage when the inventory is increasing. Respectfully submitted, By R. Willard Orr Exhibit "A" BALANCE SHEET-JUNE 30, 1943 ASSETS Current Assets Cash in banks and on hand o 41,341.65 Income cash and coupons with Endowment Trustee Light and power deposit Gatlinburg ~~~~~. ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~ ~ ~~ ~ ~ ~ ~~ ~ ~ ~~ ~~ ~ ~ ~~ ~~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~ ~ ~ ~ -~~G Accounts receivable Arrowcraft Shop 7,741.68 Inventories: Hotel Shop o 728.28 Arrowcraft Shop 9,740.81 Weaving supplies 14,295.61 24,764.70 Total Current ,Assets ' ' ' ' ' " . " . ' ' ' ' ' " . ' ' ' ' ' " . ' ' ' " . ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " . ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " " . ' ' ' ' 74,150.79 Endowment Fund Assets (Schedule No. 1) Securities . At cost (Market Value $46,612/2 (Schedule No. o).".".".".".".".".". $ 46,010.05 Principal cash Uninvested 1,136.03 Total Endowment Assets ."."."."."."."."."."."."."."."."."."."." .".".".' 47,1+6.0 Fixed Assets (Schedule No. 3) Land .. ' ' ' ' ' " . '. . ' $ 5,193x0 Less: Reserve for depreciation '~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ . ...~~~~~4 81,033.95 Livestock inventory 1,846.10 Total Fixed Assets ' .. . . ' . . ' ' " . . .' ' ' ' " . ' ' ' ' 88,073 5 Deferred Charges Other Assets Investments United States Savings Bonds (Health Unit Fund) 999.00, LIABILITIES AND SURPLUS Liabilities Victory Tax Payable ' . . ' ' '. . ' ' ' '. . .' ' " . ' ' ' ' ' ' " . " . " . " . ' ' ' " . . " $ 88.60 Surplus Reserves: Endowment Fund ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' w 47,146/m Building Fund Health Unit 1,000.00 ' ' ' ' "' ' .' . ' . . ' $ 48,231.08 Total ~ $155,994.46 General Surplus July 1, Add: Increase July 1, 1942 to June 30, 1943 (Schedule No. 1) 8,067.39 164,061.85 Total Surplus ' ' .' '. . . ' " . ' ' . . ' ' . ' ' . ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " . ' ' . . . ' ' 212,292.93 Schedule A1 ANALYSIS OF GENERAL SURPLUS June 30, 1943 General Surplus June su 1943 ".".".".".".".".".".".".".".". ".".".".".".".' ". $164,061.85 General Surplus July 1, 1942 ' ' ' 1=5,994.46 Net Increase in General Surplus July 1, 1942 to June 30, 1943: -Net income for the year Arrowcraft $ 9,581.18 Total Additions to Surplus $ 10,139.71 Building Fund reserve (Previously included in income) Deductions from Surplus: 1,000.00 Transfer to Endowment Fund (Equal to 3/4 of Active Chapter contributions) 1,072.32 Total Deductions from Surplus 2,072.32 Total Net Increase in General Surplus ' ' ' ' . . . .' $ 8,067.39. </p>
      <pb ref="arr6010039_0005" seq="05" n="46-47  "/>
       <p>46 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW ANALYSIS OF ENDOWMENT FUND June 30, 1943 Uninvested Total Securities Cash Endowment Fund Required $1,363.71 $46,073.76 Balance July 1, 1943 $44,710.05 Purchase of United States Savings Bond Series G 1,300.00 1,300.00 $46,010.05 $ 63.71 $46.073.76 Transfer from General Surplus (Equal to 3,4 of Active Chapter contributions) ... 1,072.32 1,072.32 Endowment Fund Required Balance June 30, 1943 $46,010.05 $1,136.03 $47,146.08 Schedule A2 ENDOWMENT FUND ASSETS AND INCOME June 30, 1943 Market Value Income Par Value Cost June 30, 1943 1942-1943 Bonds Bethlehem Steel Corporation, Consolidated SF 31/4's 1959 $ 4,000.00 $ 4,190.00 $ 4,220.00 $ 130.00 Brous:lyn Edison Company, Inc., Consolidated 31/4's 1966 2,000.00 2,192.50 2,205.00 65.00 Canadian Pacific Railway Equipment Trust 5's 1944 1,000.00 1,105.00 1,037.50 50.00 Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad Company Equipment Trust 2 's 1946 2,000.00 1,994.98 2,050.00 45.00 Twelve Federal Land Banks, Consolidated 3's 1955/45 3,000.00 3,198.75 3,144.37 90.00 Minnesota Power and Light Company, 1st and Refunding 5's 1955 1,000.00 1,025.00 1,071.25 50.00 New York Edison Company, Inc., 1st Lien and Refunding 31/4's 1965 1,000.00 1,026.25 1,101.25 32.50 Northern States Power Company, 1st and Refunding 31/2 s 1967 1,000.00 1,010.00 1,097.50 35.00 Pacific Gas and Electric Company, 1st and Refunding 3 's 1966 1,000.00 1,077.50 1,115.00 35.00 Public Service Company of Northern Illinois, 1st 3 's 1968 2,000.00 2,095.00 2,240.00 70.00 Socony Vacuum Oil Company, Inc., Debenture 3's 1964 2,000.00 2,107.50 2,125.00 60.00 Texas Corporation, Debenture 3's 1959 5,000.00 5,350.00 5,312.50 150.00 Toledo and Ohio Central Railway, Refunding and Improvement A 1960 1,000.00 1,042.50 960.00 37.50 Union Pacific Equipment Trusts E 23/4's 1947 3,000.00 3,039.16 3,082.50 82.50 United States of America Treasury 2's 3/15/1950/48 1,700.00 1,806.25 1,740.80 34.00 United States of America Treasury 2's 12/15/1950/48 1,900.00 1,977.78 1,980.75 38.00 United States of America Treasury 23/4's 1963/58 1,000.00 1,020.63 1,129.00 27.50 United States of America Treasury 31/8's 1949/46 2,000.00 1,962.50 2,123.00 62.50 United States Savings Bonds Series G 1953 2,000.00 2,000.00 2,000.00 50.1)0 United States Savings Bonds Series G 21/2's 1954 2,400.00 2,400.00 2,400.00 60.00 United States Savings Bonds Series G 21 's 1954 1,300.00 1,300.00 1,300.00 16.25 United States Steel Corporation, Debenture 23/2's 1953 1,000.00 1,000.00 1,022.50 25.00 Wisconsin Michigan Power Company, 1st 33/4's 1961 2,000.00 2,088.75 2,155.00 75.00 Totals $44,300.00 $46,010.05 $46,612.92 $ 1,320.75 School Land $ STATEMENT OF FIXED ASSETS AND DEPRECIATION June 30, 1943 Additions Totals Depreciation 1942-1943 June 30, 1943 1942-1943 Schedule A3 $ 5,193.00 Buildings and Improvements: Fences, walks and roads $ 1,304.99 $ 39.15 Water system and sewer 1,091.36 32.74 Chicken houses and root house 898.75 26.96 Barn 3,384.49 101.54 Hospital 2,349.05 70.47 Mary Pollard cottage 4.634.60 139.04 Industrial building 25,006.57 500.13 Log Cabin 160.18 4.80 School House 6,749.85 202.50 Stuart dormitory $ 558.87 9.681.81 290.45 Teachers' cottage 6,870.38 206.11 Agricultural shop 348.93 10.47 Small buildings 566 98 17.01 Laboratory addition 5,685.34 170.56 $ 558.87 Equipment and Fixtures: Industrial building School House Teachers' cottage Mary Pollard cottage Stuart dormitory Hospital Auto and truck Barn Chicken houses, etc Heating equipment, Stoker Farm equipment M,ivie equipment Miscellaneous equipment $ 600.00 $ 600.00 $ 68,733.28 $1,811.93 $ 4,252.84 $ 212.64 4,128.49 206.42 2,083.03 104.15 1,717.88 85.89 2,703.12 135.16 1,496.50 74.83 1,424.85 143.72 650.00 32.50 250.00 12.50 485.00 24.75 90.75 4.53 310.15 15.51 $ 984.23 $ 54.21 $ 20,576.84 $1,106.81 Livestock and horses $ 153.10 $ 1,846.10 $ School Totals ; $1,311.97 $ 96,349.22 $2,918.74 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW Arrowcraft Buildings and Improvements: Arts and Crafts shop $ 2,661.57 $ 7 Arrowcraft shop 10,792.57 21 Weaving shop 7,882.87 15 $ $ 21,337.01 $ 45 Equipment and Fixtures: Arts and Crafts equipment $ 4.01 $ 1,011.89 $ 5' Miscellaneous equipment 47.67 47.67 $ 51.68 $ 1,059.56 $ 5 Arrowcraft Totals $ 51.68 $ 22,396.57 $ 50, Total Fixed Assets $1,363.65 !118,745.79 $3,42' Schedule SCHEDULE OF PREPAID INSURANCE June 30, 1943 Policy Amount of Unexp Company No. Term EXpires Insurance Premium Porti Fire Building and Contents Milwaukee Mechanics Insurance Company 1448 3 12/9/45 $ 30,000.00 $1,200.00 $ 97, Firemen's Insurance Company of Newark, N.J 7483 3 12/9/44 30,700.00 1,218.18 58 Merchants Fire Insurance Corporation of New York 25757 3 12/9/43 26,500.00 1,037.06 15 $ 87,200.00 $3,455.24 Fire Contents Arrowcraft Sho p Firemen's Insurance Company 7438 3 6/5/44 $ 1,000.00 $ 45.00 1, Firemen's Insurance Company 7439 3 5/27/44 2,000.00 90.00 2' Milwaukee Mechanics Insurance Company 1351 3 6/5/44 1.000.00 45.00 1, Milwaukee Mechanics Insurance Company 1352 3 6/5/44 2.000.00 90.00 $ 6,000.00 $ 270.00 Automobile (Chevrolet) Firemen's Insurance Company Fire and Theft 1793 1 Firemen's Insurance Company and The Metropolitan Casualty Insurance Company Liability and Property Damage 56495 1 7/27/43 $5/10.000.00 34.85 $ 60.85 Liability Insurance (Settlement School Portion Only) United States Fidelity and Guarantee Company 70241 1 11/4/43 $5/10,000.00 $ 36.30 1 Workmen's Compensation United States Fidelity and Guarantee Company 1013283 1 11/19/43 Statutory 70.16 2 Bonds Various 1 Various Various $ 47.30 3 Total Unexpired Portion $2,01 Exhibit STATEMENT OF INCOME AND EXPENSES Year Ended June 30, 1943 Income 1942-1943 School Treasurer's Compar Books Books Total 1941-1 General: Active Chapter contributions (Schedule No. 2) Alumnae Club contributions (Schedule No. 2) Individual contributions Magazine agency commissions Interest on Endowment Fund (See Exhibit "A," Schedule No. 2) Interest on savings accounts Miscellaneous income Total General Income Floater on Films Firemen's Insurance Company of Newark, N.J. 207 1 Windstorm Firemen's Insurance Company 762 3 11/4/43 250.00 5.00 12/9/44 $ 50,300.00 $ 268.10 12' 7/27/43 Value $ 26.00 $ 1,429.76 $ 1,429.76 $ 1,74 8,574.54 8,574.54 8,4( 5,820.50 5,820.50 3,0( 1,320.75 1,320.75 1,24 $ 5.00 5.00 153.10 153.10 4! $ 158.10 $17,145.55 $17,303.65 $14,8' </p>
      <pb ref="arr6010039_0006" seq="06" n="48-49  "/>
       <p>48 49 Educational: Appropriations for teachers salaries . Agricultural School income Economics Department income Library receipts General Total Educational Income Rent alt: Rent of buildings (from county) Auxiliary: Living receipts, guests and sales Hospital income Farm: Sales Products for living Livestock increase Total Farm Income Administrative Traveling and convention Auditii3g and legal fees Endowment Trustee fees Office salary (portion) Survey Publicity Miscellaneous and Committee expense Office Supplies and Expenses Total Administrative xpenses instructional Salaries: Director Home Economics teacher Agriculture teacher Other instructional Supplies and Expenses: Home economics Agriculture General Library Total Instructional Expenses Maintenance and Operation Insurance Fuel Light Laundry Truck expenses Auto expenses Salary Handyman Repairs (net) Charge off Old Stuart cottage Telephone and telegraph (net) Miscellaneous Total Maintenance and Operation Expenses Auxiliary Living: Groceries Food from farm Salary House manager Salary Cooks Salary Laundress Furnishings Miscellaneous living expenses Total Living 1942.1943 School Treasurer s Books Books $ 1,000.00 $ 1,000.00 540.00 540.00 $ 4,788.47 4,788.47 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW Health Unit: Salary Nurse Automobile allowance Hospital $163.53 Total Health Unit $ 163.53 Christmas Fund (net) $ 10.70 Farm: Salaries Expenses $ 1,789.63 Total Farm $ 1,789.63 Total Auxiliary Expenses $ 7,312.37 Proe ince 1941-1942 Alpha East $ 362.40 Alpha West 461.51 Beta 1,775.96 Gamma 393.62 Delta 361.05 Epsilon 506.03 Zeta 140.68 Eta 698.50 Theta 475.00 Iota 639.00 Kappa 1,222.00 Lambda 349.76 Mu 1,014.51 Totals $8,400.02 Albany. N.Y $ Buffalo. N.Y Great Neck, N.Y London, Ontario Mid.Hudson Valley Mohawk Valley New York City Northern New Jersey Rochester, N.Y Schenectady. N.Y Syracuse. N.Y. Toronto, Ontario Westchester County 20.00 23.00 30.00 241.51 75.00 50.00 20.00 Totals $ 461.51 Akron, Ohio $ Athens Ohio Centra Pennsylvania Cincinnati, Ohio Cleveland, Ohio Columbus. Ohio Dayton, Ohio Fairmont, W.Va Harrisburg-Carlisle Mahoning Valley Morgantown, W.Va Ohio Valley Philadelphia, Pa Pittsburgh, Pa Southern New Jersey South Hills, Pittsburgh, Pa Toledo, Ohio THE SEPTEMBER ARROW $ 3,947.46 19.50 137.38 31.45 $ 4,135.79 S 3,947.46 $ 3,816.00 45.64 19.50 49.40 137.38 64.55 _________ 31.43 617.27 $ $ 4,135.79 $ 4,592.86 $ 1,000.00 $ $ 1,000.00 $ 1,000.00 $ 3,333.32 114.50 $ 3,447.82 $ 740.23 2,058.44 $ 2,798.67 $ 3,333.32 _________ 114.50 $ $ 3,447.82 $ 740.23 2,058.44 $ $ 2,798.67 Total Auxiliary Income Total Income $ 3,252.62 84.46 $ 3.337.08 $ 856.56 2,394.90 151.00 $ 3,402.46 $ 6,246.49 $ $ 6,246.49 $6,739.54 $11,540.58 $17,145.55 $28,685.93 $27,211.67 Operating Expenses (Schedule No. 1) 16,365.37 Net income for the Period $ 4,824.99 OPERATING EXPENSES Year Ended June 30, 1943 Depreciation (See Exhibit A, Schedule No. 3) 5 Total Operating Expenses $16,365.37 SUMMARY OF CONTRIBUTIONS Year Ended June 30, 1943 Alumna Clubs 11,762.03 28,127.40 32,776.72 $ 5,383.52 $ 558.53 $ 5,565.05 Schedule B1 Comparative Total 1941-1942 $ 319.00 $ 319.00 168.63 168.65 137.81 137.81 130.00 150.00 30.00 30.00 86.62 86.62 232.71 276.46 53.10 102.39 $ 1,177.89 $ 1,270.93 $ 43.75 49.29 $ 93.04 LIST OF CONTRIBUTIONS BY ALUMNR CLUBS AND AcTIvE CsAs raRs June 30, 1943 ALPIeA EAST Alumna Active 1941-1942 1942-1943 1941.1942 Boston, Mass $ 297.40 $ 101.60 Maine A $ 5.00 Burlington, Vt 5.00 5.00 Nova Scotia A Halifax, Nova Scotia 2.00 Vermont A 5.00 Hartford, Coon 50.00 60.00 Vermont B 20.00 Montreal 5.00 Massachusetts A 5.00 New Haven. Coon 5.00 5.00 Connecticut A Portland, Me 5.00 5.00 Totals $ 35.00 Totals $ 362.40 $ 183.60 $ 1,444.57 125.00 126.61 240.00 328.50 212.60 378.65 80.98 $ 2,936.91 $ 1,200,00 540.00 537.84 4,599.33 178.22 111.77 1,069.15 40.06 $ 8,276.37 $ 1,128.68 1,019.71 359.17 305.40 154.07 124.01 660.00 917.42 425.00 243.50 454.21 $ 3,791.17 $ 3,323.71 2,394.90 720,00 683.40 25.31 44.22 $ 7,191.54 108.16 .85 811.62 97.44 $ 5,806.34 $ 1,093.81 368.17 134.25 182.20 127.01 920.73 243.04 84.21 $ 3,153.42 $ 2,876.88 2,058.44 169.11 244.08 $ 5,348.51 108.16 .83 811.62 __________ 97.44 $ 1,540.00 $ 7,346.34 $ 1,075.40 $ 1,075,40 1,093.81 368,17 134.25 182.20 127.01 780.00 780.00 920.73 243.04 ___________ 84.21 $ 1,835.40 $ 3,008.82 $ 2,876.88 2,058.44 $ 720.00 720.00 640.00 640.00 300.00 300.00 169.11 __________ 244.08 $ 1,660.00 $ 7,008.51 ALPHA WEST $ 10.00 New York A $ 32.00 New York r 6.40 New York A Ontario A 5.00 Ontario B 5.00 197.14 Totals $ 100.00 30.00 52.55 30.00 20.00 50.00 $ 558.09 Ba rA 1942-l943 $ 5.00 4.00 2.50 20.00 5.00 10.00 $ 46.50 2.00 3.00 $ 7.00 $ 77.00 7.16 10.00 $ 94.16 75.00 6.00 17.71 185.00 715.35 75.00 73.00 100.00 30.00 10,00 278.20 30.00 40.50 75.00 45.00 Pennsylvania B $ 92.00 Pennsylvania r Ohio A 45.00 OhioB Ohioh West Virginia A Totals $ 137.00 $ 75.00 3.00 12.20 135.00 1,000.00 75.00 80.00 3.50 5.00 177.88 50.00 25.00 50.00 35.00 $1,726.58 Totals $1,775.96 $ 1,440.00 300.00 $ 1,440.00 300.00 $ 1,440.00 300.00 163.53 90.29 $ 1,740.00 $ 1,903.55 $ 1,830.29 $ $ 10.70 $ 15.51 $ 870.00 $ 870.00 1,789.63 $ 870.00 3,107.78 $ 870.00 $ 2,659.63 $ 3,977.78 $ 4,270.00 $11,582.37 $13,015.12 $ 2,918.74 $ 2,918.74 $ 2,757.15 $11,762.03 $28,127.40 $32776.72 Schedule B2 1942.1943 Active 1941-1942 Chapters 1942-1943 $ 183.60 $ 35.00 $ 46.50 358.09 1,726.58 339.67 469.48 1,331.00 181.99 137.00 55.00 43.00 315.00 73.66 7.00 94.16 80.00 41.38 262.50 35.30 721.30 200.00 228.00 364.00 654.72 72.00 292.00 59.00 262.72 839.07 340.00 175.00 248.96 90.00 50.00 936.08 89.00 88.00 $8,374.34 $1,743.66 $1,429.76 </p>
      <pb ref="arr6010039_0007" seq="07" n="50-51  "/>
       <p>50 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW Baltimore, Md ' w 80.00 Chapel Hill, N.C 15.00 Charlotte, N.C. ' ' '' '' '' '' '' 14.32 Columbia, S.C 5.00 Richmond, Va. 25.00 Tri-City ~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 22.28 Washington, D.C ' . ' 232z2 Totals $ 393.62GAMMA 25.00 $ 15.00 South Carolina A North Carolina B 5.00 North Carolina A 15.00 25x0 Virginia , 10.00 Virginia A 5.00 211z0 District of Columbia A $ 339.67 Totals 10.00 $ 5.00 6.00 33.30 20.00 25.00 4.36 5.50 EPSILON $ Kentucky A $ 30.00 $ 30 00 100.00 Missouri A 100.00 35.00 6.00 Missouri B 100.00 100.00 Missouri r Tennessee A 50.00 50.00 25^0 Tennessee B 5.00 10.00 ZETA $ 15.00 Alabama A . '. . ' . ' ." .' m 10/0 Florida A Florida ~ Florida r Georgia A DELTA 20.00 Michigan A $ 5/0 $ 5z0 10.00 Michigan B ' . ' 5.00 5.00 20z0 Indiana A ' 10.00 26.38 100.00 Indiana B 5.00 5. 10.00 00 Indiana ~~~~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~ ~ ~~~ ~ ~~ ~~ ~ ~ ~ 10.00 10 ~ 5.00 _5x0 Totals $45.00 ---41.38 m/m 259.48 15.00 15.00 33.30 8.69 Totals ' ' . .' ..' . ' ' .' .$ 315.00 $ 262.50 1,200.00 15.00 5.00 25.00 5.00 Totals $ 7366 35.50 50.00 15.00 Ann Arbor, Mich o 29.80 Bloomfield Hills, Mich 25.00 lad Mich 150.00 Fort Wayne, Tad. ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 103.00 .00 Franklin. Ind 5.00 Gary, Ind Grand Rapids, Mich 5.00 Hillsdale, Mich _ Indianapolis, Ind. . .' 62.25 Lafayette, Ind ` 15.00 Northern Indiana '.. ..' 1.00 Southwestern Michigan Southwestern Indiana 20 10.00 Terre Haute, Ind. ".' ". ..' 5z0 .00 Little Pigeon . ' ' 10.00 Louisville, Ky Memphis, Tenn 37.33 Nashville, Tenn. ' '' ' ''''''''''' 10.00 St. Joseph, St. Louis, s~~.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 10.00 Springfield, Mo 15.00 Totals $ 506.03 Atlanta, Ga 25.00 Birmingham, Ala. ". ' ' ' ". ' " . ' 10u0 Daytona Beach, Fla _ Deland, Fla 10.00 Jackson, Miss 5.00 Jacksonville. Fla.. . 17.68 Fla 5.00 Miami, Fla. 50.00 Orlando, Fla. ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 15.00 St. Petersburg. Fla ' 3.00 Totals $ 140.68 ETA Avon, Ill ' 'm Beloit. Wis. '' ''' '' '' ' 17.00 Chicago Business Women " . ' ' ' ' 35.00 Chicago North _ Chicago South 100.00 Chicago West Suburban Decatur. Du Page County, 'b~'~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 100.00 10.00 Elgin. Fox River ~~~~.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 51 ~0 Galesburg Jacksonville, ' ' " . " . ' ' ' " . ' " . 22.00 Joliet, Ill 10o0 10.00 Madison. Wis. ' " . . ' " . .' ' . ' 50.00 25.00 Milwaukee, Wis. Monmouth, Ill. '~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 200.00 -~~6 North Shore Oak Park-River Forest, Ill Peoria. Ill. ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' Rockford. .."." ." 3.00 Springfield, Ill 30.00 Individuals _ Totals Chattanpoga, Tenn. . ' o 15.00 Columbia, ' ".." 50.00 Igfnesrassonc Ftyity, mMo.o 350 50.00 55.00 5.00 30.00 5.00 $ 4.00 $ 50.00 $ 50 00 12.00 Wisconsin B 5.00 45.00 17.00 Wisconsin r 10.00 10.00 70.00 Illinois A Illinois B-A '~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 25~~ 125 0.00 50.00 Illinois u ` 25.00 25o0 100.00 Illinois Z ' 55u0 58o0 15.30 Illinois H 20.00 5/00 76.00 10.00 Totals $200.00 $ 228.00 5.00 IHE SEPTEMBER ARROW THETA 35z0 Iowa B 25o0 Iowa 25z0 Iowa Z ....' ' ozm 25o0 Manitoba A 40.00 Minnesota A .~.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 25.00 5.00 North Dakota 5.00 5.00 25.00 Totals ----$ 72,00 *uu ==== 30.00 10.00 50.00 4.00 Ames, Iowa $ 50.00 Burlington, Iowa Cedar Rapids, Iowa ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 535.00 0.00 Council Bluffs, Iowa 10.00 Des Moines: Iowa 50.00 Duluth, Minn 50.00 Indianola, Iowa Grand Forks, N.D 5.00 Iowa City, Iowa 40 00 Minn 55.00 Mt. Pleasant, Iowa 10.00 Sioux City, Iowa 15.00 St. Paul, Minn 100.00 Winnipeg, Manitoba _ ----' Totals $ 475.00 Boulder, Colo ' ' ' o 45.00 Casper. W)o 5z0 Cheyenne, Wvo ' ...' 25.00 Colorado Springs, Colo. 10.00 Denver, Colo. .~~~~~~~~~~~~ 260.00 Hutchinson, Kan 5.00 Kansas City, Kan. ' 15o0 Lincoln, Neb. ''''''''''''''' 25.00 Manhattan, Kan. ''''''''''''''' 100.00 Omaha, Neb. Poudre Valley, Colo. Pueblo, Colo 7~0 15.00 Topeka, Kan 15.00 Vermillion, S.D _ Wichita, u=. . ' ' .' ' " . ' ' ' ' ' ' " 5.00 Totals ".".' ".".' "." .$ 639.00 Ardmore, Okla ^ Austin, Tex 100.00 Baton Rouge, La Corpus Christi, r"^ 50.00 Corsicana Dallas, Tex. ".'~"~~~'~~~~~~~ 200.00 Fayetteville, Ark. ~~~.~~...~ 10.00 Fort Smith, Ark 10.00 Fort Worth, Tex. ^ Little Rock, Ark Houston, Tex. ' ' ' . . ' ' ' ' 400.00 New Orleans, La. " 25.00 Nita Stark Club, Tex 120.00 Norman, Okla San Antonio, Tex Oklahoma City, Okla 1 130.00 Okmulgee, Okla. Shreveport, La 25x0 Stillwater, Okla 10/0 Texarkana, Ark.-Tex 15o0 Tulsa, Okla e~o T,~~Tex 5/00 Waco, Tex. ".".".".".".".' - Totals ' $1,222.00 ^ ~u $ Billings, Boise, Idaho 25.00 Bozeman, Mont Butte-Anaconda C=~ . A~~ 5.00 Corvallis, Ore. Edmonton, Alta Eugene, __ Everett, Wash. Wash 25.00 Moscow -Wash 2.00 Portland, Ore. ' 25.00 Pullman _ Salem, Ore 5.00 Wash 115.00 ipokane, Wash. acoma, Wash. ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 50.00 Wenatchee, Wash 18.76 Yakima, Wash LAMBDA 25.00 ' ".' " 5.00 Montana A 6.00 Oregon A Oregon B 5.00 Washington '~'~~~~~~~~ _ Washington B 5.00 25o0 Totals $ 90.00, $ 364.00 IOTA $ 45z0 Colorado A $ 75.00 10.00 Colorado B 50.00 25.00 30.00 Kansas B _ 70.00 300.00 Nebraska B 37.00 5.00 South Dakota A .. .. . 5.00 15z0 Wyoming A 25.00 25.00 Totals $ 25.00 100.00 75.72 3.00 15.00 10.00 1.00 292.00 $ 654.72 Texas A ~ .~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~ ~ ~~ ~ ~ ~ ~~~ ~ w -_ Louisiana 25.00 Texas B 50.00 Arkansas A 40.00 Louisiana ~~ 550.00 0.00 Oklahoma Oklahoma o A ~~~~~~..~~~~~~~~~~~ 25.00 Totals $ 340o0 200.00 10.00 10.00 ".".".".'* . .. .. . .. . ............ . . . . . . .. . . . . ........... . . .. . .. ............. 5.00 50.00 5.00 25.00 5.00 Totals $ 349.76 </p>
      <pb ref="arr6010039_0008" seq="08" n="52-53  "/>
       <p>THE SEPTEMBER ARROW clue, N.M o Calif Tex ............... ............... , Calif. ''' ''' ' '' '' ' ' ' ' ach, Calif ' Z D, Calif , Calif Ariz to, Calif ! City, Utah ;6, Calif ....... Calif eo County, Calif onica, Calif. Ariz Arizona A ".".".".".' "."w 10.00 ~ 12u0 58o0 California A 10.00 5.00 3.00 California B 10,00 10.00 California r 24.00 30.00 50.00 California. ~ 25.00 25.00 127.59 Nevada A 5.00 1.00 20.00 Utah A 5.00 5.00 ,10~~ Totals $89.00 $88.00 12.80 ............. Is ----' $1,014.51 Exhibit C OF INCOME AND EXPENSES Year Ended June 30, 1943 Arrowcraft Shop 1942-1943 Sales Cost of Gross 1941-1942 Goods Sold Profit Comparative ` ' $ 1,759.15 $ 991.06 $ 768.09 $ 544.86 Dg (Cost includes labor w11,8=.99/ 45,796.61 22,536.47 23,260.14 15,426.09 " .^".".".".".".".".".".".' 1,707.63 1,052.55 655.08 , stools, etc. 504.62 i and tufted articles 732.89510.21 222.68 567.24 [aneous merchandise 5,720.22 3,849.43 1,e70.79 2,737.65 ain View Hotel Shop 2,6e6.48 1,273.20 1,413.28 1,998.93 ' ". $30,212m2 $21,779.39 als ,Exp nses' ssions Hotel sales "."."-"."."."."."."."."."."..".".-# 780.00 Hotel shop 780.00 240.00 240.00 ortation cost (Net) 133.79 216.73 7,321.29 1,500.00 1,500.00 Flower Show publicity 449.42 122.17 16.20 12,75 aneous 189.78 324.91 160.85 173.44 ice 400.00 400.00 . . . 360.14 300.00 supplies and upkeep Arrowcraft 1023.24 62.04 6.72 ' ".".".".".".".".".'.." 63.45 62.16 49.85 ; and upkeep Arts and Crafts _ 291.87 275.83 578.56 _ and expenses Arts and Crafts 400.60 568.69 _ and telegraph 65.79 37.72 :pense 80.54 29.94 expense 103.70 71.18 iation ' ' 506.33 501.89 )tal Expenses 13,177.67 $13,016.46 rating Income $ 9,264.22 $ 8,762.93 ,to /=o'me: ~ Tennessee Weaving salaries Tennessee Arts and. Crafts .~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ $ 545.50 $ 501.00 _ 450.00 " earned Savings accounts 214.54 261.76 ~ts' earned on purchases ".".".".".".".".".".".".".^".".' 135.43 248.00 stat. Additions to Income ~~------ns from Income: t'.~ ".' "."."."."."."."."."."."."."." "$ *61.66 *uo"du=ti"ns from Income ......................................................... 578.,51. ,$ 57.71 me for the Year $30~12~, $24441.89 $21,779~9 $10159.69 ~0,223.69 $ _ 57.71 Committee Iseports COMMITTEE ON EXTENSION UPON the unanimous vote of the chapters in Alpha Province East and the members of Grand Council, a charter was granted to Sigma Upsilon Nu of the University of Connecticut, Storrs, Connecticut. Installation took place April 9th and 10th and thus came into being the eighty-fifth chapter of Pi Beta Phi. It is believed to be the largest group which the Fraternity has ever initiated at an installation. The group had a distinguished record as a local and an exceedingly successful rushing season in competition with well established national rivals. This committee feels confident that in this group, Pi Beta Phi has a chapter which measures up to the high standards of the Fraternity. The Fraternity has been in touch with a local group, Alpha Lambda Mu, at Massachusetts State College, Amherst, Massachusetts, for some time. This group, the first local to be organized on this campus, is anxious to petition for a charter of Pi Beta Phi. The representative who was sent to visit this group in April, reports with enthusiasm that the group and the campus on which it is situated offer an unusually fine field for extension and it is hoped that eventually we shall have a chapter there. Inquiries which have come from the Valkyr Sorority at Missouri Valley College; Delta Chi Delta at Louisiana Polytechnic Institute; Gamma Phi Sigma at Margaret Morrison Carnegie College, have been met with cordial response. The Administration from Bowling Green State University has approached the Fraternity for the College to learn if we would be interested on that campus before allowing any of the individual groups to approach the national fraternities. Throughout the years we have had many petitioning groups from Miami University and now a great deal of interest is being shown by the Administration there, as well as by members of our Alumnae, in a local group, Cenacle Club, which is desirous of petitioning for a charter from Pi Beta Phi. This committee is ever mindful of anything new and interesting which might develop in any of the above groups. Also it wishes to take this opportunity to express its appreciation for the assistance and inspiration from Miss Onken and Mrs. Finger. Respectfully submitted, MILDRED BOWERS BALIMAN COMMITTEE ON T FER S AS. UsuAh, in the Fall a form letter was sent to all chapter corresponding secretaries, telling them of the change in Transfer Committee Chairmen and reminding them of the October fifteen deadline for re-porting transfers on the proper form. Most of the secretaries were careful about this, prompt, and really sweet in their introductions. There were reports from all but twelve chapters, telling of eighty-eight girls transferred from forty-three to thirty-eight campuses. Iowa Zeta had the largest number, nine; Illinois Zeta, eight; Illinois Epsilon and California Alpha both six. By January the material was tabulated and the list of transfers sent to Central Office. A second letter wassent to the chapters explaining their responsibility towards transfers and reviewing briefly the rules for affiliation. The transfers themselves also received letters explaining their status. The local Advisory Committee member in charge of transfers at each campus where girls had transferred was sent a list of the girls on that campus and asked to organize them if there were more than three. In addition the Province Presidents were told what had been done and asked to get in touch with the transfers upon their visits to such campuses. Respectfully submitted, KATHERINE HOSMER H LT HOUSE COMMITTEE D UMNG this year Holt House has been made more complete and has served more widely. It has been the scene of Red Cross knitting weekly, of faculty gatherings, rushing, pledging, initiation, Settlement School sale, and entertaining. The house has had a coat of paint. Ida Jamieson Mattias, Washington A, and her family have loaned some of the ancestral furniture of the Jamieson family of Monmouth. The college has loaned a grand piano for the duration. The Settlement School sent as a gift, a lovely cream hand woven coverlet and towels. The Monmouth alumnae have given dishes and goblets and other clubs have sent money for furnishings. Flat silver has been added by using coupons of General Mills. Portraits of Emma Brownlee Kilgore and Fannie Thompson painted by Alice Hyde, Oklahoma A, and presented to the fraternity at its last convention are now in Holt House. They add interest and charm. The Founders' Room and the powder room have been completed. The figurines of the Founders are on display in the historical room. This room is now cur-tained in flowered chintz. Other displays are being planned for the room by Frances Rosser Brown. Mrs. Cary, the hostess, has been receiving guests and giving meticulous care to the house. As the planting grows, the yard is becoming more attractive. Mrs. Cary has a victory vegetable garden. The committee has lost through death one of its original and most helpful members, Adeline Barnum of Monmouth. The Monmouth club has selected as its member Mrs. William Bohan. Mrs. Dallas E. Perfect of the Milwaukee club has carried on as treasurer for Florence Butler who resigned. The cooperation of Miss Onken, Mrs. Smith, the other members of Grand Council, the Province Presidents and Province Vice Presidents has been most helpful. The Committee is planning for Holt House for the coming year. And it looks forward to the time when all members of the fraternity can visit this birth-place of Pi Beta Phi. Respectfully submitted, LORETTE CHAPMAN TERRELL 53 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



