<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr6330365_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Smith, Eugenia Brooks</name></author>
                        <author><name>Schattschneider, Meta</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>March 1947</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr6330365_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">March 1947</date>, News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Smith, Eugenia Brooks</name></author>
                        <author><name>Schattschneider, Meta</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 364-367</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">39</note>
                        <note type="Folder">15</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 63, Number 3 (March 1947), Pages 364-367.</note>
			<note type="document">arr6330365_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Weaving for Arrowcraft; Miss Georgie's Afghan</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Changing Mission of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity for Women in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1944-1964</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>
                                <item>Weaving</item>
                                <item>Writing</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr6330365_0001" seq="01" n="364-365  "/>
       <p>(1) A NEw BAG--A thrilling 'addition to club orders this year. . ( 2 ) MoLLIE MooRE and her family bringing in a good supply of fringed wbig rose doilies. Read. ing from right to left: Mollie her two datigh.: , Jeri', Bertha and Minnie, a sister-in-law, Zola and Stella Ogle.. ARBUTUSMCCARTER OWNBY at the loom in, Arrozveraft.-Shop. (4) MISMO`A'S .Loom.--. On which many lovely designs for Arroweraft.are horn. (5 ~ josjt WATSON and MYRTLE CONNOR Chaining a Cashmere scarf warp, Myrtle weaves 'Material for baby things, Many who were at convention will remember josie. ~C.~ 0 LITT 10' I EON Edited by EUGENIA BROOKS SMITH, Indiana r Weaving for Arrowcraft By META SCHATTSCHNEIDER, Weaving Supervisor, in "Design Magazine" In 1912, the Pi Beta Phi Fraternity did a very wise thing when they wished to inaugurate a worthy project as a memorial to their Founders. They consulted the U.S. Government and were informed that the Smoky Mountain region of Eastern Tennessee was tremendously in need of help with education of its children. They, therefore, sent a fraternity-supported teacher to open there, for the first time, a full term school. This they have supported by voluntary contributions through the years, as it has developed from thirteen pupils in the first grade to a complete grade and high school with nearly five hundred pupils. Today, Gatlinburg is a rapidly changing community because of the building of the Smoky Mountain Highway from Knoxville to Asheville, and its most favored location at the en-trance to the Smoky Mountain National Park. Summer tourists are crowding its new, modern hotels and its attractive tourist cabins, and are thrilled to see and buy lovely mountain handicrafts. Following its original plan for the Settlement School at Gatlinburg, Pi Beta Phi is releasing responsibility for continuing certain parts of its program to the county school board, believing that only by assuming obligations as the people are able to, can civic pride grow with the betterment of their financial conditions. At present, Sevier County is providing the basic educational program in the school with Pi Beta Phi furnishing the buildings and equipment, the teachers for music, physical education and vocational training. This vocational training includes supervision of art work in the grades, with woodworking and weaving begun in the upper grades and carried through regular high school where girls learn to weave to such an extent that can later weave for the Arrowcraft Shop if they wish. Tptpa nhlme adAni nenissnce oai sansmihfiee meet ct, noi usnoanungwjm mi ust ayunudmcnedrt mreidi otceoienrorfrenawwwIt ti9a000i y4tnrl tl5khf s000i htsrnffhopetephrar oeeiudgnc tornhfal hi vrearedgn, rted Pshsiiieet f clyserBsfivai efroeotts1nast.of this workshop. Weaving is especially important in this program. Pi Beta Phi maintains a well equipped health center with a full time nurse who, besides con-ducting clinics and taking care of emergency needs, makes regular examinations of the children in Gatlinburg and six nearby rural schools. Almost immediately after establishing the school at Gatlinburg it became apparent that there was just as great a need for additional income for the parents as to furnish education and health instruction. Fortunately, these people had a heritage of weaving skill from their ancestors which, through the efforts of the Pi Phis, has been revived and has provided a most successful means of cash income for the past thirty years or more. These mountain weavers have always made their living off their steep, rocky little farms. They even raised the material for weaving their clothing. The hills, with difficult roads, provided isolation forcing dependence on their own resources. The need for weaving clothing has long since gone. This basic purpose for weaving has been transferred from clothing to cash which can be converted to satisfy at least in part, the modern standards of living. Also a Part of the Pi Phi project is Arrow-craft Shop, which represents a logical cycle, each department dependent on and influencing all other departments. Actually, the shop is built that way, with a court in the center. It is the inner circle of concentric circles extending out to include the weavers' homes, Pi Phis from the entire country and tourists from everywhere. Pi Beta Phi Alumnm Clubs provide a market far from Gatlinburg and through the years have re-turned thousands of dollars to the citizens of the community. Pi Beta Phi's profits, too, have returned to Gatlinburg along with most generous contributions sent voluntarily by members, to be used entirely in the development of the Settlement School. Arrowcraft Shop, which provides the materials, pays the weavers for. their work, and sells the weaving, has grown Into a business supplying between 80-125 weavers with all the work they can possibly do. 365 </p>
      <pb ref="arr6330365_0002" seq="02" n="366-367  "/>
       <p>366 THE MARCH ARROW Weavers come in at the side door with woven things which we inspect while checking in. Supplies are given out and orders given for replenishing stock room needs. By appointment, weavers use the warping board in the shop for making their warps. Warps are carefully weighed and recorded to make possible figuring of costs. This is the time and place, too, when new designs are explained to weavers, or in-experienced applicants are interviewed and started with work. This department continually checks the thread supply so that production need not be stopped for want of materials. After they are checked in, woven pieces are tagged with cost and selling price and placed on the stock room shelves, ready for the sales rooms and shipping department. These shelves, incoming orders, and the reaction of the public in the sales rooms, give the cue for further production. The business office is the final link inthe cycle close to and with its thumb on the en-tire situation. The reason for weaving at all determines the kind of weaving one does and the limitations. Our weavers provide our shop with woven pieces. They want to weave rapidly to increase their pay checks. The more streamlined the de-tails, the better the checks. Naturally, this makes for efficiency in techniques on their part and throws the responsibility for planning and creative designing to the weaving supervisor. While the responsibility for planning and designing is almost solely that of the weaving supervisor, the weavers learn to appreciate lovely color combinations through their constant use, and sometimes develop interesting designs on the ends of their warps on which they are encouraged to experiment. This becomes an opportunity for discovering talent. Designers who are concerned exclusively with expression have the sky as their limit in choice of materials. Because after all, for them there is complete virtue in making something different each time they weave. They need not be concerned with limitations encountered in production. They may gather up interesting bits of anything whatsoever and weave a beautiful article completely satisfying as the only one of its kind. As a designer, I must know that my materials will be available in quantity. That is always the control for me. So, often the finished design has become a more subdued simplified edition of its original conception. Which, of course, may make it much better. My own approach is this I keep in mind what article I must plan. However, for a timeand as far as possible Itry to forget the problems of production.. Believing that materials make their own good suggestions, I sit at the loom and have a good time with a variety of threads, particularly those of interesting texture and color. I do not even bother with good selvages because threads must be easily taken out while trying out different effects. At this stage ideas come with free manipulation of materials. So, in trying out threads and the possibilities of the threading of the warp on the loom, I am making many short samples which I cut apart and mount in sample books with loose pages of oak tag. Quite likely one of these samples already is satisfactory above all others. Then it is the one to use. Otherwise, it may be that parts of two will combine to advantage. Or, perhaps another will be exactly right when simplified. When color, texture, material are all very satisfactory for the article, then the article must be planned correctly to size and shape and a sample made up complete. While making the sample, production problems such as these must be met: Is or will the material be available in quantity ? Can substitutions be made without sacrificing too much of the original appearance? Have we weavers who will be able to and willing to do this work? Who will do the necessary stitchery? Has the cost for materials and work been figured to avoid future complications? Can we expect to use a reasonably good selling price? Is the new article lovely only in the eyes of the designer or will the public buy? Has each possible detail been planned previous to production? Weaviag for Arrowcraft often involves several members of the same family. The warps used by our weavers are always long, usually 66 or 78 yards. Many weavers make their warps on the warping board furnished at Arrowcraft Shop, bringing one or two people to help. Generally this means that sisters, mother and daughter, or even husbands come to help. To really be convinced that it is fun and important to weave, one must want to know the skills namely, preparation of the warp and loom. The reward of independence and confidence is won if interest in the final achievement is great enough to go through the less interesting part of the whole procedure. It is like playing the piano, if the preparation has been good the piano playing will be a pleasure. Having mastered the skills, momentum of interest carries the weaver forward, new de THE MARCH ARROW 367 signs are created, more articles are completed and this means more cash income to enrich their lives and open the way to higher standards of living. Miss "Georgie's" Afghan Mrs. Georgia Duffield weaves all the afghans for Arrowcraft. She also manages the Arrow-craft Shop at the Mountain View Hotel. When she was asked what inspired her to combine the lovely colors and create the beautiful designs she uses, she wrote the following letter to me. Some years ago, I remember picking up a magazine, and came across an article about the old fashioned crocheted or knitted afghans. The article went on to say, "if you have one tucked away in an old trunk in the attic, bring it out where it will find its place among other furnishings of your Early American home." The thought came to me "why not weave one, instead of knitting or crocheting an afghan ?" The impulse to do this grew stronger and stronger, until, finally, my hundred year old loom began weaving back and forth threads of color no pattern, except what came from something inside me a desire too strong to be controlled, until stripe after stripe, and color after color was born. It was like some living thing truly a part of me. I can't explain my feeling for color. I only know it comes from deep down in me somewhere the way I used to feel when I sang my old Southern ballads. I guess you'd call it "Temperament." I must explain that when I was forced to give up my singing, I was driven to find something to take its pace. So I found the loom and now I put into my weaving the something I used to put into my singing. The old loom has been discarded, but not forgotten, as it now occupies an honored cornerin the old log cabin on the school grounds, which the Pi Phi's use as a museum. In its place in my little Arrowcraft Shop at the Mountain View Hotel, is a beautiful new loom; solid, hand-turned cherry a gift to me from a friend. The tree from which it was made grew high up in the Great Smokies. A poem, copied from the "Christian Index" and said to be more than a hundred years old, expresses most beautifully, the way I feel about my weaving: Weaving, Weaving Yes, yes, I'm weaving, and each day The threads of life I spin, And be the colors what they may I must weave them in. With morning's light there comes the thought So I my task begin. My Lord to me new threads has brought, And I must weave them in. Sometimes He gives me threads of gold To brighten up the day; Then. somber tints, so black and drear, That change the gold to gray. His love, alas, I oft forget, When these dark threads I spin, That cause me grief and pain, but yet, He bids me weave them in. And so my shuttle swiftly flies With threads of gold and gray. And on I toil, till daylight dies, And fades in night away. 0, when my day of toil is o'er, And I shall cease to spin, He'll open wide bright Heaven's doors, And bid me rest within. Then safe at home in Heavenly light, How clearly I shall see; That every thread the dark and bright Each one had need to be. Save the Children Federation This is the organization which has received the remainder left in the Physiotherapy Scholarship Fund, and voted to be so given by the last Convention. From Dr. Howard E. Kirshner, Vice Chairman of the Federation has come a report on present needs abroad. He says, "The moral damage which Europe has suffered exceeds the physical destruction, and is far more difficult to repair. Selective relief for children who need it is the greatest need in Western and Northern Europe today. and should be continued for several years. The acute crisis in those parts of Europe has passed, but the long, bitter struggle against cold, undernourishment, lack of housing and clothing will continue for many years. The Save The Children Federation has found sponsors for more than a thousand schools in Finland, Belgium, and France, and is also assisting in these countries and among war refugees elsewhere over 3000 individual children for whom personal sponsors have been found in America." </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



