<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr6530283_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Rauch, Harriet Goodsell</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>March 1949</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr6530283_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">March 1949</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Rauch, Harriet Goodsell</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 282-285</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">40</note>
                        <note type="Folder">1</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 65, Number 3 (March 1949), Pages 282-285.</note>
			<note type="document">arr6530283_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Craftsman's Fair of the Southern Highlands</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Changing Mission of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity for Women in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1944-1964</item>
                                <item>Crafts</item>
                                <item>Music</item>
                                <item>Weaving</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr6530283_0001" seq="01" n="282-283  "/>
       <p>NEWS F OM LITTLE PIGEON Edited by HARRIET GOODSELL RAUCH, Iowa B llllllll 1111.11.1111.11111.11.1111111111111.1 lllll :raftstnan's Fair of the Southern Highlands Throughout America from late July through Ttember, the Fair's the thing! This past sum-.er beginning July 26 and lasting for four days, te Craftsmen of the Southern Highlands held teir first Fair at Gatlinburg on the greensward the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School. These Fair 1tra.nts did not come bearing their prize pump-iris or blue ribbon stock, but came bringing the nest examples of their handi-crafts as well as le equipment that they use in making their andi-crafts; the spinning wheels and the spin Pi Phi weavers, Mrs. Morton and daughter An Exhibit at the Fair dies; the looms and the black dye-pots; the quilting frames and rug-hooking frames; the kick-wheels and kilns for the potter ; the material for the magic glass-blowing; corn husks, willows, honeysuckle vines, pine bark, poplar bark, river cane for basket weaving; broom-sedge for broom-making to mention just a few. Three days before the Fair began, the Highlanders began to motor in from places dotting the entire Southern Appalachians. As soon as their well-packed cars were un-laden, they set to work to transform our Pi Phi Green into a Fair-ground. Some decade-old chestnut rails were brought in, the fence rails re-piled in good old-rail fence style across the front of the grounds. An orange canvas ticket booth was set in an opening in the fence. Orange tents with lettered signs that could be read from afar tc attract the visitors were spaced over the entire area and gay beach umbrellas were put up between the tent spaces. The smartly lettered placards on the tents proclaimed to all comer; the craftsmanship or entertainment there-in. The broom makers sat beneath a tree. The whittlers (whittling miniature figures of animals and birds from water birch, sycamore, cherry, wal. nut, holly and dog-wood) sat beneath the bead umbrellas. The basket makers sat at the shad; side of the "pottery tent." The iron dye-pot; were placed appropriately on wood-burning fire: outside the weaving-spinning tent. Clothes-line: were stretched from trees conveniently near th( dye-pots and the hanks of vegetable-dyed yarn: swung from these lines. As soon as a hank o. yarn had its desired shade in the pot it .wa: strung on the line to add to the galaxy of colo browns, blacks, grays, deep blues of the in digo ; brilliant turkey reds to delicate pinks lavenders to the purple of poke-berries; yellow to match the wild coreopsis shading to pink yellows of sedge grass; the yellow-green o the lily of the valley leaves to the deep-green o pine needles an endless variety of beautifu shades and colors. The Pi Phi High School building which ha, just been deserted by the last summer work shop class was transformed into an exhibitio 282 THE MARCH ARROW 283 and sales building. Along both the inner and outer walls of the two main class rooms, virtu-ally all of the mountain crafts were arranged in displays of all types. Identification tags were re-moved and the choicest hand-crafts of all of the craftmen were featured in harmonious color, texture and line combinations. One arrangement covering the entire inner wall space of one room caught the eye of the visitor as soon as she entered the building be-cause of its complete range of strong and delicate fall colors. A hand-woven afghan in shades of orange and browns was the draped back-ground. A little to the left of the base, a wooden bowl carved from holly wood was filled with orange pottery fruit. On a hidden shelf above the fruit bowl was the carved sturdy figure of a bent mountain woman, realistic in its approximate five inches and pale color wash. On the other side in the display a delicately carved figure of a white lamb rested in a covered niche and below it an earthy-looking, small, henna-colored clay bowl sat on the table. In the now converted cooking classroom, there, on a shelf and occupying not more than twenty inches of space, were fourteen little hand-carved wooden figures. These delicately-chiselled figures not more than two inches in height were the characters of an "old-timey" camp meeting. The minister was leaning over his pulpit, earnestness in every line. There were five singers in the choir. Two youths were sharing the same hymn book. The tenor sang with real fervor indicated by his raised head and strained throat muscles. The contralto was hatted in an unmodish red hat. The organist was leaning over the key-board of the antiquated reed-organ, evident strain in every line of foot-peddling. Two ladies were prostrate at the mourner's bench. Four weeping women had just caught the spirit. One recalcitrant sinning man was being exhorted to go forward. And at the back of the imaginary set there was one lone man with hands up-raised, obviously jubilant over having just thrown off the shackles of sin. These exquisitely executed little figuies were carved by Tom Brown, a young man from Pleasantville, Tennessee. He had done his carving at Pleasant Hill Academy and is now studying at the Art Institute in Chicago. Tucked away in another niche, there was a group of gaily colored and amusing little pottery figures made by Mrs. Clara Maude Hilton from Marion, North Carolina. There were a city woman, a high school boy, a fisher boy, a madonna, a courting couple seated on a sofa (the young man was very ill-at-ease while the young ladylooked quite smug) . Ma and Pa sat on another sofa and Pa was almost asleep. Mrs. Hilton was the one who, when asked how she made the figures, answered, "I just pinched 'em up. I didn't aim to make anybody but they come out folks." After a tour of the many skilfully arranged exhibits, the visitor walked into the sales-rooms ; the 'two back class-rooms of the high school building were teeming with activity. There, tables were strewn with linens and woolens. Improvised shelves were piled high with pottery, glass-ware, baskets and wood-carvings, all to tempt bulging purses. Out-of-doors on the fair-ground, Mrs. Snow had brought in several families to demonstrate for Pi Phi. The Ownbys and Mrs. Huskey came to work in chair-making, Mr. and Mrs. Kear (Mr. Kear's picture is the frontispiece of this issue) came to work in broom-making and the Mortons came for weaving. Mary L. and Mat Ownby had been making splay-back chairs out of native maple and walnut since 1909. They still turn the posts and splays of the chairs on the old "boom and treadle" lathe (or "lay" as they call it). Mary L. makes the white oak split seats for the chairs. She uses green wood, "straits it" with a knife and then splits it by hand. Her father was a gun-smith and Mat had an old-time cap and ball gun with him at the Fair which he proudly displayed. He said, "The style is over 100 years old." When the Ownby's two boys were in the service, one son said, "jus' give me pappy the barrel of any old-time rifle and he'll make everything else about it." The Ownbys say, "when we want to make something, we jus' set down and figger it out." Mrs. Huskey sat beside the Ownbys at the Fair making corn-shuck seats for some of the chairs. The corn-shucks were soaking in a tin tub of water while Mrs. Huskey pulled up the right hand full (measured by the feel) . Then she very deftly spliced and twisted a taut rope to be wound around the seat rounds in the chair. The straight or curved handled hearth brooms that Pi Phis have been buying from. Arrowcraft for many years have been made by the Kears. Mr. Kear's great grandfather came from Scot-land and settled in that area. The Kears have been making hand-made brooms for 18 years and now have a family industry with five members of their family working in the Kear Broom Shop. They grow their own broom corn and say that broom corn grown in the Highlands is much tougher than that grown in the Lowlands. A hand-made broom-seeder is still used to take </p>
      <pb ref="arr6530283_0002" seq="02" n="284-285  "/>
       <p>284 THE MARCH ARROW the seeds from the dried broom straw. White oak is used for the handle. After the straw is pulled up around the piece of white oak, stained poplar bark is wrapped around the long or short, straight or curved handle and the bark is securely stitched to the handle by sewing with a hand-made nail-like needle. It would have been such pleasure for the visitor to have sat and watched the Kears dexterously and swiftly make one broom after another. Maybe she could have pieced together some of the story of the hard-ships and struggles, pleasures and adventures of their Scotch great grandfather. But there were other crafts being demonstrated in the orange canvas tents on that Fair Ground: Leather, rugs and quilting, vegetable dyeing and glass-blowing, wrought iron-work, pottery making, folk dancing and folk music, and weaving. Hand-weaving is still the most important craft in the Southern Highlands. Dr. Allen Eaton in his book "Handi-Crafts of the South-ern Highlands" says, "Gatlinburg, Tennessee, is one of the largest and most important weaving centers in the Southern Highlands. There the Pi Beta Phi Sorority through its school has set a high standard of work and its looms turn out practically every type of weaving from crude but attractive linsey-woolsey and striped patterns of the olden times to modern striped plaids and figures in scarfs, shawls, afghans, couch covers and many other textiles for home and personal uses." Mrs. Cora Morton and her daughter, Jane, demonstrated weaving at the Fair for Pi Beta Phi. Mrs. Morton has been weaving for Arrowcraft for 22 years. She learned how to do plain weaving with Miss Evelyn Bishop up at the Old Grade School. Then her sister, Emma Reagan Cox, showed her how to put the warp on the loom. She first wove towels in the old monksbelt pattern but now she likes best to weave the well-known Whig Rose Coverlet. Jane Morton, an attractive modern girl of 19, went through the 12 grades of the Pi Beta Phi School and learned to do plain weaving at the school. A friend and neighbor, Mrs. Fred Own-by, taught her how to weave the different pat-terns. Jane has been weaving since she was 12 years old and (like her mother) prefers weaving the Whig Rose pattern. Mrs. Morton has a family of ten children, nine of them still at home. The visitor asked her, "when do you find time to weave ?" She answered, "after the work's done mornings and afternoons I weave to relax. I just guess I like it or I wouldn't do it." . Miss Sarah Dougherty from Russelville, Tennessee, was the Chairman of carding and spinning for the Fair. She runs a thriving handicraftcenter called The Shuttle Crafters where sh, says, "we practice the arts of our grand mothers." Members of four generations of the Dougherty family are weaving for The Shuttle Crafters at the present time. Miss Dougherty ( most charming and gracious lady) had example, of weaving by five consecutive generations or display in the spinning-weaving tent. From he] great grandmother, there was a simple whit( counter-pane woven in a pattern called th( "Adam Mast." From her grandmother's loom. there was a coverlet in the Rose in the Garder pattern in dark blue of the indigo and light red of the madder colors. Her mother's weaving wa. represented with the old favorite Whig Rosi coverlet. (Miss Dougherty said that the Whig Rose pattern came to this country from England but she had read that it had its real origin in Italy.) A beautiful brown-grey-yellow coverlet was Miss Dougherty's own contribution. When the visitor asked her to name that pattern, she said, "Oh, that's just one I fixed up myself." A coverlet in soft cream, tan and white a variation of the Whig Rose was the example from the youngest generation's loom, woven by a niece. Miss Dougherty had arranged an exhibit which explained every step of the process of flax-growing through to the spun finished fabric. Flax seeds are sown in the spring. When about one-third of the flax seed is ripe, the flax is pulled, tied in bundles and laid in the barn-loft. The following spring it is spread out in a field to "Ret" (or rot.) After it is "retted," it is broken on the flax-break. For this process, the flax is laid on a board called the scutching board and, with a scutching knife, the "shives" or woody parts of the straw are knocked away. The flax is then scoured, put into a big black iron kettle (along with a few wood-ashes which serve as a softener and cleanser) and boiled. After it has cooled, it is washed thoroughly and dried in the sun. Then it is put on the distaff the staff which holds the bunch of flax in spinning. The city visitor, overwhelmed by the whole procedure, said, "There is real art in putting flax on the distaff." Miss Dougherty laughed and answered, "oh no, just a little art." Formulas used in making vegetable dyes at the Shuttle Crafters have been handed down from generation to generation in Miss Dougherty's family. Some of the formulas are the same as those used in England as far back as the year 1600. The formula for dyeing madder is the one she still uses. Madder is one of the oldest dye plants and gives shades graduating from peach to deep red. Miss Dougherty grows her own THE MARCH ARROW 28 madder and said that in olden times every family had a madder bed. Her great grand-mother was a "professional" indigo dyer. While Miss Dougherty still has her formula for dyeing blue, her blue is dyed by a neighbor whose "indigo pot" has been kept going now for ninety years. After walking reluctantly away from the weaving and spinning tent, the visitor stopped to talk with a handsome Indian, Goin' Back Chiltoskie. One of the finest wood carvings in the exhibition building (the figure of a tired soldier boy) had been carved by Goin' Back. He teaches at the Cherokee Indian Reservation School. 'Goin' Back had studied or worked in various universities, Oklahoma Agricultural College, Purdue University, Art Institute in Chicago, Corcoran Institute in Washington, But, he said, " I learned more during World War Two at Alexandria, Virginia, where I made working models for inventions and instructional aid models." The visitor watched the jack-knife in his hand adroitly whittling away on a block of water birch and asked, "what are you carving there ?" "Oh, I'm making a carving of my brother who is making Democratic book-ends." "Democratic book-ends ?" "Yes, he's been making donkey book-ends for over ten years now. It begins to look like he'll have to change his model." (Influenced by the polls, no doubt.) The hand on the clock in front of the entertainment tent stood at four time for the dancing. Six young couples (students from Berea College, Kentucky) under the direction of Mr. Frank Smith came to the Fair to entertain all comers with folk dancing and ballade singing,dances and ballades indigenous to the Southern Highlands. Mr. Smith teaches recreation in th Department of Sociology at Berea College any is recreational specialist working in the moun tains of Eastern Kentucky. These twelve yours; people are members of one of his student ox ganizations called the "Berea College Countr Dancers." Two years ago they successfully barn stormed their way across the country, via co: lege Campuses, from Kansas City to Berkele3 California. There was such gaiety, spontaneity, an, variety in their entertainment that the orang tent was crowded for each performance. To er able the dancers to catch breath between ma) be, "Old Dan Tucker" and "The Sword Dance or "Gathering Peas Pods" and "Dosie-Do" ( Kentucky running dance) , Pi Phi Nurse, Ma. jorie Chalmers sang some of the old ballades "Barbara Allen," "No-No," "I Wonder As Wander" with her dulcimer accompaniment. The car came to take the visitor away froi the Fair. With the strains of "Choose Yot Partner and Then Jump Josie" (the last of ti running-set dances) still ringing in her ears, sl left the first Craftsman's Fair. The roar of tI Little Pigeon River drowned out the noise an music but as the highway led away from tl river bed, she could still remember, above a: the rhythmic sound of the beater on the loor And the words of an old Swedish proverb she seen on the blackboard in the school, came mind, "Fly, Shuttle, Fly. Weave Joy and Pleasure to my soul, Weave beauty to my eye." Entre Nous Observes 50th Anniversary Fifty years ago, as the University of Southern California was making its groping start toward becoming the great institution it is today, seven S.C. coeds were making an equally humble beginning. Feeling the need for a closer campus tie, these seven organized a social group which they named Entre Nous now Pi Beta Phi on the Trojan campus. Entre Nous was active continuously from its founding in 1898 (it was in preparatory form as early as 1895, but it wasn't until 1898 that it was a recognized part of campus life) until 1917, when it was chartered as California T chapter of Pi Beta Phi. Members of the local social group were in-itiated into the national sorority, but did allow Entre Nous to die. It has retained its ent. throughout the years, with frequent meetings keep the spirit of Entre Nous alive. This fall Entre Nous celebrated its Gold Anniversary with a giant reunion in Glenda Honor guests were five of the original see founders, while other Entre Nous me bers came from distant places for the celeb tion. In 1917, when Entre Nous had reached maximum point of organization just prior its absorption by Pi Beta Phi it had a me bership of 146. At present, it has 115 meml and 62 of these were in attendance at the Gl dale 50th anniversary celebration. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



