<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr6640351_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Rauch, Harriet Goodsell</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>May 1950</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr6640351_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">May 1950</date>, News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Rauch, Harriet Goodsell</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 350-352</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">40</note>
                        <note type="Folder">2</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 66, Number 4 (May 1950), Pages 350-352.</note>
			<note type="document">arr6640351_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Arrowcraft Shop</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Changing Mission of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity for Women in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1944-1964</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>
                                <item>Weaving</item>
                                <item>Community</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr6640351_0001" seq="01" n="350-351  "/>
       <p>NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON Edited by HARRIET GOODSELL RAUCH, Iowa B rrrettrreaaeaaaaaearaeeatereratearrppeeererueerreapereererrrrrreeeaeerrrprurraeeeeeerrrarrareeaeeerpeeeeemmeae:aeeeteeaeteeereeeeeaeeeeaaaepreeerererereeearreepraaartrarterrrtatrueeeatepterrrrn Arrowcraft Shop Every fall the Settlement School chairmen for the Alumnx clubs and active chapters through-out the country scan the Pi Beta Phi Arrowcraft price and order list. Hand-woven coverlets, afghans, shawls, baby clothes, towels, table linens, scarfs, bags, purses, aprons, and hand-made baskets and brooms make a tempting array for the purchasers. And Pi Phis and Pi Phi friends know that when the order arrives, the display of beautiful hand-made articles will represent the most meticulous skill in design, form and color of our Pi Phi craftsmen. Aunt Lizzie Reagan, one of our first weavers and one of the most picturesque characters in all Eastern Tennessee, once said as she looked at a favorite skirt: "I have seen that Balmoral runthrough the fields on the back of a lamb. I've seen it heaped up in sheared wool and plucked cotton. I've seen it suck up the color from the juice of mountain herbs and berries." In those words, Aunt Lizzie, while spinning threads and yarns into clothes for herself and children from wool and cotton that she had grown, expressed some of the satisfaction found in her handicraft. We (unlike Aunt Lizzie) find satisfaction in the privilege of handling and owning these lovely things from Arrowcraft and in realizing the financial help that our purchases mean to the people of the Gatlinburg community. The Settlement School has featured and pre-served the traditional weaving patterns and our Mrs. Snow and Miss Tina with their helpers in the shop. 350 THE MAY ARROW 351 weaving designers (in addition to their multiple duties in lavishing great care and affection into the supervision of the work of the weavers) have created new designs to add to the old. Just this year, Miss Tina has given us the distinctive Queen Anne and Lace Weave patterns in the linens and some of the traditional in her own Scotch background has blended into the scarfs and ties. There are no more Aunt Lizzies left to us but their philosophy, their culture, their pride in their way of life and work as well as the pleasant anecdotes surrounding their lives have survived. Fortunately for us and the preservation of the craft, there were mothers and grandmothers who showed their daughters and granddaughters how to warp up a loom and turn out the linsey-woolsey and patterns of olden times. Now, Miss Tina tells us that there are more young people weaving than at any time in the history of the.Setdement School. Among the young weavers, there are the Bales sisters: Gertrude, Beulah and Glenna. Gertrude graduated from the Pi Phi school. Miss Tina says, 'she's a very adaptable weaver. She learned weaving at the Pi Phi school and weaves doilies and doll mats. Her doll-matweaving is quite a feat. She weaves five mats at a time side-by-side on a loom." Beulah is one our best and weaves the evening purses and cotton purses on the same warp so that they can be interchangeable. Glenna worked with our much-loved Miss Georgic at the Mountain View Hotel and now weaves some of our finest table linen. The Maples family, according to Miss Tina, is our "weavingest family." The mother and seven daughters weave for Arrow Craft. When they started with us, they asked if they could be assured of regular work so that they could depend on it. After this was promised, they bought a house back up in the hills and reserved one room for their five looms. They are linen weavers and good linen weavers are mighty hard to find and develop because of the various types of linens. The Maples family do all of our exquisite lace weave towels as well as our Greek lace doilies. Miss Tina taught them how to do these patterns. Alice Maples drew the largest single check ever given out by Arrow Craft-$163.50 for one delivery of Queen Anne Lace guest towels. One of the seven Maples girls is helping her GI husband through college with her Arrow Craft earnings. Mary L. and Matt Ownby (who have made the beautiful chairs for over 33 years) have two daughters who weave for us. Another young weaver cares for an invalid sister and a niece Lulu May Ogle at Her Spinning Wheel through her work on the sturdy red, yellow, green, blue, black and white pot-holders. May Ogle, a young mother with several children, is one of Pi Phi's speediest weavers. We can never give enough credit to the weavers of the older generation who still work for the Arrow Craft Shop. Izora Keener, Myrtle Connor, Lulu May Ogle, Cora Morton and Mollie Moore comprise part of this group. Izora is one of our best wool weavers and has been weaving constantly for Pi Phi for 29 years. She takes great pride in her work (and, properly so) and weaves the yardage for the baby garments and neckties. We know her besti. how-ever, by the rainbow shawls (we now call them "Izora shawls") . Her 88-year-old mother ties the fringe on each shawl. Myrtle Connor, Izora's sister-in-law, has been weaving for Pi Phi since 1925 and at the present time is our only weaver on baby material. Lulu May Ogle and Cora Morton weave cover-lets. Lulu May was Arrow Craft's first coverlet weaver. Mrs. Morton, mother of ten children of whom seven are weavers, has woven the Whig Rose pattern for thirteen years. Mollie Moore and her family two daughters and a daughter-in-law are also Whig Rose weavers. Mollie has been weaving for us since 1926. Day after day, a succession of weavers, young and old, come to Miss Tina's weaving room to receive material, to get help in working out new patterns or to collect their pay checks for their finished work. In writing of Arrowcraft too much emphasis </p>
      <pb ref="arr6640351_0002" seq="02" n="352-353  "/>
       <p>THE MAY ARROW cannot be placed on the elements involved in the , merchandising: marketing, distribution, transportation, building up of stock during slack months, tagging, compiling yearly price lists, selling and greeting the public in the shop. All of these duties are carried on under the most able direction ,of Mrs. Ethel Snow, Iowa Gamma Pi Phi. She has successfully guided the work at Arrow-craft since 1934 and knows the problems well through her constant association with them. Part of her service consists of maintaining a happy relationship among her helpers. There is Mrs. McCutcheon who manages the attractive shop in the Mountain View Hotel. Lura Ownby, whose mother was one our first weavers, came as a helper to Arrow Craft in 1934. Lois Christopher, Hattie Trentham and Edna Cook assist with selling, wrapping, tagging and packing and Hattie's daughter, Mildred, helps during the summer months. So the essentials of weaving, designing and selling are all linked indispensably. And every Pi Beta Phi can feel a rare pride in the craftsmanship developed, displayed and sold at Arrowcraft Shop or through . the Settlement School sales. Honor for Dr. Leona aumgart er, Kansas Alpha "Many thousands of children and mothers throughout the Nation will benefit increasingly from the action we are now taking," Oscar R. Ewing, Federal Security Administrator, predicted in inducting into office Dr. Leona Baumgartner, as Associate Chief of the Children's Bureau. Serving under Katharine F. Lenroot, Chief of the Children's Bureau, Dr. Baumgartner, who has been Assistant Commissioner of Health in New York City, will have special responsibility for the Bureau's health services. Dr. Baumgartner comes to the Children's Bureau after 12 years of service in the New York City Health Department, including work as a District Health Officer, and as director for 8 years of that Department's' Bureau of Child Hygiene. Trained as a pediatrician, Dr. Baumgartner has been on the pediatric staff of New York Hospital, is Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, Public Health and Preventive Medicine at Cornell Medical College, and is licensed to practice medicine in New York State. Kansas University Alumni gave Dr. Baumgartner their Distinguished Service Award fora fellow alumna in 1947, and she won the American Design Award for creative work in designs for living for children in 1945. At the invitation of the French Ministry of Health, Dr. Baumgartner spent some time in that country in 1945 as an advisor on child health. A member of the Executive Board of the American Public Health Association and chair-man of its Committee on Child Health, she is also a member of the American Academy of Pediatrics and of the American Pediatric Society. In addition to her medical degree, which she obtained at Yale University, Dr. Baumgartner has a Ph.D. in public health, also from Yale, and an M.A. in bacteriology and immunology from the University of Kansas. At Yale, she held the Sterling and University fellowship for research; later she spent a year of research at the Kaiser-Wilhelm Institute in Munich, Germany. Before engaging in public health work, she had several years' experience in high school and university teaching. Born in Chicago, Illinois, Dr. Baumgartner is the wife of Nathaniel M. Elias, a consulting engineer. --4 Margaret. Malitz Texas Beta Quill Queen and ROTC Queen Cathy Altepeter Missouri Beta Sweetheart of Sigma Chi Pat Clawson Utah Alpha Colonel of Air Force ROTC Sponsors Barbara Boonstra Utah .Alpha RO'I`L Sponsor at Utah Note unusual number of Queens from Utah Alpha </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



