<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr6620167_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Rauch, Harriet Goodsell</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>December 1949</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr6620167_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">December 1949</date>, News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Rauch, Harriet Goodsell</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 167-170</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">40</note>
                        <note type="Folder">2</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 66, Number 2 (December 1949), Pages 167-170.</note>
			<note type="document">arr6620167_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">A Day at School</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Changing Mission of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity for Women in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1944-1964</item>
                                <item>Education</item>
                                <item>Arts</item>
                                <item>Physical Education</item>
                                <item>Extracurricular activities</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr6620167_0001" seq="01" n="166-167  "/>
       <p>166 THE DECEMBER ARROW mas party and gave them to the pledges. A province president on the West coast ordered a set as a present for a newly-chartered chapter, and a national officer bought a group of five as a gift to Holt House. A Texas house mother is a regular customer; she buys replicas of Penelope, the practical bell ringer, for wedding gifts. They are both appropriate and appealing worked into a table decoration for a party, whether clustered about a bouquet of wine and blue carnations or wired to a "tree" drifted over with cotton batting clouds. The Kansas City Alumni Club sells them at $5 per figurine, including all postal fees and a handsome wine and blue gift box. The price isa special one, providing a profit far less in percentage than that of professional retailers. The angels first were sold at $4 apiece; this price tag was discarded when it was found the project was barely breaking even.) Mrs. Howard Craw-ford is chairman of the project and is filling orders at her home at 505 West 38th Street, Kansas City 2, Missouri. She points out there is a premium of one angel free to any Pi Phi sending in an order for twenty or more. Scarcely an order goes out from Kansas City that a reorder is not received in return. As one delighted purchaser aptly put it, "They're right out of this world !" -* 4 Four Pi Phis were among the candidates for Miss America in the contest in Atlantic City last summer, among them Trudi Germi, Illinois Z, who was Miss Illinois, and Carol Quinn, South Dakota A, who represented her state. Names of the other two girls have not been reported to the ARROW. -* -* At the fourteenth national convention of Mortar Board held at Breezy Point Lodge in Minnesota from June 21 through 25, there were nine members of Pi Beta Phi present. Eight were official delegates and Mrs. Roth was the Acting Secretary. Since the total official delegation numbered eighty-one, we thought that it would be of interest to all Pi Beta Phis to know that such a good percentage were members of our fraternity. Standing from left to right are: Joan Pacey, Illinois Beta Delta, Mrs. Esther Bowman Roth, Montana Alpha, Nancy Fraser, Indiana Epsilon. Seated left to right are Marjory Jacobsen, North Dakota Alpha, Bonnie Greene, Arizona Alpha, Joyce Atchison, Michigan Beta, Marjorie Wagner, Ohio Zeta, Betty Bruce Stake, Missouri Beta, and Vera Stenger, Missouri Alpha. a.taasaas ***** NEWTS FROM LITTLE PIGEON Edited by HARRIET GOODSELL RAUCH, Iowa B A Day at School Seven bicycles were parked near the door and a brown dog of doubtful parentage was resting on the cinder driveway waiting for his master. As we came up the steps, there was that drone of voices, the noise that comes from open windows of most any elementary school. We were visiting the Pi Beta Phi Schools in Gatlinburg. We walked into a second and third grade room because the door stood open and we could see six vacant seats. Miss Latham, the teacher, was giving reading-readiness tests to the second graders and comprehension tests to the third graders. After greeting us, she said,"I have six absentees, all boys. It's a seasonal disease." We _pondered over an unusual epidemic that affected boys only. She laughed, "Oh, nothing serious. Fishing season opened to-day." It was May 16th and we noticed that it was bare-foot season for some of the boys, too. The walls were plastered with individual reading records. Bird stickers were used instead of stars to mark accomplishment. The reading tests continued and we were quietly informed that the results would point up certain weaknesses, for example: the need for emphasis on paragraph comprehension, more emphasis on A Corner of the High School Building 167 </p>
      <pb ref="arr6620167_0002" seq="02" n="168-169  "/>
       <p>168 THE DECEMBER ARROW A Gatlinburg group watching the potter word meanings, emphasis on word recognition technique. Since it was an important test day, we moved on to the fourth grade. There were forty en-rolled in this grade seven absentees because of the `fishing epidemic.' On three walls, in addition to the `Books I Have Read' and the `Books Are Friends' charts, there were elaborate health study charts and black-board exhibits of protective and energy foods. We were just in time for geography class from the blue-backed book, `Journeys Through Many Lands.' The upper halves of the blackboards were covered with a series of murals called `Singing Wheels' beginning with the stage coach continuing through to the river-boat. These had been made by the children and it was creditable pastel chalk work for fourth graders. After brushing up a bit on our fourth grade geography, we wandered into Miss Cardwell's first grade room. Her thirty-seven youngsters were divided into four groups for recitation and drill, grouped according to ability. She was drilling nine children with some flash cards of her own making when we entered. The study program for the year was in line (in a way)with the Tennessee State Conservation program study of trees and leaves of trees in the fall and winter. In the spring, study was devoted to birds. While we were there, they were reading about or drawing or coloring some of the useful birds: the indigo bunting, yellow warbler, oriole, cardinal and flicker. The good old re-ward system was evidenced by stars affixed to individual reading and spelling charts. One little red-headed, freckle-faced boy, dressed in `spanking' clean overalls was leaning over his desk directing the coloring done by a pretty little blonde girl. He was satisfied only now and then with her technique but she followed his directions without question. He was blissfully happy to let her do the work while he gave the directions a budding executive, no doubt. The local parent Teacher Association runs the cafeteria in the basement of our much over-crowded elementary school. About two-hundred-and-forty children have lunch there every day and because of the lack of space are fed in four shifts. Some sixty children are given their lunch free. The others pay fifteen cents per lunch. The cramped quarters were made as THE DECEMBER ARROW 169 attractive as possible. Hand-made pottery bowls filled with arrangements of wild honey-suckle and field-grown daisies were in the centers of the bench-like tables. Steaming and delicious-looking corn pudding, fresh string beans, compote of dried peaches and prunes, peanut butter sandwiches and milk made up the luncheon for that day. After lunch we visited Sue Kelly's third grade. These youngsters were studying mountain birds from material furnished by the Tennessee Conservation department. The children had made their own booklets, writing a story about each bird describing his color, his nest, the eggs, his song, his winter and summer home. In a prong of the tulip tree just outside the window of this room, a pair of robins had built a nest in the early spring. These third-graders had watched and protected the nest at play-time until the babies had flown. Since 'Gatlinburg is situated so near the Cherokee Indian Reservation, the winter project had been an Indian one. So our trip through the elementary school was not unlike a trip through any elementary school except that because of Pi Phi help the program offered is so much richer than the County alone could possibly offer. Among other things (as Pi Phis know) we provide the Art and Craft teacher for the elementary and High school. We are very proud indeed of the work our Fay Van Roekel is doing in the school and community. We visited her sixth grade art class. Thirty-seven boys and girls were working with charcoal that day. She had begun charcoal work with them in the fall when they used pine trees as models which gave her the opportunity to stress light and dark contrasts and to insist on free easy strokes with no fussy details. By May these sixth graders had progressed to posed models. She used three models. that period: a boy swinging a baseball bat, a boy shadow-boxing, a girl hoeing in an imaginary garden. She said, "Now five minutes for the first pose. Work fast. Remember that professional models are well paid. Make your strokes light. Draw quickly. Draw with a sweep with charcoal. Sketch in good strong lines. Then shade. Always keep in mind the possibilities of charcoal." There was rapt interest and complete absorption in the work and the only sound heard was the sweep of the charcoal on the paper. Fay's classes are all carrying on various projects at the craft house. She told the committee that she was very pleased with the equipment provided by Pi Phi but her main problem is lack of space, storage space for projects andequipment, the crying need for our elementary school from all sides. High school was in its near-graduation time confusion. The senior class was getting ready for its annual trip that their hard-earned money Nancy Holmes, Illinois Zeta, is the new assistant to the Director of the Settlement School. had made possible. They made this money by selling candy and cold drinks at games, selling Christmas cards and wrappings, selling ads for the Senior play and ticket sale receipts from their play. Pi Phi coach Joe Johnson was taking them to historic Williamsburg and including a visit to the Navy and Marine bases at Nor-folk. Coach Johnson and Mrs. Mines (our Assistant director at the Settlement School) had been co-sponsors of the 1949 senior class. Mrs. Armstrong, the Pi Phi music teacher, having just finished a successful grade school operetta, was polishing glee club and chorus work for the graduation festivities. Mrs. Lighter, the English teacher and librarian was checking over final poetry reports for the year. Every room in the building was teeming with winding-up activities. As we walked from the school, it was after-noon recess time. The girls were playing 'hop-scotch.' Two soft-ball games were in full swing in the field behind Arrowcraft building. There was no professional call such as, `in comes the pitch. It's high and out-side for ball one' but the excitement and din seemed almost as deafening as a world series event. As we started toward Teachers Cottage, Pi Phi nurse Chal mers drove up in her car and called, "hop in </p>
      <pb ref="arr6620167_0003" seq="03" n="170-171  "/>
       <p>170 THE DECEMBER ARROW and ride up to the glades with me. I'm taking a boy home. No real damage but he has a `shiner' coming up. He was hit in the eye with the soft ball." We rode away with Marjorie, waved to Arlie, Pi Phi handi-man, who was plowing potatoes in the field behind Health Center and noticedtwo weavers who were going into Arrowcraft with their arms laden with finished weaving. How proud we can be of the school-health-craft work at our Settlement School, all made possible by the continued help of Pi Phis from every part of the country. State Mother for .Massachusetts WAS a wonderful thrill for a Malden woman, lying in considerable pain in Mal-den Hospital, to learn that she had been selected as State Mother for Massachusetts to compete for the title of "American Mother of 1949." Mrs. Ethel Piper, Massachusetts A, known affectionately as "mother" by scores of young men and women she has aided and by children she has brought up, could scarcely believe the news. So doubtful was she of the honor that she had her sister, Edith Piper, confirm it from the Golden Rule Foundation, who made the selection. Sixty-five years old, Mrs. Avery had lain immobile in a bed in Malden Hospital since she fractured her collar-bone in the garden of her home 10 days earlier. (Date of this clipping not given ALC) Mrs. Avery, whose husband is Alfred H. Avery, has two grown-up children of her own, Dr. Harlow Fuller Avery of Milwaukee Chil Ethel Piper Avery dren's Hospital, and Faith Avery, a graduate of Syracuse University, who is working in the medical branch of the University. But Mrs. Avery has mothered children other than her own. In her home, at present, are two British youngsters, brother and sister, Elizabeth Denstad, 18, and David, 16, who came to her during the London blitz and stayed on. Stu-dents from China, India and Hawaii, as well as from Europe, have also stayed with her and been aided in education for Christian Leader-ship. In order to do this, Dr. and Mrs. Avery established a fund called the Parshad Holding Corporation, the first name of which means "Gift of God," to help young people through college. Born in Boston and educated in schools here, she received her A.B. degree from Boston University in 1906 and then taught in schools in Kittery, Maine, Attleboro and Lexington. After her marriage in 1913, she and her husband further developed their interest in young people and worked closely with the American Youth Foundation and International Council of Religious Education, giving many scholarships though these organizations. Her husband, co-partner with her in these enterprises, is a well-known Methodist lay-man, scientist and industrialist. He is a retired executive of the duPont Company and chair-man of the North American Holding Co. He planned his life to devote the first 25 years to getting the best education possible, the next 15 years to making a fortune, and thereafter to retire and devote his fortune to philanthropy. Mrs. Avery modestly cites her husband to illustrate what they wanted out of life and what they wanted to give. And they have done both. In 1946 Mr. Avery was named winner of the national Russell Colgate distinguished service citation by 1261 laymen and women of the United States and Canada. Like many people who have done so much for others Mrs. Avery is publicly shy, but she does not disguise her happiness in being selected "State Mother of Massachusetts." iminnoglommunninnolmifimumnumnimlluHHH1111mmmmmmiumnolmlimmunnninannumnumnuluuninmunlomninniunnninnunnuuntunnnummininnnumnlunm linugumnutminumimulnunul FROM PI PHI PENS Edited by MARY ELIZABETH BARNETTE, Ohio A PHYLLIS CRAWFORD, Let's Go, Henry Holt and Company, 73 pp. Dedicated for "Joan and Peter," this lively book should be the delight of all the Joans and Peters whose Pi Phi mothers learn of its existence. These mothers, and dads too, may find to their joy that it has a salutary effect upon those small beings whose clamorings of "Do hurry" and "Let's go" are anathema to the slower moving adult. However, the skill of Phyllis Crawford, the author, has seen to it that the moral is neither too serious nor too obvious to spoil the pleasure of five to eight-year-old readers. "Let's Go" will intrigue and stimulate their imaginations as well as encourage their vocabulary. It would be a pity to destroy all the suspense by revealing the story in its entirety, but a little of it will guide parents in making their book purchases this year. Tom, the hero of the tale, is, not unlike many of his contemporaries, always in a hurry, ever urging his parents on, pulling up his carrots as soon as their tops appear above ground, and never walking if he can run instead. It seems not at all unbelievable, therefore, when a patch of quicksand takes him to the land of "Quick" where everyone rushes and everything grows big and fast. There Tom meets Mr. Long, whose name aptly describes him and who uses exceedingly long words to match. Here, in a reversal of the usual state of affairs, Tom finds it hard work to keep up with everyone else. How he gets back home and what effect his experience has upon him you will find in your own reading of "Let's Go." AUTHOR INTEREST: "'Hello, The Boat!,' " "Last Semester," "Second Shift," The Secret Brother," and "The Blot: Little City Cat" are among the other juvenile books written by Phyllis Crawford, Virginia A. "Let's Go" is the first book this native of Little Rock and now resident of New York has done since 1943, for she took time out to do editorial work. She writes that it is her first attempt at fantasy, but the reader soon discovers that that has not prevented the job from being well done. AGNES WRIGHT SPRING, The Cheyenne and Black Hills Stage and Express Routes, The Arthur H. Clark Company, 418 pp. Greeted by critics as "a book for all lovers of western Americana to keep" and "not only an amazingly good research job but a colorful and vivid piece of writing," Mrs. Spring's latest study of earlier days in the West covers the Black Hills' gold rush period of between 1874 and the mid 1880's. It is not a Work of fiction, and, in fact, Mrs. Spring spent much time in the territory and on the trails, retracing these early stage routes and sifting the fiction from the fact so as to produce a completely authoritative book. Despite the fact, however, that the book is a reference one primarily, its subject material makes it an adventuresome one to read. This is because in addition to recording the precise details of the various routes from Cheyenne into the Black Hills, she also includes the human element and reports on the activities and roman-tic experiences of the stage drivers, owners and messengers in their encounters with swollen rivers, Indian attacks, blizzards and hold-ups by the scores of bandits who preyed upon those traveling the route. There are, in addition, plentiful 'illustrations, a fold out map of the routes prepared by the author, an extensive bibliography, and numerous appendices. AUTHOR INTEREST: One time editor of the ARROW, Wyoming A's Mrs. Spring is in deed' the proper person to write a book such as this, for being the daughter of A pioneer Colorado and Wyoming stage owner, she knows the subject from first hand observation. After growing up on a Wyoming ranch, she attended the University of Wyoming and following graduation studied journalism at Columbia. She's the former state librarian and historian of Wyoming and has written several other books which have been reviewed here. FLORENCE ZACHARIE ELLIS NicHoLLs, But-ton Hand Book; privately published, 128 p.p. This is a book written for a specialized audience, antique button collectors, but even to the layman it is evident that Mrs. Nicholls has 171 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



