<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr6520205_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Rauch, Harriet Goodsell</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>December 1948</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr6520205_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">December 1948</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Rauch, Harriet Goodsell</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 205-207</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">40</note>
                        <note type="Folder">1</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 65, Number 2 (December 1948), Pages 205-207.</note>
			<note type="document">arr6520205_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">The New Health Center</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Changing Mission of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity for Women in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1944-1964</item>
                                <item>Health care</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr6520205_0001" seq="01" n="204-205  "/>
       <p>scellaneous Honors Dorothy Shaner Alberta Alpha Blue Stocking Club Beverly Stickel Illinois Eta odince Improvement Award NEWS FROM LITTLE, PIGEON Edited by HARRIET GOODSELL RAUCH, Iowa B 01!11$1111113IIIIIIIIIIIIMOIIII lllllll lllll llllll 1113111I.IIIIIIIIIIIIIIIII311111.111.11111.1.111.1.1.111111.1113131111111t The New Health Center Our first nurse for the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Phyllis Higinbotham, Ontario A, went to Gatlinburg in 1920. There was great beauty in the Smokies; the brilliant and variegated show of fall colors in October icicles hanging from the trees transforming the mountains in winter; the procession of spring flowers and flowering trees beginning with the first wood violets and wind flowers in March through the dogwood season and the pink mountain laurel to the flaming azaleas of May ; the white rhododendron blooming until late in July and the ever-changing white clouds hovering over the peaks of the foot-hills. But mid all of this beauty "Miss Phyllis" found great need for health and emergency medical assistance. There were no doctors or nurses within a radius of many miles and health and sanitary standards were unknown. Nurse Phyllis had no clinic, no hospital, no office, but carried her clinic, hospital and office in her brown saddle-bag as she rode over the almost impassable roads on her horse, "Lady." She served the people out of her saddle-bag for two years until the old Ogle Cottage was remodeled into a combination clinic, hospital and nurse's living quarters. Our first Jennie Nicol Memorial Hospital was dedicated on May 8, 1922. "Miss Phyllis" in addition to answering her many calls, taught hygiene, taught a class of mid-wives, examined the school children for nose, throat, eye or general health troubles and in her six years of service there built the Ogle Cottage into a model rural health center. Since then the new highway has been built through Gatlinburg and the Great Smoky National Park has been completed. Our health program has outgrown the little Ogle Cottage. Our present nurse, Marjorie Chalmers, in her report of last year said, "The modern tendency for education and prevention in medicine is quite apparent in comparing the work of the past fifteen years. Typhoid and diphtheria inoculations have not increased much, while vaccinations for small-pox, forbidden in some homes in 1933, have trebled in number. Serum for whooping cough is almost universal now. Field visits have dropped nearly one-third butoffice calls are up two and one-half times. In 1933 1,600 pupil inspections were made and last year there were 4,180. When we stop to consider there are nearly seven hundred students in the district served .by the Health Center and nearly as many younger children, we realize the importance of education. Regular Friday afternoon well baby clinics were held throughout the year with special ones added from time to time. Community health is a community problem. It is bigger than any one individual or any one organization. It re-quires leadership but more than that it must have the approval and support of the community. Through the many years of service, the Fraternity has supplied the leaders and community support has grown steadily. It should be a source of pride and satisfaction to know we have the cooperation of individuals and civic organizations. Without it, we would be, to a certain extent, interlopers. With it, we can go far in service to humanity." This past June, nurse Marjorie Chalmers moved into our newly built and completed health center. Funds for this building came largely from the estate of Dr. W. F. 'Garshwiler of Indianapolis, Indiana; $1,000 from Washington, D.C., A; and California Alpha's contribution. Dr. Garshwiler's contribution was given in memory of his wife, Florence Province Garshwiler, who was an Indiana B and a loyal supporter of all Indiana chapters as well as the Indianapolis Alumnae Club. Washington, D.C., Alpha's contribution was given in memory of Mabel Scott Brown, a former D.C. A II . California Alpha's gift was part of the money which the chapter had left in its funds when the chapter was withdrawn from Leland Stan-ford University because of university action. On July 12, while the Settlement School Committee and Miss Onken were in 'Gatlinburg, the new health center was appropriately dedicated to its broadened health service. The building stands conveniently on the main highway near Arrowcraft Shop. It is built of hand-hewn, native, white-pine shingles. It has field-stone trim and a grey slate roof. The architecture corresponds to that of Arrowcraft 205 </p>
      <pb ref="arr6520205_0002" seq="02" n="206-207  "/>
       <p>THE DECEMBER ARROW 207 and, in time, the shingles will take on the same lovely grey sheen as those of Arrowcraft. The entrance hall, office, and class-room are finished with pine walls. The first-aid room and clinic are finished in standard white. The windows of the three former rooms are hung with hand-woven draperies, made by Arrowcraft weavers. The panels on the windows at either side of the front door were designed by Mary Elizabeth Sullivan of Eugene, Oregon, one of the staff of the summer work-shop. Mrs. Eleanor Simms of Gatlinburg gave the pen and lamp for the desk in the office. There was a new air-guide, a gift of Mrs. Elizabeth Peck, a former director of the school. The many beautiful flowers which brightened all of the rooms for the dedication service came from the gardens of Mr. and Mrs. Elvin Trentham. Gatlinburg friends came to witness the dedication and there were numbers of little folks there who had known "Miss Marjorie" and the old health center well. They had their picture taken and had to be "weighed in" on the scales in the new clinic room. The dedicatory service was very simple. Reverend Blanton gave the invocation. Ruth Barrett Smith, Chairman of the Settlement School Committee, read the Love chapter from the Corinthians. Mrs. Armstrong, our Pi Beta Phi Musical Director, brought nine of her young high school girls who sang "Bless This House." Miss Onken gave an interesting resume of the life of Dr. Jennie M. Nicol, one of the founders of the Fraternity, and one of the first American women to enter the practice of medicine. The old Health Center had been dedicated to Jennie Nicol twenty-five years ago. Becauseof her life of service, the new building will be called `The Jennie Nicol Health Center.' Miss Ruth Dyer, our resident director at the Settlement School, gave a fitting tribute to the interest and painstaking care of the men who had labored on the building. Nurse Chalmers said, "All things considered, I should be at least three times as happy as any one else here tonight. "First, because I am a citizen of Gatlinburg and, as such, have a civic pride in this beautiful building, not only because of its architectural worth, but because of its value to the life and safety of the community. "In the second place, I am proud to be a member of the staff of the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School and to have some small share in the generous and untiring work of the Pi Beta Phi Fraternity. "And, last of all, and greatest of all, in the personal pride and gratitude in so attractive and efficient a center. The old building has served its purpose well. Its doors have ever been. open to the folk of the community, whatever their need. "Together, we have seen much joy and much sorrow. From you I have learned much of kindliness and patience, and the innate goodness of mankind. We have changed from the old to the new building but the spirit of service remains the same and shall so continue so long as the house, itself, shall stand." With the words, "we dedicate this building to the service of mankind," the new Jennie M. Nicol Health Center entered upon its official service in the community of Gatlinburg. 444 Chapter Meetings One of the dangerous tendencies in some fraternities at present is the slighting of ritualistic practices, particularly in the conduct of regular meetings. There are so many things going on in modern college life that there just doesn't seem to be time to do everything and so the old, time-honored chapter meeting suffers. The inflated size of chapters today has contributed to the difficulty to the extent that old chapter halls and meeting places will no longer accommodate the large number of members. "Close communion in the chapter hall" is a mockery and the time for thoughtful programs and discussions doesn't seem to be available. The present tendency, if it is not checked, is certain to change the aspect of the American college fraternity. The fraternity has been a unique institution, combining the features of free masonry, the old-fashioned literary society, the co-operative boarding house, and the social club. Through it all has been a fine idealism and a close cementing of abiding friendships which constant contract with ritualistic ceremonies engendered. A "return to the altar" was never so strongly indicated. Banta's Greek Exchange </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



