<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr6140401_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>LeRoy, Beth Brainard</name></author>
                        <author><name>Wild, Marianne Reid</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>May 1945</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr6140401_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">May 1945</date>, News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>LeRoy, Beth Brainard</name></author>
                        <author><name>Wild, Marianne Reid</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 401-404</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">39</note>
                        <note type="Folder">13</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 61, Number 4 (May 1945), Pages 401-404.</note>
			<note type="document">arr6140401_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Maytime in the Smokies; The Natural Unfolding of our Handcraft Program; Memorial Fund; Gatlinburg Gleanings; Dr. Garshwiler's Bequest</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Changing Mission of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity for Women in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1944-1964</item>
                                <item>Handicraft</item>
                                <item>Summer craft workshop</item>
                                <item>Funding</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr6140401_0001" seq="01" n="400-401  "/>
       <p>THE MAY ARROW ,f the word, besides the actual administrathe company. Each company has a First at who is in effect a confidential secretary Company Commander as well as super-f her own office. She has a staff of clerks lake up the pay rolls, muster rolls and apany records and correspondence. (An is never supposed to do any clerical work. alisted girls do that and we sign our "winning the war with our fountain But oh, how responsible we are held e accuracy of everything we sign our to! girls at present are living in 4 different :s belonging to other companies, and ut on subsistence (they mostly do clerical etc., at Headquarters Marine Corps) . difficult situation now, but in another or 2 our own barracks will be completed ey'll have a nice new "house" of their Women Officers' Quarters are just across eet from the Mess Hall. I now "rate" a very nice room of my own and it's comfortable sort of existence. We don't have to fight the Washington mobs very often as practically all our needs are stocked here at our own PX. There's a reasonable amount of social life official parties with much "gold braid" in evidence many private parties much too many at times, considering the long hours a company officer works (from 7:20 A.M., personal inspection of the troops, to 5 and some-times 8 P.m., with just time enough out for chow) . Occasionally we get a Saturday of and either head for New York or spend the day sleeping depending on the state of fatigue, or what enticements are offered elsewhere. Unanimously, our goal is to do as good a job as possible, whatever our assignments, in order to get the whole thing over. You're doing the same thing back at home, without benefit of uniform, subject to a few less regulations. Any-way, we're all working toward the same end, and may the inhabitants of the entire world eventually do the same. var Planning ment prepared by Dean A. R. Warnock at lest of the editor of the Sigma Rho Bulletin, publication of the Illinois chapter of Beta 1ccessful merchant looks aheatif..io 'see what rs' future wants will likely 13'e and then al) to meet their needs. Thus people say of e: "You can get it at Brown's." 's a realistic way of suggesting what a fra-:hapter could do in planning to meet post-war r demands, these customers being students, seats and society in general. If it has a large of customers to choose from, it can be in a to select a preferred membership. fraternity's pre-war stock in trade admittedly it to select from the best, and, in as far as should be stocked again in the post-war ion of activities. The following items, some of !w, seem to me to be in customers' minds, in-Uncle Sam's, for post-war specifications of -aining in fraternities: bystcal fitness, for peacetime living and, as an the hole, for military preparedness. There is I reason why pride in physical fitness of mem-)uld not become as much a chapter tradition in social fitness, for instance. This does not ootball ruggedness and size. . . It means ordinary good health and vigor, plus intellitention to various organs and accessories of y. It involves encouragement of physical exerroper diet, reasonable habits in living and and periodical health examinations.. All .e within the range of chapter controls. urposeful study that is, study consciously ed with its later use. . . . The chapter should ally keep before each member the query: are you getting your mind ready to do ?" ractice of democracy and democratic skills in business and chapter house living. Here is anideal small-scale practicum for training in making democracy work; and there is going to be much popular insistence that American youth receive such training as a form of defense of our way of life. 4. Training in self-discipline this means training which will automatically create habits of discipline over one's self and one's capacities. Both military and industrial agencies will be putting on this pressure; it is a demand for an end to the sloppy, irresponsible, devil-may-care behavior common to many fraternity members, and other students, in pre-war years. A well-regulated chapter-house routine exacting barracks-like attention to conduct, manners, neatness in dress and in rooms, reliability, punctuality and honesty can provide excellent training without taking all the fun out of life. In this respect a chapter house should be like the framework of a mold into which is poured wet concrete, not jelly or mush, so that later, when the mold is removed, the product will of itself keep the permanent form and characteristics of the mold. That is done by habit forming, day by day exercises. 5. Citizenship information, particularly in the form of chapter discussion programs and guests' nights, in which current affairs are discussed and digested, much as football, movies and girl topics are ordinarily discussed and digested. Society is going to demand more of this at the youth level; sheer patriotism demands more of it at the fraternity man's level; before the war, fraternity members were often peculiarly ignorant of such matters. If these items can be added to the traditional personality and character training offered in the past by fraternities so successfully, and to the idealism in the ritual, and the comfort and recreational privileges of Beta houses, and if the chapter can get a reputation of this kind, then customers, students, parents and society will say: "The fraternity house is a good training place for a young citizen." And that is all that needs to be said to bring prosperity to the house in the practical, realistic post-war years. NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON Edited by BETH BRAINARD LEROY, Massachusetts A Maytime in the Smokies Come to the Great Smokies to fill your May baskets. There are fifteen hundred species of wildflowers and nearly as many ferns from which to choose. Each glade and glen reveals new "pretties" as Mother Nature is prodigal with her treasures. Rich purple violets, graceful trillium, white fringe-petaled phacelia and trailing arbutus half hidden under the leaves and adding fragrance to a breeze already ladened with fresh outdoor odors ; snowdrop and anemone, hepatica and Indian pink grow in great profusion. On the mountainsides the trees and bush are burgeoning; the leucotho or dog hobble, the silverbell, laurel, azalea and rhododendron. The dogwood, white and lovely against the green of the forests, vies with the trees planted on the highway by the Gatlin Garden Club, several years ago, and which are now in full blossom. Even the birds feel the enchantment of spring and the robin, thrush, scarlet tanager and cardinal are bursting into song which is enhanced by the magical rhythm of the trickling brooks and waterfalls. The whole section is attune as the shuttle of life weaves back and forth, blending materials and color into a matchless pattern. Here in Nature's garden are motifs galore for our weavers and here are untouched stores and sources of supply for creative craftsmen. Here again in Gatlinburg, Pi Beta Phi starts this summer a new project which forges a new link in its chain of service. The Natural Unfolding of Our Handcraft Program Ever since those early days of the Pi Beta Phi School in Gatlinburg when it became necessary to bring down the looms from the rafters in the cabins and to revive the art of weaving to meet an economic need, there has been a gradual unfolding of a handcraft pro-gram. First there were only a few weavers, older women who had learned from their grand-mothers old patterns and designs which they hadused from colonial days in their cabin homes. These were used once more by the supervisor of weaving as a basis for other designs and from which to originate new patterns. The supervisor taught new weavers and supervised the work of those who already knew how to weave, setting for all time a standard which each weaver must attain in order to weave Arrowcraft. There are three grades of weavers, learners, apprentices and trained weavers. A learner has had no background of experience in weaving and must begin with the rudiments first of all. Nothing made by a learner is sold at the Arrowcraft Shop. Three per cent of the weavers are learners. Next in the scale come the apprentices. They have had some background of experience and have passed the learners' tests successfully. A well-trained weaver has had well-directed craft instruction and can weave even the most intricate patterns. The weavers of Arrowcraft are all adults and this year one hundred and twenty-three women have woven Arrowcraft. Handcraft has always played a part in the educational department of the Pi Beta Phi School. Sewing was the first art taught in the Home Economics Courses with weaving for the upper classes in the High School. Wood-working has always been popular with the boys. For several years an Arts and Crafts course, made an especial appeal to upper classmen. This was an elective course. Two years ago the development of a larger crafts program than .1-lad ever before been attempted, began to take shape. An Arts and Crafts Course, sponsored by Pi Beta Phi, which should be given to all students in the elementary grades with weaving and wood-working for the high school students, was included in the curriculum. The purpose of the course was to develop in the elementary school children a love of beauty of line and color, and to teach them the use of simple materials close at hand for making articles of utility and decoration. These courses have proven to be of value. For the older students weaving and wood-working have provided a paying hobby, have developed co-ordination of hand and mind so that articles above the average in workmanship have been made, and have prepared the way for future work for 401 </p>
      <pb ref="arr6140401_0002" seq="02" n="402-403  "/>
       <p>THE MAY ARROW craft if the pupil desires to turn his or ent in that direction. old Arrowcraft building has been in use reral years for craft work and a year ago named the Emma Harper Turner Craft and is the nucleus around which the craft center is to be developed. [ now in conjunction with the University nnessee, Pi Beta Phi sponsors a Craft hop for six weeks this summer of 1945, 'r-eight years after the inception of our ay and thirty-three years after the estabnt of the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School for of our Founders. Vision with faith ~ought fulfillment of purpose and this lop is an added link in Pi Beta Phi's chain rice. Dmorial Fund ['he Memorial Fund with gifts in nory of loved ones is being used for vial needs at the Health Center. Please ember to send contributions to Mrs. nk Prouty, 1760 Locust St., Denver, o. Mrs. Prouty will acknowledge your s by a card and will send an engraved l to the family of the person for whom gift is a memorial. Gifts of any size welcomed. Lnburg Gleanings it days at Gatlinburg have put light back le countenances and fight back into the of those who had surrendered to hard stances. Resignation is no longer an )n which cannot be remedied, but hope measure of success with the loom have vl starved minds to the joy of the fulfill-)f some of their dreams. A weaver's day )ng and busy one. One weaver went to craft with her weaving at nine o'clock in )rning. "I've been trifling this morning. L't git up until four-thirty. Then I did. ores and came here with my weaving. ou git to see a baar ? I saw one in my ard this morning. He upset my garbage didn't pay any mind to it. I was fixin' to town." )ther was disturbed that her child could t to school, as she was recuperating from illness. "He's a well-turned child. Hit a chance," she confided. March Mr. and Mrs. Charlie Ogle enter-at the New Gatlinburg Inn in honor of their son, Earl, who had returned from the Pacific areas for a furlough. Friends were present from Maryville, Sevierville and other sections and many Gatlinburg people welcomed the serviceman who had always lived in their midst. A six piece orchestra added to the merriment of the occasion., The Parent-Teacher Association has been very active this winter. The younger mothers took charge of the lunchroom and had excellent results in their planning and cooking. The menus were simple and nourishing and lunches were served promptly to the hungry children. This service is greatly appreciated. Late in January the body of Staff Sergeant Claude Ogle was brought to Gatlinburg for a military funeral and interment. Mr. Ogle's family lived in Gatlinburg many years ago. He married the daughter of Mrs. Giles Reagan. On account of the heavy rains and deep mud, the casket was carried by hand up the steep hillside to the little cemetery where under the shadow of Mt. Le Conte, the military salute was given and his body was laid to rest. Carl Ogle, our farmer, has six hundred chick-ens, many of which are ready to be used as fryers, others are nearly ready for the laying season. Gardens are being planted and plans for a variety of vegetables for the summer have been made so that a succession of succulent peas, corn, tomatoes and beans, standbys for summer menus, will ripen in proper seasons, and lettuce, radishes, spinach and the Swiss chard will mature early. Potatoes and onions have their own places in the garden and Carl is ready for all emergencies, spraying and weeding to the fore. Mrs. Dorothy McWilliams Young, Ohio Alpha, the new music teacher at the school, has al-ready made a fine place for herself with the mountain people. She has entered heartily into her work, has tested the voices of all the grade school children and has graded them accordingly. The best singers in each class form the choir for that particular grade and sit in special seats for the music period. Mrs. Young visits each grade twice a week, has a Glee Club in the High School and has two assemblies each week. Her use of two radio-victrolas makes it possible to achieve music appreciation from a new angle. Records of fine music are especially needed for this valuable instruction. A letter from Gatlinburg gives this special paragraph, "Mrs. Young's ability is unquestioned and besides this, she is a lovely person to know." Good craft reference books bought with craft funds are available to students and help crys THE MAY ARROW 403 tallize their ideas and inspire further work. Other books are selected from the regional library and access to them is given to all craft students. Miss Petrie shows posters, dolls and weaving made by her pupils this year and Mr. Carl Huskey has an increasing number of articles made under his supervision. Pi Beta Phis, have you sent in your application to teach at the Settlement School this fall? What is the "quality of your contact" with the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School ? Dr. Garshwiler's Bequest By Marianne Reid Wild, Assistant to G.V.P. A bequest of two thousand dollars to the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School and one seventh of the remainder of his estate after other bequests have been taken care of are the generous gifts of Dr. William P. Garshwiler of Indianapolis, Indiana. Dr. Garshwiler was born in Johnson County, Indiana, and strangely enough was named in honor of the man who was eventually to become his father-in-law, William Province. He at-tended Franklin College where he became a member of 'cl) 0 and was graduated from Indiana University Medical School. He c'ame to be recognized as an outstanding surgeon and gynecologist. He married Florence Province, who was born and raised in the same community and who became the tenth initiate of Indiana Beta Chap-ter of Pi Beta Phi. Mrs. Garshwiler's nieces the daughters of Oran Province became members of Indiana A in recent years. They are Florence Province Dyer of Indianapolis and Julia Province Quinn of New York City, at present living in Maryland where her husband is now stationed, in army service. Still a younger daughter, Mary Elizabeth, is attending boarding school at Tudor Hall for Girls in Indianapolis. The brother of these three girls and son of Oran Province, Dr. William B. Province, is a Major with Patton's army in an Army Medical Unit on the western front. Mrs. Garshwiler had another brother who never married. Everyone was conscious of Mrs. Garshwiler's loyalty and devotion to the Fraternity. When I first came here to live, hers was among the first names I learned as she was always active in the affairs of the club. I think Pi Phis knew Dr. Garshwiler almost as well as his wife forhe shared her interests. Their home was frequently opened for meetings of the Club. He would be on hand to greet the guests and when meeting time arrived he quietly disappeared and when the guests were leaving he appeared again to take them on a tour of their garden "Florence Province Garshwiler, Indiana B, in whose honor the Garshwiler Loan Fund was created at Indiana University. and see them to their cars. Mrs. Garshwiler was a regular convention attendant. Although Dr. Garshwiler never went along, her room upon arrival was filled with flowers and his enormous boxes of candy were "looked forward to" features of convention. In recent years they spent their winters in Florida and they stopped at the Settlement School en route. Four friends accompanied them on their first trip. They were all Pi Phis and they purchased many items at Arrowcraft. Shortly after Mrs. Garshwiler's death, Dr. Garshwiler told the alumni of Indiana B that if there was an interest and some money forth-coming from the alumnae that he would give one thousand dollars to establish a loan fund for members of the fraternity at Indiana in memory of Mrs. Garshwiler. The result was that the alumnae raised such a substantial sum that Dr. Garshwiler doubled his contribution. The fund is administered by the University. Its present total is $3,175.00. Mrs. Garshwiler's interests during college were chemistry and Pi Beta Phi. During her_ </p>
      <pb ref="arr6140401_0003" seq="03" n="404-405  "/>
       <p>THE MAY ARROW life her social interests centered in She reorganized and became the first in 1909 of the Women's Study Club. a charter member of the local Tri hapter a state-wide philanthropic or-n. She was always active in the Pi Phi Club in both Franklin and Indian.-d up to the time that Panhellenic rules alumnae participation, she took part in :ng activities of Indiana A. :ended the Tabernacle Christian Church lin and from time to time gave finan-;tance to needy students studying for stry of the Christian Church. She was re in the women's organizations of the as a member of the Indianapolis chap-AUW. At the time this group became d in Franklin she was not as well and right Before Initiation s the night before initiation, and the were being brought in one by one to it pledge mothers tell them just what hould mean to them. The only light in n came from the fireplace where the burning low. One of the girls was lightly apart from the rest, and as she Ito the fire, her thoughts turned back ight before she was initiated. nspiring words came back to her now. host as though she were reliving those when her pledge mother began to sorrow's the day you've been waiting for m just as happy as you are to be able )me you into Pi Phi. I'm sure you'll 'De as happy about it in the next few I have been. Believe me, I'm positive will mean as much to you as it does to .e Pi Phi into your heart its marvelous is and ideals really live it. 've seen the fun we all have together, er the fun there is a bond that is deeper. was withdrawing from some of her social interests. Dr. Garshwiler left his library to Franklin College in memory of Mrs. Garshwiler and her brother, Dr. Clarence Province. According to the terms of his will, Dr. Garshwiler left $1,000 to the Indiana Beta Student Loan Fund, for members of that chap-ter, $2,000 to the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School and other specific gifts to St. Vincent's Hospital in Indianapolis, John Herron Art Institute, Indianapolis, Berea College, Kentucky, Father Flanagan's Boystown in Nebraska and to several members of the Province family. After these bequests are satisfied, the remainder of the estate is to be divided among the family, one seventh to the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School and one-f6urteenth to the Indiana Beta Scholar-ship Loan Fund mentioned above. If it were merely a means of making social contacts or teaching social graces, of providing a place to eat and sleep then it would defeat its purpose. But it means so much more than that. Pi Phi will be to you just what you want it to be. "Do you remember the part in the pledging ceremony that said that every act of yours reflects either credit or discredit upon your sisters? Now that you are going to be an active, that is even more true. There will be some times when you cannot understand the actions of some of the other girls in the house, but remember that instead of criticizing look deeper, and perhaps you can find a way to help. "Being a good Pi Phi isn't easy. There are some sacrifices you will have to make. Personal interests and pleasures can't always come first but all I can say is that it's worth it. "The beauty of tomorrow will express more fully what I've tried to tell you. I'm proud that you will be a Pi Phi !" EDYTHE DOHMEN JANET HANSON Wisconsin Alpha tine Rutledge Orton, West Virginia A, of Col. and Mrs. William R. Orton of Fort Ga., is a second lieutenant in the Army fnited States. rton completed basic training here in April, id attended Army Administration School at Tex. Upon graduation from the school, she tied to Drew Field, Tampa, Fla., where she did personnel work until reporting to Officer Candidate School here. Lt. Orton has two brothers in the service, Cadet George Orton of the U. S. Military Academy at West Point, and Staff Sgt. William Orton, Infantry, overseas in the European Theater of Operations. Col. Orton is with the Infantry Training School, Fort Benning. .araaaaeerareaearreeaarerea.eaaaaeeaaeearraareeaeaaeaaeeerarereaarretaerrraaerraaarrerereaeaeaaeaeaeaaraaaereaaaaeeaareerarreaaraareaeeaaereaaaaeaaeeaereaaareaeeeeeareeeearaaeeaaraeaaaetateaearara OM PI PHI PENS Edited by MARY ELIZABETH LASHER, Ohio A F MARY GRAY PECK, Carrie Chapman Catt, H. W. Wilson Co. The following review, writ-ten by Ada Comstock Notestein, is reprinted from the Autumn, 1944, issue of the Yale Re-view by permission of that quarterly, copyright Yale University Press. "The lover of biography is likely to hesitate before taking up the story of a life written by a contemporary, especially if the subject of the book is still living. The disadvantages under which the author works are obvious. Perspective and proportion suffer from so near a view; certain reticences are unescapable; and certain inclusions, such as honors and tributes, are made in recognition of those concerned rather than to enlighten the reader. And yet, a biography by one who is seeing Shelley plain has its own peculiar interest and value. Small significant facts of which perhaps record would be lost can be established. If the subject has a characteristic humor or turn of phrase, quotations can be made and verified ; and the intention which lay behind acts and policies can be stated on first-hand authority. A co-worker, as Miss Peck was, can communicate also the" glow of feeling and the strain of effort which attend achievement, but which are hard to recapture after a generation or more has passed. One way of describing Mrs. Catt would be, to say that she responded with extraordinary vigor to some of the widely felt impulses of her time. With the odds against her, she secured for her-self the college training so recently made avail-able to women. She considered daringly the possibility of a professional career as doctor or lawyer. She became, in fact, superintendent of schools in Mason City, Iowa, when such a post was almost unheard-of for a woman. Teachings of experience, working in her eager mind, soon lifted her above personal ambitions and led her to devote herself for the rest of her life to two main causes the enfranchisement of women in this country and outside of it, and the education of Tomen in political thinking. Since Mrs. Catt pursued her aims with concentration, turning to a new campaign only when its prede-cessor could justly be set aside for awhile, it is possible for Miss Peck to follow a chronological scheme without confusing the reader. Not much effort is made to placethe fight for woman suffrage in the general pattern of social and political change, though an occasional reference shows that the author is not unaware of the larger web. Throughout the book the point of view of the suffrage leaders is steadfastly held. This procedure keeps the spotlight on the main figures and is favorable Carrie Chapman Call to clarity and vividness ; but an opportunity is lost of interesting the reader who would like to see the suffrage movement related to the general evolution of democracy. Nevertheless, Miss Peck's book serves its purpose in giving a convincing portrait of a woman of stature. Mrs. Catt began early to show the characteristics of leadership. Even as a little girl she thought and acted with imagination and initiative. She was endowed with a fine appearance, a voice made for public speaking, a pungent humor, and a gift for attracting and holding disciples. She had even the touch of mysticism which gave her commitment to her main causes something of the quality of Paul's experience on the road to Damascus. Above all, she had a native sense of the means whereby emotions once aroused may be given a channel 405 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



