<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr6130267_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>LeRoy, Beth Brainard</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>March 1945</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr6130267_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">March 1945</date>, News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>LeRoy, Beth Brainard</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 266-270</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">39</note>
                        <note type="Folder">13</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 61, Number 3 (March 1945), Pages 266-270.</note>
			<note type="document">arr6130267_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Mt. LeConte, the Sentinel; Gatlinburg in Isolation; Dedication Program; School Activities</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Changing Mission of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity for Women in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1944-1964</item>
                                <item>School programs</item>
                                <item>Curriculum</item>
                                <item>Health care</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr6130267_0001" seq="01" n="266-267  "/>
       <p>I lllll I II I II lllll SIMS. lllll 511.11.0.1.11.011SAI.I.. OM. 51111.11 111.0111111111110.110.11 $1111 11.1111111.1111111111111.1 1 M. NEWS F OM LITTLE PIGEON Edited by BETH BRMNARD LERoY, Massachusetts A I .,eConte, the Sentinel LeConte, majestic sentinel of the Great !s, guards Gatlinburg with its 6,593 feet :zling frozen beauty, illuminating the scene with spectacular silvery splendor. aturies she has stood gazing with impas-,untenance as changes have come to her i valley. has seen the redskins roam the trackless n. pursuit of game and watched them stalk De, the white men, with relentless strides. zed the pioneers on the Old Indian Gap . trail worn by moccasined feet, plodding Le steep, hazardous ridges through forest, to sink in apathy and deject the western slopes of the hitherto im-[e mountains. at the turn of the century she viewed us'picion stray travelers who wandered le community and in 1912 she saw a and new sight, a delegation of women ft the little narrow gauge train at Sevier-rid journeyed into Gatlinburg by wagon bumpy, rutted road. She watched them school and for the next few years she with interest the improvement in the of the mountain people, the raising of ndard of education and the opportunities ound economic background through craft r own making, all bringing new hope and Irposefulness to the entire section. Pi Beta d come to Gatlinburg. vIt. LeConte stood vigil, a sound of steel !1 began to echo through the mountains on the last link between Asheville and ille was forged with a wide macadam ver the mountains which brought an unprocession of high-powered motorcars horde of tourists through the new Great Mountain Park, decidedly quickening the md changing forever the tempo of the Inky. Proudly Mt. LeConte watched as ople adjusted to the changes, giving her approval to the march of progress and ig with assent as she saw the Pi Beta Phi city guiding and stabilizing the forces, ift and too abrupt, which threatened the progress of the mountain Burg, weeding e influences which were subversive and weaving into everyday living ethical principles and practices suited to a more complicated world than they had hitherto enjoyed. Mt. LeConte, which has been a silent observer over the ages, glistens in the sunlight and stands a beacon to attract more and better opportunities for her mountain people. Gatlinburg in Isolation For several days this December the bus over the mountain highway did not run on account of the icy roads and heavy sleet storms. Once more Gatlinburg was cut off from the rest of the world by the same barriers which kept it hidden away in the mountain "pockets" for so many years. But what a changed community! Now the inner resources of the people, the "abundant living" which Pi Beta Phi has developed, the many kinds of activities and many ways of spending their days fruitfully, have so enlarged their vision that it disturbed them little whether they were hedged in by storms or not. Christmas festivities were underway and life was full of interest. Do you remember that it is only thirty-three years ago since Dell Gillette told the story of the Christ Child to children who had never heard it before? Dedication Program The following dedicatory program was given in the Auditorium of the Pi Beta Phi School at Gatlinburg, Tennessee on October 26, 1944 at 7:30 F.M. Devotional Third Grade National Anthem Third Grade Pledge to the Flag Third Grade America "The Role of the School" Dorothy Maples Miss Ruth Dyer, Director Mrs. Clarence Sale, Chairman of the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School Committee "We Have Much for Which to be Thankful" Jack Jenkins Glee Club Mr. O. R. Medlin Special Music "Speed Thee, My Arrow" Glee Club. When the Pi . Beta Phi School opened this 266 THE MARCH ARROW 267 last fall, both staff and student body were enthusiastic over the new stage curtains and cyclorama which had been installed during the summer vacation. Plans were soon under way for a suitable program of dedication with Mrs. Clarence Sale, chairman of the Settlement School Committee, speaking for the Pi Beta Phi Fraternity, presenting the gifts to the School and dedicating them to the service of the young people. The devotional exercises were opened with the parting of the curtains to show the tiny tots of the Third Grade, a dozen strong, who under Mrs. Blanton's direction, gave the devotions in a very reverent manner, after which they led the audience in the National Anthem and the pledge to the flag. The curtains were then closed while two large baskets of leaves were placed beside a table on the stage. The entire stage was a mass of beautiful dahlias Six girls sang, `Speed Thee, My Arrow" after which Mr. Fleming concluded the program by thanking the Committee for the gift and called upon Miss Fenn to demonstrate how the curtains and cyclorama worked and how many ways they might be used, also the proper use of the dust bags when the curtains were not in service. Many letters were written to Mrs. Sale voicing appreciation and excerpts from two are revealing. Edward Phillips says, "They seem to have an effect upon the whole school. They certainly make our . stage look one hundred per cent better. They seem to make our auditorium bigger and brighter so I am one of many who are thanking you." And Jack Jenkins adds, "I am writing this letter in appreciation of the beautiful curtains for the stage. They make the whole school something to be proud of. They not only make the stage look beautiful, Center: Wilma and Faye, twin daughters of our farmer, Carl Ogle. Left and right: Groups of mountain children in the second grade. contributed by Mr. Lawson and the colors blended harmoniously with the curtains and cyclorama. After the audience had sung "America," Dorothy Maples spoke briefly on the "Role of a High School in this Wartime Period." Miss Dyer, DirectQr of the Pi Beta Phi School, introduced Mrs. Sale who spoke of the long association of Pi Beta Phi with the Gatlinburg community and expressed the idea that Pi Beta Phi is a fellow-citizen, working with them all for the best interests of the mountain people. She then dedicated the curtains "to a future of working together that our boys and girls might have stronger bodies, keener minds, and the opportunity for economic independence." Jack Jenkins accepted the curtains and ex-pressed the appreciation of the student body, simply and effectively. After a number by the Glee Club, Mr. Medlin expressed the appreciation of the citizens of Gatlinburg for all that Pi Beta Phi has done in the past and specifically for the curtains.but they will save much hard work in producing plays. To show my appreciation I will do my best to take care of them and to keep them clean. In closing I again express my gratitude to you and all the other people who helped pay for the curtains." School Activities Some of the activities which have made this last fall eventful are the Hallowe'en Carnival, the Parent-Teacher Association rummage sale, netting $105, the affiliation of the Parent-Teacher association with the National organization, starting a hot lunch program, the dedication on October 26th, Thanksgiving programs and a week of festivities at the Christmas season. Miss Dyer writes: "Miss Redding had a . Christmas meeting for her weavers. They sang Christmas carols and listened to a Christmas sketch which Miss Redding read to them. I showed my collection of Christmas boxes and there were ice cream cones for refreshment." </p>
      <pb ref="arr6130267_0002" seq="02" n="268-269  "/>
       <p>The complex problems of this modern cosmopolitan burg in 1945 are just as vital but diff erent and more complex than those of the neglected, isolated community which pioneer Pi Beta Phi women found in 1910. The Pi Beta Phi School acts as a stabilizing influence in Gatlinburg whose people have met with intelligence far above the average their too fast changing needs while .. . In Miss Petrie's weaving class there are fifteen interesting girls. Miss Petrie held a party for them at the Helmick House and the newly organized dramatics club held a party at the school. Mrs. Chalmers was hostess to the staff at the Health Center and the dormitory students were "at home" at Stuart Cottage on Thursday evening, entertaining with records of good music and folk-dancing. Over at the school the Christmas spirit ran riot. At assembly there was a fine program under the direction of Miss Fenn. Their choral readings and other numbers showed fine direction. The teachers provided candy and alum= clubs sent gifts for the younger children. The room mothers made cookies for the parties. The school program Friday morning was unusually well done. Mr. Huskey and the grade teachers had worked out the Christmas story. The older children took part in the pageant of the nativity with each room assigned carolswhich were sung in special places in the pro-gram. The new curtains made a lovely setting for the affair. Miss Georgie said that she had never seen a better entertainment. It made a lump come in your throat to see how reverently it was given. The Ames Alumnae Club furnished a rosy apple for each child who attended the program." Meanwhile during the Christmas holidays it began to rain. The rivers were high, swollen and overflowing their banks. The back country roads were impassible and the fields were deep with water. Fortunately the roof of the barn had been repaired before these torrents descended and the livestock were well taken care of by Carl Ogle, our farmer. A new cow has been bought to supply more milk for the children in the dormitories. Hens are laying, seed catalogues are being pored over for spring buying and soon the fields will again be ready for the plowing and planting which means so 268 lust off the highway conditions, primitive and insistent, challenge constantly the combined efforts of sc~ nurse and weaving supervisor to bring "life, liberty and the pursuit of happiness" into every day living. is the birthright of every American. much to our school. Much planning and con-serving means added results on the farm later in the year. The physical education program under the direction of Mr. Muneyhun is giving much satisfaction. Three mornings a week classes in physical education are held and one evening a week is given over to basketball. New game equipment has been ordered and the old Ag room is ready for the recreational programs. Arrangements have been made for a music teacher and house mother at Stuart Cottage, longtime needs, for the remainder of the school year. The wood-working classes have completed several projects and the level of the arts and crafts work has been appreciably raised. The nurse is busier than ever these days with coughs and colds, fevers and burns added to the regular clinic and class work, while one ofthe weavers writes, "We are weaving all time now. I wove right up to Christmas. I wove 235 white bags in December." F phase of the School brings its quota of hu interest, which vitalizes the Fraternity's S( ment School and adds flavor to its work. Have you any jigsaw puzzles not in These are a favorite pastime of many of boys and girls and a large assortment ar( quested for our recreational room as we: for use in the dormitories. A projector is much needed for visual cation in the health classes. Can you supply 1 It would be of great value in teaching pre Eon of many of the serious diseases w devastate our land. The mountain people 269 </p>
      <pb ref="arr6130267_0003" seq="03" n="270-271  "/>
       <p>THE MARCH ARROW to the fact that many fatal illnesses could 'aided and our nurse is eager to give them ecessary training and information, but she proper equipment. -- Le chairman of the Settlement School Come in each chapter and club is a "key" per-Keep in close contact with her that you know the needs of our School and that may help make vital contributions to the ncement of the mountain folk through an 'rstanding of the changing requirements. nuch has been accomplished during the thirty-three years. So much more can be :zed in the immediate future by working :her with a definite purpose opportunityfor them opportunity for us progress and development! Don't forget to write to Miss Emma Woerner, 912, Cherokee Rd., Louisville, Ky., for the films for use at a Settlement School tea. These films tell the story of the School in fascinating form, showing all phases of the work in technicolor. There are three films available, each requiring about twenty minutes time. Miss Woerner will also be glad to tell you of the specific needs in the educational department of the School. !.. You Interested. in The Camp Fire Girls ? rom Martha F. Allen, National Executive, Lp Fire Girls, comes the following stimulattetter: 3n my desk this morning was a copy of new Handbook for Guardians of Camp Fire s. To me, it's an exceedingly valuable piece terature, for I know it represents the time, :ght and energy of many leaders in the s of education and social welfare and of the y thousands of fine women who have served :amp Fire leaders in these 33 years of the nization's existence. More than that, I see in it one effective ver to the question every thoughtful, soy-concerned American woman is asking, Lat can we do to combat juvenile delin-Icy?' Many facts and figures have been pub that point to the need to combat juvenile aquency, but little has been said in print lt how we can better utilize the agencies 1dy well-established! We wish it were possible to explain to every aan how simple and enjoyable the Guard-s job really is and what an enriching exence it can be. We would like to be able to I a copy of this handbook to every one of r alumnae groups in the country, to be rev.ed and discussed at a meeting preferably the local Camp Fire Executive present to offer further clarification and explain how an association may sponsor a Camp Fire group. Whether or not a woman has the time or inclination to become a volunteer leader, we believe that familiarity with our work will be a step toward furthering the kind of effective community cooperation so greatly needed. "Would it be possible for you to find the space to convey this message to your readers (or even publish this letter itself) and suggest that they send for a copy of the handbook for discussion ? The price is 60ct and requests should be sent to Camp Fire Girls, Inc., 88 Lexington Ave., New York 16, N.Y. "We have a message, too, for your college age girls about the professional opportunities in youth-serving agencies. Copies of the enclosed folder, "There's a Job for You in Camp Fire Girls," are available on request. We'd be de-lighted if you would announce and perhaps quote from it! "With all good wishes, "Sincerely yours, "MARTHA F. ALLEN "National Executive" P.S. Among Pi Phis who are Camp Fire executives is Blanche Farrens Ball (Mrs. John H.), Nebraska B, in Crockett, Calif. 1' F OM Y'II PHI PENS 1.11 Edited by MARY ELIZABETH LASHER, Ohio A. WELTHY HONSINGER FISHER, Frederick Bohn. Fisher WORLD CITIZEN, The Macmillan Co., 254 pp. In her husband, one of the youngest Methodist bishops and certainly one of the most broadminded of ministers, Welthy H. Fisher has a subject both warm and colorful, practical and impetuous. She has written her biography of the late Frederick Bohn Fisher in a conversational manner, almost as one women might speak to another of a husband whom she both admires and loves, and this treatment fits her central character as a more pedantic one would not. When Fred Fisher's grandmother, a border-line Southerner, spoke to him in her soft drawl of different races, saying briefly "God was color blind" he received, according to his wife, his earliest lesson in world unity. Almost from that day can be traced his career as "world citizen." As a young man, only two years past twenty, he began the travels, to which he devoted much of his life, and his work which was, essentially, improving the understanding, religious and otherwise, among the peoples of the earth. In India where he was first sent from this country, Fred Fisher met Hindu and Moslem scholars and cut through and away the red tape which bound the more orthodox missionaries. It was typical of him that, shortly after his arrival in India, he married a young couple upon their request only to learn later that American missionaries had no right to perform the marriage ceremony there. The other missionaries were appalled and even more so when the new arrival calmly telegraphed the case to the Viceroy over the heads of all other India officialdom. Results, despite dire predictions, were, how-ever, immediate and gratifying, for the Viceroy not only understood the mistake, realizing that regulations were quite different in the United States, but also eliminated the embarrassing regulation. These human incidents, which bespeak the man, enliven the book as Mrs. Fisher speeds her reader through a career consistently mounting in importance. In ten short years Fred Fisher became a leader of American Protestant-ism, at 38 being elected bishop and assigned to Calcutta. This, nevertheless, was not sostartling as his resignation of the bishopric ten years later to make way for an Indian bishop to lead the Indian Church. Indeed, this is a rare book about a Man of God . . . one with religious import and secular appeal. AUTHOR INTEREST: Welthy Honsinger Fisher, New York A, was born in Rome, N.Y., educated at Syracuse University and well before she met her world-girdling husband, went to interior China where she was principal of the Baldwin School for Girls. During World War I she served with the army in France and thereafter married Bishop Fisher. Among her other books are: Beyond the Moon Gate, Freedom, A String of Chinese Pearls, and Top of the World. Lois DONALDSON KOEHLER, Nicaragua, Costa Rica, Uruguay, El Salvador, four children's books on geography in story and picture form, Albert Whitman and Co., average 30 pp. Children of eight and nine, we predict, will become fast friends with their Good Neighbors and learn their South American geography les sons in a painless, after-school fashion when they read these books written by Lois Donaldson Koehler and cheerfully illustrated by Kurt Wiese. Simple, but pictorial language, make a pageant of what could so easily be a staid pro cession of facts and figures, boring to the young mind. Even adults will find these "books for youngsters" appealingly clear-cut and their reading a quick way to assimilate essential facts about four countries often in the news today. AUTHOR INTEREST: Lois Donaldson Koehler, Florida A, has written numerous books for boys and girls and does them well perhaps because as she herself says, she "has always loved books." Among her earlier efforts are Runsel-Punzel and In the Mouse's House. AGNES WRIGHT SPRING, William Chapin Deming of Wyoming, privately printed in a limited edition by The Arthur H. Clark Co., 650 pp. As is so often the case, the life of a newspaperman, for that was what Mr. Deming was, is the life and history of the community and the people in which and with whom he worked. William Chapin Deming has proved no exception and his biography, written by Mrs. Spring from material in the publisher's scrapbooks and from interviews with him parallels the development of Cheyenne and of Wyoming itself. 271 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



