<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr6040371_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>LeRoy, Beth Brainard</name></author>
                        <author><name>Snow, Ethel M.</name></author>
                        <author><name>Landrum, Sue</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>May 1944</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr6040371_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">May 1944</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>LeRoy, Beth Brainard</name></author>
                        <author><name>Snow, Ethel M.</name></author>
                        <author><name>Landrum, Sue</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 371-375</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">39</note>
                        <note type="Folder">12</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 60, Number 4 (May 1944), Pages 371-375.</note>
			<note type="document">arr6040371_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Gatlinburg Gleanings; Miss Redding, Director of Weaving, writes on Weaving in Wartime; An Open Letter to Pi Beta Phis; Opportunity Knocks; First Graders; Music and Folk Dancing; Nurses' Aide Susie</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Changing Mission of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity for Women in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1944-1964</item>
                                <item>Weaving</item>
                                <item>War </item>
                                <item>Students</item>
                                <item>Music</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr6040371_0001" seq="01" n="370-371  "/>
       <p>as a chapter as a club as an individual like to contribute one or more of the charming decorative objects now being assembled for the furnishing of Holt House (in addition to your usual contribution for maintenance) ? WOJGI YO t like to be responsible for the purchase of a mantel clock? a flowered bonnet box? a hand-drawn music score? a turquoise blue plush picture album? a fancy-work frame? a Swiss music box? a pair of mercury glass tie-backs? a carved antique love seat? a three piece Hepplewhite banquet table? an antique china dresser set? an early type sewing machine? an antique Victorian dresser? These and many other delightful objects have been selected by the committee. Their purchase is being delayed until the necessary funds are available. Some of the gifts already donated by chapters and clubs include an antique pine trunk, a small antique wood-burning stove, a brass student lamp, a melodeon, andirons. Framed acknowledgement cards in the entrance hall of Holt House will give credit to the donors of each of these gifts. Your money gift, whether large or small, will add one more lovely furnishing to the House. Write to the chairman of the Holt House committee for a list of items which might be purchased in your name. Be sure to specify the amount you desire to give. Mrs. Oliver B. Simmons 6415 Morningside Drive Kansas City 5, Missouri Chairman, Holt House Committee 370 .atullisell.11111111.11111.11.111.19.15II.M.I.1111111.11511811111111.1111013118111011.11.011.11.11.11111S.010.1111111111.111110 0.1111111.1.1111.1111.1181A.1111.1111,40.1118111.11111.2BIA... NEWS FROM LITTLE PIGEON Edited by BETH BRAINARD LEROY, Massachusetts A II 011. II I 1.11.11111.1111I.N.11111111.1111.111.111111IIIIIIIIIIII.1111.111111.011110.11101.1.111181IIIIIS1111.1,11111111.1 ,,, 0,1111.111.11111111111.11.111I...1111111i. Gatlinburg Gleanings Spring has come again to Gatlinburg, bringing its glorious azaleas, laurel, dogwood, and rhododendron, and its thousands of wild flowers making a lush carpet of fragrant blossoms, bespangling the hillsides. Bluets and violets, trilliums and trailing arbutus, columbines and hepaticas form a tapestry of color woven by the Master Artist. Inside the cabins are our weavers working with color, too, weaving into each article made for Arrowcraft some of their hopes and dreams. At first they wove literally to keep the wolf from the door. Now they weave to keep their homes intact and to bring a measure of comfort to their families. Miss Redding, Director of Weaving, writes on "Weaving in Wartime" I wish I could make you see our one hundred and twenty weavers as women like yourselves. All of them keep house, even though their houses are small and many of them poorly equipped. Nineteen of them are doing it while their husbands are in the army or navy. Most of them in addition to caring for their children, also milk a cow or two, tend a flock of'chickens, make a vegetable garden, this year to be larger than ever before. They do all their canning by the bushel. Shelf upon shelf of the most beautiful and appetizing looking vegetables and fruits are their reward for months of work. They may be talking about taking fathers in other places, but in Gatlinburg the fathers have already gone. I have one weaver whose husband is under thirty-eight. They have seven children. The father works in a defense plant, but has already had his blood test and expects to be called any day. Don't ask me how the mother finds time to weave. I don't know the answer. There have been fifty-eight husbands and sons of weavers called to the armed forces and one has been killed in action. One weaver has five children, one has three and several have two in service. They worry, too, as every one else does. They want the war to end and theirmen to come home. When their home on furlough, they do not w( sometimes delays your orders. I them for that. Do you? . Getting weaving done in war t ferent. We did not expect to have than we could fill, but such has b Up to the present we have been obtaining all the materials we have and buying in large quantities, s lasted. The end is in sight for colored towels for instance. From towels will be all white with colore^ lavender ones at all. We shall colored linen for the duration. 'linen towels if my linen weavers jobs. I cannot train linen weavers It is specialized weaving. The sam: certain degree with wool. We will l of wool this year and hope to ha wool articles. We have been lucki in having money to invest in y quantities as it has been available. doing this for two years and have keep ahead of the game. Last year we combed the "hills and found thirty-six new weaver of whom are still working. This number ever to start weaving i Several of our older and most rely have stopped working and it is i find others to replace them in skills. I might mention one bl though. One of the weaving famil and two daughters (the son is in tr me that they must depend entirel weaving this year because plowin4 for Minnie. Minnie is the eight( daughter. We are running one of the larg the Shop has ever had with less I can see that we are busy. Just ke( five women at a time working, a. have ever had at this season of t job in itself and soon more custo appearing in the Shop, too, with e: upon our time. It takes patience at humor these days and we must all 371 </p>
      <pb ref="arr6040371_0002" seq="02" n="372-373  "/>
       <p>THE MAY ARROW :tier from one of the weavers says, "I hev been g so hard. I hey wove 2 warps sence Christmas a putin' on a nother today. My daughter is .th me. She has got 2 cunning kids. They are iy to me. Both my boys are overseas now." he Mountain View Shop "Mis' Georgie" con-her splendid service for Pi Beta Phi. She has 1 tourist trade in this Shop ever since 1931 lcomes each year, old as well as new friends owcraft. With each article she gives added a in selling also the Pi Beta Phi School and fits to the mountain people. )pen. Letter to Pi Beta Phis PI PHI5 ALL: )ughout shipping I wanted the chance to thank [ for your patience and understanding. It d me no end not to fill your orders more corn-But if I had sent out all the Utility doilies Akins you asked for, all of our eighty weavers have had to weave every minute on that one And you do want variety. Ater from someone this week has the wishful t that we may surprise you with some lovely ings in place of the hooked mats and pewter are no longer obtainable. These days we are to have new things take the place of the old .re running out of so many of the materials for Baby things, linen towels in the colors and le lowly pot holder have met with that very [ and express were naturally slower this year. oes out from Gatlinburg daily except Sunday. p by car in to Knoxville adds a day to the Arts and Crafts Course in the schools !ar has been of unusual interest to the !n, so great has been the variety of artihich they have made. Miss Petrie has had . projects for each month, fruits for sgiving and decorations for Christmas .e has taught, too, many new ways to make ,mes and persons more attractive. For the , braided rugs, table decorations, fingertime allowed. Express has to be taken to Sevierville in the school truck. One trip a week is all that rationing allows. We try to have a full truck each week Bess does most of the packing and when we are working against time to get out a load of express she is completely exhausted at the end of the day. Arlie ties some of the heaviest boxes but otherwise this is a Women's Shop run by the Pi Phis. Many of our number start their letters "Dear Sirs", however. It could be an empty shop but I am keeping all the lovely antiques and other furniture that can no longer be replaced. Perhaps some day you will all have the opportunity to visit your Shop. With Knoxville and its surroundings running over with people, many of them think they have solved some of their problems when they find our Shop. I have had a hard time convincing them that money cannot buy everything. They do buy a great deal of our Arrow-craft. That was one of the reasons why our shelves were not piled high at the beginning of shipping. Also you have advertised our wares so well for so many years that customers wrote in from all parts of the country. To shops it was easy to say that we were adding no new customers to our list, but we do want to keep our old friends for the time to come when supply and demand will return to normal. It is hard to realize that we were selling even more this year with demand so far ahead of supply. One good that came out of it at this end was that hardly a thing was returned. We are still sending goods to the Clubs. And now that we have recovered our breath, we shall be glad to take on more sales. With thanks from your shopkeeper at Arrowcraft. Sincerely, ETHEL M. SNOW painting and refinished furniture are within the abilities of the children and for personal adornment braided belts and lapel ornaments, etc. Mr. Fleming has also helped the boys make meat boards, sandwich trays, bookshelves and bookends. The children are eager for the arts periods and revel in new ideas which can be put to immediate use. "Opportunity Knocks" ACH YEAR the Settlement School Committee urges Pi Beta Phis to apply for teaching ositions in the Pi Beta Phi School. The opportunity for service is great, for whatever )ur ability, it is needed in Gatlinburg. Many times teachers feel that they will be sideacked if they go into a little mountain town and rusticate for a few years. This is not le case here, however, for you cannot rusticate and the world does not pass your door. very minute of your time will be intriguingly filled and challenged and the world alks right up to your door and comes in. You are not away from the war effort, either, )r the Red Cross, Nurses Aide, scrap and paper drives, "Buy Bonds"' drive and all facets f war, even to care for returning soldiers may be met in Gatlinburg. Each teaching )ad is ,heavy, but each teacher finds time for extracurricular effort. She must have it to !-create enthusiasm and strength, both of which are tremendously needed. Several short :oriel by the teachers themselves are of interest. THE MAY ARROW 373 First Graders By JOSEPHINE FLEMING The First Grade room has thirty-four children enrolled, the majority coming from homes away from the "paved streets" of Gatlinburg. Some come from the very poorest homes and some from the more prosperous. When the group of fifty-four was divided last fall, I received thirty-four of the most immature children part were physically immature, part socially immature. Timidity was one of the greatest problems. Books to many were toys, and turning the pages of a book and the proper use of a book had to be taught. There was no desire to take up a book to read and not once did a child ask to take one home. After six months the children wish to take books home to read, and each night most of them take one or two books to read to their parents. A note comes to me the next day from the parents that the child has read aloud. We have made small colored books, in the shape of animals, in which all books each individual child has read, are listed. Half of the children are reading in First Readers now, having completed many pre-primers and primers. Some old torn picture books have been taken, pictures cut out and lovely new picture books made from them. A gift of some stiff material has proven the incentive for this project. One mother became sufficiently interested to secure funds for the furniture to have a new coat of paint. The children are so pleased with the jade green enamel, with table tops, cup-boards and piano being dark oak varnish. A Mother Rabbit (black) with her four white and six black bunnies were taken to the school room for a week. This furnished first hand information about caring for pets. Also it was excellent material for songs, games, chart reading, number work, and art work. The after-noon we were to take the rabbits home each child had to say "Good-by." Later this spring ewe want to take a hen, sitting on her eggs and hatch the baby chickens in the class room. Four goldfish, three tadpoles, and a terrapin are the other live animals in our room. One very small, immature, freckle-faced lad of five years and eleven months wore the same pair of blue over-ails and red and white striped polo shirt every day for six weeks. As cooler weather came, a green striped shirt was added on top, and as still cooler weather came a green plaid. flannelette shirt was added on top. The day the child came with an entirely new outfit 211 the children shouted at once, "Look at Andy." Those bright brown eyes, shining through all that dirt pierce right into one's own heart. Never have I read a story or a book that this child fails to say, "Please, Mrs. Fleming, read one more page." Could I refuse? At first they did not know how to listen to stories, now, to stop is the problem. This week they gave a program for the High School group at their morning assembly. The program included sacred songs, Bible verses, prayer songs, patriotic songs, and non-sense songs. How they love to sing and do they carry a tune! Finger painting was introduced this week, and they enjoyed each minute from the wetting of the paper to the constant daily admiration of their finished products. They are eager for their art periods. Clay modeling, crayon work, and free hand cutting of paper have proven the most popular art experiences. To many the Christmas party was the high light of the year. A tree, decorated entirely with ornaments of their own making, stood in the room. Some packages for each proved to bring unexpected happiness to them, and tears of joy to me. A dear friend of ours in New York had sent each a package necklaces for the girls and coloring books and crayons for the boys. One box of crayons was a bit soft from its nearness to a radiator. One lad replied, when asked why it was so soft, "No wonder, it came all the way on a train from the North Pole." No doubt, that celebration was the only Christmas celebration any of them had. On each table in our schoolroom is a little pottery animal. To get different groups to the front of the room I ask for all the ducks, all the puppies, etc. to go to the small chairs. When I asked all the elephants to go to the chairs, I noticed one little boy still sitting. When I went to him and asked if he heard me tell all the elephants to come up, he said, "Yes, but I'm not an elephant !" This year has been one of the happiest of my life. This group is a part of me and it gives me a new thrill each day to be with them. I consider it a great privilege to have had this opportunity to be a member of the Pi Beta Phi School faculty this year and to work with these thirty-four dear little beginners. And fortunate, indeed, are the children! Music and Folk Dancing By Lois FENN About six weeks after school opened last fall, I noticed that the High School girls were </p>
      <pb ref="arr6040371_0003" seq="03" n="374-375  "/>
       <p>THE MAY ARROW :crested in folk dancing and we began to vote one of the two physical education periods :h week to this activity. There was a division classes which made small "workable" groups one of freshmen, one of sophomores and one juniors and seniors together. Since the maity of the students here are familiar with axe dancing, we found it easy to begin with adrilles which were the English and early aerican ancestors of the square dances. We !d some of the singing calls, in both quadrille I circle forms, in the Henry Ford collection. also learned one or two simple English itra-dances and a peasant dance or two for ich we had records. Of course music is alt's a major consideration in carrying on folk Icing classes, and we have been obliged to records. I hope that when the girls (and imps some boys, too) become fairly proficient the simple dances we have learned with rec-Is, we may interest Miss Evelyn Bishop in ying occasionally so that we can do some ire varied dances Danish, Swedish, and glish. Folk dancing is such a popular form of reation and I believe strongly in its social-Icatiorlal value. I am not an expert in this rk, but I plan to go back to the Campbell lc School for another short course and I )e that we can carry on the classes another r. arses' Aide Susie By SuE LANDRUM kfter graduation from the University of Inessee, I decided to teach Home Economics [ accepted a position in the Pi Beta Phi .00l in Gatlinburg. After I had taught a r weeks I missed my nurses' aide work so ch and since most of my Saturdays were own, I went back to Knoxville on the bus Saturdays and continued my work at .t Sanders Hospital where I had worked durmy school days. Gatlinburg is forty miles more from Knoxville and it was rather invenient to commute such a distance for only .ay's work. I found that in Sevierville, only Zen miles away, there is a small hospital run a very efficient doctor and his wife. The pital is recognized by the American Medical ;ociation, so I asked to transfer my working Irs there. Special permission was granted and )retinue to give my Saturdays to this war eft. Although the hospital is small and lovely look at, it is very well equipped with wonful x-ray machines, very good surgical in-[malts, pharmacy, autoclave for sterilizationand many modern improvements. Dr. Broady is a graduate of the University of Pennsylvania, his wife a registered nurse from Philadelphia General Hospital and there is a ward assistant. I found I could be of help. After I had worked a couple of hours the first morning Dr. Broady asked me to go on a maternity case with him. I had no training along technical lines, but he told me that I knew enough to help. I grabbed my coat and flashlight and a small bag and he got two larger bags and we travelled about ten miles out of town before turning onto a dirt road, and then four miles more back into a Sue Landrum, Home Economics teacher. Her classes have recently completed an apron project and the aprons were modeled at a chapel exercise. Her activities include work with the Red Cross and assisting the Girl Scouts. "holler" wedged in the hills. Then we walked half a mile up to a very small cabin. It was the crudest place I have ever seen, deep cracks in the walls, only a small fireplace for heat, with a "kittle" of water setting over the fire. The mother was on the bed moaning; the mother-in-law had two small children in her arms and two others of about six and eight were running in and out of the house. The doors were wide open and in full view was a table piled with dishes left from several meals. I felt so insignificant, yet horrified by the conditions. The doctor and I scrubbed with lysol solution and he told me what equipment to get from THE MAY ARROW 3 the bags. We spread it on the floor on sterile material we had brought. I had to wash a glass in order to have a clean one to give the mother her medicine. I helped with the anaesthetic, which was local. Then I held the flashlight over the low, unsheeted, dirty-quilted bed and handed supplies to the doctor with my free hand. For two hours I stood by and gave what help I could, only handing equipment and holding thread ends with my free hand, which was sterile gloved. Finally a beautiful, well formed baby was born. After the oil bath and dressing, I helped with the mother and the job was finished with many crude devices which we improvised for the emergency. I had, forgott, the time of day. Only the house and a precio bundle of humanity were dominant in my min And that there are still such places in Americ My work does not usually take me on sup cases, but we do manage to meet adequate whatever comes at the hospital and the wo is fascinating and always new. -- Are you sending in an application to tea, at the Pi Beta Phi School this fall? -N,,P+C. Pledges Aid to Armed Services AT ITS MEETING October 30 to November 1 National Panhellenic Congress passed the following resolution: . . that N.P.C. commit itself to active support of the appeal of our military leaders and implement such commitment with a program to urge girls graduating from college to consider seriously enlistment in the armed services." The resolution expresses in words the attitude of the women's Greek-letter societies that are members of N.P.C. To transfer attitude into action the congress directed the Committee on War and College Women to include in its program whatever will aid N.P.C. groups in responding to the urgent call of the armed services for the enlistment of women so that men can be released for the war fronts. In every city or large town are recruiting offices for the WAC, WAVES, SPARS, and Women's Marine Corps. If you are a senior or an alumna without primary home obligations, contact your local recruiting center. Many thousand women are urgently needed. The hard period of the war is at hand. Do your bit. College women are not influenced by pretensions of glamour. They know the jobs mean just plain hard work. We hope they enlist in the spirit of seeing a job through the spirit that matches a brother's spirit of endurance in the foxhole. Women already trained in special skills have greater opportunity for active work and advancement because they require only the preliminary military training. While this appeal is primarily for aid to the armed services, the Committee on War and College Women feels it should be pointed out that college and alumnm chapters and individual members of women's Greek-letter groups have not only a fine record for enlistment in women's branches of the various strictly armed services, but also in meeting the need for nurses and dietitians who serve with the armed forces. In addition, Greek-letter women have done their bit in the purchase of war bonds, working for the Red Cross, contributing to the blood bank, aiding the USO, and serving in many phases of civilian defense. The war is so vast that individual and group effort count for most when tied in with the large national agencies developed to handle the complex problems of the war. Greek-letter women will not only continue to aid all these agencies, but will also continue their good record of enlistment in the armed services. The freedoms for which this war is fought are the freedoms that protect the right to organize into wholesome social groups, one of the basic rights of a democracy. Dictators destroy that right. So, the Greek-letter groups have a stake in the fight for freedom! N.P.C. COMMITTEE ON WAR AND COLLEGE WOMEN L. Pearle Green, K A 0 Mary B. Merritt, M Mary Love Collins, Chairman, X </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



