<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr6510091_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Settlement School Reports</title>
                        <author><name>Smith, Ruth Barritt</name></author>
                        <author><name>Dyer, Ruth</name></author>
                        <author><name>Snow, Ethel M.</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>September 1948</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr6510091_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">September 1948</date>, Settlement School Reports</title>
                        <author><name>Smith, Ruth Barritt</name></author>
                        <author><name>Dyer, Ruth</name></author>
                        <author><name>Snow, Ethel M.</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 91-114</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">40</note>
                        <note type="Folder">1</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 65, Number 1 (September 1948), Pages 91-114.</note>
			<note type="document">arr6510091_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Report of Chairman of Settlement School Committee; Report of Director; Arrowcraft Report; Report of Weaving Department; The Jennie Nicol Memorial Health Center; Report of the Principal; Financial Report of the Physical Education Department; Report of Craft Department; Home Economics Department; Supervisor of Public School Music; Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, Report on Audit, Year Ended June 30, 1948</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Changing Mission of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity for Women in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1944-1964</item>
                                <item>Budget</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>
                                <item>Education</item>
                                <item>Health care</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr6510091_0001" seq="01" n="90-91  "/>
       <p>MU PROVINCE Club Res. Paid Am't No. of Average SettleArrow Holt Mag. Active Chapter Senior SettleLoan Mag. Holt 1947-48 Alum. Mem. Total MeetAttendment Craft House Loan ComChapter Dues ment Fund CornHouse Dues ings ance School (gross Fund missions School missions sales) Berkeley, Calif.* 435 81 fI.00 8 50 $ 2.50 $827.00 $ 2.50 $ 25.00 $ 3.10 $125.00 California Beta $17.00 8 8.95 El Paso, Tex.* , 33 20 3.00 9 12 5.00 105.40 5.00 5.00 6.75 5 .00 California Gamma 10.95 Fresno, Calif.* 44 30 2.00 4 21 20.00 623.94 10.00 20.00 21.85 California Delta 6.00 $2o.00 14.90 $30.00 Glendale, Calif.* 128 73 3.00 9 40 25.00 10.00 5.00 100.00 Nevada Alpha 9.00 27.95 - Honolulu T,H.* 50 37 3.50 8 30 50.00 1614.50 10.00 10.00 41.80 Arizona Alpha 15.00 7.55 15.00 Long Beach, Calif.* 125 37 3.I0 II 35 20.00 5.00 Io.00 9.95 50.00 New Mexico Alpha 3.00 15.00 11.25 15.00 Los Angeles, Calif.* 65o 215 4.00 q Sr. 6o 200.00 899.51 20.00 5.00 24.80 50.00 8 Jr. 25 6BP 25 Marin County, Calif.* 24 17 2.00 10 9 50.00 575.44 3.00 3.00 .90 New Mexico Alumnae* 44 24 5.00 8 17 5.00 1333.94 5.00 5.00 25.85 Gifts Palo Alto Calif * 110 3 3.00 10 30 25.00 456.02 3.00 10.00 9.10 10.00 Pasadena, Calif.* 275 141 2.00 9 70-75 2s.00 667.70 S-00 1.00 22.25 26.00 Phoenix, Ariz.* too 37 2.50 8 35 5.00 509.35 5.00 5.00 4.50 65.00 Reno, Nev.* 93 38 4.00 II 33 10.00 306.75 2.50 2.50 6.25 396.00 24 3.00 9 20 10.00 850.33 10.00 I0.00 32.00 10.00 Sacramento, C;,'if.* 40 San Bernard no. Calif.* 29 22 2.00 4 12 1.00 1.00 1.00 San Diego, Calif.* 95 53 2.50 9 40 100.00 794.58 5.00 5.00 13.45 San Fernando Valley* 85 45 4.00 12 25-30 10.00 5 5.00 25.10 San Francisco, Calif.* z56 67 3.50 8 25-30 75.00 1071.00 10,00 25.00 31.50 25.00 San Jose, Calif,' 20 20 3.00 I0 12 30.00 571.80 10.00 1.00 ' 58.65 I0.00 San Mateo County* 5o 23 1.50 8 18 15.00 5.00 25.00 18.95 25.00 Santa B arbara-Ventura*. 32 22 4.00 9 19 5.00 315.10 5.00 5.00 45.20 Santa Monica-Westwood* ioo 53 4.00 II 43 40.00 219.58 5.00 5.00 g6.i5. 20.00 South Coast Club* ..:.. 41 35 2.50 8 26 50.00 194.55 2.50 2.50 15.95 10.00 Tucson, Ariz.* 75 40 3.00 9 40 28.38 370.25 15.00 5.00 Gifts * Gave to local causes. Settlement School Reports We give in full these reports instead of merely summarizing them. They seemed too vital and interesting to be omitted. REPORT OF CHAIRMAN OF SETTLEMENT SCHOOL COMMITTEE N 1711 Joseph Addison wrote in the "Spectator," "I consider a human soul without education like marble in the quarry which shows none of its inherent beauties 'till the skill of the polisher fetches out the couleurs, makes the surface shine and discovers every ornamental cloud, spot, and vein that runs through the body of it." Pi Beta Phi found its quarry in Gatlinburg, Tennessee in 1912, a spot inaccessible and isolated for more than a century but where the marble thereof was of purest texture, having been Anglo-Saxon in its origin. With but one teacher to do the original polishing of thirteen pupils, the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School had its beginnings thirty six years ago. Hundreds of willing hands and loyal spirits have labored to bring out the best therein; other hundreds have continued to improve and polish into high-lights, that original project. It stands today as a living memorial to our Founders and continues to hold our interest beyond college years. We are envied by the other fraternities and admired by all for our accomplishments in the Southern Appalachians, familiarly known as the Smokies. From humblest beginnings the Settlement School has grown to one which offers a full curriculum of twelve grades where this year ten teachers taught more than five hundred pupils and both grade and high school buildings were crowded beyond capacity. For the past five years, the County has assumed as far as possible the same basic responsibility toward the Gatlinburg Schools as toward the others of Sevier County. In 1943 the plan which had been recommended by Dr. Holton and again by Dr. William S. Taylor in his survey, and for which the Settlement School Committee with Ethel H. Copp as Chairman had worked so tirelessly, went into effect. The buildings were leased for a nominal sum to the County and the County assumed the salaries of the teachers but Pi Beta Phi continued to supervise and direct the activities. Pi Beta Phi was soon to discover that the "basic" responsibilities assumed by Sevier County were not all that was desired or needed for our School. In con-sequence we have supplemented.the program in various ways in order to give the children some of those things which make for better living anywhere. Again this year we have paid the full salaries for a Physical Education teacher, a Music Supervisor, a Crafts teacher, and for a part-time teacher in Wood-working. Also in order to be assured of the return of Mr. William King, who had received his Master's degree during the past summer, as Superintendent, Pi Beta Phi found it necessary to supplement the salary paid by the County. Mr. King remained at the School until January 1 when he resigned to accept a position with the Veterans' Administration in Nashville, Tennessee. Though the community was sorry to lose Mr. King, Gatlinburg and Pi Beta Phi were proud to have the County Board of Education ask our Mr. Joe Johnson to assume the temporary assignment of Superintendent in addition to his other duties. Mr. Johnson came to Pi Beta Phi at Pi Phi's expense two years ago as the Physical Education teacher and through his integrity, his ability, and his interest in young people, made for himself a niche which he alone can fill in Gatlinburg. This was attested to when he and his basketball teams were honored with a banquet early this spring. While ably carrying on his duties as superintendent, this was not Mr. Johnson's chosen field and he will be back next fall on the old teaching and coaching schedule again. Knowing that "Music must take rank as the highest of the fine arts as the one which, more than any other, ministers to human welfare," the Settlement School Committee two years ago brought Mrs. Aletha Armstrong to the school as its Music Supervisor. When one hears her objectives as she teaches nine elementary grades, has an elementary chorus, a High School Glee Club, plans for music for school assemblies, leads one of the church choirs, volunteers her services on every occasion, one knows she is almost indispensable to Gatlinburg. These were her objectives: "To afford the joy of singing for each child; to enable pupils to use their voices correctly, thus encouraging beauty of tone and safe-guarding voices for maturity; to provide a background of musical culture ; to promote a sense of cooperation and service through group activity in home, church, and community ; and to encourage the creative spirit." It is a far step from the harp singing of previous decades and Mrs. Armstrong feels that the best sign of in-creasing musical appreciation has been the increasing demand for our singing groups on the part of the community, as well as the wholesome eagerness with which they perform. The fraternity policy has long been that of furthering interest in the Crafts among the younger mountaineer people by giving them the opportunity to learn some of them at least at school. Our wood-working instructor, Mr. Huskey, has taught the boys how to produce creditable pieces of small furniture while Miss Petrie with her own fine appreciation of the beautiful has endeavored to instill that same appreciation in her students. Weaving, Pottery, Block-printing, Leather work, all came in for attention. If we are to keep step with others in the encouragement of all types of crafts, this is a splendid starting place. This spring, our Home Economics department, under the direction of our Home Economics teacher was used as a practice teaching center for Seniors from the University of Tennessee. There is talk that our school will be named one of fifteen such practice centers in the state and this would assure us a teacher of experience and a higher level of instruction. Pi Beta Phi would welcome this. Since the arrival of the first nurse in 1920, pro-grams of community nursing, public health instruction in hygiene, home nursing clinics, and regular health inspections in our school and three rural mountain schools have been maintained. In 1933, 1600 pupil inspections were made, while this year there were 4180. Friday afternoon is always set aside as Clinic 91 </p>
      <pb ref="arr6510091_0002" seq="02" n="92-93  "/>
       <p>92 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW day with special emphasis on Maternal Health and Infant Welfare. A large group of our own former pupils marry and establish homes in the community and start their families. Mrs. Chalmers says, We don't expect too much change from the old-timey ways of the parents but we do see results every year." With nearly seven hundred children of school age and almost as many younger children the importance of Health Education can be seen. Community health education requires leadership ; this, Pi Phi, through the fine work of Mrs. Chalmers and abetted by the two local doctors and local organizations, gives. Those of you who attended Convention two years ago will recall the resume of the Pi Phi Health pro-gram given by Mrs. Chalmers and her dream of a new Health unit for Gatlinburg. Today that dream is a reality; for last month the new Jennie Nicol Health Center was opened. The building is modern through-out with an office clinic, first aid rooms, class room with full connecting bath for sick-room demonstration. Its exterior is of hand hewn white oak shingles and native stone, with slate roof. It stands conveniently on the highway not far from the Arrowcraft Shop, with which architecture it harmonizes. It is cheery inside, with bright Arrowcraft hangings against knotty pine walls and with necessary new equipment added to the old. Funds for the building came largely from the estate of Dr. W. P. Gershwiler of Indianapolis, whose wife was Florence Province Gershwiler, Indiana B, and the generosity of the California A and the District of Columbia Alpha Chapters. Next month while the Committee is meeting in Gatlinburg, this lovely new building will be appropriately dedicated to broadened health service. From the first days of the Settlement School when a Chicago committee member was inspired to take some of the native artistry home to sell, this branch of our activity has held the interest of Pi Beta Phis from coast to coast. True, there were years when the regular Settlement School funds had to carry the cost of the Arrowcraft Shop; true, there have been lush years, particularly those when foreign imports were unprocurable; but through lean years and rich we have rendered a great service to the capable mounraineer who otherwise would have had little outlet for her artistry and no income from it. At the same time thousands of Pi Phis and others have enjoyed the beauty of these wares. To Ethel Snow whose business ability has carried the Shop through depression as well as prosperity we owe a great deal. Sales, both last year and this, mounted above previous years and work has been assigned to a greater number of weavers. Twenty-six more clubs and three more active chapters have carried Arrowcraft products (though there have been more goods returned). Clubs and chapters must bear in mind that the Arrowcraft Shop has definite rules on what percentage of an order may be returned if unsold and what things cannot be sent back. Two changes in the personnel at Arrowcraft came this year. August first our talented "Miss Meta" Schattschneider resigned as Weaving Supervisor to accept a teaching position at Highlands University, Las Vegas, New Mexico. Hers was a difficult place to fill. Then this spring "Miss Georgie" Duffield who had been a friend of Pi Phi in Gatlinburg for many years, who had woven the beautiful distinctive afghans for many of us, and who had kept our shop in the Mountain View Hotel, felt she must resign because of ill health. She will be greatly missed. Mrs. NicCutchan, with Pi Phi relatives and Pi Phi interest, has taken over the shop and her love both for Pi Phi and for the crafts should make her a valuable asset. We were without a Weaving Supervisor until March and Lura Ownby Porter, the assistant, deserves special commendation for the way she carried on alone, keeping the weavers supplied with warps and the stock built up while we searched for a successor to "Miss Meta." We feel fortunate indeed to have convinced Tina McMorran of Eugene, Oregon, to come to Gatlinburg. She knew the opportunities through having attended our Workshop in 1947 and she brings years of weaving experience and an under-standing personality to her associations with the weavers. Evidences of her ability are on display here. To walk into our grade school and high school buildings today one could scarcely recognize them as places where the three Rs, or Science or Math are taught for nine months of the year. In the High School building is the bang of the beater as the weavers do their stint for the day, or the sound of a hammer tells you that some rare, original piece of jewelry is being evolved from a flat piece of silver, or the sight of screens laid carefully on yardage shows that soon Textile decorations will be finished. All the classrooms have become workrooms but the most amazing transformation appears at the grade school where thirty-five students are now living for six weeks. This then is the Summer Workshop in progress. Started four years ago on a trial basis, it operates in conjunction with the University of Tennessee to teach the Crafts and by now has survived the experimental period. This is the second year for the dormitory system. With the University's access to war assets and its willingness to loan some of its surplus to us, cots, mattresses, chests, blankets, pillows, mirrors, and many other things helped to furnish the schoolhouse-dormitory. Staff and students are also housed in Teachers' Cottage, in the old Health Center, and in the regular dormitories, Stuart and Pollard. This year the session, with two three week periods extends from June 14 to July 21. For the first session twenty-four of the forty eight states are represented, spreading from Oregon to Florida, and New Mexico to Massachusetts. The larger percentage are teachers of Home Economics, Art and Occupational Therapy though Home Demonstration Agents, Recreational Center program directors and college students are there, too. Enrollment is limited by the amount of space and equipment available. The largest of the weaving classes accommodates only twenty students. It pays to have Pi Phis in high places. The satisfying and happy relations with the University of Tennessee are largely due to Miss Jessie W. Harris, Tennessee A, Vice-Dean of the College of Home Economics there. We could neither visualize nor execute the Workshop without her guidance and her contacts. The extensive correspondence and the transition from school to workshop, as well as the execution of the plans fell upon Ruth Dyer and Esther Mines. This summer our staff includes as Director, Miss Marian Heard of the University of Tennessee who will also instruct in Advanced Jewelry; Mary Elizabeth Sullivan, Washington A, who studied with Dorothy Liebes, in Sweden, and at Cranbrook Academy, heads the weaving; Ingeborg Longbers, now on the faculty at the University of Tennessee but formerly one of the heads of her own weaving school in Sweden, who will teach advanced weaving and -lag making; Jane Glass of the Tennessee faculty who teaches Textile Design and Recreational Crafts; Helen B. Watson, also of the University of Tennessee, who THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 93 is Director of Social Activities and Community Recreation; Mr. Allen H. Eaton, outstanding authority on American Crafts, formerly with the Russell Sage Foundation, as lecturer. We have two graduate assistants there on scholarships, Nancy Alexander, Iowa of Iowa State, and Margaret Gibson of the University of Tennessee. Recreation, both organized and impromptu, is always part of every summer program and Gatlinb.urg, with its easy access to the trails and streams of the Smoky Mountain National Park, offers endless opportunities. This year the Gateway Stock Company of New York City under the direction of Mr. John Richards asked to return to Gatlinburg and lease the High School Auditorium where for five nights a week, they will offer another form of recreation to the residents and visitors to Gatlinburg. The plays are well selected and well staged and could point the way to a summer theater project of our own, one day. This year we are delighted to have placed our stamp of approval on the first Craftsman's Fair ever to be held in the southern mountains by loaning our grounds for that purpose for four days following the close of the Summer Workshop. It is sponsored jointly by the Southern Highlands Handicraft Guild and Southern Highlanders, Inc. to both of which we belong. It is a venture to show the highest standards of the crafts of the region as well as to acquaint the public with the difference between poor and well-made articles. In our area of the Southern Appalachian range there is greater diversity of crafts and a larger number of craftsmen than in any other comparable area in the entire country. This Fair will allow people not only to see well-planned exhibits of these crafts but also to see representatives of at least sixteen crafts such as Weaving, Basketry, Cabinet making, Pottery, Metal work, Leather work, Stone-polishing, Wood-working and Wood-carving, Glass-blowing, and Chair-making demonstrating their various skills. Never before has one had such an opportunity to see and talk with as many craftsmen in one place. You will perhaps recall that in Dr. Taylor's survey he visualized cottages placed on our beautiful hillsides where Master Crafts-men might one day come and work with their students. This time they will be under canvas tops but the idea is perhaps there for us. Thus far we have told you of much that is done at the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School but there has been little said of how these things get done. To read the Manual for the Director of the Settlement School gives no complete concept of her responsibilities. One needs to spend a few days at Teachers' Cottage to appreciate the many demands made upon her time. To cite a few: The janitor for the schools has broken his leg and someone must be found to fire the furnaces; not that it's OUR job it's the County's but in zero weather our boilers must be protected. Three Pi Phis from Colorado, or was it Maine, full of interest and questions, too, come to call and would appreciate a personally conducted tour. The cows are out and into the field newly landscaped by the hotel! Or the Southern Highlanders are meeting and wouldn't it be nice to have a tea for them in Stuart Cottage? Or perhaps even the Committee chairman writes and wants bids on a new note-book! Hats off to Ruth Dyer; her slogan is ever the protection of our property in Gatlinburg and of a job completed on time. Last year Helen Borgstrom, North Carolina A, who served as Assistant to the Director, resigned to be married. From the opposite coast in January came Esther Hensel Mines, Washington A. Her training in Music and in social welfare makes us feel we are fortunate in finding her and she has already endeared herself to the community. This spring, in memory of Dorothy Cansler Geis, Oklahoma A, who passed away in December, her husband and family, her alumnae club (Houston) and other friends donated to the children of Little Pigeon an Ampro 16 mm movie projector equipped with sound recorder and screen. This will be much used and appreciated as fine educational films are available through the University of Tennessee Extension Department. We have also received a number of contributions to the Memorial Fund which will be wisely expended ment. We have also received a number of contributions We need more Pi Phis working for Pi Phi in Gatlinburg to help spread their spirit of good will. In times past we have been both envied and criticized in the 'Burg. It was gratifying this spring to receive a letter which spoke of the fine feeling toward Pi Phi and the wonderful spirit that the Pi Phis bring to Gatlinburg as they come there. Also to learn of the life at the school itself through the closing paragraph of one of the reports this year: "May I tell you how much I enjoy my work . . . with its congenial co-operative staff and the happy family life at Teachers' Cottage!" Wishing to keep you informed as far as possible, the Committee reports these recent developments for the School. In 1943, following the joint acceptance by the County and Pi Beta Phi of the "Lease and Agreement," we had felt assured that Sevier County would acquire suitable land and build a grade school building adequate in size to care for the increasing enrollment. Other than that Pi Beta Phi was to approve the plans before the building was started and that it be constructed on land adjacent to the school, there were no restrictions placed on the County concerning size of the site nor upon the size, type and cost of the building itself. At no time has Sevier County been able to carry on an adequate school program without state and federal aid. In 1946-47, the County budget allotted $20,000 for the Gatlinburg area, but of this only $6,000 came from the County itself, the balance being from State and Federal aid. The County purchased a small lot adjoining our School property in compliance with the lease but did no building because of the war. This past year financial help has come to Tennessee Schools through the new sales tax voted by the legislature and effective June 1, 19.47. Seventy percent of the first twenty million dollar ($20,000,000) income from this sales tax is assigned to educational purposes. A little more than half will be used toward increased salaries for all teachers while the balance will aid the budgets of all state and county schools. A percentage of any overage above the first mentioned twenty millions will be assigned the County schools for building, maintenance and transportation purposes. Sevier County in its planning has relied on this last source to assist in building four County schools. In the spring of 1947 a survey of the Sevier County school system was made by the State School Planning Commission. Its findings for the Gatlinburg are these: It recommended consolidating with Gatlinburg, four neighboring one and two room schools: </p>
      <pb ref="arr6510091_0003" seq="03" n="94-95  "/>
       <p>94 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW Gatlinburg 345 pupils 9 teachers The Glades 67 pupils 2 teachers Banner 53 pupils 2 teachers Cartertown 26 pupils 1 teacher Big Ridge (isolated) 17 pupils 1 teacher 508 pupils 15 teachers It recommended the acquisition of sufficient acreage for a large elementary school unit and the eventual construction of a High School building there also. Though the present High School set-up is fairly adequate, they advocated keeping the two schools together. It felt the site acquired by the County adjoining our property too small. It considered a lease-agreement with Pi Beta Phi on a twenty year basis, too short a period to justify the expenditure of funds by the state. Since this survey, the town of Gatlinburg, the County, and Pi Beta Phi have attempted to work out a solution with the County Court and the State Board of Education. Last year the Gatlinburg Site Committee reported the following motion made and unanimously carried: That the Committee go on record and make preference that the Pi Phi School property be selected as the first choice site for the development of schools for the Gatlinburg area for present and long range development, providing sufficient acreage could be secured to meet the requirements of the State Board of Education." Mr. Lee, lawyer to Pi Beta Phi, did not advise selling any of our acreage. It was found that buying adjacent property would work a hardship on the owners since some of it was income property (tourist cabins). The State did not recommend building the grade school property on leased ground which was proffered by Pi Beta Phi for a fifty year lease, renewable. Last August the Settlement School Committee and Grand Council jointly agreed (a fraternity requirement) to offer this proposition as per this telegram sent to Squire Charlie Clabo of Gatlinburg, August 3, 1947: "In order to help Gatlinburg people satisfy State recommendations for School property, Pi Beta Phi will give one acre land where present grammar school stands in addition to eight-tenths (8/10) acre already offered. Boundaries of said acre will be determined by Phillip Elwood, Landscape architect. Grammar school and other buildings to remain property of Pi Beta Phi and may be removed if necessary. All property leased or given must revert to Pi Beta Phi if used for other than school purposes. The fraternity hopes happy relations with community for best interest of your schools will long continue." (signed by your Chairman) The County Court has now put the matter into the hands of the County Board of Education. Southern mountaineers do not always move with the dispatch evident in some other parts of the country and though investigations proceed, no conclusions as to site have been reached and no final decisions made. Our latest word from the County Superintendent and Gatlinburg's City Manager is that each anticipates meeting with the Settlement School Committee during our July meeting at Gatlinburg. This is America where we live in the democratic manner. We choose our leaders and once chosen we stand behind them but nevertheless we are free to criticize if we desire. This holds in Pi Phi, too. The Settlement School Committee welcomes your criticisms for, favorable or otherwise, they will help us to guidethe destinies of your Settlement School. We also, how-ever, ask for your understanding. If and when you visit Gatlinburg please try to remember that the school is understaffed and over-crowded and in consequence, the staff lives under high pressure ; that the native mountaineers are retiring people, sometimes reticent to talk. When one goes visiting with the nurse one sees how long it takes her to arrive at the real object of her visit, although they know her. If your questions receive an answer which seems incomplete, or unsatisfactory, write someone in close touch who knows the answer. The Publicity member of the Committee or its Chairman should know. We would like 'funds to maintain a "Public Relations" Pi Phi in Gatlinburg who could clarify some of your requests. One of these questions might be, "Are we still badly needed in Gatlinburg?" Our help is needed. The County could not meet the full state requirements without our aid. By our providing the extra teachers, by lending laboratory and other equipment we have helped to place the school on the accredited list of Tennessee schools. The evident income-producing main street does not extend far. Next time you visit Gatlinburg, turn right at Charlie Ogle's store and follow the river bank lane! The health of the community still depends upon our services. The arrival of two doctors in Gatlinburg relieves us of critical responsibilities but their fees, though not exorbitant, are beyond the pocketbooks of many. A program of disease prevention is import-ant, too, and our nurse can supplement the work of the doctors in many ways. Everywhere there is a trend toward consolidated schools. With our school serving as a central unit and drawing pupils from the outlying mountain districts, we offer an Extension program such as was started in the Sugarlands some years ago but without the cost of added equipment: The School is the heart of the community, serving as a center for elections, civic and PTA gatherings, and entertainments. There is no doubt that the whole cause of fraternities would suffer if the enterprise which was the pioneer altruistic project for both men's and women's fraternities, the one still most successful in its achievements, and the one universally recognized were to be curtailed. To get down to cold hard facts: At present the County receives no income from us in taxes but the lack of that revenue is more than balanced by many other returns they receive from us. Without our school, ' we would lose the "Not for Profit" classification and our holdings would become subject to local, county, state and federal taxes. And to go just one step farther: were this to happen even the "Not for Profit" classification of the fraternity itself might be in jeopardy. Your Committee knows that without the backing of the fraternity as a whole its chapters and its clubs we could do nothing. We constantly find more things to do than our budget allows. One could scarcely imagine the helplessness which would be evident both in the community and at the School were our interests there to be withdrawn. As in a family more children bring widened horizons, heavier duties and larger expenses, yet we would not neglect our oldest child in favor of one of the others. Nor do we send our adult children who have depended upon us out into cold reality without giving them our best assistance. Your committee asks that as you plan your chapter budget or your club activities for the year, consider please that the fraternity's oldest child is the THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 95 Settlement School and dedicated to our Founders. Starting out in a new fraternity position as in any other is not easy to do. There is much to learn and three of us were new on the committee during this convention interim. To Emma Woerner of Louisville, our Treasurer who goes off the Committee this summer and whom we shall sorely miss, we owe much for her knowledge of the Committee background and for her faithfulness. Also I owe much to my predecessor, Milder Odell Sale, for her counsel. From a personal standpoint, to have known all of my commit-tee previously has made my tasks pleasant and their complete cooperation has made them lighter. Miss Onken, as contact member from the Grand Council has been of great assistance, for her experience and her judgement furnish a balance for what sometimes might be termed mis-directed enthusiasm. We welcome Grace Adams Granger, Indiana of Indianapolis as our new Committee member. The April issue of Coronet magazine carries anillumination dedicated to American Teachers. The prose is by John Ruskin and might typify a part of that which we would do in Gatlinburg: "Education does not mean teaching people what they do not know. It means teaching them to behave. It is not teaching the youth the shapes of the letters and the tricks of numbers, and then leaving them to turn their arithmetic to roguery and their literature to lust. It means, on the contrary, training them into the perfect exercise and kingly continence of their bodies and souls. It is a painful, continual, and difficult work to be done by kindness, by watching, by warning, by precept, and by praise; but above all, by example." To the Grand Council for its confidence in appointing me to this committee I am grateful. To the Fraternity, my pledge is to carry out its wishes to the best of my ability. Respectfully submitted, RUTH BARRITT SMITH REPORT OF DIRECTOR EARS ago Anna E. Hamilton wrote a little poem called Influence. The words are these: "This learned I from the shadow of a tree, That to and fro did sway against a wall. Our shadow selves, our influence, may fall Where we ourselves can never be." This little poem has always reminded me of the thousands of loyal Pi Phis who, through the thirty-six years of the existence of the Settlement School, have contributed of their time, energy, and money to the success of our project in the Smokies. Times change and the isolated mountain settlement has be-come a thriving tourist town. It is hard to say just how much of this transformation can be traced to the influence of the Fraternity and the Settlement School. The advancement of education, better methods of sanitation and health, the cultivation of beauty of surroundings and the economic help given through the years, has helped to widen the pathway to the gate of the Great Smoky Mountain National Park and to enrich the lives of many peoples. Community Visitors to the village will notice a number of changes that have taken place in the last year. There are a number of new shops and homes. Other places have been made more modern in appearance. The new Methodist Church is gradually nearing completion. A visiting tourist gave the church a carillonic system by means of which music is sent out over the valley every Sunday and on special occasions. The American Legion purchased four acres of ground from Squire Maples and is developing the area as their funds permit. This summer they are sponsoring a ball team with a well laid out diamond. They hope to make the facilities of the grounds available for community recreation. Gatlinburg now has a very creditable little newspaper that is published each week by The Mountain Press. There has long been a need for such a venture so we are grateful that in The Gatlinburg Press the news of the community is so well presented. The city still has no water or sewage systems but plans are more advanced for the installation of the water system. A Tourist Bureau has been of much service in placing visitors and tourists in wanted accommodations as well as advertising the area in other resort sections. Pi Phi visitors will be most interested in twochanges that have greatly enhanced the beauty of our property. Approaching from Knoxville, the removal of two fences from the field in front of the Mountain View Hotel has made a green expanse of lawn a most welcome break in the closely built up town. The second improvement is even more noticeable. The old privet hedge along the street east of Arrow Craft Shop has been removed exposing to view the new Health Center. A small hemlock hedge has been set out back of the building and while the season is too late to permit of landscaping we will have a green lawn and some annual plantings around the base of the building. Two contributions to community life last summer were the third Workshop held by Pi Beta Phi and the University of Tennessee and the theatrical engagement of the Gateway Stock Company of New York. Ninety different people attended the Workshop for six weeks of intensive study in crafts and recreaction. The Stock Company played in the school gymnasium for nine weeks, giving plays in a professional manner. Office Helen Borgstrom, North Carolina A, who was my very efficient assistant for fifteen months, resigned in August to be married. She is now Mrs. J. K. Lydecker of Midland, Texas. It was difficult to secure a Pi Phi successor but in January Esther Mines of Washington A came to join the staff. She brings new enthusiasm and varied talents that are proving to be most helpful. School Starting with the 1947-1948 school year, newly enacted school laws made a nine months' school year mandatory for all rural and elementary schools in Tennessee and gave salary increases to all teachers. Additional revenue from the two per cent state sales tax is also to be allocated to the counties for building purposes. Sevier County Court action has been very slow. To date $40,000 has been set aside for the purchase of a school site in Gatlinburg but nothing has been acquired. School enrollment is over 500 with all facilities crowded. We have had two first and two second grade rooms making ten teachers in the Elementary School. It was necessary to convert the room adjoining the Home Economics laboratory into a class room for one of the first grades. Enrollment </p>
      <pb ref="arr6510091_0004" seq="04" n="96-97  "/>
       <p>96 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW n the high school has been such that the County would provide another teacher if space for a class room could be found. The only change in teaching personnel occurred at Christmas time when Mr. King resigned to accept a position with the Veterans' Administration in their training department, at Nashville. Mr. J. B. Johnson, the teacher hired by the Fraternity for Physical Education work, took over the duties of the principal and Mr. Lawson, a former Science teacher, was secured for the necessary class work. The usual plays and programs were given. The Senior play, "Let's Grow Up," was especially well cast and produced. This class has been very active during their four years in school. They earned enough money to take the class and two chaperones to Washington, D.C., in a chartered bus, for their class trip. Twenty seniors will graduate May 21. Basketball is the favorite sport. Our teams did well during the season, finishing up with several victories, The girls' team from the Elementary School won the County Tournament. The high school boys won the consolation trophy and the girls the runner-up trophy at the Tenth District Tournament. A new addition to the gymnasium, housing shower rooms for boys and girls, has added to the physical education program. This project was paid for by PTA, County and Pi Phi funds. Mr. Johnson did some extra work making shelves and benches to make the rooms more comfortable. This spring the Home Economics Department of the University of Tennessee used our Home Economics department as a practice teaching center. Two seniors from the University spent a month at the school teaching under Miss William's direction. They lived at Teachers' Cottage and entered into the life of the school and community. Should this be a permanent thing it would mean that the teacher in our school would automatically be selected by the University. A high level of instruction could be expected. The school program has again been enriched by fraternity funds that have provided two full time teachers, one for music and one for arts and crafts, plus a part time wood working teacher for the boys. Mrs. Stanley Armstrong has handled the music instruction with Esther assisting at the piano for assembly and chapel programs. The children have a natural love for music. Their soft voices respond beautifully. Miss Petrie has increased their love of the beautiful in arts and crafts and given them the joy of constructing things with their hands. Weaving, pottery and other skills have been used in the classes. Mr. Carl Huskey has devoted two hours a day to instructing the boys in wood working. PTA contributed to worth-while improvements at the School. They have operated the school lunch room all year and have made plans for a summer Bingo campaign to raise money for next year's projects. In addition to the $750 paid towards the showers they spent $400 rewiring the high school building. They also spent some money renovating the office of the Elementary School principal. This room serves as the library of the grade school children. Proceeds from one rummage sale was spent to buy books for this library. Funds were provided for a platform in the music room. The high school library has also received some nice gifts from clubs and individuals. Mrs. Benjamin Wier gave a steel filing cabinet and a hand-some handmade walnut desk. Committee purchased a set of the New World Book Encyclopedia which has been most useful to all the students. In memory of Dorothy Cansler Geis, Oklahoma A, who diedin December, 1947, her family and husband presented the School with an Ampre 16 mm movie projector equipped with sound recorder and screen. These articles, marked with appropriate silver plates, add the service of the latest aids in visual education to our equipment. Dormitory With the use of the kitchen for feeding the Work-shop students it was necessary to modernize as much as possible. The old coal range was replaced by two electric ranges. One electric hot water heater proved to be inadequate so a booster heater which is connected to the furnace had to be added. A radiator to provide heat in winter, new linoleum and fresh paint have all helped to make the kitchen more comfortable and efficient. Before Workshop, many more dishes had to be purchased and some cooking equipment. At Stuart an electric ventilating fan for the third floor made that house more livable during hot weather. It was necessary to treat this house for termites as they had made quite a start on the living room floor. Most of the year we have had three boys living in the dormitory under Mr. Johnson's guidance. Miss Hodgen has the supervision of the eight girls in their work schedules and until the time that Esther Mines came was also their chaperone. Since January Esther has lived in the downstairs suite at Stuart and has been in charge of the girls. All the students seem to enjoy life at the school and I am sure receive more benefit than they realize. Farm The Farm continues to supply the school table with eggs, chickens, dairy products and fresh vegetables. Workshop students especially appreciated this feature of life at the school. We have sold some eggs and chickens to the Mountain View Hotel. Increased cost on baby chicks and all feeds made it imperative that we raise fewer chickens this season. There is some revenue from the rental of the mules. A number of people like their help in getting in small gardens. Health Center Before many weeks the new Health Center building made possible by a most generous gift from the estate of Dr. W. P. Gershwiler (the wife of Dr. Gershwiler was Florence Province Gershwiler, a member of Indiana B), of Indianapolis, Ind., gifts from California A and D.C. A chapters and Fraternity funds, will be in use. Barber and McMurray of Knoxville designed the building to harmonize with Arrow Craft. The exterior is of hand hewn white oak shingles and native stone with a slate roof. Inside finish is of random width knotty pine for hall, class room and office. The first aid and clinic rooms are in gleaming white enamel. There is a lavatory near the front door and a full bath connected to the class room so that home sick room care may be demonstrated. Such an addition to the physical plant will mean much to our very important health program. Mrs. Chalmers has carried on this program through the year with the usual inoculations and inspections in our school and the three rural schools that we include in our work. Special emphasis has been placed on education along health lines. Talks to parents of school children and newspaper publicity added to the work done in classrooms all helps to spread the gospel of good health. The State Mobile X-Ray Unit spent two days in the village. Between 400 and 500 people were given free chest X-rays. Friday afternoon Clinics have been held all during the year THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 97 with special stress on Maternal Health and Infant Welfare. Many new names have been added to the files. r sent fifty dollars towards our health program. There have been other gifts of money and material items to advance the work. Most of the year there was no County doctor or nurse. Thanks to Pi Beta Phi the health of this community is good. Arrowcraft There have been two important changes in personnel in this program during the year. Our talented, artistic Miss Meta resigned to accept a position at Highlands University in Las Vegas, New Mexico, on September 1. From then until March 1 we had no designer or "Weave Boss," as the weavers say. Mrs. Snow and Lura carried on with splendid help from the girls in the shop. The new designer is Tina McMorran of Eugene, Oregon, who was one of the students at the Workshop last summer. With a fine background of study and many years of weaving experience she has already proved that she is capable of handling our rather complex system and of working out beautiful new designs for the shop. Another change occurred when Miss Georgie, after many years of faithful service, felt that her health made it impossible for her to continue her work as manager of the Hotel Shop. She will be greatly missed. The distinctive afghans that she has woven to satisfy many customers may never be duplicated. At present that shop is closed but we hope to have a manager for it before the realseason opens. The year has been a banner one for the shop. Twenty-six more clubs and three more active chapters than last year have had goods. This increase is partly offset by more returns than last year. In many instances more than the twenty-five per cent allowed was re-turned. Money returns from seven clubs have averaged over $1,000 each. The checks for weavers reached an all time high in April when they amounted to over $5,000. We have considerable stock on the shelves and hope that it is not too much for the demands of the coming season. Each year there are more shops opening in town. The quality of the weaving offered for sale by them is improving and more real competition is experienced. We are fortunate in that in addition to the tourist trade in town we have our Club orders and outlets through the different Guild shops: Mrs. Snow expects to take a large stock to Convention and we have been asked to have stock ready for the big Craftsman's Fair to be held on the School grounds later in the summer. At the close of another year I wish to thank all members of Pi Beta Phi who have made possible the extension of the influence of the Settlement School far beyond its boundaries. It has been a pleasure to work with the Grand Officers and members of the Settlement School Committee who give so many hours of unselfish labor to the work. Respectfully submitted, RUTH DYER ARROWCRAFT REPORT 12 ST year I compared gross sales from June, 1935, to the present. This year while we are still making a profit it might be interesting to compare that phase of Arrowcraft. There were months around Christmas of that first year when our own pay checks had to wait so as to meet the pay roll for the weavers. If the Clubs would send in their money as they sell the goods it should never happen. Their reports are due in May, I believe, but if you noted accounts receivable as of April 30 report, they still owe in cash or have goods amounting to over $25,000. 1935 did show a profit, even so, of $2,992.04; 1936 $4,663.83 ; 1937 $6,702.86; 1938 something over $9,000. 1939 in-creased $2,700 but 1940 remained stationary. In 1941 the trend was decidedly up, profit amounted to $14,103.08. 1942 and 1943 dropped back to some-thing over $12,000. Then we began to climb again. 1944 was $18,095.88; 1945 $20,762.85; 1946 $28,217.63; 1947 $37,377.58. 1948 so far is $31,-768.61, which is two months short of a year. If more of the Clubs settle this month we should come out ahead of last year. April just past doubled the profit for March. May is usually low again but we should then have some good months through the summer. As far as stock goes we have never before had as large an inventory, $36,306.62 as of April 30. But with weaving supplies still a bit over $25,000 it seemed wise to get as much of that as possible ready for the summer months, Convention, The Craftsman's Fair, and the Southern Highland Shops. Quite a few of the Clubs had Spring sales, in fact there has never beFn a quiet month throughout the year. Back in the thirties there were three or four months when we had to look for things to do instead of wondering if there would come a time for the year's thorough cleaning. But I do think this is the time to Stop, Look, and Listen. With more and better handicrafts throughoutthe Country there may come a saturation point, especially if money gets tighter and tighter and living cost keeps on soaring. Competition is also getting much keener in Gatlinburg and some of the things other shops sell a bit better. After not having enough to satisfy either the Pi Phis or customers for the past several years, one hesitated about curtailing production for this year at least. But there soon may be a danger of overproduction. Returns from the Clubs were much worse than last year. Many sent way more than 25% .back. There were 26 more Clubs sent for goods than last year and three more Chapters. There have been only seven Clubs who have sent over $1,000 in return. The next two months should change that also. You all know how very much I like to work with Tina McMorran. It is a joy to feel she is behind me 100% and will cooperate in any way possible. There is no reason why we cannot have some very beautiful weaving to sell with the cheaper things. But we can not lose track of the fact that very beautiful weaving commands a high price. While our basket bags were selling for $3.50 a Pi Phi wrote me they were selling in New York for $15, $20, and $22.50. That cheapens our things instead of enhancing their value, and a young man in the Shop told me ours. were every bit as good as Saks. Lura deserves honorable mention as never before. She carried a hard and difficult job from the time Miss Meta left until Tina arrived. She kept the weavers busy as they have never been busy before and it is due to her that we have so many shelves and boxes of finished products. I am quite sure that anyone in Gatlinburg will agree with me that I have three of the best girls in the village. Tina had only been here a short time when she was marveling at their loyalty to me, and </p>
      <pb ref="arr6510091_0005" seq="05" n="98-99  "/>
       <p>98 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW by being loyal to me I consider them loyal to Pi Phi. They take a personal interest in the appearance of the Shop and a keen interest in the things that they sell. From the little I wait on customers, Pi Phi and other-wise, there are many difficult and impossible questions to answer. It is too bad there has not been a folder to hand out for the past three years, because there is propaganda against the Shop and the School up and down the street. It is safe to say that more than half of the Pi Phis who come along still say "this is all made in the School!' In closing I want to give due praise to my good friend, Eunice Cole. She not only keeps me straight on facts and figures but is the balance that is needed. The two months I was away from the job this winter went smoothly due to her help to the girls. I only hope that I can keep all the staff at Arrowcraft until my own retirement. Respectfully submitted, ETHEL M. SNOW REPORT OF WEAVING DEPARTMENT HAVING been at Arrowcraft but two short months, my report will of necessity be short. With Lura's able guidance, I have called on some thirty-five of the weavers in their homes and have met most of the others through office calls and our spring meeting of the Weaver's Guild. Mindful of the suggestions from the committee, I have given special effort to planning items which will put into production old stocks of materials on hand. While this may not show up at once in reduced inventory, it will clear the way for newer and more interesting threads. Also at the suggestion of the committee, I have tried to find a source of supply for the heavy chenille which was used in the bath rugs of some years ago. So far, I have found nothing available without a wait of several weeks for special dyeing. We are weaving a small number from old stocks on hand and trying out some in candlewick and Rugro for your approval. We have quite a supply of Rugro in dark colors and feel that rugs of these will sell for bedroom use as well as bath rugs. These will run somewhat less expensive than chenille. We are submitting an adaptation of the Greensboro prize napery in a doilie and napkin and a simple doilie in Pi Phi colors which will tie in with our pastel blue napkin for the trade, but will have a blue napkin with Pi Phi letters for orders. We are indebted to Mary Elizabeth Starr Sullivan, Washington A, for the Whig Rose apron with its ingenious belt 'arrangement. It simplifies the sewing so we can have the weaver bring them in finished in-stead of having to handle them twice through the shop. We also adapted the idea to our other apron, as well as the dirndls. The Mother and Daughter dirndls are selling in limited quantities and since they and the basket bags are seasonal, we are making them cautiously. The basket bags are selling rather briskly and the basket makers are working out new shapes to our order. They make a splendid project for using many materials, some very old and some in limited amounts. We have also used up a large box of old warps on these and the small runners and doll mats. We still have a large stock of the Irish linen and filler linens bought during the war emergency and for these we designed the new towel set in Spanish lace weave, a dresser scarf in the same weave and part of the Greensboro set. We feel that these can all run for a year with no new addition of those threads. There are a few new ties with neck scarves to match some of them, and two new neck scarves with head squares to match. Due to the increase in volume of weaving, as shown in the attached report, we are having difficulty in finding space to store our stocks of materials. Putting surplus upstairs necessitates many trips a day carrying heavy packages. Orlie is working on getting some more shelves in the work-shop, which should give us a more orderly arrangement and save much time. In conclusion, may I tell you how much I enjoy my work at Arrowcraft with its congenial, co-operative staff and the happy family life at Teacher's Cottage. I am doubly appreciative of the opportunity for the summer classes with Miss Langbers which will, I hope, bring profit to us both. Respectfully submitted, TINA I. MCMORRAN Weaving Purchases 1942 Total $13,398.38 42-43 '43-44 44-45 45-46 46-47 47-48 July 379.84 726.41 807.20 384.00 2,009.60 2,409.74 August 569.98 1,124.32 1,588.11 1,806.50 2,755.63 2,525.20 September 887.02 992.67 2,620.01 1,818.53 2,878.20 2,267.10 October 1,788.14 2,073.02 2,194.93 2,920.42 3,463.11 3,223.88 November 1,966.45 2,122.85 2,442.42 3,021.83 4,954.42 4,794.86 December 2,991.67 3,367.66 3,632.91 2,507.10 4,331.51 5,584.34 January 59.59 455.87 1,773.14 1,926.68 3,172.94 4,359.43 February 378.50 1,739.70 2,899.11 3,376.09 4,680.46 4,682.50 March 470.28 1,892.43 2,301.93 2,543.96 3,141.90 4,343.11 April 804.13 2,243.01 2,084.93 2,481.11 2,500.71 5,148.92 May 820.89 1,875.48 2,376.78 2,521.77 3,583.04 June 1,667.31 2,997.38 2,486.51 3,096.29 2,222.98 12,701.61 21,610.80 27,207.98 28,481.58 39,693.50 39,392.56 (10 Mo.) 45,766.28 Weaving Sales 81,105.17 104,226.11 108,970.18 71,485.38 82,174.28 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 99 Weaving Supplies Used 207.79 488.85 455.92 215.72 1,238.39 1,600.59 July 927.38 August 260.02 752.25 1,561.31 992.62 1,666.21 1,587.62 . 668.22 September 319,97 1,302.77 1,356.18 1,061.71 1,694.31 1,440.34 1,725.91 October 956.28 2,140.93 2,017.97 November 1,409.28 1,472.12 1,570.71 1,769.85 3,155.46 2,915.41 2,004.63 2,132.40 2,279.71 1,472.36 2,667.34 3,509.82 December 7 261.50 1,046.62 1,089.53 1,984.38 2,558.93 i,aeril,,uruarayry 1434:g 1,062.62 1,658.01 1,943.94 2,990.45 2,701.00 March 263.70 1,090.87 1,299.48 1,450.55 2,100.60 2,366.98 463.36 1,356.55 1,134.31 1,386.10 1,551.97 2,970.95 April ............................ 558.00 1,178.71 1,407.80 1,363.47 2,350.65 May ............................. June 1,160.57 1,699.29 1,483.15 1,846.40 1,463.26 7,905.30 13,466.13 16,180.58 16,318.16 25,006.95 23,669.61 THE JENNIE NICOL MEMORIAL HEALTH CENTER THE MODERN tendency for education and prevention in medicine is quite apparent in comparing the work of the past fifteen years. It is a surprising thing to note the variation in some things. For instance, Typhoid and Diphtheria inoculations have not in-creased much, while vaccinations for Small Pox, for-bidden in some homes in 1933, have trebled in number. Serum for Whooping Cough was not given then, and is almost universal, now. Field visits have dropped nearly a third, but office calls are up two and one half times. This year, three times as many First Aid dressings were done, although in those days, they had a full time assistant constantly on duty. We realize there has been an increase in population, but we now have two doctors in town, and many cases go directly to the office of one or the other. In 1933, 1,600 pupil inspections were made, and last year, there were 4,180. We made nearly three times as many health talks, and picture shows and newspaper articles helped in the educational program. Mothers' meetings were held in the rural schools, and though the attendance was poor, a start was made. When we stop to consider there are nearly seven hundred students in the district served by the Health Center, and about as many younger children, we realize the importance of eduCation. We have, also, a large group of young folk, out of school, who are working in the area. Many of them marry and settle down in the community, establish their homes and start raising their families. We don't expect too much change from the old timey ways by the parents, but we do see results every year. The regular Friday afternoon Well Baby Clinics were held throughout the year, with special ones added from time to time. Last year, we didn't have a County Health Doctor or Nurse, and were unable to secure the services of the State Officers for the annual Pre-School Round-Up. As a consequence, we had a serial affair, which lasted most of the summer. By means of cards and home visits, we managed to contact most of the beginners, and had a satisfactory response. This year, the Parent-Teacher Organization has taken over the responsibility of advertising the Round-Up. They have secured the services of a local doctor and dentist for consultation, as well as a State Nutritionist. They have promised to provide assistants for the day, and transportation to and from the Clinic, if necessary. It has already been postponed twice, but will be held as soon as the new building is ready for occupancy. It is very gratifying to know that there is such a spirit of cooperation and interest in the work of the Health Center. Reminder cards are sent to prents of small children during the year, for inoculations and checkup. Reports to parents are sent home with each child following the annual physical examination in the schools. The records show a goodly response, and in many instances, defects are promptly corrected. Stu-dents aer given inoculations when due, and individual inspections are given regularly. This Spring, State Health Officers contacted dentists of each locality, and secured the promise of every one to give some time regularly to the school program. Students who were unable to pay for the service were given dental corrections, and the cost of the material was paid by the State and the Board of Education. Only one of our dentists cooperated, and he so reluctantly that but five of our children received the benefits. It was a great disappointment to the teachers and the students, for we had worked hard to create interest and enthusiasm in the venture. The State Mobile X-Ray Unit gave us two whole days in February, and between four and five hundred people were processed. We arranged programs in all the High Schools of Sevier County, with speakers and uniformed nurses from Knoxville. We assisted the city officials during the Rabies danger, giving Pasteur treatment for the children and Anti-Rabic shots for dogs. With the assistance of the e r Corrective Fund, and the wholehearted cooperation of the local Lion's Club, several children were provided with glasses. Six children were given milk to supplement their diets until the parents could make arrangements to provide it regularly. Two girls were given tonics, and clothing of various sorts and sizes was distributed. Our one Polio case was taken to the Crippled Children's Clinic several times, provided with braces, and given prescribed therapy daily for a period of time. He was admitted to the Children's Hospital this past month, and will remain there for an indefinite time. Maternal health and Infant welfare continue to be an important part of our work. Special inoculations ordered by different physicians for allergies, asthma, anemia, and the like, are given, and First Aid is given in emergencies, as usual. Talks for various groups, and in the school room, picture shows, and newspaper articles are ways of spreading the gospel of health, and we try to help any agency that will advance that end. The days are very full, and the years seem to pass all too rapidly to accomplish the things that should be done. We look with longing eyes at the beautiful new building, and wonder if we will be able to reach more people from that center. The doctors are very </p>
      <pb ref="arr6510091_0006" seq="06" n="100-101  "/>
       <p>100 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW helpful, and no request has ever been refused. The members of the Fraternity are generous and interested, and the local organizations most cooperative. Community health is a community problem. It is bigger than any one individual or any one organization. It requires leadership, but more than that, it must have approval and support of the community itself. Through the many years of service, the Fraternity has provided the leaders, and community sup-port has grown steadily. It should be a source of pride and satisfaction to know that we can have the support of individuals and civic organizations. With-out it, we would be, to a certain extent, interlopers. With it, we can go far in service to humanity. Class of *Work 1947-8 Field Visits 862 998 Office Calls 2805 2776 First Aid 2184 2208 Diphtheria Immunizations 88 62 Small Pox Vaccinations 257 218 Total Typhoid Inoculations 588 451 Completed Typhoid Series 404 325 Total Pertussis Inoculations 119 57 Therapeutic Inoculations 217 91 Health Talks 119 89 Pupil Inspections 4180 4036 Pasteur Treatments 15 Anti-Rabic Inoculations 14 20 Newspaper Articles 31 2 MARJORIE CHALMERS, R.N. 1946.7 REPORT OF THE PRINCIPAL N THE start of the school year of 1947-48 I instructed all the High School and the 6th, 7th, and 8th grades in Physical Education. I taught all the High School Boys and Girls in Health. I also did all the coaching for the boys and girls basketball teams. Our basketball season extended over five months and during this time we practiced from 3:15 to 5:15 and from 6:30 to 9:00, five days a week, with the girls practicing in the afternoon and the boys at night. Though we did a lot of extra work practicing, am sure it paid off. Despite the handicap of having the worst gymnasium and smallest' school in our district, our boys won third place in our basketball tournament and our girls second. This is the first time in our school's history a boy's team has won a trophy and the second for our girls. Our girls won their first one last year. We placed two boys and three girls on the all-tournament team only one other school was able to do this. Newport with 400 students, Sevierville with 600 and Pi Beta Phi with 140 students, each had two teams on the floor receiving trophies at the conclusion of the tournament. Both Newport and Sevierville had a coach for each of their teams but I was the only coach from Pi Beta Phi. Besides the trophies, we received $161 as our part of the gate receipts, the largest amount received by any school. During the regular season our girls won 20 out of 23 games. This is a record that is seldom reached. Our boys won 15 out of 25 games, which, I think, is an outstanding record as all of our opposing schools are much larger than ours. With the help of the PTA, which gave $650, Pi Beta Phi Fraternity, which gave $300, and the county, which gave $300, we were able to install showers inour school. In addition, an estimated $250 improvement in the shower rooms, was made by the school in building shelves, benches and putting a rubber mat on the floor. The money for these improvements was taken out of the athletic fund and I did the work. There are four shower heads in each of the shower rooms, and our showers are the best I have seen in our county. The senior class of 1946-47 left $35 for which to build stage scenery. With this money I bought material and built stage props with an estimated value of $200. These are so constructed that they can be used year after year. When Mr. King left and I assumed the duties of Principal, I discontinued instructing the 6-7-8 grades in physical education, but I continued teaching health until the end of the 6th month. I have continued to instruct all the high school students in physical education in addition to duties of Principal. As co-sponsor of the senior class I helped with all the class functions as far as time would permit. As "house father" I feel sure I should have more time to spend with the boys. We are still a little too easy with them though two of the boys left because they thought we were too tight on them. I do feel the boys have improved in most respects unless it is their work on the farm. To me they are lazy in this respect. The PTA paid for the installing of new lights in our school building. They have proven to be very successful. The PTA also paid for the installing of a stage in the music room. With money from the PTA we have been able to keep soap and paper towels in our wash rooms. Respectfully submitted, J. B. JOHNSON FINANCIAL REPORT OF THE PHYSICAL EDUCATION DEPARTMENT Balance brought forward from 1946-47 $ 220.99 Ogles store for hardware 22.47 Dentons Drugs for tape 14.94 Income Mountain Press, season tickets 5.00 Ball games $ 528.40 Joe Manleys-athletic equipment' 44.00 P.T.A 128.69 urpheys Cleaners 8.50 Collected for ball suits 121.50 Womans press 2.00 Tournament 161.82 American Institute of Family Relations 8.75 Mass. Society of Family Relations 1.00 Total $1,161.40 Otha King, chewing gum 1.00 Albert Mock, Health Material 2.00 Expense Return of P.T.A. money 32.00 Officiating ball games $ 101.00 Stair Tech, ball game 20.00 Transportation to ball games 80.00 A. J. King Lumber Co 26.95 Athletic House for athletic equipment 58.97 Rawling Cleaners 21.70 Max Freedman for athletic equipment 61.70 Electrical Appliance Co 1.78 Bowers for athletic equipment 268.86 Knox Sporting Goods Co 4.95 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 101 Cash Hardware Co 27.88 Eats during tournament 61.00 Tax 102.26 Expense of gas on ball trips 20.00 Total $ 999.61 Amount carried forward for 1948-49 $ 161.79 This is not an exact report as there are still a fey bills to be paid. Respectfully submitted, J. B. JOHNSON REPORT OF CRAFT DEPARTMENT FIVE years of Crafts in Pi Beta Phi school has proved to be a satisfactory and enjoyable experience. The children are eager for each new project, and take pleasure in the discovered use of their hands. This has been the busiest of the five years because of three additional classes. There have been two first grades, and because of the size of the seventh and eighth grades and the limited space in the shop, those two grades were divided into two classes each. This made twelve grade school classes, and the high school class which met for two hours every day. Both the boys and girls high school classes were made up of juniors and seniors this year, because so many seniors who planned to enter college found they lacked credits and had to take extra math. This left room for juniors to enter the craft classes. Both Mr. Husky and I felt the change in the type of student this year and we found it necessary to make every effort in order to produce satisfactory results in our high school classes. The girls were happy in their work and some did very well, but I missed the enthusiasm of previous classes. Weaving instruction was carried on in the usual manner, then pottery which became even more popular. We visited the Pigeon Forge Pottery, and Marcus Ceramics, the new pottery here in Gatlinburg. Block printing proved to be especially interesting this year as each girl used her name from which to make her design and printed it on aprons, skirts, and other items. Bound books with crayon decorated covers were made, leather purses, braided gimp bracelets and character dolls. We were fortunate at Christmas to have Mrs. Lexow come to the shop and give a demonstration of Christmas decorations which could be made at home. Miss Williams was invited to join us with her third year Home Economics class. Both classes later made several of the items. I reserved a loom for the 8th grade girls and they came in whenever possible the entire year until each girl has had the opportunity of weaving a small pieceof overshot material. They have also done pottery. made leather purses, gimp bracelets, stenciled Christmas cards, learned to make cross stitch designs on checked cloth, and finally asked if they might make character dolls too. The 7th and 8th grade classes have visited our local pottery and Mrs. McDonald ,gave a demonstration of turning a pot on the wheel. The 7th grade story is practically the same as the 8th. The junior group of the 4th, 5th and 6th grades, have studied lettering, color and design. Some interesting pictures were made with crayons, then painted with black tempera. Many of these were quite charming and the teachers were happy to pin them up in their rooms. Pottery was done in the 6th grade but there were too many children in each of the other grades for work in clay. A table loom with a colorful warp was put in a second grade room and in the third grade. There was much excitement the day I brought the looms. I have been pleasantly surprised with the weaving these little children have done. I took clay to one of the second grades, one of the mothers wanted to come help, and it was one of the happiest class periods of the year. Charles Earl Ogle modeled his father's motor boat, and Miranda made a turtle. At the beginning of the year I bought twelve copies of famous paintings and at various times we had a lesson in art appreciation. The story of the artist was told, and the painting described. The children showed great interest and each teacher was well pleased and has said she would like that particular work continued. I believe the five years of crafts has been helpful as well as enjoyed by the children. Many mothers have spoken to me of the work done, and that they were pleased with the crafts taught the children. It has been a happy time for the children and for me, and we have learned much from each other. Respectfully submitted, ELIZABETH PETRIF HOME ECONOMICS DEPARTMENT A' THE close of this first year of teaching experience, I leave with many happy memories collected from working with students. As I am getting married this summer, I will not be returning to Gatlinburg this fall. I have enjoyed working with the faculty and living at our Teacher's Cottage. From the remaining money in my budget, plans have been made to secure a new treadle Singer machine. Providing this machine is not obtainable at the present time, other pieces of sewing equipment will be purchased. With the other money, a much needed Irish linen table cloth has been added, several new books and many small pieces of kitchen equipment. The students enjoyed a very interesting as well asprofitable experience. The University of Tennessee chose Pi Beta Phi as one of their training centers for girls majoring in Home Economics. Two Senior girls were sent to work with me and the students for one month. During this time, they lived at the Teacher's cottage and assumed the responsibilities of a faculty member. The student teachers felt it was a privilege to come to Gatlinburg and work with our students. The FHA has been very active this year in that we had several community activities. We attended several meetings at UT and Sevierville. At the meeting in Sevierville, two of the girls were elected officers and I was chosen as their counselor. In the Junior class, the girls especially enjoyed </p>
      <pb ref="arr6510091_0007" seq="07" n="102-103  "/>
       <p>102 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW their project on refinishing the floors of the department. They did a beautiful piece of work and it was a good learning experience for them. Other individual projects were: clothing construction, advanced meal preparation, candy cookery, management of department, planning Junior-Senior banquet, vocational guidance and Courtship-Marriage. Outside speakers and film were used to aid in interest development. The sophomore class enjoyed their study of clothing construction, meal preparation, manners, child care. Their most interesting problem was on Courtship-Marriage. We had as our guest speaker, Reverend Ashley who read the marriage ceremony and discussed the importance of a happy marriage. I feelthat the girls learned a great deal of practical knowledge from this problem. The freshman girls greatly enjoyed their problem on child care. We had a playschool for children from the ages of 2-6. The students enjoyed working with them. Other projects were: nutrition, personal grooming, manners, basic foods and basic clothing techniques. As sponsor of the Junior class, there were many extracurricular activities which included chapel pro-grams, class social functions, money making ideas, class play and Junior-Senior banquet. Respectfully submitted, SUE WILLIAMS SUPERVISOR OF PUBLIC SCHOOL MUSIC A. Area of Instruction Nine elementary grades; elementary chorus; high school glee club; high school assembly. B. Objectives for the Year Afford the joy of singing for each child. Enable pupils to use their voices correctly, thus encouraging beauty of tone and safe-guarding voices for maturity. Provide a background of musical culture. Promote a sense of co-operation and service through group activity in home, church and community. Encourage the creative spirit. C. Record of Work Done in the Elementary Grades Grade One: Procedure Careful attention to voices, ;special help to those unable to sing on pitch. Conservation of the voice above all; presenting songs as enjoyment; something pleasant to hear pleasant to express in words and melody; rhythmic activities; impersonation-creative interpretation; listening to suitable records. Accomplishments Two Assembly programs presented; Mother Goose, School Days; Rhythm Band functioning. Grade Two: Procedure Rote songs as in First grade; use text book for Study songs; ear-training program extended to make association with eye training; further rhythm experiences: dramatizing songs. Accomplishments Successful assembly programs: Safety First, Health Program, Valentine; tonal effects "Chimes" for Christmas program. Grade Three: Procedure In addition to Rote songs, using study and observation songs; new ideas of musical notation; time drills; reading readiness emphasis; use of piano keyboard as pictured in textbook; appreciation emphasis. Accomplishments Assembly program "February calendar"; choral reading and Russian folk song for Christmas program; "Easter chorus." Grade Four: Procedure Tone drills; rhythm exercises, stepping and clapping; tonal patterns; studying types of music; discovery of contemporary composers; singing rounds as preparation for two-part singing. Accomplishments Program of unusual folk songs presented at P.T.A. installation; Appalachian carols used at Christmas; "Seven Joys of Mary"; "Twelve Days of Christmas"; story of the flag, an original sketch using six new flag songs. Grade Five: Procedure Further notation; emphasis upon ability to use the printed language of music; time drills; drills in the music of our country; recognition of classical themes; tonal elements in music reading, chording; development of a songrepertory; chromatic sharps and flats. Accomplishments Modern songs learned, among the most popular "April Showers" Silvers; songs by Hoagy Carmichael, Romberg, Berlin; carols from the French and Dutch given at Christmas program; traditional mountain ballads given at Weaver's meetings; folk songs presented at annual P.T.A. meeting; use of talented pupils in accompanying class. Grade six: Procedure Continued appreciation periods, singing along with favorites records; correlate folk music with other subjects, such as history, customs, geography; notation drills; creative chording. Accomplishments Many new songs presented at assembly; unusual songs from Belgium and England for Christmas programs; vocal arrangements of "Blue Danube" and "Tales from the Vienna Woods," Strauss. Grades Seven and Eight: Procedure Added emphasis upon notation; twoand three-part songs; study of keys and time; development of good tones; formation of elementary chorus; teaching chorus manners. Accomplishments Rare carols presented at Christmas; Patriotic service, using "The Freedom Train," "An American Prayer." At promotion, featuring: "The Skaters' Waltz," Waldteufel; "That's America to Me," Robinson; "Chiapanecas," Mexican folk song; "Joshua Fit de Battle of Jericho," spiritual. The eighth grade gave an unusual musical sketch at Lion Club Banquet "Mountain Drama." In April, the elementary grades presented the Operetta "The Obliging Clock," learning twenty-five new choruses, besides supplying leads and solos and duets, etc. More than a hundred children were used on the stage. D. Record of Work Done in the High School Procedure: Accent on good tone work; drilling on chorus manners; coaching of many individual singers, ensembles; aiding the various classes in their assembly programs; developing a larger glee club. Accomplishments Seasonal musical numbers; on two occasions glee club was presented at assembly programs; the phonograph-radio combination has proved popular; music department has furnished two assembly pro-grams, featuring various types of music; glee club attempting three-part as well as two-part. At P.T.A. meeting gave: "Gay Fiesta" Tejada; "Grandma" Cain. At baccalaureate service sang: "The Lord's Prayer" Malotte; "Verdant Pastures" Handel. Class night, "Serenade," Romberg; "A Wish," Chopin-McKay; "One Alone," Romberg. At library Valentine Party presented: "Voices of the Wood" Rubin-stein; "Short'nin' Bread" traditional; "Soldier, Will THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 103 You Marry Me?" ; Mountain ballad. Commencement Program: "Serenade" Franz Schubert; "River, River" Chilean folk song. Christmas Program: "Birthday of a King"; "Angels and Shepherds" Bohemian folk song. Have furnished soloists for Community meetings, At Library party: "Rose Marie"; "L'Amour Toujours, L'amour" Friml. For Church specials, several groups. E. Recapitulation Probably the best sign of increasing musical appreciation has been the increasing demand for our singinggroups on the part of the community. And on the part of the youngsters themselves, is the wholesome eagerness with which they preform. Since the local P.T.A. has given the platform for the Music room, there has been an evident development of poise, grace, self-discipline and social-mindedness. The use of good records is showing the value of the record-player as many different groups request access to our library. Respectfully submitted, ALETHA MAY ARMSTRONG PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL, GATLINBURG, TENNESSEE, REPORT ON AUDIT, YEAR ENDED JUNE 30, 1948 August 11, 1948 To the Settlement School Committee Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Office of Settlement School Treasurer Louisville, Kentucky DEAR MESDAMES: We have examined the Statement of Financial Condition of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School of Gatlin-burg, Tennessee, as of June 30, 1948, and the Statement of Operations for the year ended on that date, have reviewed the system of internal control and the accounting procedure of the organization and without making a detailed audit of all the transactions, have examined or tested accounting records of the organization and other supporting evidence by methods and to the extent we deemed appropriate. The subsidiary records of the School and its Arrow-craft Shop at Gatlinburg, Tennessee, were not included in our audit. The report for the eleven months 'ended May 31, 1948, concerning these records, rendered by Homer K. Jones and Company, Public Accountants of Knoxville, Tennessee, and the monthly reports for the month of June, 1948, rendered by the management, were accepted by us without further verification. Combining the data furnished by Homer K. Jones and Company, the management and the information taken from the treasurer's books, we have prepared the attached financial and operating statements. Our examination was made in accordance with generally accepted auditing standards applicable to the circumstances and include all procedures which we considered necessary and which are shown below as Scope of Engagement. In our opinion, subject to all comments contained herein, the accompanying Statement of Financial Condition and related Statement of Operations, present fairly the position of the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School at June 30, 1948, and the result of its operations for the fiscal year ended on that date in conformity with generally accepted accounting principles applied on a basis consistent with that of the preceding year. Very truly yours, JOHN S. PETOT AND COMPANY SCOPE OF ENGAGEMENT The procedure followed in our examination of the subject organization included the following methods and extent or verifications: Assets and Liabilities Cash On Hand Balance taken from audit report rendered by Homer K. Jones and Company. Cash In Bank Cash deposited with The Louisville Trust Company, State National Bank and Harris Trust and Savings Bank Confirmed with depositories. Balance of cash deposited with various banks located in Tennessee taken from reports rendered by the management and audit report rendered by Homer K. Jones and Company. Accounts Receivable Customers Balance taken from reports rendered by the management and audit report of Homer K. Jones and Company. Inventories Balance taken from reports rendered by the management and audit report of Homer K. Jones and Company. Investments Endowment Fund Confirmed with trustee. Other Funds Bonds and other, supporting data examined and inspected. Fixed Assets Balance to July 1, 1947 verified with prior audit reports. Invoices and other supporting data inspected for current additions on Treasurer's books. Other current additions were taken from reports rendered by the management and audit report of Homer K. Jones and Company. Deferred Charges Computed by us. Employees' Withholding Tax Balance taken from reports rendered by the management and audit report of Homer K. Jones and Company. Reserves Balance to July 1, 1947 verified with prior audit reports. Current year's changes computed by us. Net Worth Surplus Balance to July 1, 1947 verified with prior audit reports. Current year's changes computed by us. Operating Transactions Comprehensive test checks were made of certain income and expense accounts on the Treasurer's books. The operating statement of the School and its Arrowcraft Shop, located at Gatlinburg, Tennessee, was taken from the audit report rendered by Homer K. Jones and Company and reports furnished by the management without further verification. </p>
      <pb ref="arr6510091_0008" seq="08" n="104-105  "/>
       <p>104 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL, GATLINBURG, TENNESSEE ANALYSIS OF STATEMENT OF FINANCIAL CONDITION AS OF JUNE 30, 1948 ASSETS In reading this analysis, please refer to Statement of Financial Condition, page 105. Current Assets Cash--$30,724.95 On hand $60.00 School $ 10.00 Arrowcraft Shop 50.00 $ 6o*oo Imprest funds maintained at Gatlinburg, Tennessee for petty expenditures and charge fund. In Bank Checking Accounts Balance Balance Per Less Per Bank Outstanding Books Statement Checks The Louisville Trust Co., Louisville, Ky. (School Treas.) $ 9,370.44 $ 9,370.44 State National Bank Texarkana, Ark. (School Treas.) 6,000.00 6,000.00 Servier County Bank Servierville, Tenn. (Settlement School) 805.74 $ 21.50 784.24 Servier County Bank Servierville, Tenn. (Arrowcraft) 7,914.09 2,519.29 5,394.80 Servier County Bank Servierville, Tenn. (House) 633.08 33.53 599.55 Bank of Servierville Servierville, Tenn. (Health Center) 560.23 87.30 472.93 Totals 25,283.58 2,661.62 22,621.96 In Bank Savings Account 4,344.95 Bank of Servierville, Servierville, Tenn. (Arrowcraft) Hamilton National Bank, Knoxville, Tenn. (Arrowcraft) 2,199.48 Tennessee Valley Bank, Knoxville, Tenn. (Arrowcraft) 1,465.81 8,010.24 In Bank Income Cash Balance Harris Trust and Savings Bank Chicago, Ill... 32.75 Amount of interest received June 15, 1948 on the Endowment Fund Bonds by the trustee, Harris Trust and Savings Bank, Chicago, Illinois, which had not been paid to the Grand Treasurer at June 30, 1948 Total Cash 30,724.95 Accounts Receivable $18,943.25 Amount due from Customers Arrowcraft 18,933.25 Overpayment of Employers' Withholding Tax 10.00 18,943.25 Amount due from customers is the amount due from various Alumnm Clubs and individuals for sales made by the Arrowcraft Shop. Overpayment of Employees' Withholding Tax resulted in overpayment of the tax withheld by the School treasurer in June, 1948 and will be absorbed as an adjustment to the tax to be withheld during the quarter ending September 30, 1948. Inventories $68,958.17 Value placed on finished goods and supplies in stock of the Arrowcraft Shop at June 30, 1948. Finished Goods Arrowcraft Baskets 418.89 Chairs 90.20 Hooking 192.50 Miscellaneous 3,452.21 Weaving 34,961.78 39,115.58 Hotel Shop 683.89 39,799.47 Weaving Supplies Arrowcraft 29,158.70 Total 68,958.17 For Insurance Coverage, please refer to Page 110. lnvestments $102,525.00 Endowment Fund Stocks and Bonds (Page 108) 52,458.41 Uninvested Cash 1,761.59 54,220.00 Sinking and General Fund U. S. Government Bonds Series F (Page 108) 30,155.00 U. S. Government Bonds Series G (Page 109) 18,000.00 Dominion of Canada Second Victory Loan Coupon Bonds 150.00 Book value of securities detailed on pages enumerated above. Stock and bond purchases are carried at cost. Uninvested cash of the Endowment Fund is the accumulated balance of three-fourths of the Active Chapter Contributions paid to Harris Trust and Savings Bank, Chicago, Illinois, trustee of the Endowment Fund. The School treasurer purchased $6,000.00 of Series G Bonds during the current year out of current earnings. Series F Bonds costing $11,470.00 were redeemed during the current year to cover partial cost of the new Health Center. Fixed Assets $100,881.25 Net depreciated value of real estate, buildings and improvements, equipment, fixtures and livestock owned by the Settlement School and Arrowcraft Shop as analyzed on Page 109. For Insurance Coverage, please refer to Page 110. Deferred Charge $2,094.85 Pro-rata of expense applicable to subsequent operations: Prepaid Insurance Premiums (Page 100) ,. $ 2094 85THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 105 LIABILITIES AND RESERVES Current Liabilities Employees' Withholding Tax $272.50 School 57.90 Health Center 25.90 Arrowcraft 188.70 272.50 Reserves $72,231.51 Endowment Fund 54,220.00 Amount provided out of three-fourths of the Active Chapter Contributions. Three-fourths of the Active Contributions for the current year totaled $1,654.70 and loss on sale of securities totaled $189.16. Sinking Fund 17,906.94 Consolidation of the Post War Building Fund and Health Unit Building Fund after deducting cost of the New Health Center as follows: Balance July 1, 1947 Post War Building Fund 25,647.50 Health Unit Building Fund 14,000.00 Total 39,647.50 Less Amount Transferred to New Health Center 21,740.56 Total 17,906.94 Memorial Fund 178.51 Unexpended Contributions of the Memorial Fund that will be used to purchase future music sup-plies and equipment. Current year's contributions totaled $75.00 and there were no current expenditures. Total Reserves $ 72,305.45 NET WORTH Surplus-$251, 549.72 Balance July 1, 1947 205,626.58 Add Arrowcraft Shop's Net Profit for the year 38,273.28 Decrease of Reserve for Health Unit Building Fund and Post War Building Fund through building of New Health Center 21,740.56 Decrease of Reserve for Endowment Fund through loss on Securities sold 189.16 265,829.58 Less Settlement School Net Loss for the Year 12,550.16 Transfer to Reserves Endowment Fund (Equal to three-fourths Active Chapter Contributions for the current year) 1,654.70 Memorial Fund (Total Memorial Contributions received during the current year) 75.00 14,279.86 Balance-June 30, 1948 $251,549.72 Assets Current Assets Cash $30,724.95 Accounts Receivable 18,943.25 Inventories 68,958.17 $118,626.37 Investments 102,525.00 Fixed Assets Land 5,427.35 Buildings and Improvements 112,187.51 Equipment and Fixtures 29, 226.36 141,413.87 Less Reserve for Depreciation 47,800.27 93,613.60 Live Stock 1,840.50 100,881.45 Deferred Charges 2,094.85 Total Assets 324,127.67 Liabilities Current Liabilities Employees' Withholding Tax 272.50 Reserves Endowment Fund Memorial Fund 54,220.00 Sinking Fund 17,906.94 178.51 72,305.45 Net Worth, represented by Surplus 251,549.72 Total Liabilities, Reserves and Net Worth $024,127.67 48,305.00 102,525.00 STATEMENT OF FINANCIAL CONDITION AS OF JUNE 30, 1948 For Analysis of Statement of Financial Condition, please refer to Pages 104 and 105. </p>
      <pb ref="arr6510091_0009" seq="09" n="106-107  "/>
       <p>106 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW COMPARATIVE STATEMENT OF OPERATIONS FOR THE Two YEARS ENDED JUNE 30, 1947 AND 1948 1947-1948 School Books !n,ome General ....................... Alumnx Club Contributions Gifts (Net) Individual Gifts Magazine Agency Commissions Interest on Endowment Fund ................... Interest on Series G Bonds Interest on Series F Bonds Sold Interest on Canadian Bonds, Less-Exchange ~~~.~~~~~~~~~~~~~ Interest from Sale of Cook Books Memorial Fund Contributions Total General Income 9.09 Educational School-General Receipts Appropriations for Salaries '~~"."." .'~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~. ,~o ~m '~~~~~~n 6,63*.70 Appr.opriations for Maintenance Music Department Receipts 00 Summer Session Receipts 3,676.52 Total Auxiliary Living Receipts 3,907.45 Hospital Income 91.75 Water Rent-Servier County ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' . . ' ' . ' 00 Total 4,112.18 Farm Agriculture Club .'....".'.".".'-".".." o _ 1,300.04 Sales ~~~~~~~~'~~~~~ 2,898o5 Total e=m Income 4,198.09 Total Auxiliary Income 8,310.27 Treasurer's Total Books $ 2,206.26 $ 2,206.26 11,075.03 11,075.03 12.00 12.00 .00 9.09 7,855.90 7,855.90 1,332.00 1,332.00 .00 300.00 300.00 568.00 568.00 .00 1,055.30 1,055.30 75.00 75.00 675.00 675.00 20.10 20.10 25,174.59 25,183.68 7,785.40 x 6,633^70 .00 .00 2,72 2.22 6,398.74 .00 3,907.45 91.75 112.98 4,112.18 .00 12.30 1,300~4 1,006 2,898.05 2,656.78 4,198.09 3,675.98 8,310.27 8,748,30 Total 1946-1947 10.41 820.65 2253.00 .00 .00 21,447.33 10,698.96 4,743.96 173.40 94.05 60.91 5,072.32 26,414.98 13,477.71 ~~nz 40,894.59 Total ~ 27,950.42 24,492.43 52,442.85 54,468.67 OExpenses COMPARATIVE STATEMENT or OPERATING .EXPENSES FOR THE Two YEARS ENDED JUNE 30, 1947 AND 1948 1947-1948 School Treasurer's Books Books Administrative Traveling and Conventions $ 1,279.22 Auditing and Legal .. ' 325.00 ............................ Endowment Fund-Trustee's Fees 139.24 0 Publicity '~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~m 92.92 83..75 Expenses Miscellaneous and Committee 101.22 454.19 Office Supplies and Expense . . Loss on Sale 189.16 Cost of Cook of Stocks 00 Survey 00 194.14 $ 3,791.62 Instructional Salaries Supplies and '~~~~.' ' ' ' ' ' " . ' ' ' " .' " . ' " . ' ' ' " . ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ~aa 2 ~ Music ~~z' ~ ~ ' ' . . . ' ~ 33/38 Library ' 00 Other Expenses Summer Session Expense ".".".".".".'.".'." 6,438a4 2,952.75 Total Instructional Expense 6,886.26 13,446.13 Total Total 1946-1947 $ 1,279.22 $ 1,467.97 325.00 240.00 139.24 137.06 920.00 1,449.00 83.75 127.10 493.98 461.29 555.41 285.36 189.16 333.75 773.05 417.98 $ 3,985.76 $ 5,692.56 10~93.38 16~33.55 14e.82 248.17 33.38 12.51 .00 5.00 9,*91o9 4,110.55 267.72 313.75 2,1,023.53 10,493.38 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 107 Maintenance and Operations Insurance 1,079.92 Fuel 901.84 Light 58e.28 Truck Expense 106.27 Auto Expense 39.22 Salary Handiman ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 1.310.00 Repairs 908a5 104.60 Telephone and Telegraph 185.96 Miscellaneous ''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''' 10.40 Transportation ' ' ' ' ' " .' ' ". ' ' . . ' 135.0 Total Maintenance and Operating Expense 5,283.52 1,184.52 6,468.04 6,477.05 Auxiliary Living Groceries 3,095a3 3,095.33 3,871.11 Food from Farm 2,898^5 2,898.05 2,656.78 Salaries 1,100.00 99.00 1,199.00 1,089.00 Cook 840u0 840.00 847.00 Laundress 857 9 857a9 786.50 Maid 735.0735.00 xm Repairs 52,47 52.47 123.91 Miscellaneous Living Expense Furnishings 52.50 Extra House and Farm Salaries "."."."."."." 389.19 389.19 654.50 _ Total Living Expenses 10,28 3.12 99z0 10,382.12 10,513.16 Health Unit Salary Nurse 2,411.20 2,411.20 2,117.50 Automobile Allowance .. " . ". ' " ." .' ' " . ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " . ' ' " 400.00 400o0 400.00 Hospital 131.92 131.92 309.33 _ Total Health Unit Expense 131/92 2,811.20 2*43.12 2,826.83 Farm Salary "."."."."."."."."."."."."."."."."." 1,532.00 1,532u0 1,485.00 Expenses 3,639.46 3,639.46 3,445.41 Total Farm Expense 5,171.6 5,171.46 4,930.41 Total Auxiliary Expense 15,586.50 2,910.20 18*9'6.718,270.40 Depreciation 00 3,159/6 3,159.96 3,00 5.13 __ covPA"ATm" STATEMENT OF OPERATIONS-ARROWCRAFT SHOP FOR THE Two YEARS ENDED JUNE 30, 1947 AND 1948 1947-1948 Cost of Gross 1946-1947 Sales Sales Profit Comparative Income Baskets ..$ 1,334.96 $ 712.16 Weaving 124,714.68 Chairs, Stools, etc. ".".". ".".".".".".".". 494.88 297.35 Hooked Miscellaneous Merchandise '. ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 10,1874.35 99.92 5,871.01 Mountain View Hotel Shop 2,586.69 1,161:25 $ 622.80 $ 400.65 70,902.72 59,900-61 197.53 271.00 411.80 194.65 4,328.91 5,043.43 1,425.44 2,557.55 __ Totals ^ wo,2o /8 62,316.28 77,889.20 68,367~9 Less Discount Allowed Alumn Clubs 25,353.94 .00 25,353.94 18,698.13 Net Totals 114,851:4 62,316.28 52,535.26 49,669-76 Operating Expenses Commissions Hotel Sales 1,050.00 Rent Hotel Shop Transportation Cost (Net) 240^0 240.00 Salaries Arrowcraft 319.55 273.49 Convention 9,637.96 9,082.32 87.58 Publicity 307.92 Miscellaneous .."."."."."."."."."."."."."."."."."."." =6.2' 102.00 Lights Insurance 291.10 255 ".".".".".".',"."."."."."."."."."." 124.09 118.39 Office Supplies ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 500.00 ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " .' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' . ' ' " _ 84.42 500.00 274.69 289.81 93.92 101.88 165.12 Repairs and Upkeep 440.68 129'.64 Telephone and ~~~~~'~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~..~~~~~ 861.31 ma .38 68.68 57.91 Car Expense Truck ' ' ' . ' . ' ' 74.88 99.08 Deprecia~n .. ~ ~ ~ ~ 259.12 112.05 =1^6 591/9 Total Operating Expenses .............................................. .. 15,203.27 13,652^61 Operating Profit </p>
      <pb ref="arr6510091_0010" seq="10" n="108-109  "/>
       <p>108 THE SEPTEMBER ARRow Other Income State of Tennessee Weaving 543.28 Interest Earned Savings Account ".-".".".".".".".".".".".".".' 79.31 ' Discount Earned ' ' ' . . ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " .' ' ' ' ' ' 329.50 Total Other Income ^'.".".".".".".".".".'.. 952.09 Total '."."."."."..".".".".".".".".'^".".".' 38,284.08 other Deductions Discount Allowed 10.80 Net FPOand mTArEMm",=,E "OWMm=FUND ASSETS AND INCOME AS OF JUNE 30, 1948 Income Year Par Ended Value Cost 6-30-48 United Wisconsin Michigan Power Company, 1st 3?,'/4's 1961 (Called 56-48) 103.33 Union Pacific Railroad, 1937 Equipment Trusts E 2 's 1947 (Called 73-47) Toledo and Ohio Central Railway, Refund and Improvement A ' 3*'^ 1960 $ 1,000.00 $ 1,042.50 37.50 Wisconsin Michigan Power Company 1st 3's 1978 2,000.00 United States of America Treasury 2's 12/15/1950/48 . United States of America Treasury 23/4's 6/15/1963/58 1,000.00 1,020.63 27.50 United States Savings Bonds, Series G 2,000.00 2,000.00 50.00 United States Savings Bonds, Series G 2 's 2,400.00 2,400.00 United States Savings Bonds, Series G 1,300.00 1,300.00 United States Savings Bonds, Series G 1,100.00 1,100.00 27.50 United States Savings Bonds, Series G 21/2's 8/1/56 .50 United States Savings Bonds, Series G 21/2's 8/1/56 ...".".'^"."." 3,000.00 3,000.00 75.00 United States Savings Bonds, Series G 2 's 11/1/56 3,500.00 3,500.00 87.50 United States Savings Bonds, Series G _ 7/1/57 3,000.00 3,000.00 75.00 United States Savings Bonds, Series G 2V2's 8/1/57 4,600.00 4,600.00 115.00 United States Savings Bonds, Series G 21/2's 11/1/57 3,000.00 3,000.00 75.00 United States Savings Bonds, Series G 2 's 7/1/58 6,000.00 6,000.00 150.00 United States Savings Bonds, Series G 2V2's 8/1/58 United States Savings Bonds, Series G 2V2's 9/1/58 1,900.00 5,200.00 5,200.00 1,900.00 47.50 United States Savings Bonds, Series G 2V2's 4/1/59 3,000.00 3,000.00 75.00 United States Savings Bonds, Series G 2V2's 7/1/59 4,700.00 4,700.00 58.75 United states Savings Bonds, Series s2V2's 3/1x60 1,700.00 1,700.00 .00 .____. STATEMENT OF U. S. GOVERNMENT BONDS OWNED-SERIES F AS OF JUNE 30, 1948 Serial Date of Issue Maturity Number First Day of Value Q296668F May, 1943 .' '..'....' ' o 25.00 25.00 C639157F May, 1943 . C639158F May, 1943 . ~~~~~~~...~~~~~. .~~~~~~~. ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 1100.00 00.00 Q617972F February, 1944 ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 100.00 Q617973F February, 1944 25^00 25.0 C867358F February, 1944 100.00 C867359F February, 1944 100.00 C867360F February, 1944 100.00 M731360F February, 1944 1,000.00 M731361F February, 1944 1,000.00 D700754F July, 1944 C1093188F July, 1944 ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ ~~6 C1093189F July, 1944 ^ 100.00 D3943324F July, 1944 . "."."."."."."."."."."..."."...' 500.00 M873275F July, 1944 ^ 1,000.00 M873276F July, 1944 1,000.00 M873277F July, 1944 1,000.00 D439385F November, 1944 500.00 M161851F November, 1944 1,000.00 M161852F November, 1944 1,000.00 M161853F November, 1944 1,000.00 V81181F November, 1944 5,000.00 V81182F November, 1944 5,000.00 M1206325F May, 1945 1,000.00 M1206326F May, 1945 ' 1,000.00 1,000.00 ' 1945 -~~~~ May, `~o~o M1206329F Ma, 1945 " 1945 _ .".".".".-"."."."."."."."." z~o~o May, 100.00 May, 100.00 Q98811F May, 1945 ^ -' -' " .' ' ' ' ' " . ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' . . ' 25.00 0988119F May, 1945 25.00 D518492F May, 1945 500.00 M1205827F August, 1945 1,000.00 M1205828F August, 1945 __ M1205829F August, ^ 1,000.00 M1205830F August, 1945 00 Q989137F August, 1945 ~ ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ i~~ Q989138F August, 1945 25.0 X194901F August, 1945 10,000.00 Totals $4o,750.00 273.44 86.16 427.26 786.86 36,804.01 18.12 $36,785.89 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW STATEMENT OF U. S. GOVERNMENT BONDS OWNED-SERIES G AS OF JUNE 30, 1948 Serial Date of Issue Maturity Number First Day of Value M4881896G August, 1946 $ 1,000.00 M4881897G August, 1946 1,000.00 V612698G August, 1946 5,000.00 V612699G August, 1946 5,000.00 Bonds Purchased June 29, 1948 which had Not Been Issued at Date of Inspection (7-27-48) 6,000.00 Total STATEMENT OF DOMINION OF CANADA-SECOND VICTORY LOAN COUPON BONDS (MARCH, SEPTEMBER) OWNED AS OF JUNE 30, 1498 Date of Date of Maturity Par Purchase Issue Date Value 1944 3-1-42 3-1-54 $ 50.00 1944 3-1-42 3-1-54 50.00 1944 3-1-42 3-1-54 50.00 L Loss When Called $106.25 43.75 39.16 Serial Number H418741 1.1418772 1-1538105 Cost $ 50.00 50.00 50.00 Totals $150.0 0 $150.00 STATEMENT OF FIXED ASSETS OWNED AS OF JUNE 30, 1948 Cost Balance C. Current 6-30-48 Dep, Additions School 6-30-47 Land $ 5,427.35 $ 5,427.35 Building and Improvements 1,304.99 1,304.99 $ Fences, Walks and Roads Water and Sewer System 1,516.51 1,516.51 Chicken and Brooder Houses 898.75 898.75 Barn 3,384.49 3,384.49 Hospital 2,349.05 2,349.05 Mary Pollard Cottage 4,634.60 4,634.60 Industrial Building 25,006.57 25,006.57 $189.16 Log Cabin 160.18 160.18 School House 8,027.56 8,027.56 Stuart Dormitory 9,907.81 9,907.81 Teachers' Cottage 6,870.38 6,870.38 Agricultural Shop 348.93 348.93 Small Buildings 566.98 566 98 Cost Laboratory Addition 5,685.34 5,685.34 $ 18.50 Miscellaneous Improvements 110.37 $ 392.95 503.32 18.50 Health Center 19,685.04 19,685.04 74.00 74.00 Totals 70,772.51 20,077.99 90,850.50 74.00 18.50 Equipment and Fixtures 18.50 Industrial Building 4,252.84 4,252.84 18.50 School House , 4,128.49 521.46 4,649.95 74.00 Teachers' Cottage 2,083.03 2,083.03 74.00 Mary Pollard Cottage 1,717.88 1,211.27 2,929.15 74.00 Stuart Dormitory 2,703.12 2,703.12 740.00 Hospital 1,496.50 114.50 1,611.00 740.00 Auto and Truck 1,424.85 587.20 2,012.05 18.50 Barn 650.00 650.00 74.00 Chicken and Brooder House 250.00 250.00 74.00 Heating Equipment-Stoker 485.00 485.00 370.00 Farm Equipment 90.75 90.75 740.00 Movie Equipment 310.15 310.15 740.00 Miscellaneous 2,258.08 117.11 2,375.19 740.00 Health Center 1,682.29 1,682.29 370.00 740.00 Total 21,850.69 4,233.83 26,084.52 740.00 Livestock and Horses 1,840.50 1,840.50 740.00 3,700.00 School Totals 99,891.05 24,311,82 124,202.87 3,700.00 740.00 Arrowcraft 740.00 Building and Improvements 740.00 2,661.57 2,661.57 Arts and Crafts Shop 740.00 10,792.57 10,792.57 Arrowcraft Shop 740.00 Weaving Shop 7,882.87 7,882.87 740.00 74.00 Totals 21,337.01 21,337.01 74.00 18.50 Equipment and Fixtures 18.50 Arts and Crafts Equipment 1,196.89 1,196.89 370.00 ............................... 1,569.76 375.19 1,944.95 740.00 Miscellaneous Equipment 740.00 740.00 Totals 2,766.65 375.19 3,141.84 740.00 18.50 Arrowcraft Total 24,103.66 375.19 24,478.85 18.50 $ 24,687.01 $148,681.72 L 7,400.00 Total Fixed Assets and Depreciation $123,994.71 $30,155.00 </p>
      <pb ref="arr6510091_0011" seq="11" n="110-111  "/>
       <p>110 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW STATEMENT OF INSURANCE IN FORCE AS OF JUNE 30, 1948 Policy Expiration Company Number Term Date Fire and Extended Coverage Settlement School Buildings and Contents *Tennessee Insurance Company 46006 3 12/9/49 $18,550.00 $ 876.49 *Merchants Fire Assurance Corp 1617 3 12/9/49 28,200.00 1,168.16 "'Milwaukee Mechanics' Insurance Company 2208 3 12/9/48 28,200.00 1,109.90 *Firemen's Insurance Company 9840 3 12/9/50 28,200.00 1,168.16 **Continental Insurance Company 1108 3 12/9/49 9,275.00 438,24 **Travelers Fire Insurance Company 1038538 3 12/9/49 9,275.00 438.24 Fire and Extended Coverage Contents of New Arrowcraft Shop Firemen's Insurance Company 9477 3 6/5/50 2,000.00 104.85 67.51 Milwaukee Mechanics' Insurance Company 2756 3 6/5/50 4,000.00 208.00 Floater on Films Firemen's Insurance Agency 582 1 11/4/48 Boiler and Machinery Public Liability Travelers Indemnity Company 898883 3 2/16/50 10,000.00 129.00 70.21 Travelers Indemnity Company 815991 3 10/7/49 10,000.00 70.35 Fire and Extended Coverage Health Center ***Firemen's Insurance Company Binder 3 months 7/10/48 6,666.00 ***Milwaukee Mechanics' Insurance Co. _Binder 3 months 7/10/48 6,667.00 ***Merchants Fire Assurance Corp Binder 3 months 7/10/48 6,666.00 Automobile 1939 Chevrolet Sedan Firemen's Insurance Company 175972 1 7/27/48 Combination Fire and Theft Actual Cash Value Collision ($100.00 Deductible) Actual Cash Value Property Damage 5,000.00 Bodily Injury 10/20,000.00 Medical Payments 500.00 (ruck 1947 Ton Dodge **Travelers Fire Insurance Company 8182365 1 11/28/48 Combination Fire, Lightning and Trans portation Collision ($50.00 Deductible) Public Liability Insurance (Settlement School Portion Only) ****United States Fidelity and Guaranty Co. 2819 1 11/4/48 5/10,000.00 31.20 10.86 Workmen's Compensation Statutory United States Fidelity and Guaranty Company 169449 1 11/19/48 Requirements 177.02 68.87 Owners', Landlords', and Tenants' Liability Policy ** United States Fidelity and Guaranty Co...2441323 1 11/4/48 Public Liability 5/10,000.00 Property Damage 1,000.00 ****Bonds 1 1/10/48 $20,000 Limitation 55.00 29.23 Total Prepaid Insurance $2,094.85 INTote: * Including unearned premium endorsement. Policies also contain coverage on livestock and poultry. ** Premiums paid by Servier County Board of Education. * * * Premiums will be paid when policies are issued to take the place of the binders. * * * * These policies were not available for inspection as they are being held by the Grand Treasurer. COMPARATIVE STATEMENT OF CONTRIBUTIONS BY PROVINCES OF ALUMNIE CLUBS AND ACTIVE CHAPTERS FOR Two YEARS ENDING JUNE 30, 1947 AND 1948 Prepaid Amount Amount Premiums $ 562.21 164.20 951.60 250.00 5.00 133.92 1.74 29.81 63.45 4.69 112.85 1,300.00 Actual Cash Value 20.64 Alumna, Club 1946-1947 1947-1948 \Ipha East $ 206.00 $ 178.25 A 1pha West 560.00 980.80 Beta 2,440.68 2,332.00 Gamma 465.20 474.00 Delta 498.07 615.47 Epsilon 2,041.00 1,868.00 Zeta 223.00 182.00 Eta 744.00 808.86 Theta 270.80 242.00 Iota 813.00 943.91 Kappa 1,039.44 1,015.66 Lambda 612.00 712.00 Mu 785.00 721.88 $10,697.99 $11,075.02 Active Chapter 1946-1947 1947-1948 $ 81.26 $ 45.00 45.00 25.00 258.80 163.78 138.94 103.17 161.00 173.70 245.00 273.75 115.00 155.00 285,00 378.00 60.00 40.00 261.75 333,86 380.00 375.00 116.50 75.00 89.86 65.00 $ 2,238.11 $ 2,206.26 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 1 1 z COMPARATIVE AND ACTIVE CHAPTERS FOR THE Two YEARS ENDED JUNE 30, 1947 AND 1948 ALPHA-EAST 1947-1948 1946-1947 1947-1948 $ 82z ".'-" ' 0 10.00 $ 10.00 50.00 Vermont A 25.00 Connecticut A 2.50 . .. 110.00 5.00 65.00 .25 z~o B 15.00 5.00 I.00 1.00 Vermont a 20.00 20.00 $ 178.25 Totals w 81.26 $ 45u0 ALPHA-WEST Albany, N.Y $ 20.00 $ Buffalo, N.Y 75^00 Ithaca, N.Y. ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' '. ' ' zm London, Ontario 5,00 Mohawk Valley 00 55.0 New York City 105z0 475.00 Northern New jersey 250.00 200.00 Poughkeepsie, N.Y 00 5.00 Rochester, N.Y. ' ' " . ' 50.00 50.00 Ridgewood Glen Rock 00 10.50 Schenectady, N.Y 00 25x0 Syracuse, N.Y 25z0 25.00 Canada 15.00 15.00 Westchester County 10.00 10.00 BETA Akron, Ohio $ 160.00 Athens, Ohio "..' 10o0 Central Pennsylvania ' 25u0 Charlestown, W.Va 10.00 155x00 Clarksbury, W.Va. '''''''-- Columbus, Ohio Dayton, Ohio ~~ 175~0 Fairmont, W.Va 35.00 100.00 Mahoning Valley; Yorktown 22.42 Ohio Valley 25.00 Oxford, Ohio Philadelphia, Pa. .. 5063.26 0.00 Pittsburgh, Pa 75.00 . New ~- -__ South Hills, Pittsburgh, Pa 25.00 25.00 Toledo, Ohio 40.00 40.00 Totals $2,440.68 42,332^00 Boston, Mass. ... Burlington, Vt Hartford, Conn Montreal, .... New Haven, Conn. ... P Stanford, ortland, CoMe. nn. ~ ~~ ~~ ~ ~ 1946-1947 . .' ' 'w 130.00 _ 50.00 10.00 5.00 10.00 "... 1.00 Totals '.".w 20*o0 .. ...... .. .. ...... .. .. ...... .. .. ...... .. .. ...... .. .. ...... .. .. ...... .. ..... ..... ..... ..... 20.00 A m 5z0 $ .00 75.00 r 00 10.0o 10o0 New York A 10.00 .00 5.00 Ontario A 20.00 10.00 Ontario o 10u0 5x00 Total $ 45.00 $ 25x0 Totals "."."."."."."^ 258.80 $ 163.78 160.00 Pennsylvania w 42.00 $ 35.00 5.00 Pennsylvania 26.80 8.78 Ohio A 150.00 65.00 10.00 Ohio B 15.00 180.00 Ohio A 10.00 West Virginia A ..~....~~~....~~~~~~~ 10.00 10.00 5.00 5.00 750.00 Ohio E 10.00 10.00 250.00 Ohio Z 15.00 15.00 100.00 75.00 25.00 100.00 12.00 5.00 10.00 500.00 10.00 75.00 Baltimore, Md. ..' ' $ 50.00 Chapel Hill 50.00 Charlotte, N.C 5.00 Columbia, S.C 5.00 Richmond, Va. ".".'."." 20.00 Washington, D Wilmington, D~. ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ ~~0 Norfolk, Va 5.00 G^amA $ 100.00 Maryland A 30.00 A 3.50 North Carolina 13 2/00 North Carolina A 5.00 Virginia r 25.00 Virginia A 280o0 D.C. A o3.' Maryland B 5.00 .. .. .. .. .. .. ... . . ... ... ... .. .. ... .. .. ... .... $ 25.00 ... 5.00 $ 5.00 ^ .'. 30.00 30.00 ... 20.00 8.00 18.94 5.00 25.00 40.17 ... 10.00 10.00 ... 5.00 5.00 ... ... Totals m 465x0 $ 474.20 Total ".".".".".".".w 138.94 Ann Arbor, Mich 35.00 Bloomfield Hills, Mich 5.00 Bloomington, Ind. Detroit, Mich. ~~~~~~~~~~~~ 525.00 0.00 Fort Wayne, Ind. ".".".'.' 10.00 Gary, Ind. Grand Rapids, Mich. Franklin, _ ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 2~00 Hillsdale, Mich 10.00 1u0 Indianapolis, LaFayette, Ind 280.07 Lansing, East Lansing, Northern Indiana '~~i ~~~~~~~~~~ 25.00 Richmond, Ind. ... ' ' ' ' ' " .' ". , .00 "."."."."." z/m Shelbyville, Jackson, M~^ ".".".".".".".' 1z0 Total o 498.07DELTA $ 35.00 Michigan A o 12.00 $ 10.00 100.00 Michigan B 100.00 60.00 25.00 Indiana A 5.00 5.00 25.00 Indiana B 16.00 30.40 10.00 Indiana r 6.00 5.00 20.00 mm 10o0 1.00 Indiana E 6.00 5.00 8.00 Michigan r 11.00 48a0 1.00 200.00 139.47 5.00 2.00 1.00 1.00 40.00 2.00 $ 615.47 161.00 Total $ </p>
      <pb ref="arr6510091_0012" seq="12" n="112-113  "/>
       <p>112 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW EPSILON 5.00 Kentucky A 100.00 Missouri A "."."."."..".".".m 5.00 c~u ".".".".".".".".' 10.00 500.00 Missouri B ~~~~~~~~~~"-"."."." .o~o Missouri I' Tennessee A ' ~~.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~' 20.00 25.00 Tennessee B 5z0 10.00 _ 10.00 Total m 245z0 1,200.00 15.00 1.00 20.00 z20.00 Total $2,041.00 $1,868.00 Chattanooga, Tenn 5.00 Columbia, Mo 60.00 Jefferson City, Mo 5.00 Kansas City, Mo. ..^ 500.00 Little Pigeon 10^0 Louisville, Ky 25x00 Memphis, Tenn 10x00 Nashville, Tenn 10.00 St. Louis, Mo. Springfield, Mo. ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~.~ 1,400.00 Knoxville, Tenn 1.00 Atlanta, Ga. ".".".'..".' '$ 10*u0 Birmingham, Ala 15z0 De Land, Fla 20.00 Jacksonville, Fla. . Lakeland, Fla. ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 105.00 .00 Miami, Fla 25.00 Orlando, Fla.. St. Petersburg, ~~.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 215.00 5.00 Tampa, s= 5^00 $ 50.00 Alabama A ".".".".".".".".w 15.00 Florida A 20.00 Florida B ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 5.00 Florida I' 2.00 Georgia A '.'.."."..'. 25.00 35.00 25.00 5.00 Total o .00 $ 30.00 10.00 10.00 85.00 75.00 o00w .00 20.00 115.00 $ 155.00 Total w 223.00 $ 182.00 ETA Avon, w 5.00 Beloit, Wis 15.00 Chicago Business Women .. 10.00 Chicago North 25o0 Chicago South '' ''''' - Chicago West Suburban 5.00 Decatur, Ill. ... Du Page County, 35.00 10.00 Elgin, ~~~~~~~~~~~-~00 Fox River Valley, Wis 15.00 Galesburg, Ill. . Illinois Fox Valley, Ill 5.00 Jacksonville, 15.00 Joliet, Ill. ''''''''''''''' 10.00 *Madison, Wis. Milwaukee, Wis. "."."."." 150.00 z~~u Monmouth, North Shore, ~ ~~~~~~~~~ _~0 Oak Park-River Forest, b~ ' ~ 35.00 Peoria, 140.00 Rockford, 00 $ 7.00 "."."."."_"."^ 50.00 $ 50.00 20o0 Wisconsin B 50.00 50.00 4.00 75.00 50.00 100.00 10.00 .00 5.00 Illinois B-.A, -50.00 .00 25.00 Illinois E 50.00 Illinois Z ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~" 25.00 133.00 5..0 Illinois H 25z0 .00 35.00 Illinois ~ 00 75.00 10.00 5.00 Total m 285z0 $ 378.00 15.00 5.00 15.00 15.00 5.00 50.00 200.00 5.00 102.86 50,00 25.00 25.00 30.00 Total 0 744.00 $ 808.86 " Note. Madison's contribut:on totaled $100.00 for the year but $50.00 was counted as a Memorial 10.00 5Ames, .00 Ced $ 20.00 $ 20.00 Burlington, Iowa 10.00 5.00 Cedar Rapids, Iowa 25 0 20.00 Council Bluffs, Iowa Des Moines, Iowa 10.000 10.00 15.00 Duluth-Superior, Minn 75.00 75.00 Grand korks, N.D 5.00 5.00 Minneapolis, Minn 15.00 10.00 Mt. Pleasant, Iowa ~ 10.00 10.00 Sioux City., Iowa 10o0 10.00 St. Paul, Minn 50o0 32.00 zri Cities 3.00 10.00 Winnipeg, M~~~~' .._~~~.. .~~.~. . 11.00 10.00 Total $ 270.80 $ 242o0 .. Iowa B Iowa ... Iowa Z Manitoba A . M~~o~A ~~ .................... "m .................... ...................... .................... .................... ~... Total ....'.'^' "."$ 60.00 $ 40.00 .. .. THE SEPTEMBER ARROW 113 Alumnae $ 50.00 $ 50.00 Kansas City, Kan 20.00 20.00 Laramie, Wyo 28.00 27.00 Lawrence, Kan 25.00 25^0 Lincoln, Neb 26.00 25.00 OgdenManhattan, Kan 100u0 100.00 , Utah . ."."."..".' 10.00 Omaha, Neb 25z0 65.65 Poudre Valley 1.00 Pueblo, Colo m.ou 10.00 Salt Lake City, Utah "."."...' 10z0 10.00 Topeka, Kan 25x00 Vermillion, S.D 1.00 1.00 Wichita, Kan' 5.00 10.00 Total "." o 813z0 $ 93m Ardmore, Okla $ 10.00 $ 15.00 Austin, Tex. . . 86.00 100.00 Baton Rouge, La 5.00 Corpus Christi, Tex 40.00 40.00 Dallas, Tex 200.00 200o0 Little Rock, Ark 15.00 15.00 Houston, Tex. McAlester, Okla. ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ ~~ 00 _200.00 Muskogee, Okla 10.00 15x0 *New Orleans, La. Nita Stark Beaumont, ~~~'~~~~~~~~~~ 117.44 35.00 120.66 Norman, Okla 15.00 10.00 Oklahoma City, Okla. 0krnulgee, Okla. .~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ ~3.00G Ponca City, Okla. Shreveport, La. ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 21.00 255.00 .00 Stillwater, Okla 16:00 10.00 Texarkana, Tex 10 0 10.00 Tulsa, Okla. . . . _ ' ' 25x00 25.00 Tyler, Tex 5.00 50.00 Wichita Falls, -__ 10.00 5.00 Total 'o1,o39.44 $1,015.66 * Note: New Orleans' contribution during the current year was $35.00 but this was applied against returned check for year 1946-1947 which was not made good. Boise, Idaho "."."..'.' $ 50.00 $ 50.00 Bozeman, Mont 5.00 5.00 Butte-Anaconda, Mont 5.00 5.00 Edmonton, Alberta '. ' ' " ' ' .' ' 10.00 5.00 ' . ' ' . . . .^ 5.00 5.00 Everett, Wash. .'''''''''''''''' 25.00 Pullman, Wash 15/0 25.00 Salem, Ore. "..".".' 55 0 50.00 Spokane, Wash 25.00 25.00 *Tacoma, Wash 100.00 110.00 Vancouver, Wash. * 00 3.00 =h. ."."...' 50o0 25.00 Seattle, ~~ 10.00 10.00 --~. Wash 200.00 200.00 Total o 612^00 $ 712.00 * Tacoma's contribution for the year ended June 30, 19:48 totaled $115.00 of which $5.00 was counted as a Fund Contribution. Memorial Wenatchee's contribution for the year ended June 30, 1948 totaled morial Fund~~r ~~~~.~. '~"=~ counted =^ M Active Colorado A ".".".".".'." 'w 75.00 $ 75z0 ' "."."."."." 50o0 50z0 Kansas A 20.00 zozm Kansas B 21.75 100.00 Nebraska B "."."."."." '. `mm 43.86 South Dakota A 20.00 20.0C Utah A '".".".".".".".".' 45.00 20.00 Wyoming A 20 0 5.00 Total m 261.75 $ 333.86 Texas A 100.00 $ 100.00 Louisiana B 25.00 20 0 Texas B 50.00 50.00 Arkansas A 25.00 25.00 Louisiana A 100.00 100.00 Oklahoma A 50.00 50.00 Oklahoma B ~ .~~ ~ ~ ~~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ 30.00 30.00 Total $ 380.00 $ 375x0 Alberta A ".".".".^' " ".$ 7.50 $ 5.00 Idaho A ".".". '.'....".." 5.00 ~m Montana A 35.00 ~^~ Oregon A 5.00 ~oo Oregon B .~. ~ ~ ~~ ~ ~ ~~~ ~~ ~ ~ ~~ ~ ~~ ~ ~~ ~~ 10.000 Washington 15.00 Washington B 5.00 5.00 Oregon , 44.00 20.00 Total w 116.50 75.00 </p>
      <pb ref="arr6510091_0013" seq="13" n="114-115  "/>
       <p>114 THE SEPTEMBER ARROW Mu $ 5.00 Arizona A $ 29.86 2.50 California A 5.00 California B 20.00 California I' 10.00 25.00 California A 30.00 .00 Nevada A 20.00 Utah A 200.00 New Mexico A 20.00 10.00 15.00 10.00 Total $ 89.86 5.00 25.00 25.00 5.00 10.00 .00 100.00 75.00 10.00 30.00 15.00 5.00 1.00 40.00 50.00 28.38 Total $ 785.00 $ 721.88 ' Note. San Jose's contribution for the year ended June 30, 1948 totaled $35.00 of which $5.00 was counted as a Memorial Fund Contribution. New York City Panhellenic Fellowship Loan Fund Since one of the objects expressed in the constitution of the New York City Panhellenic, Inc., is "to stand always for the encouragement of higher education," the members are happy to announce they are resuming their major pre-war project, i.e., a Fellowship Loan Fund. Here are the stipulations for carrying out this plan : 1. Loan is to be awarded for graduate work in New York City. 2. This loan is open to N.P.C. women only. 3. Amount of loan is $400.00. 4. Loan available every two years. 5. Loan to be made on basis of recommendations, investigations, need and type of study. 6. Notification of award is to be sent to thesorority organs and to such publications as committee deems advisable. 7. Selection of recipient and administration of fund to be in hands of committee of five appointed by the president of New York City Panhellenic with the approval of the Board of Governors. If you are interested in applying for this Fellowship Loan award, please furnish the following information: 1. A completely filled in Application Form. (This blank may be obtained by writing your request to the chairman of the New York City Panhellenic Fellowship Loan Fund.) 2. Recommendations from: a. Two professors, concerning your qualifications for work desired b. Two alumnae or friends, not on faculty A dean of women d. A national or district officer of your fraternity 3. Transcript of college record 4. Health certificate from a graduate physician 5. Recent photograph The name of the successful applicant will be announced April 30, 1949 and the Fellowship award will be available for use in the Fall of 1949. The closing date for the filing of the above data is February 15, 1949. Send all applications and communications to the chairman of New York City Panhellenic Fellowship Loan Fund. 3 Fox Lane Flushing, New York Albuquerque, N.M $ .00 Berkeley, Calif 00 El Paso, Tex 5.00 Fresno, Calif 10.00 Glendale, Calif 25.00 Honolulu, T.H 100.00 Long Beach, Calif 20.00 Los Angeles, Calif 200.00 Marine County, Calif 15.00 Reno, Nev 10.00 New Mexico 00 Palo Alto, Calif 20.00 Pasadena, Calif 25.00 Phoenix, Ariz 5.00 Sacramento, Calif 10.00 Salt Lake City, Utah 00 San Diego, Calif 100.00 San Francisco, Calif 125.00 San Fernando, Calif 10.00 *San Jose, Calif. .. . 25.00 San Mateo County, Calif 15.00 Santa Barbara, Calif 5.00 San Bernardino, Calif Santa Monica West Wood, Calif. 40.00 South Coast, Calif 15.00 Tucson, Ariz 5.00 $ 15.00 30.00 5.00 $ 65.00 MRS. RICHARD TRAPIER BELL, Chairman Committee Reports COMMITTEE ON LOAN FUND July 14, 1948 To the Grand Council Pi Beta Phi Fraternity: During the year 1947-1948 loans made increased more than 10% over the previous year. I believe this upward trend will continue for some years. I submit herewith report of operations for the year 1947-1948. Loans made 1947-1948 Undergraduate . $3,521.41 Repayments on loans 943.00 Interest paid on loans 81.40 Contributions Active Chapters 880.50 Alumni Clubs 1,243.00 Outstanding Loans-Undergraduate Past due loans 1,573.50 Loans due in 1948 350.00 Loans due in 1949 1,245.00 Loans due in 1950 2,721.41 Loans due in 1951 900,00 6,789.91 Graduate Loans 500.00 7,289.91 Detailed list of contributions from Chapters and Clubs is attached. Sincerely, JOSEPHINE MCCLEVERTY, Chairman CONTRIBUTIONS TO LOAN FUND YEAR 1947-1948 Chapters Clubs ALPHA EAST Boston, Mass $ 2.00 Burlington, Vt 2.50 Halifax, N.S 1.00 Hartford, Conn 5.00 Montreal, Quebec 7.50 New Haven, Conn 1.00 Portland, Me 2.00 Stamford, Conn 1.00 $23.50 $22.00 (100%) ALPHA WEST New York A Albany, N.Y $10.00 New York r $10.00 Buffalo, N.Y 5.00 New York A Ithaca, N.Y 10.00 Ontario A 8.00 London, Ont 5.00 Ontario B 5.00 Mohawk Valley 3.00 New York, N.Y. $23.00 Northern New jersey 2.50 Rochester, N.Y 10.00 Schenectady, N.Y. Syracuse, N.Y 10.00 Toronto, Ont 15.00 Westchester County, N.Y 5.00 $75.50BETA (Continued) Fairmont, W.Va 5.00 Harrisburg-Carlisle 5.00 Mahoning Valley -0 5.00 Morgantown, W.Va 5.00 Ohio Val'ey 5.00 Oxford, Ohio 2.50 Philadelphia, Pa 10.00 Pittsburgh, Pa 5.00 South Hills, Pa 5.00 Toledo, Ohio 20.00 $157.50 GAMMA Baltimore, Md. N.C $ 5.00 Chapel Hill, C5.00 Charlotte, N.C 10.00 Columbia, S.C 2.00 Norfolk, Va 2.00 Richmond, Va 5.00 Wash. D.C. Senior Group 10.00 Wash. D.C. Junior Group 5.00 (100%) Wilmington, Del 1.00 Durham, N.C 2.50 $47.50 (100%) DELTA Michigan A . $10.00 Ann Arbor, Mich $ 5.00 Michigan B 25.00 Bloomfield Hills, Mich. 10.00 Michigan 5.00 Bloomington, Ind 5.0(1 Indiana A 5.00 Detroit, Mich 5.00 Indiana B 10.00 Ft. Wayne, Ind 5.00 Indiana r 5,00 Franklin, Ind 2.50 Indiana .1 5.00 Hillsdale, Mich 1.00 Indiana E 5.00 Indianapolis, Ind 10.00 Jackson, Mich 2.00 $70.00 Lafayette, Ind 5.00 (100%) Lansing, Mich 2.00 Northern Indiana 2.00 Richmond, Ind 1.00 Southwestern Indiana 15.00 Shelbyville, Ind. . 1.00 Grand Rapids, Mich 5.00 Gary, Ind 1.00 $53.00 ZETA (100%) Alabama A $15.00 Atlanta, Ga $10.00 Florida A 10.00 Birmingham, Ala 10.00 Florida B 20.00 De Land, Fla 2.50 Florida 15.00 Jacksonville, Fla. 3.00 Georgia A 15.00 Lakeland, Fla 5.00 Miami, Fla 10.00 $75.00 Orlando, Fla 5.00 (100%) Tampa, Fla 5.00 St. Petersburg, Fla. 5.00 $55.50 (100% ) Maine A $10.00 Vermont A 1.00 Vermont B Massachusetts A 5.00 Massachusetts B Connecticut A 5.00 Nova Scotia A 2.50 Maryland A Maryland B $ 5.00 Dist. of Col. A 10.00 Virginia A 10.00 Virginia r 5.00 North Carolina A 8.00 North Carolina B 5.00 South Carolina A 5.00 $48.00 EPSILON $77.50 (100%) Missouri A $10.00 Missouri B 15.00 Missouri I' 15.00 Kentucky A 5.00 Tennessee A 5.00 Tennessee B 15.00 Chattanooga, Tenn $ 5.00 Columbia, Mo 5.00 ,Jefferson City, Mo 2.00 Kansas City, Mo 5.00 Knoxville-Little Pigeon 1,00 Louisville, Ky 5.00 Memphis, Tenn,._ . 5.00 Nashville, Tenn 10.00 (100%) St. Louis, Mo 10.00 Springfield, Mo. 5.00 $65.00 ETA BETA Pennsylvania B $15.00 Akron, Ohio $ 5.00 Pennsylvania r Athens, Ohio 5.00 Ohio A 5.00 Central Pennsylvania 10.00 Ohio B 10.00 Charleston, W.Va 5.00 Ohio A 10.00 Cincinnati, Ohio 10.00 Ohio E 5.00 Clarksburg, W.Va. Ohio Z Cleveland East 15.00 West Virginia A 5.00 Cleveland West 10.00 Columbus, Ohio 25.00 $50.00 Dayton, Ohio 5.00 Wisconsin A $ 50.00 Wisconsin B 10.00 Wisconsin r 25.00 Illinois A Illinois B-A Illinois E 20.00 Illinois Z 10.00 Illinois .H 8.00 Illinois e 25.00 $148.00Avon, Ili $ 7.00 Beloit, Wis 5.00 Carthage, Ill 1.00 Champaign-Urbana, Ill 10.00 Chicago Business Women 5.00 Chicago North 1.00 Chicago South 5.00 Chicago West Subur ban 5.00 115 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



