<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr7740015_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Dix, Helen Boucher</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Summer 1961</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr7740015_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1961</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Dix, Helen Boucher</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 14-16</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">40</note>
                        <note type="Folder">13</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 77, Number 4 (Summer 1961), Pages 14-16.</note>
			<note type="document">arr7740015_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Highlights of the Year; Arrowcraft Weavers from Generation to Generation</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Changing Mission of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity for Women in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1944-1964</item>
                                <item>Weavers</item>
                                <item>Extracurricular activites</item>
                                <item>Healthcare</item>
                                <item>Tourism</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr7740015_0001" seq="01" n="14-15  "/>
       <p>NNOweNUyt UVeuveN3 FROM GENERATION TO GENERATION Mrs. Blanche Huskey, left, and Miss Ruby Huskey represent two-thirds of the weaving team which supplies many articles to the Arrowcraft Shop from the Huskey's basement weaving room. The other third is Miss Brenda Huskey, now a fresh-man at the University of Tennessee and an honor graduate of the Pi Beta Phi High School last June. Brenda has been weaving for Arrowcraft the past two years and plans to continue during her college career as a means of financing her education. In this picture Mrs. Huskey is winding thread on a spinning wheel that belonged to her grandmother. Three generations of weavers for Arrowcraft are shown here. Weaving is a family occupation in the Carver-Watson household. Seventeen Members of he'r family have been taught to operate a hand loom by Mrs. Martha Watson. All four of her daughters, all six of her daughters-in-law, and her four granddaughters throw the shuttle expertly for the Arrowcraft Shop. Pictured here are, left to right, Mrs. Beaulah Carver, a daughter-in-law, tying fringe on , bookmarks; Mrs. Martha Watson, standing to the left of the loom; Miss Jean Carver, a granddaughter, weaving a Breezeway mat, and Mrs. Laura Watson, a daughter, winding thread on a shuttle. Two of Arrowcraft's oldest weavers are pictured here in front of the shop's veteran warping board. On the left, Mrs. Izora Keener watches her ,`;sister-in-law, Mrs. Myrtle Connor, as the latter winds up the thread in preparation for a new warp of Breezeway mats. Both of these women are highly skilled weavers, having woven for over thirty years a variety of items sought by members of Pi Beta Phi and their friends over the country. ~~ecu~ /rom Iit/e Pigeon Edited by Helen Boucher Dix, Ohio B HIGHLIGHTS OF THE YEAR The Grace Coolidge Library at the Settlement School received from John Coolidge this year four books which had belonged to his mother, First Lady of the Land from 1923 to 1929. Mrs. Coolidge, Vermont B, retained an active and devoted interest in Pi Beta Phi during her lifetime. The personal efforts of Sarah Pomeroy Rugg, former ARROW editor, to secure these treasured books are greatly appreciated. THE SCHOOL Marion W. Mueller, Director of Settlement School, reported that the eight girls and nine boys who were accepted for the dormitory program last fall formed a very interesting and challenging group. Four of the boys were on the football squad, with two being on the first team. Nine students were on the basketball squads, boys and girls. James Huskey, president of the Boy's Dormitory, was also president of the Junior Class. A Halloween Party was held in the Owls Nest for the dormitory students at which the boys elected a queen and the girls, a king. Awards were given to the dormitory girl and boy with the highest grades for the first grading period. For the second period the award was for the most improvement. At christmas time each of the thirty-eight children of The Glades School received a present and an orange. Extra gifts were included in case little brothers or sisters were visiting! In the lower grades of the Pi Beta Phi School thirty-six students were remembered with presents, while all children in the first three grades received an orange. The dormitory boys and girls were given a Christmas Party in the Owl's Nest with a tree, a gift from Settlement School for each, an exchange gift, and remembrances from Ruth Spelman, Housemother for girls, and Marion Mueller. Christmas refreshments completed the festivities. HEALTH CENTER The Health Center Summary for 1960 gives a graphic picture of the services rendered by the Pi Beta Phi nurse, Marjorie Chalmers: 644 Field Visits Office Calls 4378 Service Given 3925 Preventive Inoculations 1502 Teacher-Nurse Conferences 207 Family Conferences 256 Chest X-rays 1195 Audiometer Tests 194 Optometric tests 565 RED BARN RECORD The Red Barn with its facilities for meetings or for lodging, or both, was used as follows: Craftsmen attending the Southern Highland Guild Craftmen's Fair at Gatlinburg, October 18-22, were lodged in The Red Barn. On January 14 twenty-four Guild members met in the Owl's Nest. February 9, 10 were the dates when the Council of Mountain Workers met in the Owl's Nest, the Chanticleer's Lounge, at Staff House, and at the Health Center. On March 22-25 there was a Craft Seminar in the Owl's Nest with additional bookings for lodgings. Early in May there was a Southern Highland Guild Weaving Workshop by Lilli Blumenau, creative weaver from New York City. MRS. MUELLER HEADS FAIR Marion Mueller has been named Chairman of the Southern Highlands Guild's Craftsmen's Fair at Gatlinburg in October, 1961. The Pi Beta Phi University of Tennessee Craft Workshop has joined the American Craftsmen's Council. The Southeastern Area of the American Crafts-men's Council met at Settlement School during the Southern Highlands Guild's Fair at Gatlinburg last October. Mrs. Vanderbilt Webb, Chairman of the Council Board, stayed at Staff House during the meeting. The December Issue of AAA contained an article about the Southern Highlands Guild's Fair in Gat 15 </p>
      <pb ref="arr7740015_0002" seq="02" n="16-17  "/>
       <p>16 THE ARROW OF P1 BETA PHI linburg, with a picture of a girl weaving. The girl is jean Carver, whose picture appears here with other members of her family who weave for Arrowcraft. Lorine Pruette, Ph.D., Tennessee A, who has at-tended the Craft Workshop for three summers, wrote two articles on the Workshop which were printed in The Gatlinburg Press. Some years ago the ARROW carried an article about Dr. Pruette, who is the author of several books. TOURS, GUESTS, AND GIFTS On October 29 twenty-six members of Tennessee Alpha made their second annual tour of Settlement School, with stops at Arrowcraft, Stuart (where they met some of the girls), and Staff House, where they were served punch and cookies. Sixty-two members and friends of the University of Tennessee faculty were served a buffet dinner on the Virginia Brackett Green Patio of The Red Barn on October 1, 1960. The gifts received from chapters, clubs, and individuals included cash, clothing for the dormitory children, baby clothing for the Health Center, Christmas gifts for dormitory children, trading stamps, cancelled stamps for stamp collectors, toilet articles, toys, iris bulbs, cakes, candy, and magazine subscriptions for Staff House. The Resident Staff and the Settlement School Committee are looking forward to the several fraternity meetings which will bring many members of Pi Beta Phi to Gatlinburg this June. ANGLES FOR ANGELS Evelyn Peters Kyle, Director of Programs If you were to ask a fraternity woman what single factor of her college years, aside from her education, she felt had most influenced her life after college, you would, in the majority of cases, find that the unhesitating reply would be her training in fraternity education. For every fraternity woman upon taking her place in community life, finds that through fraternity education,' she is able to make tangible the intangible. Because she has developed scholarship, she has developed her mind. She has also developed leadership, will power, perseverance, and a code of conduct all as a result of her fraternity education. PVP AWARD The Province Vice-President's Award, a large silver bowl which has been given annually since 1954 for best fraternity education program, has recognized the achievements of a chapter in building fraternity spirit and national viewpoint as a means of developing strong alumnae. The basis of this award is contained in the following five phases of chapter work; Pledge Training, Fraternity Education Programs, Officer Training, Active-Alumnae Relations, and Fraternity Study and Examination. Each Province President nominates one chapter in her province by letter to the Grand Vice-President. From the chapters nominated Grand Council selects one chapter which in its estimation has best fulfilled the requirements specified for the award. Currently, Texas Beta is the proud possessor of this award. Each chapter nominated had excellent ideas which, although presented here in capsule form, show the methods of development in a character 'building organization. THE ANGLES Pledge Training was successfully aided by a supplementary Pledge Book compiled in addition to the national book. In the back of the book was a space for weekly counseling remarks by Sponsors. These, after they were recorded and reviewed with the Advisory Board on a monthly basis, made that Board feel it was extremely well qualified to vote on initiation eligibility. In appointing Sponsors, two were designated one as a "Pledge Mother" and a second for scholarship. Fraternity Education Programs were based on a background of Pi Phi as well as local chapter history in conjunction with a display of archive treasures. A consideration of the Standardization and Survey re-port was made so that weaknesses might be strengthened. Considered of utmost importance in Officer Training were procedure notebooks with "job descriptions" of each office. Close check was kept after installation on all officers by the President and the Corresponding Secretary. At Founders' Day Active-Alumna' Relations were emphasized by attendance at its celebration of each active accompanying an alumna. Newsletters were sent to the alumnae of the chapter by the chapter Vice-President. And special entertainment or parties were planned at Holiday time for alumnae and their families. When time for the Fraternity Examination approached, programs were scheduled to give careful consideration by the chapter to the material used. Posters, cartoons, and poems stressing the importance of the examination were displayed on bulletin boards. Through concentrated efforts to improve these five phases of our organization, strength is developed in the chapter as well as in the individual. A strong Pi Phi is an informed Pi Phi. On a firm foundation of fraternity education a bridge is being built. May those who follow continue the cycle unbroken since 1867, of leadership, perseverance, high character and community service. Operation Abolition Interfraternity Research and Advisory Council, of which the Chairman of your National Panhellenic Conference is a Trustee, has been provided prints of the film: "OPERATION ABOLITION." It shows an attempt of the Communist Party to influence students. J. Edgar Hoover says that the San Francisco riots of a few months ago were Communist-inspired and directed. See for yourself what happened at the House Un-American Activities Committee hearings. Answer for yourself the question: "Who is trying to do away with the H.U.A.C. and why ?" You will never forget some of the shocking scenes in this film. Obtain the film from the office of National Inter-fraternity Conference, 15 East Fortieth Street, New York 16, New York. Show it to your local councils. IT IS FREE. You pay only shipping charges. FRANCIS S. VAN DERBUR, President Interfraternity Research and Advisory Council 17 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



