<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr7810033_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Christian, Nevada</name></author>
                        <author><name>Mueller, Marion W.</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Fall 1961</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr7810033_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1961</date>, News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Christian, Nevada</name></author>
                        <author><name>Mueller, Marion W.</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 33-35</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">40</note>
                        <note type="Folder">14</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 78, Number 1 (Fall 1961), Pages 33-35.</note>
			<note type="document">arr7810033_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">The Arrowcraft Shop 1961, Settlement School Honors '60-'61</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Changing Mission of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity for Women in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1944-1964</item>
                                <item>Facilities</item>
                                <item>Handicraft</item>
                                <item>People</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr7810033_0001" seq="01" n="18-19  "/>
       <p>excianaes a Colley. not. Edited by Freda Stafford Schuyler, Arkansas A PUBLIC RELATIONS With the advent of fall, rushing, and the installation of new chapters, we should give special consideration to the attitude of the general public to-ward Pi Beta Phi. An excellent editorial in the Spring issue of the Delta Chi Quarterly entitled "Your Public Is Watching You" appears well worth our thought and attention. Summarizing the article briefly, it begins with a quotation from the National Interfraternity Conference Yearbook (1946) . "Public Relations are molded by what we do rather than by what we say. It is consequently hoped that our members will turn their attention to constructive programs, not of what they believe, but of what they will do, individually and collectively, to demonstrate to the public the real character of the college fraternity and the spirit which dominates it." Public Relations is not a new concept, but is as old as life itself. "It is a deadly serious business in a highly competitive society." The fraternity point of view demands that we start with the individual member. "What is his relationship to other members? Does he fit well into the group? Does he have similar ideals? Does he have the desire to identify himself with the group in keeping the ideals of the fraternity foremost in all group decisions and in passing those ideals along to those who will follow in his footsteps? His individual actions become a part of the tapestry of the group and will be important in the image which the chapter presents to the public." First, the individual must consider the image he presents to his friends, because, to them, he is hisfraternity. He must consider the image created by his relationship to his family and others in his home town. Another part of the public relations picture is the relationship of the undergraduate member to the alumni members. Good relations do not "just hap-pen." It is wise for an undergraduate chapter to cultivate unceasingly good relationships with alumni. We should strive for friendly relationships with other organized groups. We should remember, also, that people are prone to generalize, and "Publicity resulting from one act of indiscretion by one fraternity man may bring condemnation to the whole fraternity system." We have a responsibility to every other fraternity man. Other good relations should be established between the fraternity and members of the college or university administrative and academic staffs. We should not be accused of "snobbishness," and a far-sighted chapter builds and maintains friendships with unaffiliated students or "independents." "Public Relations is a way of life with the knowledge that, in the end, the action of an individual, multiplied perhaps as it is in group action, is the determining factor in the public image of your fraternity." FRIENDSHIP Quoting President Margaret Paddock Haller in The Trident of Delta Delta Delta, "Friendships should develop within a fraternity, not just within a chapter. .. . Friendships do not have to be restricted to your fraternity, but all members of the fraternity should be friends." Fraternities must become the vanguard or they must die. Perhaps our going out of the campus scene would be greeted by many with more jubilation than sorrow. Unfortunately, if fraternities go from our campus the American way of life, as we know it, the great American dream, will have become a night-mare. The first you lead on your campus therefore, is not just to keep fraternities strong and great; our fight is to maintain the ideals fraternities stand for and since fraternities stand for the freedom of every American you now find yourself in the challenging and inspiring position of fighting for America as well as your fraternity. W. P. SHOFSTALL, Sigma Tau Gamma Dean of Students, Arizona State University (as quoted in Banta's Greek Exchange) 32 /rom Zttie Pigeon Gfl~ Edited by Helen Boucher Dix, Ohio B The Arrowcraft Sho1961 By Nevada Christian, Nevada A The shop built by Pi Beta Phi 21 years ago be-side the country road in Gatlinburg is dimensionally, at least, the same shop. However, the transformation of the 'Burg into a popular resort town of the Great Smoky Mountain National Park region has inevitably inspired some change in personality of the ARROWCRAFT SHOP from the staid and home-spun to the contemporary, with a touch of the sophisticated. The public image of the shop has likewise been evolving from that of a kind of crafts museum to a place where the sound of the cash register rings pleasantly. Always welcome will be the wearers of the Arrow our "family" and our loyal and tireless super saleswomen to come and see first-hand the place that has been part of their imagining since pledge days. Still interested in interpreting the role of Pi Beta Phi in its Settlement School project are members of the shop staff ; but, more than ever, they are alert to the opportunity of increasing sales. Ours is a "soft-sell," glossed with lore of the region and a store of information about the "school" and our craftsmen. Weaving designs and some craft items, particularly pottery and metal work, reflect awareness of contemporary tastes. Our veteran home weavers are demonstrating a remarkable facility for translating new designs into the web of their well-used looms. Clear demonstration of Pi Beta Phi's role in the community's economy was the record payroll of $8,300.00 last December for a single month of weaving. Coming as it did just before Christmas in a season of maximum unemployment, our payroll was a definite contribution to happy holidays for about 70 local families. The shop employs 75 weavers during peak months. Part of the face lifting this year is the handsome new wrought iron sign enhancing the stonework of the shop's facade and a new signpost near the side-walk. A cement walk was laid early this spring by Orlie and Neal Watson connecting our parking lot with the front door, and new shrubs further beautify the shop front. More lighting, both interior and exterior, has been installed, both to draw atten Lion to our shop and our wares and to better display the color and texture of our weaving. The new combination heating and air-conditioning unit installed in the spring has already proven its worth. In contrast with past summers when customers literally fled the shop's heat and humidity, an increasing number of customers come to the shop and linger. It has also been a boon to the comfort and morale of the shop staff. Adding a third dimension to our displays is our use this summer of the little court just off the main salesroom. In this "patio room" we have an attractive background for brooms, baskets, pottery, and bird feeders. Our newest project about to get underway is the addition of a packing room for our shipping department. It is hoped that construction of this addition will be finished by September, so that club orders this fall can be handled more conveniently and efficiently. This addition will also provide some additional storage space in our jam-packed attic. During the past year, Winogene Redding, our weaving designer, underwent surgery for a fractured hip and has, by degrees, abandoned her crutches and cane and is now able to walk and weave again. This spring we added another member of the Cooke family, which has already provided ARROW-CRAFT SHOP with three fine girls, to our staff. June Cooke, youngest of the family, was graduated from Pi Beta Phi High School this May. Her oldest sister, Edna, worked at the shop for a number of years before her marriage. Faye Cooke is in charge of shipping, and her twin sister, Nella Cooke Hill, is assistant to Miss Redding. Our other sales girls are Gene Hembree and Shirley Roberts, with Ruby Watson working part-time during the summer season. Eunice Cole, who previously handled the shop's bookkeeping under Mrs. Snow, returned to handle this important job soon after Nevada Christian became manager, June 1, 1960. She instituted a new policy of mailing monthly statements to the clubs, which has proved more than satisfactory from the shop's standpoint and appears to meet with club approval. Elizabeth Waitt Rue, ex-manager of AR 33 </p>
      <pb ref="arr7810033_0002" seq="02" n="20-21  "/>
       <p>34 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI ROWCRAFT SHOP, has boosted sales tremendously in her part-time role as manager of the branch shop in the Mountain View Hotel. A new four-color brochure was designed by Mrs. Christian this spring telling the story of ARROW-CRAFT SHOP. It is distributed by the Chamber of Commerce, leading hotels, motels and restaurants in Gatlinburg and nearby Pigeon Forge and by some of our leading local craftsmen. It is aimed at the public, which knows nothing of the shop's relationship to our fraternity project. About 160 alumnae clubs held Arrowcraft sales last fall and early this spring, their efforts rangingfrom limited home showings to all-out bazaars. There remains among the 150 other alumnae clubs a rich potential *of wider markets for our hand-crafted articles. It is our hope that the new sales kit and 1961-62 Price List will arouse the interest of some of these in Arrowcraft merchandise. The top ten clubs, in amount of Arrowcraft sales the past year were: Pittsburgh, Champaign-Urbana, Oklahoma City, Arlington Heights (Ill.), Grand Rap-ids, Akron, Northern New Jersey, Ann Arbor, Philadelphia, and Schnectady. Together they ac-counted for $23,158.76 in sales. Settlement School Honors '60-'61 By Marion Mueller, Settlement School Director Each year more of our dormitory students enter into school activities. To realize there were enough honors for a special topic is amazing to me. There seemed to be a culmination of many activities this year. Of course, there are still shy and demure children, yet somehow there were enough leaders to challenge the best. Four girls were members of Beta Club (honorary) Linda Whaley, Ruby Wright, Linda and Virginia McFalls. Ben Ogle had a part in the Senior play; Ruby Wright, Linda McFalls, and Randy Trentham were in the Junior play. Football captain, Bill Morris, was in our dormitory four-and-a-half-years. Ben Ogle, James Huskey, Bob Ownby, Ray Wright, and Melvin Ogle were on the squad. Bill was also co-captain of the boys' basketball team. (Ray Huskey, dormitory senior in '59-'60 was co-captain of both football and basket-ball.) Melvin Ogle, Doug Price, Ben Ogle, and Ray Wright were on the basketball squad, while James Huskey served as manager. Girls' Varsity team usually had Ruby Wright and Linda McFalls. Ruby made All-County and All-Tournament Teams. Ruby and Linda were elected co-captains for '61-'62. Janette Ogle played on the Girls' Junior High team. All the above made Letter Club. Bill Morris was Student Council president. The first or second Honor Roll claimed Ruby Wright, Linda McFalls, Virginia McFalls, Randy Trentham and Linda Whaley at various times. Two were chosen candidates for Prince and Princess at the Halloween Carnival. James Huskey served as president of Junior class, John Gross sergeant at arms of the Freshman. Commencement awards were gratifying not only to the recipients but to our staff who had coaxed, prodded and encouraged all year every year. The faculty selected Bill Morris as best All-Round boy. The senior receiving the PTA award for the most improvement during the year was a two-year dormitory student, Walter McFalls. The junior receiving the same award was James Huskey. John Gross who came to the dormitory in the eighth grade was the freshman recipient. Our Randy Trentham received the faculty award in Arts and Crafts. Receiving these awards and honors gave a slight measure of success to several young people. Yes, we are "right proud" of our Mountaineers at Pi Beta Phi! The Pi Beta Phi School in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, is the only school in Sevier County to have Arts and Crafts and Music classes for its students. Pi Beta Phi Fraternity provides the teachers for this program. The United States Information Service sponsors tours of Crafts Exhibits around the world. Last year Arrowcraft articles were sent to New Delhi, India on such a tour. The Arrowcraft Weaving Designer, Winogene Redding, has examples of her personal weaving on tour now. Does anyone have Arrowcraft articles of the early years (1915-1930) which would be suitable for an historical section of the Arrowcraft weaving display to be held at The Smithsonian Institute during the Pi Beta Phi 'Convention in Washington, D.C. in June 1962? Please contact Mrs. Albert G. Mueller, Director, Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee. Five new Arrows have been pinned to the Pi Beta Phi Alumnae map since publication of the last issue of the ARROW. This brings the total number of clubs on August 1, 1961, to 312. This total does not include seventeen junior groups and twenty-two area divisions which share large city charters. There are two Area Councils. Other unchartered groups meet across the United States and Canada, and we hope these groups will wish to add their names to the chartered list of Pi Beta Phi Alumnae Clubs. Each one strengthens the national prestige of Pi Beta Phi and our Arrow chain of friendship and service. ALPHA PROVINCE West Suburban (Boston) Massachusetts President Patricia Cloward Erikson (Mrs. W. T.), Florida Alpha, R.F.D. 2, Old Farm Circle, Way-land, Mass. Vice president Mary Fergusson Funk (Mrs. W. L.), Arizona Alpha, 41 Dartmouth Ave., Needham Heights, Mass. Corresponding Secretary Alice Hopkins Helms (Mrs. J. S.), Indiana Gamma, 54 Crestwood Drive, Wellesley Hills, Mass. Treasurer Betty J. Buell Kennedy (Mrs. Sheldon W.), Colorado Beta, Rich Valley Road, Way-land, Mass. IOTA PROVINCE Quincy, Illinois President Frances Golick Castle (Mrs. A. L.), Wisconsin Beta, 1847 Grove, Quincy, Ill. Vice president Mary MacDill Knapheide (Mrs. H. W., Jr.), 225 Woodlawn Ct., Quincy, Ill. Corresponding Secretary Constance Chatten Gra ham (Mrs. Ralph), Illinois Alpha, 3724 N. 12th Street, Quincy, Ill. Treasurer Joan Channon Verner (Mrs. Walter), Illinois Beta-Delta, 5 Hawthorne Hill, Quincy, Ill. LAMBDA PROVINCE Camden, Arkansas President Ruth Moore Malone (Mrs. Charles E.), Arkansas Alpha, Chidester Road, Camden, Ark Secretray Julia Street Walker, Arkansas Alpha P.O. Box 365, Camden, Ark. Hattiesburg, Mississippi President Minnie Lenz McCain (Mrs. W. D.) Mississippi Alpha Vice president Monroe Tate Thomson (Mrs W. A.), Mississippi Alpha Corresponding Secretary Edith Brown Bass (Mrs I. H., Jr.), Mississippi Alpha Treasurer Caroline Roberts Bass (Mrs. Ray), Mis sissippi Alpha MU PROVINCE Alliance, Nebraska President Aurel Foreman Hord (Mrs. Thomas) 1015 Laramie, Alliance, Nebraska Secretary Gerdie Hord Heath (Mrs. Stanley) Lakeside, Nebraska. Treasurer Raye Robb Ellis (Mrs. Wade), 102 Big Hord, Alliance, Nebraska 444 The Requirements for Chartered Clubs Are Easy to Meet and Maintain: 1. Charter applications may be obtained from Grand Vice president. 2. The application blank, accompanied by tl $2.00 club fee for charter and supplies ar $2.50 yearly national dues per member, sent to the Grand Vice president who issu the charter and forwards the fee and du to Central Office. 3. Each chartered club agrees to a minimum 1 four meetings per year: One to active chapt interests, one to fraternity history and constit tion, one to Settlement School, and one to t] observance of Founders' Day. 4. Each club agrees to support fraternity proje( and further fraternity ideals as a club to t: best of its ability. All contributions are vole Lary. No club is ever taxed ! 35 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



