<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr7730015_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Dix, Helen Boucher</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Spring 1961</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr7730015_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1961</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Dix, Helen Boucher</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 14-16</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">40</note>
                        <note type="Folder">13</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 77, Number 3 (Spring 1961), Pages 14-16.</note>
			<note type="document">arr7730015_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Where Are the Pi Phis?;Philadelphia Alumnae Club Gets Soaring Pigeon Award</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Changing Mission of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity for Women in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1944-1964</item>
                                <item>Summer crafts workshop</item>
                                <item>Staff</item>
                                <item>Employment</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr7730015_0001" seq="01" n="14-15  "/>
       <p>etuO /rom tittle Edited by Helen Boucher Dix, Ohio B Where Are the Pi Phis? A comment heard last summer at the 1960 Summer Craft Workshop made us pause and wonder why, "Everyone knows about the Workshop except the Pi Phis," and where have they been that they do not know that the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School and the University of Tennessee jointly have operated the Summer 'Craft Workshop for sixteen years. Together they have pioneered so successfully in this field that Gatlinburg is now recognized as one of the leading craft centers in the United States, in addition to its reputation as the center of traditional hand-weaving. We, the members of the fraternity which twice has led in opening new fields of education for this area, seem to be the last to recognize or to take ad-vantage of the opportunities available to us through our own enterprise and vision! Since 1945, there have been 1160 different students who have benefited from taking 1630 workshop courses. They have come from every state in the country and numerous foreign countries; relatively few have been members of Pi Beta Phi. Among those people interested in or working with the crafts, some of whom write for publications ranging from The New York Times to The Spinning Wheel, the leadership of this community in the crafts field is common knowledge, as is the fact that it was made so by the efforts of Pi Beta Phi to revive the ancient crafts of the area and to provide a market for the products. The October, 1960, issue of The Spinning Wheel, a national magazine about antiques, contains an article, "Hand Weaving and Looms," by Helen Bullard, from which the following paragraphs are quoted: . . Even in the Great Smoky Mountains of Tennessee and North Carolina most of the old looms were stored away in attics and sheds when, in 1912, the Pi Beta Phi Fraternity came to Gatlinburg, Tennessee, to offer its help in educational development and community betterment. Not long after its Settlement School was organized, the Pi Phi staff realized that one of its major contributions could be the development of home industries, the revival of the ancient crafts. Outstanding among these crafts were the old-time "kiverlids," or coverlets, woven of hand-spun, vegetable-dyed wool in intricate allover designs of great antiquity. "With the help and craftsmanship of Aunt Lizzie Reagan and Aunt Lydia Whaley, the school helped to revive many of the ancient crafts and found mar-kets for the products. The two old women taught their neighbors, some of whom needed only a re-fresher course in spinning and weaving. Others were new recruits eager to learn a craft they could work at right at home and sell for cash. "Old looms were found and reconditioned. For-gotten "drafts," the strange looking patterns for coverlets and other weaving with designs began to turn up on yellowed and wrinkled paper. Most of these were tied with bits of thread and showed in-numerable pin pricks where the weavers had marked their places on the pattern. Then the all but lost art of dyeing yarn with native barks and berries was snatched back from oblivion. "By 1925 enough weaving and other crafts were being produced to justify the setting up of the Arrowcraft Shop in Galinburg. Since then Galinburg's place as the center of old-time hand weaving has continued to grow. Paralleling its growth were projects at Berea College in Kentucky and the Allan-stand group in Asheville, North 'Carolina, as well as many lesser weaving centers. "Much fine hand weaving of modern webs is now being done in other parts of the country, especially in New York and New England which boast many important centers and individual weavers. But Gatlinburg remains the present-day center of traditional hand weaving in the United States." On Sunday, October 15, 1960, The New York Times contained an article, "Craftsmen Lend A Hand To Gatlinburg Fair," by Rick Krepela, which stated; "Unique on the roster of fairs to be held this month is the annual Craftsman's Fair that will take place here in the heart of the Great Smoky Mountains. This region is noted for its scenery, but it also has established for itself a reputation as one of the foremost craft centers in the country. Hundreds of individual workers, many of them practicing crafts handed down from their pioneer past, make and sell a variety of items that blend function with beauty. `... Visitors will notice that most of the crafts-men display a membership plaque in the Southern Highland Handicraft Guild. This non-profit group is instrumental in preserving the unique flavor of "mountain crafts" and assures the tourist of a good selection of authentic items that meet high standards of workmanship. Membership in the guild is a much coveted honor. (Ed. note the Pi Beta Phi Arrow 14 MRS. ETHEL TRAINER, a Workshop student for 16 summers. 1960 WORKSHOP STAFF. Seated: Lin L. Phelan, Mrs. Marion Mueller, Miss Marian Heard and Miss Helen Worrail. Standing, Miss Jane Glass, Miss Jean Strange, Miss Lula E. Smith and Mrs. Marjorie Chalmers. WORKSHOP SCENE. Seated at the loom is Miss Ida Mamora from Sarawak and looking on are her instructor, Miss Bessie Stanford and another student, Miss Corazon B. Basas, Manila, P.I. </p>
      <pb ref="arr7730015_0002" seq="02" n="16-17  "/>
       <p>16 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI craft Shop is a charter member.) ". . . Dozens of weavers also will demonstrate their skill at the fair. Using hand-operated looms, they will produce a variety of pioneer-inspired fabrics ranging from place-mats to full size draperies. Hand-woven fabrics are so much in demand. that at least 1,000 workers practice the art. For example, one Gatlinburg gift shop (Ed. note Arrowcraft Shop) keeps sixty-five weavers busy full time turning out cloth for its customers. ". Guild members run a full range of age and interests. They use everything from cornshucks to imported glass in making the things they do. Some members are in their eighties. One of the youngest is 16-years-old Richard Teesatuskie. A 'Cherokee Indian, he still attends high school while using his spare hours to make the silver jewelry that has won the recognition of his fellow craftsmen." Continuing the thought of the above paragraph, Marion Mueller, Director of Settlement School, re-porting on the 1960 Workshop, stated that the slogan might well have been, "Neither Too Young Nor Too Old," and that twenty-two states and three foreign countries were represented. So wide-spread has our reputation grown that the United States Department of Agriculture has asked us to particpate in the United States' exhibit for the International Agricultural Exhibition to be held in Cairo, Egypt, March 21-April 20, 1961. For this we are sending examples of our weaving and pictures of the craftsmen at their looms. One group which has been making an effort for many years to see that our own members benefit from our work in this field is the Southern California Area Council, which annually awards a $400 Workshop Scholarship to a Pi Province active. (See p. 196, the ARROW, Summer 1960). In the near future, another Workshop Scholarship, established by and honoring Virginia Alpha, will be available each summer to a Delta Province active. Perhaps other provinces will become interested in pooling efforts to provide other such scholarships. We have much to be proud of let's see that all of the Pi Phis know of it! PHILADELPHIA ALUMNA CLUB GETS SOARING PIGEON AWARD Settlement School Chairman Helen Russell has announced a correction in the report appearing in the Information Issue of the ARROW. The Philadelphia Alumnx Club should have been in 4th place last year in remittances to Arrowcraft. The total for the several groups which comprise the club should have been $2,702.31 instead of $1,368.81 for the Main Line Group only as announced at convention and as reported on page 43 of the Information ARROW. A Soaring Pigeon Award has belatedly been sent to that club, with apologies for the error. 4-WANTED!! WHO: Two Pi Phi Seniors, graduating in June, with Art Major or Minor WHY: To be Graduate Assistants at the 1961 Craft Workshop WHERE: Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee WHEN: June 10 to July 20, 1961 WITH: Fun! Free board and room! Free course! Financial reimbursement! WRITE: Chairman Settlement School Committee: Mrs. Robert R. Russell, 6823 Crest Avenue, University City 30, Missouri V),fli.flerJona htieJ Edited by Dorothy Davis Stuck, Arkansas A Mrs. Chandler receiving the Austrian Gold Insignia of Honor from Dr. Friederich E. Waller, Austrian Consul general for the Western United States. international Recognition CALIFORNIA'S DOROTHY B. CHANDLER RECEIVES HIGH HONOR FROM AUSTRIA A California Pi Beta Phi, widely known for her work in development of worthy cultural programs, has become the first American woman to receive the Republic of Austria's Gold Insignia of Honor. She is Dorothy Buffum Chandler (Mrs. Norman), a California Alpha. L700 Attend Reception Mrs. Chandler received the award at a November reception at the California Club attended by over 1,700 persons including Southern California leaders in many fields. Also honored at the reception was (Continued an page 56) 17 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



