<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr7930011_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Gordon, Sally Wild </name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Spring 1963</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr7930011_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1963</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Gordon, Sally Wild </name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 10-11</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">40</note>
                        <note type="Folder">15</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 79, Number 3 (Spring 1963), Pages 10-11.</note>
			<note type="document">arr7930011_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">May We Introduce . . . Nurse Brenda Ann Allison; Arrowcraft Manager Maria Lou Tate; Music Instructor Glenn Terry</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Changing Mission of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity for Women in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1944-1964</item>
                                <item>Staff</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>
                                <item>Summer craft workshop</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr7930011_0001" seq="01" n="10-11  "/>
       <p>News from Little Pigeon Edited by Sally Wild Gordon, Wisconsin A May We Introduce . Introductions are in order from our Settlement School ; for since fall three popular new staff members have been serving at the Arrowcraft Shop, the Health Center and the School. It gives us pleasure to present them to you now. Nurse Brenda Ann Allison Miss Brenda Ann Allison, the attractive new nurse at the Health Center, started her work in November and now feels very much a part of the Settlement School. Miss Allison, a native of Alabama, came to Sevierville in 1954 when her father was transferred to the Douglas Dam. She graduated from Sevier County High School and then entered the University of Tennessee Memorial Research Center and Hospital in 1958. During her nurse's training she earned enough hours to qualify as a Red Cross Nurse. Since her graduation in 1961 she has worked at the University Hospital and recently served as head nurse in its Nursery. Because of her great interest in Nurse Brenda Allisonworking with children, she was particularly attracted to this position at the Settlement School. The Health Center obviously is in very good hands. Arrowcraft Manager Maria Lou Tate Mrs. Hutchins Tate, the new Arrowcraft Shop manager, is a Florida Beta Pi Phi. Mrs. Tate lived in McMinnville, Tennessee, until she went to Tallahassee, Florida to attend Florida State College. Later she studied at Peabody College in Nashville. She was a charter member of the Nashville Alumnae Club and has already become a member of the Little Pigeon Alumnae Club in Gatlinburg. Her one son is a Navy flyer stationed at Corpus Christi, Texas. Mrs. Tate has had fine experience in business management and has a deep appreciation of handcrafts. Pi Beta Phi is very fortunate to have such a charming capable person in charge of the Arrowcraft Shop. Arrowcraft Manager Maria Tate 10 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI Music Instructor Glenn Terry Glenn Terry of Knoxville, Tennessee came to the Pi Beta Phi School last fall as Instructor of Music. Although he had received his Bachelor of Music degree from the University of Tennessee in June, 1962, he already has had a great deal of experience in band work and has served as choir director, as organist and as accompanist at the University's Opera Work-shop. While at the University he was a member of Phi Mu Alpha Sinphonia, professional honorary music fraternity. He also had the honor of performing as soloist when the Knoxville Symphony Orchestra presented a piano concerto he had composed. The Symphony Orchestra has featured a number of his compositions on its programs, including a dance suite on the Honors Program at the University last June. More recently Mr. Terry has had his own music studio and he \promises to be a great asset to the school. Fort Lauderdale Club Arranges Library Display The Broward County Alumnae Club of Fort Lauderdale, Fla., presented a most attractive display of Arrowcraft handwoven articles in the Fort Lauderdale Public Library for the entire month of January. Photographs of the Arrowcraft Shop, some pictures of weavers at work and the displays at the special exhibit at the Smithsonian Institution in Washington, D.C., ' last June all helped to tell the story of Arrowcraft and the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School. TO ALL II PHIS . .. See Your Settlement School *Enjoy a Creative Vacation *Attend the 1963 Craft Workshop REGISTER TODAY Dates and courses offered appear on the hack cover of this ARROW. Virginia Alpha Scholarship Applications Due April 1 When fraternities were removed from the Ran dolph-Macon campus, the members of Virgini Alpha felt the best way they could honor their chap ter was to use the interest from their assets for scholarship to the Summer Craft Workshop. This is a wonderful opportunity for any under graduate Pi Phi who is interested in art and crafts. Application letters should be sent by April 1, t( Miss Mary Williams, 2600 Monument Avenue Richmond, Virginia. Attention Pi Phi Seniors The 1963 Craft Workshop has openings for twi Graduate Assistants available to graduating senior who are art majors or minors. This affords an opportunity to live at the Settle ment School for six weeks early this summer. As sistants receive financial reimbursement, free root: and board and one free credit course. Persons interested should write at once to Mn Robert R. Russell, Chairman, Settlement School Corr] mittee, 6823 Crest Avenue, University City 30, Mis souri. 1962 CRAFT WORKSHOP SCENE-Betty Casteel, Albuquei que, N.M. Alumnae Club Craft Scholarship Winner, Id works on pottery bowl under the watchful eye of Barbar McDonald, pottery instructor who will return in 1963, an Emily Burchfield, who is the Pi Beta Phi School Arts an Crafts Instructor. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



