<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr7110055_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Committee Reports</title>
                        <author><name>Green, Virginia Brackett</name></author>
                        <author><name>Dyer, Ruth</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Fall 1954</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr7110055_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1954</date>, Committee Reports</title>
                        <author><name>Green, Virginia Brackett</name></author>
                        <author><name>Dyer, Ruth</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 54-67</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">40</note>
                        <note type="Folder">7</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 71, Number 1 (Fall 1954), Pages 54-67.</note>
			<note type="document">arr7110055_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Chairman of the Settlement School Committee; Report of Director of Settlement School, 1954</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Changing Mission of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity for Women in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1944-1964</item>
                                <item>Healthcare</item>
                                <item>Budget</item>
                                <item>Summer crafts workshop</item>
                                <item>Education</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr7110055_0001" seq="01" n="54-55  "/>
       <p>Committee /eeportrs CHAIRMAN OF THE SETTLEMENT SCHOOL COMMITTEE "There is nothing so permanent as change," was the thought-provoking statement made at the 1953 Province Officers' Workshop by Jessie Harris, the Asheville Convention Initiate. Dean Harris was reminding Pi Beta Phi that change has taken place in the entire world during the last forty years and it was encouraging that the work at the Settlement School has met the challenge of the changing needs through-out the years. The right kind of change is progress. If conditions were the same as back in the picturesque days of 1912 when Pi Phi took over the one room school, the fraternity might well feel discouraged and class its philanthropic project a failure. It is impossible to look forward to the good old days and be progressive. Just as the automatic washer is a far-cry from the wash board, the Pi Beta Phi Gatlinberg schools are a "fur piece" from the first one room school. There were twenty-four teachers and a principal besides five cafeteria workers, three bus drivers and a custodian who made up the staff. The state and county supported the basic educational program but once again the school's curriculum was enriched by courses and teachers provided and paid by Pi Phi in the fields of arts and crafts, music, physical education and creative writing. The number of courses offered was limited even after the addition of chemistry, creative writing and home economics for boys. There is a need for more language and mathematics and there is a danger of losing some of the courses now taught. If your child attended the Pi Beta Phi schools, and he would if you lived in Gatlinburg, you would be most grateful for these extra Pi Phi teachers for there is not a great number of electives from which to choose. Ann Smith taught the Arts and Crafts courses again this year and Katherine McIntosh, and Alabama Pi Beta Phi and a Music major, took over the music classes when Mrs. Armstrong resigned upon the death of her husband. Mr. Chan Huskey returned to teach Physical Education and to coach the boys' and girls' basketball teams. Mr. Carl Huskey, owner of the Village Craft Shop, was the part-time teacher of Woodworking. Mr. Huskey built more than furniture; he built men and women for in his quiet way he solved discipline problems and inspired his pupils to achieve. In and around Gatlinberg are many craft shops where hand made furniture is made. Many of the boys find their way into these shops from the Woodworking classes. Joan Newcomer, the assistant to the Director, taught the Creative Writing class which put out the Highland Echo, the new school paper. Joni was the sponsor for the Student Council, which she promoted, as well as a Senior Sponsor. Money put into teachers' salaries is a good investment. The only thing more expensive than education is ignorance. The boys' and girls' dormitories made it possible for eleven boys and girls to continue their high school education. These folks live too far to come to school via the school bus. Joni Newcomer served as house-mother for the girls and Ira Gladson was the "dorm Dad" for the boys. The girls helped in the kitchen, served in the dining room and did light cleaning after school to partially pay for room and board. The boys helped with the care of the grounds and buildings. This housing and training was highly praised by Principal Large who said the dormitory students were outstanding in studies and deportment. Another contribution made by the fraternity to the educational facilities of the school was comfortable, reasonable lodging for staff. The Ruth Barrett Smith Staff House, with the attractive dining room where the resident staff and teachers ate their meals, continued to be a source of pleasure during the winter as well as Summer Craft Workshop. This building helps to attract and hold teachers in a town where rents are high due to tourist trade. Some generous gifts made it possible to add necessary furnishings to the Staff House as well as to pay for the original purchases which were required before moving into the house. The committee thanks the following clubs and individuals for the assistance in this worthy project: Amy B. Onken Club Los Angeles Club (Final payment on bedroom) Some members of Detroit Club Jackson, Michigan Club Chicago South Club Indianapolis Club (Final payment on bedroom) Ames, Iowa Club Franklin, Indiana Club (Final payment on bedroom) Shreveport, La. Club Austin, Texas Club Oklahoma City Club Stillwater Club Ponca 'City, Oklahoma Club \Wichita Falls, Club Dallas, Texas Club Texarkana Club Abilene Club Beaumont Club Houston Club McAlester Club Champaign-Urbana Club (Payment on bedroom) Fox River Valley Club Monmouth Club Madison, Wisconsin Club Pittsburgh Club Everett Washington Club Springfield, Illinois Club Seattle, Washington Club (Payment on Bedroom) Mrs. Atlen Rankin Mr. and Mrs. Ronald Stevenson (Bedroom) Virginia Brackett Green (Bedroom) There were one hundred and forty-four chapters and clubs which participated in the Penny Parade for Loyalty Day last January. The final count totaled $565.32 and as the result of this sum and a generous discount, a Storey and Clark spinet piano was purchased for the Staff House living room before the Summer Craft Workshop. It will be a source of pleasure for years to come. The toughest form of mountain climbing is getting out of a rut. To,prevent such a danger, this year as in the past, the committee re-evaluated the work and the support of the ,schools. In conference with the County Superintendent of Education, Mr. Roy Ledwell, and some of his bOard, the Committee was assured that the Pi Beta Phi teachers were needed. The Settlement School Committee felt that Mr. Ledwell was a sincere public servant and so were impressed by his explanatiOn of the County's problems. Just so many teachers can be supported by the County funds. If the fraternity withdrew its teachers, the other teachers would have to double up for none could be hired to replace them. Perhaps some figures quoted from the News 54 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI Record and The Gatlinburg Press will explain the reason for the inability of the County to assume full responsibility. In May 1954 the papers reported the property tax rates of Tennessee counties In 1953 varied from $1.05 to $5.75 per $100 of assessed value. Sevier County tax rate was $4.35. The median tax rate of all Tennessee counties was $3.00. Only eight counties in Tennessee levied a higher tax rate than Sevier County and eighty-six levied a lower rate. Sevier County furnished approximately $50,000 from the tax levy towards County educational expenditure of more than $900,000. This meant that Sevier County paid only about $9 per year per student for school operation while the State paid the remainder or about $141. In other words the State furnished approximately 94% of the school money while Sevier County supplied 6%. All of the counties surrounding Sevier County paid teachers more money in amounts running from $5 to $50 per month. This said to the Settlement School Committee that withdrawing the support of the teachers would be like getting off of the train before reaching one's destination. Some improvements were made in the physical plant through the efforts of the principal and the cooperation of the County Superintendent. Due to lack of funds, the buildings were not maintained by the County according to the desired standard. Evidently the County Conrt was not realistic in budget-making. It always has too much year left at the end of the money and Mr. Ledwell cannot do the impossible. For months there has been a growing conviction on the part of school patrons that the entire County was in need of better school facilities. An invitation was issued to the State Department of Education to send in a team of experts to study the needs of the schools in cooperation with the Sevier County Board of Education. As a result a bond issue of $550,000 was floated for buildings and improvements in the County. Gatlinburg was allocated $60,000 to build an auditorium on County property in the rear of the school and $10,000 for remodeling present structures. Sevierville received a much larger amount be-cause the facilities there were not only deplorable but dangerous. It does a man no good to sit up and take notice if he keeps on sitting, so it is evidence of real progress that the County is willing to combine emotion with action. All of this will take many plans and time. With the health program flexible enough to allow for meeting the various needs of the people as they arise, it is easily understood that Nurse Marjorie Chalmers' activities were somewhat different than those of the first 'Pi Phi nurse. Back in 1919 when the flu epidemic swept the nation, it became apparent that a health program was needed. Miss Phyllis traveled horseback and carried her medicines in the saddlebags but today Mrs. Chalmers can reach most places by car. In early days there was ,no doctor in the area but now that the people can depend upon the doctor more fully, the Health Center can enlarge the educational and advisory phases of service and thus extend the outreach. The Pi Phi nurse continued to give guidance and cooperation to the community and to serve in any way that furthered the health and safety of the people. . Adult service consisted mostly in treating emergencies since the necessity for assistance in home care has become less urgent due to more frequent hospitalization. Naturally the nurse was on duty during the Summer Craft Workshop ready for any emergency. Maternal and Infant Welfare continued to be an important phase of the Health Center's work. Mothers brought the babies to the weekly Baby Clin: responded well to the post card reminders ti oculations were due. Under the sponsorship P.T.A. and with the cooperation of two docta pre-school roundup was most successful. The department of Health Center is that which p to school work. Each student in the three rura and in the schools at Gatlinburg received the physical examination; the parents were notified results. Each received his booster shots as the) due. The.philosophy of the health program is a fence at the edge of the precipice than a h at its foot." Health and Safety instructions were given ir room talks during regular inspections but the also reached the children via the eye-gate wil strips and slides. The pupils in the drab littl, schools welcomed Mrs. Chalmers' regular vis the pictures helped them quickly forget the p the needle. A great deal of effort was put ini licizing -the Chest X-Ray Clinic. Several meet. the Sevier County Medical Society were held Health Center with gratifying attendance and st ing discussions. Since Gatlinburg is the center ( cal areas, Nurse Marjorie was active in the Ci fense program and attended two Civil Defense shops last year besides serving as a member State Women's Advisory Committee for Cii fense. Jennie Nicol, the first Pi Phi doctor dreamed of the Atomic First Aid classes whic taught in the Health Center named in her hon Mrs. Chalmers' stock of layettes and "h (diapers) were depleted and she mentioned fully the clubs and individuals that replen. shelves from year to year. The articles need new but must be in good condition. Sigma Phi friends again gave funds for Eye Correction at jorie tried to meet each need whether it was for clothing, shoes or professional assistance. S called u0o~ to cooperate with the P.T.A., t Manager's Office, the Chamber of Commerce a Scouts which made for good public relations is listed a $.ummary of activity: Field Visits Office Calls First Aid, etc. . . Small Pox Vaccinations Diphtheria ImMunizations Total Typhoid Inoculations Completed Typhoid Series ^ Total Pertusses Inoculations Completed Pertasses Series Total Triple Vaccine . Completed Triple Vaccine .Tetanus Immunization Therapeutic Inoculations Health Talks Pupil Examinations '~~i~~~~~'~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ Chest X-Ray The Armwoaft Shop was the first buildi Pi Phis visited the Settlement School. In to the lovely articles designed by Tina M( the Arroweraft Designer, Mrs. Marion Mue Arroweraft Manager, made every effort to variety of products from native craftsmen for and Pi Phi sales. Mrs. McMorran attended signer Craftsman's Show in New York and fresh inspiration from close touch with the crafts. Arrow Craft exhibited at the Craftsra of the Southern Highlands in Asheville, Not lima Ma.rian Heard, the 1954 Convention was one of the important members of the cl on arrangements that brought together craftsn seven mountain states. </p>
      <pb ref="arr7110055_0002" seq="02" n="56-57  "/>
       <p>56 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI Approximately two hundred clubs and twelve chapters sold Arrowcraft products. The shipping season began in the fall and lasted almost until Christmas. It is only fitting that grateful recognition should be given to the marvelous spirit of the Arrowcraft staff who, with Marion Mueller and Edna Cook, assistant to the Weaving Supervisor, cheerfully averaged an extra three nights per week work for about two months in order that the clubs might not be disappointed. Nellie Cook, Ruby Watson, Susie Maples plus Betty Lewelling, the bookkeeper and Tina McMorran, Designer and Weaving Supervisor, completed the staff. Betty, wife of one of the teachers, took over the accounting department when Katie McIntosh assumed the duties of Music Supervisor in the schools. Mrs. McCutchan was in charge of the shop at the Mountain View Hotel. There were nineteen clubs that paid $1,000 or more to Arrow Craft during the fiscal year. That was an increase of four clubs over the year before. May their tribe increase! Portland, Ore $2,756.12 Champaign-Urbana 2,396.78 Pittsburgh, Pa 2,295.65 Everett, Wash' 1,572.00 Pasadena, Calif 1,490.48 Albany, N 1,411.47 Houston, Texas 1,397.66 Oklahoma City, Okla 1,339.66 Omaha, Nebr 1,279.69 St. Louis, Mo $1,268.96 South Hills of Pittsburgh, 'Pa 1,184.56 South Bend, Ind 1,158.32 Milwaukee, Wis 1,125.15 Albuquerque, N. M 1,118.59 Los Angeles, Calif 1,073.19 Northern New Jersey 1,066.31 Seattle, Wash 1,058.23 Madison, Wis 1,030.42 Indianapolis, Ind $1,006.87 Two innovations were tried this year. Color swatches were sent with the new price list and letter of instructions in August. This was an aid to chair-men in selecting products or ordering to match special color schemes. Bulletins featuring "specials" or new articles were included with the statements. A decided effort was made to clear the old stock and eliminate "as long as they last" numbers. This policy will be continued in order that more new items may be available. Since Arrowcraft must meet a monthly pay-roll for the weavers and staff and pay for supplies, clubs were urged to pay regularly on their Arrow Craft accounts rather than to wait until the end of the club year. This is good business and Marion Mueller appreciated the many who were willing to cooperate. Between fifty and sixty mountain women wove for Pi Beta Phi last year. At a party nine of these were honored for they had woven for Arrow Craft at least twenty-five years. A pin was presented to each with initials and' "25 years with Arrow Craft" inscribed. Other weavers will be so honored as they qualify. Because hundreds of weavers are now weaving nylon bags, Arrow Craft does not feel obliged to spread its work and can produce more and better products with fewer weavers. Little did Pi Beta Phi dream of the many women who would prosper because of the early efforts to revive the art of weaving. From 1927 through May 1954, according to a conservative estimate, Arrow Craft paid approximately $467,151.00 to weavers. Many shops in Gatlinburg sell woven products and Pi Phi can be proud that it pioneered and perhaps inspired others in the preservation and development of native crafts. The Gatlinburg Press recently stated, "This pioneer Settlement School has been instrumental in making Gatlinburg a major craft center and the leading area for hand weaving in the country." Pi Beta Phi Settlement School Committees through the years have had concrete opinions but not the kind which were thoroughly mixed and permanently set. At various times outstanding, unprejudiced educators surveyed the project and made recommendations. The Summer Craft Workshop was started ten years ago as a result of the surveys. It has accomplished many things. First, year-round use is made of the plant; further impetus is given to the arts and crafts pro-gram which was started long ago. Outstanding instructors from all over the country attract craftsmen to the Workshop, Pi Phis, students and folks in search of a hobby. The pupils return home to teach, work with the handicapped or in correctional institutions or give valuable service to their communities as volunteers. Those who have been closely associated with the Settlement School or the Workshop were thrilled when Marian Heard, the Director of Workshop for the last seven years, was chosen as Miami Beach Convention Initiate. Sponsored jointly with the University of Tennessee, Pi Phi depends upon the staff of UT for wise counsel. Last November Miss Jessie Harris, Vice Dean of the College of Home Economics, Miss Henrietta R. Sivyer, Head of the Department of Related Arts and Crafts, Miss Ruth Buckley, Head of the Department of Foods and Nutrition, Miss Marian Heard, Professor of Craft Design together with Miss Dyer, Miss Newcomer and the chairman, met to formulate plans for the 1954 Summer Work-shop. The final course of study included Decorative Design, Metal Work, Jewelry, Weaving, Rug Weaving, Textile Design, Enameling, Advanced Recreational Crafts and Pottery. Two Pi Phis, Mollie Law-ton, Tennessee Alpha, and Donna Stavreff, Ohio Beta, served as graduate assistants. There were 106 enrolled in the various classes from 22 states, Hawaii and the Philippine Islands. The enthusiasm of those who came to Workshop in 1953 made us anxious to publicize the Workshop on a larger scale. A letter, urging the chapters to inform members of the opportunity offered, was sent out with the bulletins. Each chapter was asked to check the bulletin boards in the Arts and Crafts Departments to make sure an announcement was posted. A publicity release was included which allowed space for local names and chapters were urged to submit the article to the school paper. A similar plan was followed with the alumna clubs except they were asked to use the publicity in the local paper. He who. finds he has something to sell And goes and whispers it down a well, Is not so apt to collar the dollars As he who climbs a tree and hollers. The committee wants both actives and alumnae * to help "holler" about the wonderful privileges made possible at Summer Workshop. It has been suggested that an alumnx club might offer a scholarship to a person who would. accept it with the understanding she was to return to give special volunteer service in training leadership that would work with disabled veterans, Scout troops, handicapped folks, etc. This plan would help Workshop, give good publicity to the club, provide trained leadership for the community besides publicizing the Pi Beta Phi-University of Tennessee Summer Workshop. The Southern California Area Council cooperated this year by sending Nancy Jones to Summer Workshop. When one person is helped, that is fine but when a person is trained to go out and work with many others, ability to assist others is multiplied many times. That is one of the THE ARROW OF PI' BETA PHI 57 exciting features of the Workshop. Pi Beta Phi's belief in the values of crafts leaves Gatlinburg with each student and spreads far and wide. Marian Heard says with more leisure time available, there is a need for creative activity. A flying rumor never has trouble in landing. Such a thing has been buzzing about that Settlement School no longer needs the support of the clubs and chapters. Costs have increased for the Settlement School the same as they have for homes; buildings must be kept in repair, too. Once again St. Louis Club headed the list of clubs contributing $150.00 or more to the Settlement Schciol. St. Louis, Mo $1,000.00 Kansas City 363.67 Philadelphia, Pa 250.00 Cleveland East 250.00 Indianapolis, Ind 210.00 Northern New Jersey 175.00 Denver, Colo 152.00 Milwaukee, Wis 150.00 Houston, Texas 150.00 The committee appreciated all of the contributions and the efforts which made them possible. Be assured they gave careful consideration before spending any of the funds. Every now and then a man's mind is stretched by a new idea and never shrinks back to its former dimensions. This was true of Pi Phi after the Settlement School was established. Ideas are funny little things. They won't work unless you do. Wouldn't it be wonderful if each club and chapter set a goal for itself and made a contribution to the Settlement School during the coming year? The fiscal year was changed to end May 31 and some were late with gifts this year but this can be easily remedied. If each member of an alumnae club and active chapter gave a sum equal to a 1 postage stamp each day, the Settlement School would have three times as much money. The committee is not requesting a drive for a special project but naturally would be glad to receive any contribution from a group that had been unable previously to help with the "wishing list" and now found itself in better condition. The Deep Freeze or some means of providing ice cubes for the staff dining 'room (luring the hot summer months still heads the list. The freezer would make it possible to take care of surplus garden produce for the winter use not to mention the advantage of buying meat in quantity. Scattered all over the country are isolated Pi Phis unable to enjoy membership in an alumnae club and to have an active part in the suppOrt of the national projects; however they are only a 3 postage stamp away from the Settlement School treasurer, Mrs. Thomas Graham. The northern New Jersey club presented twelve ceramic founders to the fraternity. It is quite fitting that they will be displayed at the Arrow Craft Shop. The check for $7,276.36 from the Magazine Agency was received with gratitude. This was approximately $600 less than the previous year. Several reasons might have caused this decline but if we each set a goal for the coming year, there is a chance to regain lost ground. Each group should select a dependable chairman and maintain an up-to-date file. Often ashut-in, who can participate in few outside activities, will be the very best chairman. Can't we aim for $8,000 from magazines this season? While we are asking for things, we would like to ask for one Settlement School program in each club or chapter. The Arrow Craft Sale cannot really be counted as a program in the most cases. The commit-tee has prepared two sets of new color slides and a continuity to be read during the showing of the slides. Almost every group will have a member who will be happy to use her equipment to show the slides. The movie is getting old and will be sent only on request. In many ways the slides will make a fine replacement when the movie can no longer be used. The fall mailing will contain program material and last year's suggestion is still good. As a new chairman, I have been very appreciative of the cooperation of committee members. Olivia Moore has been the contact member from Grand Council and her previous experience as Settlement School Treasurer has made her extremely helpful. The Grand President has been ready and willing to give advice when asked. Ruth Barrett Smith, the former chairman, has demonstrated her loyalty to the school by cheerfully helping the new chairman. Ethel Smith's term of committee membership terminated in May and we will miss her. We welcomed Edna Archibald, a former PVP, to the committee and know her years of fraternity service will assist her in her new work. There will be many changes at the school this year. The efficient principal, Dewey Large, has been called to a larger field of work and Mr. Chan Huskey, the Pi Phi Physical Education teacher, will assume Mr. Large's duties. Ann Smith and Katie McIntosh will return to the universities for advanced study. Both will be missed in many places. Joni Newcomer, resigned to go abroad. Her many activities on and beyond the call of duty will cause many people to regret her departure. Last but not least by any means we regret to announce the resignation of Ruth Dyer who as Director of the Settlement School for almost eleven years, represented Pi Beta Phi in Gatlinburg. Her conscientious, loyal performance of duties has made a valuable contribution to the Settlement School. Mrs. Marion Mueller, the Arrowcraft Manager, will become the new Director. Her chance to work with Ruth during the last few months will be a great help in the days ahead. Marion will continue to supervise Arrowcraft until a new manager can be brought in after the hectic shipping season. Any names of Pi Phis who might qualify as a manager will be welcomed by the chairman. Nancy Jo Hayes from University of Tennessee and a Pi Phi was trained by Joni and took over the middle of June as Assistant to the Director. Wonderful reports have made us realize we made the right choice. As I' write this report for the thousands of Pi Phis who can make so many wonderful things come true, I hope I have said the things which will make you enthusiastic about your national project. I wish I could tell you the human interest stories which space does not permit and which prove there are many opportunities for service often unknown to the average member. Shall we go forward by design or backward by default? VIRGINIA BRACKETT GREEN Color slides of the Settlement School are now available for use of alumnae clubs and chapters. A continuity to be read comes with them. They may be secured through Mrs. Frank Gibson, 4510 Post Road, Nashville 5, Tennessee. </p>
      <pb ref="arr7110055_0003" seq="03" n="58-59  "/>
       <p>58 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI REPORT OF DIRECTOR OF SETTLEMENT SCHOOL 1954 Looking back over the ten and one half years that I have spent at the Settlement School is like looking down the tube of a childhood kaleidoscope. The variegated pattern has been ever changing. This re-port will attempt to tell some of the forms assumed by the colored chips in the last year. Community Many changes and improvements take place each year in the village. Church additions include the completion of a new Catholic Church on Airport Road. In the other end of town, the Roaring Fork Baptist congregation built a new parsonage with an adequate social hall for the church family, in the basement. Swimming pools are beginning to be built in a few places to increase the facilities for hotels and motels. One of these was constructed adjacent to the New Gatlinburg Inn. Next to it there is a chair lift that takes passengers to the top of the mountain back of the hotel. The Mountain View Hotel added a very nice recreation hall which they call. the Andy Huff House. The earth moving machines are seldom idle as new Motels, shops and restaurants spring up, and these are often located on sites that have been dug out of the hills. The move was made into the new Post Office across from the New Riverside Hotel. A new City Manager, Mr. Walter W. Mynatt, and a new Director of the Chamber of Commerce, Mr. Jim Hays, have taken their place in the local scene. Television came to Knoxville during the year. It has made possible quite good reception for Gatlinburg people who have high aerials on the mountains. The usual Thanksgiving and Easter services were held and in the winter several fund raising parties brought the lo-cal people together for a social evening as they helped raise money for church and philanthropic projects. Girl Scouting was kept alive by an interested local committee. One of their projects was the lighting of the Community Christmas tree across from Arrow Craft Shop. This was done with the help of the local Garden Club which again staged their show of Christmas greens and decorations in the Mountain View Hotel lobby. This show seems to get better each year and creates much interest in town. The judges always give us high praise and are pleased with the exhibits that the Arts and Crafts students and the girls from the Home Economics Department contribute. There has been an effort made to bring more conventions to the town, especially in the winter months. In early spring the J. C.'s of Tennessee met here. The S. E. Arts Association brought 350 members from eight states and later on a big Tennessee Bar Association meeting taxed the facilities of the hotels and courts that are heated. In February and March two annual meetings came off The Council of Southern Mountain Workers and that of the South-ern Highland Handicraft Guild. Craft exhibits were featured at both of these conventions. School Activities started even before school opened. Joni, Ann Smith, and a couple of the other teachers arranged two exhibits for the Sevier County Fair. The theme was "Gatlinburg Pi Beta Phi School Enriches its Program Through Arts and Crafts." Two blue ribbons and $60.00 in prize money were earned by the attractive display. For the first time the state of Tennessee provided free text books for all grades. Our enrollment was higher than usual and the students were soon engrossed in many projects in addition to their studies. Football games were played under lights on the American Legion Field for the first year.' Halloween was observed with a big All School Carnival that was sponsored by the Senior Class. This was one of the ways in which they earned money for their Senior trip. National Education Week saw the whole school staging a big parade. The primary children had a great thrill, riding in the loco-motive .owned by the Sevier County Veterans of Foreign Wars. The Art department helped with some floats that made a good showing and with every child in school participating in the project, the public was made aware of educational needs. That evening there was an . Open House for parents and friends with refreshments served at the lunch room. In November the Junior Class play, "Where's Laurie ?" was given two nights. The Junior Mothers gave a nice party following the final performance and there was a big party in honor of the football team. We had two days of vacation at Thanksgiving. I can see the bits of glass fairly dancing as December events come to mind. It is always a colorful and happy time even if the weather may be dreary. Joni wrote and staged a clever variety show called "The Senior Sillies" that was fun for everyone. Every room was bright with trees and Christmas decorations. There were room parties in the lower grades and celebrations for the high school classes. Katie McIntosh put on a very good musical Christmas pro-gram the morning of the last day before vacation. The children love the old carols and sing them very well. At this program the boys contributed more than in former times. After vacation came semester exams and great interest in basketball. This was our most successful year, ever, for the girls and boys teams both got to play in the District Tournament at Jefferson City. The girls were eliminated rather early, but the boys won time after time, only to lose by two points in three minutes of overtime play in the final game. It was a hard blow for the coach, Mr. Chan Huskey, and the boys who had done so well. We did place three men on the All-Tournament Team, more than were placed by any other team. Our talented Joni contributed to the school program by teaching a class in Creative Writing. The little paper called Highland, Echo, that the class put out, won the highest rating possible for schools of our size in the -state contest. The paper sponsored the formation of a Student Council and a contest for a new school song. Joni's original words and music won this competition. The University of Tennessee had fifteen student teachers doing practice teaching in the school during the spring quarter. The Home Economics department of the University used our school for teacher training in that field and Carolyn Freshour had two girls working with her. These young people fitted into the program very well, bringing fresh enthusiasm and new ideas. Several of them helped with the Field and May Day sport event that was held on the campus and with plays and outside events. Katie presented the children of the first four grades in a beautiful little operetta called "The Farmer in the Dell." The Senior Class play was a period piece "Turn Back the Clock." Here again, Joni's talents were visible for the production was superior to the general run of high school plays. She and Betty THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI 59 Underwood, the other Senior Sponsor, worked hard with the class in all of their final programs. It was the largest class in history 28 in number. Their class trip to Washington, D.C. was a wonderful experience for all of them. Mr. Large and his wife chaperoned the trip, and reported that they were most co-operative and well behaved. We followed the usual Commencement week events. A dignified Baccalaureate service with the student chorus giving the musical numbers a Class Night that was more informal and fun for the class with their silly gifts and prophecies, called "Seniors on Trial," and the final exercises when diplomas were presented and awards made. A surprise award of twenty-five dollars was given to Joe D. Manley by some Ann Arbor Pi Phi friends of Mrs. Alfred White in memory of her husband. Joe's mother, Dorothy Manley, was a Pi Phi who taught here before her marriage and now that her children are older is again teaching in the system. We were pleased that her son merited the award which is to be used towards his college expenses. On the social side of Commencement week there was the dinner that I gave at Staff House for the Speaker and others who were on the program preceding the final program and a reception held at the Andy Huff House for the faculty members, parents and friends of the Class. The Beta Club was reactivated and some of their members made a trip to Nashville. Other trips were taken by Science classes to Oak Ridge, Home Economics girls to Knoxville and the Journalism students to a U.T. Conference. I know that I have omitted many interesting groupings of the colored bits but it really was a most stimulating and worth-while year for the school. P.T.A. Due in part to greater student and teacher participation in the programs, the monthly meetings were very well attended. There seemed to be more interest on the part of the fathers this year. Money making projects consisted of several rummage sales and the third big Minstrel Show that was given two nights. This brought in over $400.00. The organization contributed to equipment for the new Chemistry department, some lunch room and Home Economics equipment and other minor projects. The school lunch program had its most successful year. Mrs. John Morell is the very efficient manager. She and her helpers served 350 lunches a day at a cost of $.25 per person. This was made possible by state and federal grants of food which help supply a very well balanced and nourishing meal. It is often the only good meal that some of the children have during the day, especially the ones that are given free tickets by the P.T.A. Dormitory We had Mrs. Mabel Hesler with us during the winter months as House Manager. She left before the preparations for Workshop started. Mrs'. Lela Adams has been our very efficient cook who has fed us well with the help of the Dormitory girls and one maid. The Staff House has been used for several Community affairs such as a big Garden Club meeting, an after-theater party for the cast and friends who put on the P.T.A. Minstrel show, a luncheon meeting of the Knoxville-Little Pigeon Alumnae Club and a small music recital. We have entertained many dinner guests and members of the family have entertained Club and Church groups. The piano at Stuart was again used by Mrs. Henry who gave private lessons to school children. Practically all of the Dor-mitory students were on the honor roll. One senior girl, Marie Davenport, was class Valedictorian. One of the freshman girls, Dorothy Floyd, won the P.T.A. award for most improvement during the year and Ruth Wright represented the high school at Girl's State. Our students rate above the high school average scholastically and in addition, by their work duties, learn many things to help them through life. The Dormitory program continues to be one of the most valuable contributions of the Fraternity. Farm City regulations made it necessary for us to dispose of our few pigs. Now our livestock consists of two mules, John and Coalie, and we carry on our chicken project. Richard Watson, our good farm manager, takes care of the flock and works our fine garden, with the help of the Dormitory boys. We have chicken and eggs for our table and there is a ready market for the extra fresh eggs. The garden provides us with many vegetables in season and potatoes for the winter months. This year, Richard planted a few peanuts which Mrs. Hesler would serve, salted, as something extra. Health Center The brightly colored bits of glass fall into shape to show another important division of our work that of the Health Center and the services rendered by our nurse, Marjorie Chalmers. The building is used as headquarters for the visits of the State T.B. Mobile Unit. At the last visit 874 persons were X-rayed. It also serves as a meeting place for the County Medical Association. The pre-school clinic cared for 64 children and the weekly Friday afternoon clinics are at-tended by many young mothers who seek the advice of the nurse. During the regular school year the students in the local school plus the ones in three country schools are given their health examinations and preventive shots in the Clinic room. I call this place "Marjorie's shooting gallery" for many are the -shots" given there, each month. The path to the back door is well traveled by the youngsters who go to see the nurse for treatments for their cuts and bruises and for first aid in emergencies. She teaches first aid classes to groups of Girl Scouts and Home Economics students and represents the town in Atomic Nursing as part of the Civil Defense plan. Some generous gifts made possible a number of eye corrections that could not be paid for by certain parents. In addition to the $50.00 given annually by the Sigma Phi Gamma International Sorority, one of their Port-land, Oregon, Chapters gave $15.00. Our own Berke-ley Alumnae Club gave $25.00, some Indianapolis Alumnie friends of Ethel Rous Curryer sent $32.00 as a memorial to her and the girls who attended Epsilon Province Workshop sent $5.00 that had been left in their coke "kitty." Other clubs and individuals have sent gowns and various baby items, something that is always needed. Arrow Craft The showcase of Pi Beta Phi in Gatlinburg is our lovely Arrowcraft Shop. We are all proud of the artistic building in its beautiful setting where the finest of mountain crafts are attractively displayed for sale. Through the welcoming doorway come many of our own members from distant states and far away places. Some of these are the Settlement School Chair-men for their Alumnae Clubs who come to select items for their sales. They are always pleased to see behind the scenes the shipping room, the looms and thread </p>
      <pb ref="arr7110055_0004" seq="04" n="60-61  "/>
       <p>60 THE ARROW OF P1 BETA PHI supplies, Tina's office, and the warping bars. Others come to look and to purchase a special gift for some Pi Phi relative or friend, a gift that will have added significance since it came from "our shop." Perhaps a group from some foreign country, making an inspection trip to T.V.A. and the University of Tennessee, will arrive and want to see good American crafts and learn of our methods in helping the mountain people who have long produced for the shop. Gatlinburg entertains many celebrities who come to the Park and they usually visit our shop. Last spring, John D. Rockefeller Jr. and his wife spent a week in town. They were good customers who bought among other things, seven of our lovely afghans for gifts. The Fraternity may be justly proud of the work that they have done during the years in bringing the Arrow Craft Shop to its present high rating as an outstanding Craft outlet. As an old Turkish proverb says, "With patience, mulberry leaves become satin." Workshop A very congenial group made up the faculty and student body at the 10th Summer Workshop in Crafts. Miss Marian Heard, the Director, has the happy faculty of inspiring students to do their best. She is largely responsible for the kindly spirit of co-operation and friendliness so noticeable in the group. Those of us who know her best and have worked with her in the Workshop were delighted to have her wear the Arrow for she has always expressed the best of Pi Phi ideals and has been loyal and helpful in our Craft program. The students and faculty were pleased about Miss Heard's initiation also. Though they arrive as strangers they are loth to leave their new friends when the sessions close. The meals served in the Staff House dining room, the trips in the area to other Craft centers and picnics in the mountains provide the necessary recreational breaks in the intensive work schedules. This year we had eight Pi Phis in the group. One of these, Nancy Jones, California Zeta active, was here on a scholarship provided by the Los Angeles Area Alumnae Clubs. It is truly amazing to see the beautiful displays of the work accomplished that are shown at the two Open House evenings. Each year they seem better than the ones the years before. Permanent Improvements and Some Special Gifts The gay pieces of glass assume many shapes and forms as I think of the new storage shed that was built to hold the Workshop materials, the new front windows at the Arts and Craft building, the flag-stone walk that goes from Staff House to the street, and widened and graveled road that leads in to the back of the house. Inside there are other improvements. The lovely piano gives the lounge the finishing touch and brings much enjoyment to us. Green slat blinds keep the afternoon sun from the porch and the installation of two fans and added insulation in the attic makes the upstairs rooms more comfortable. In the upstairs hall we have a telephone table and bench that were gifts of Edith Rankin in memory of two Pi Phi nieces. The Pasadena Alumnae Club sent a lovely silver tray that we use when we entertain. We were remembered at Christmas time by other timely gifts. The Chicago Business Women's Alumna Club sent subscriptions to Holiday and Time magazines to the Staff House while other clubs and chapters sent us gifts of sweets and seasonal decorative items. The usual gift boxes for the children brought joy to the students in the three rural schools that our nurse visits regularly, the little tots in our lower grades, and needy children in the area. Gifts of money from Clubs and Chapters made possible atreat of oranges for the rural schools, everyone who attended the big Christmas program and some extras for our Dormitory girls and boys. The Pittsburgh Alumni Club again sent a check which was spent for records. The library received a number of memorial books and a valuable recording from Mrs. Marc Bisosway, entitled "This is America." The parting gift of the Senior Class was a new radio-phonograph combination that will be useful through the school. The men who work here think that the best improvement of all has been the new Dodge truck that replaced our very much worn out old model. Conclusion just as the internal parts of the kaleidoscope are constantly changing, the work at the Settlement School changes, though always bearing in mind the idea of service. I want to express my grateful appreciation to Grand Council and Committee members with whom it has been a pleasure to work, to Joni Newcomer, my assistant, and now to Nancy Jo Hayes who is taking over Joni's work so well. The local staff have evidenced a faithfulness and helpfulness that I have always appreciated and will long remember. I am confident that with Marion Mueller at the head, they will carry on and the Settlement School project go on to bigger and better things. Respectfully submitted, RUTH DYER, Director Settlement School Committee Pi Beta Phi Settlement School Mrs. Thomas E. Graham, Treasurer Oklahoma City, Oklahoma DEAR LADIES: We have audited the books, records, and supporting data of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, May 31, 1954, and present this summarized report for use in publication to the general member-ship: Exhibit A Balance Sheet Exhibit B Statement of Operations Exhibit C Endowment Fund Exhibit D--Sinking Fund and Memorial Fund Schedule 1 Summary of Contributions Received Schedule 2 Statement of Club and Chapter Con tributions Exhibit A Arrowcraft Statement of Profit and Loss SCOPE OF AUDIT Our examination embraced comprehensive and complete verification of all assets by independent means. Cash on hand was counted, cash in banks was con-firmed by correspondence with the depositories, all receivables were confirmed by communication with the debtors, inventories were viewed in location and inventory valuations and computations thoroughly tested. Securities were verified by direct communication with the Trust Agents. All operating income and expenditures of the Treasurer were examined in detail and Arrowcraft transactions were exhaustively tested with-out a detailed audit of all transactions. CERTIFICATE In our opinion, the financial position of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School as of May 31, 1954 is properly set forth in the accompanying Exhibit A and the sup-porting Exhibits and Schedules. Little Rock, Arkansas July 26, 1954 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI 61 COMMENTS We wish to commend your committee for the high degree of diligence exercised in your fiscal operations and for the general excellence of your accounting forfunds entrusted to your care. Very truly yours, JOHN W. DORNBLASER, Certified Public Accountant Member American Institute of Accountants PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL GATLLNBURG, TENNESSEE COMPARATIVE BALANCE SHEET MAY 31, 1954 EXHIBIT A 6-30-1953 5-31-1954 ASSETS Current Assets: Cash Funds: Imprest Cash Funds $ 60.00 Treasurer's Bank Balance 28,482.33 Operating Bank Balance 8,398.69 Savings Account Balances 546.70 Total Cash Funds $ 37,487.72 Investments: Endowment Fund Securities $ 60,172.50 General and Sinking Fund Securities 23,970.26 Uninvested Cash-Endowment Fund 1,905.92 Inventories: Arrowcraft Merchandise and Materials $ 84,143.55 TOTAL CURRENT ASSETS $220,182.12LIABILITIES Current Liabilities: Withheld Income Taxes $ 319.50 $ 387.20 Social Security Taxes Payable ... 43.24 89.45 Other Payables 215.57 104.56 Endowment Fund: Created by Annually Setting Aside 75% of Active Chapter Contri butions 62,078.42 63,743.53 $ 61,827.50 Sinking Fund: Special Reserve for Additions to 26,820.26 Buildings and Equipment . . .. 6,000.00 9,000.00 1,916.03 Memorial Fund: Special Reserve Contributed for Purchase of Music Supplies 892.29 985.29 TOTAL LIABILITIES AND RE SERVES $ 69,549.02 $ 74,310.03 General Fund Surplus: 314,629.81 301,859.75 Analysis of General Fund Surplus: $ 65,752.12 Balance July 1, 1953 $314,629.81 Add: Workshop Balance Set up on Books 106.31 Accounts Receivable: Due from Arrowcraft Customers $ 12,502.17 6-30-1953 5-31-1954 $ 210.00 27,476.17 17,250.96 5,582.93 $ 50,520.06 $ 578.31 $ 581.21 $ 86,048.68 $ 90,563.79 $ 8,537.75 $215,373.72 Fixed Assets: Real Estate $ 5,427.35 $ 5,427.35 Buildings and Improvements 189,061.04 189,061.04 Equipment, Fixtures, Autos 40,827.30 42,450.87 $235,315.69 $236,939.26 Less: Depreciation Reserve 73,627.47 78,909.78 TOTAL FIXED ASSETS-NET VALUE $161,688.22 $158,029.48 Other Assets: Prepaid Insurance Premiums ..2,308.49 $ 2,662.01 Taxes Paid in Advance 104.57 $ 2,308.49 $ 2,766.58 TOTAL ASSETS $384,178.83 $376,169.78 Total $314,736.12 Deduct: Operating Deficit to 5-31-54 ..$ 8,118.26 Transfer to Sinking Fund 3,000.00 Transfer to En Endowment Fund 1,665.11 Transfer to Memorial Fund 93.00 12,876.37 Balance May 31, 1954 $301,859.75 TOTAL LIABILITIES, RESERVES AND GENERAL SURPLUS ...$384,178.83 $376,169.78 Patronize your ARROW CRAFT Shop! Gatlinburg, Tennessee </p>
      <pb ref="arr7110055_0005" seq="05" n="62-63  "/>
       <p>THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI EXHIBIT B Year Ended 6-30-1953 COMPARATIVE STATEMENT OF OPERATIONS May 31, 1954 11' Months Farm Other Income 84.90 148.20 5-31-1954 Laundry 6.00 _ House Student Fees 395.70 337.00 Staff Fees 4,674.20 4,519.00 Guest Fees 3.50 8.65 Gifts, Refunds, Sundry 627.39 947.92 TOTAL SCHOOL $ 16,570.27 $ 17,372.47 TOTAL INCOME $ 70,304.85 $ 55,012.55 Expense: General and Administrative Exhibit B-1 $ 8,606.54 Instructional Exhibit B-2 17,909.96 Operational Exhibit B-3 21,710.99 Summer Session Prior Year 8,376.45 Current Year Advances 2,085.53 Provision for Depreciation 6,781.16 6,608.31 $ 9,803.05 17,509.98 19,661.74 9,547.73 ,e General: 1tributions Alumnx Clubs $ 8,229.33 $ i.lumnx Clubs Staff House 2,069.00 Oumnx Clubs Piano .ctive Chapters 2,118.58 ndividual and Bequests 8.00 ndividual Staff House 758.64 Aernorial 62.85 !rest on Investments 1,491.66 gazine Agency 7,532.10 )k Book Sales 215.90 ditorium Rent 825.00 rowcraft Net Profit 27,227.36 fit on Sales of Bonds 3,164.16 scellaneous 32.00 e of Right of Way TOTAL GENERAL $ 53,734.58 $ 37,640.08 ue School: lamer Session Prior Year $ 7,073.93 $ 9,030.99 'spital Revenue 159.03 209.78 rm Produce Sales Outside . 2,750.31 2,170.93 rm Produce Sales Internal 795.31 TOTAL EXPENSE $ 65,470.63 $ 63,130.81 NET INCOME OR (DEFICIT) $ 4,834.22 ($ 8,118.26) 7,611.46 1,327.00 560.58 2,220.15 2,044.70 442.96 93.00 2,183.35 10,276.36 430.50 962.00 7,988.02 1,500.00 ENDOWMENT FUND . May 31, 1954 wment Fund, June 30, 1953: $ 62,078.42 Earnings Remitted to Settlement vestments $ 60,172.50 School Treasurer 1,251.20 linvested Cash 1,905.92 BALANCE, ENDOWMENT FUND, MAY 31, 1954 nits: Represented by: terest on Investments . ..$ 1,577.95 % Actual Chapter Contribu Investments Schedule 1 $ 61,827.50 tions 5-31-1954 1,665.11 3,243.06 Uninvested Cash: $ 65,321.48 Harris Trust Co 250.92 Pi Beta Phi Grand Treasurer .. 1,665.11 ursements: 1.lst Agent's Fee and Expense ..$ 304.80 $ 63,743.53 rchase of Accrued Interest .... 21,95 EXHIBIT D SINKING AND MEMORIAL FUNDS Sinking Fund Memorial Fund rice, June 30, 1953 $ 6,000.00 Balance, June 30, 1953 $ 892.29 ed by Committee Action 3,000.00 Contributions Specified for Memorial Fund 93.00 rice, may 31, 1954 $ 9,000.00 Balance, May 31, 1954 $ 985.29 SCHEDULE 1 SUMMARY OF CONTRIBUTIONS May 31, 1954 7; no. Clubs: Regular 1pha East $ 112.50 1pha West 441.25 !ta 1,145.00 amma 190.50 elta 629.50 asilon 1,578.21 sta 210.50 a 718.00 beta 151.00 591.00 apps 757.50 smbda 559.50 .0 527.00 Ldividuals TOTAL CLUBS $ 7,611.46 EXHIBIT C 1,577.95 $ 63,743.53 Staff House Piano $ $ 7.00 7.79 25.00 32.29 11.89 580.00 54.40 5.23 17.19 187.00 45.76 35.00 23.08 20.97 160.00 31.49 130.00 29.55 210.00 34.96 442.96 $ 1,769.96 321.60 Staff Active Chapters: Regular House Piano Alpha E=t $ 79.25 Alpha West 90.00 Beta 3.90.40 Gamma 50.00 Delta 155.00 Epsilon 4 5 . 0 0 265.00 Zeta Eta 281.00 Theta 55.00 Iota Kappa 300.00 415.00 = ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 104.50 Mu 190.00 TOTAL CHAPTERS v 2,220.15 TOTAL CLUBS AND CHAPTERS .' ' " . ' ' ' " . " . " .' " .' ' ' " . ' ' ' ' ' " . ' . ' ' ' ' ' w9,831.61 $ 1,769.96 ====' ==== SCHEDULE 2 STATEMENT OF CLUB AND CHAPTER CONTRIBUTIONS May 31, 1954 238.98 560.58 ALPHA-EAST Staff Regular House Piano Boston, Mass. . " o 20o0 Burlington, Vt 2.50 Hartford, Conn 25u0 Montreal, Que 20.00 New Haven, Conn 35.00 Portland, Me. "~"."." .~~~~~~~ ~G Eastern ~~~~ ~~~'~~~~~~ 2.00 Albany, N.Y ~ 25.00 Buffalo, N.Y 50.00 Poughkeepsie, N.Y 10o0 Syracuse, N.Y 10o0 Westchester County, N.Y 20.00 Long Island N.Y.C. Long Island North Shore 5.00 Regular $ Maine A .'.." '. $ 10.00 $ 1.00 Nova Scotia A ~ 2.00 Vermont A .0o 4.50 Connecticut A 15.00 2.00 Massachusetts B 19.25 .50 Vermont B 20.0 Piano $ 79.25 $ 3.00 ALPHA WEST $ 1.06 6.73 New York r $ 30.00 $ 5.00 New York ' ' 20.00 3.20 Ontario A 20.00 $ 1.94 Pennsylvania B $ 38.40 $ 1.55 Pennsylvania 10.00 5.00 Ohio A Ohio B 42.00 2.70 25.00 10.00 Ohio A 10.00 5.00 10.00 West Virginia A 50n0 2.10 Ohio E 10.00 2.50 Ohio Z ~.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 5.00 5.00 Pennsylvania $1,145.00 $ 25.00 $ 32.29 $ 190.40 $ 33.85 Akron, Ohio "."."."o 55.00 Athens, Ohio 5.00 Central '; Pennsylvania 15.00 ''eharleston, W.Va 25.00 7Cifijitnati, Ohio 50.00 'Cleidland (East), Ohio 250,00 *CIfteland (West), Ohio 10.00 Colurnbus, Ohio 100.00 Dayton, Ohio 25.00 South Hills Pittsburgh, Pa 25.00 Springfield, Ohio 5.00 Toledo, Ohio 100u0 Arlington Alexandria $ 5.00 Columbia, S.C 2.00 .. . Richmond, 25x0 Washington, D.C. Norfolk, Va.. ".".".".".' '~G Washington, D.C., ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ ~00 Chapel Hill, N.C ' ' . 10.00 Maryland A $ $ 2.00 North Carolina B 5.00 $ 1.00 3.00 North Carolina A Virginia r 10.00 2.30 e.89 Virginia A 25.00 8.06 District of Columbia A 10.00 _ 50.00 11.36 </p>
      <pb ref="arr7110055_0006" seq="06" n="64-65  "/>
       <p>64 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI Alumna) Active DELTA Ann Arbor, Mich $ 10.00 Bloomfield Hills, Mich 35.00 Bloomington, Ind 25.00 Columbus, Ind 4.50 Detroit, Mich 82.00 285.00 Fort Wayne, Ind 10.00 Franklin, Incl 30.00 135.00 Gary, Ind 15.00 Grand Rapids, Mich 5.00 Indianapolis, Ind 210.00 130.00 12.35 Lafayette, Ind 50.00 1.50 Lansing East Lansing, Mich 1.00 Richmond, Ind 5.00 Southwestern Indiana 50.00 Southwestern Michigan 5.00 Jackson, Mich 2.00 30.00 1.00 Southwestern Indiana 50.00 4.35 South Bend Mishawaka, Ind 30.00 2.60 Hammond, Ind 5.00 Muncie, Ind 3.00 Terre Haute, Ind 2.00 $ 629.50 $ 580.00 $ 54.40 $ 155.00 24.05 $ 2.25 Michigan A $ 1.00 Michigan B Indiana A Indiana B 9.46 Indiana r 5.00 Indiana A 3.86 Indiana E 5.00 Michigan r Indiana Z 25.00 $ 20.00 10.00 50.00 10.00 10.00 5.00 10.00 15.00 7.75 1.25 3.15 1.33 3.00 4.57 3.00 1.77 4.26 Chattanooga, Tenn $ 15.00 Columbia, Mo 52.54 Kansas City, Mo 363.67 Little Pigeon, Knoxville, Tenn 5.00 Louisville, Ky 50.00 Memphis, Tenn 20.00 Nashville, Tenn 20.00 St. Louis, Mo 1,000.00 Springfield, Mo 15.00 Tri-State Joplin 5.00 Blue Ridge, Tenn 30.00 Lexington, Ky 2.00 EPSILON $ Missouri A $ 60.00 Missouri B 12'5.00 3.02 Missouri r 5.00 6.47 Tennessee A 10.00 1.00 Tennessee B 30.00 Tennessee r 15.00 5.00 Kentucky A 20.00 3.08 2.21 $1,578.21 Atlanta, Ga $ 35.00 Birmingham, Ala 10.00 De Land, Fla 25.00 Miami Coral Gables, Fla 25.00 Jacksonville, Fla 20.00 Orlando, Fla 35.00 St. Petersburg, Fla 20.00 Tampa, Fla 5.00 Tallahassee, Fla 5.00 Pensacola, Fla 25.00 Athens, Ga 2.50 Columbus, Ga 1.00 Lakeland, Flit 2.00 $ 210.50 5.23 ZETA $ 7.00 1.06 1.40 2.18 2.00 3.55 17.19$ 265.00 $ 15.55 Alabama A $ 10.00 $ Florida B 10.00 Florida r 10.00 5.00 Georgia A 5.00 Alabama B 10.00 10.00 45.00 15.00 ETA Avon, Ill $ 10.00 $ Beloit, Wis 25.00 Champaign-Urbana, Ill 100.00 100.00 Chicago Business Women 5.00 Chicago North 15.00 Chicago South 100.00 5.00 Chicago West Suburban 25.00 Decatur, Ill 5.00 Depage County Nina Harris Allen 5.00 Fox River Valley, Wis 10.00 Illinois Fox River Valley 5.00 10.00 5.00 Galesburg, Ill 10.00 3.63 Jacksonville, Ill 10.00 50.00 .57 Joliet, Ill 5.00 2.00 Madison, Wis 25.00 10.00 Milwaukee, Wis 150.00 11.28 Monmouth, Ill 3.00 2.00 North Shore, Ill 35.00 7.06 North Shore, Ill., Jr 5.00 3.00 Oak Park-River Forest, Ill 50.00 2.00 Peoria. Ill 25.00 3.10 Rockford, Ill 15.00 Springfield, 111 30.00 '10.00 Arlington Heights, Ill 50.00 $ 718.00 $ 187.00 $ 45.76 $ 281.00 27.10 $ 1.00 Wisconsin A $ 5.00 $ 5.00 Wisconsin B 50.00 4.15 3.00 Wisconsin r 25.00 Illinois B-A 25.00 1.55 Illinois E 10.00 9.00 Illinois Z 56.00 3.00 2.25 Illinois H 10.00 Illinois 25.00 4.40 1.87 Illinois A 30.00 THE ARROW OF n BETA PHI 65 Ames, Iowa $ 25.00 Burlington, Iowa 3.00 Council Bluffs, Iowa Cedar Rapids, Iowa 50.00 Des Moines, Iowa 15,0 Duluth Superior Indianola, Iowa 5.00 Mt. Pleasant, Iowa Iowa City, Iowa 5.00 ~ 10.00 Sioux City, Iowa ... Minneapolis Afternoon 10.00 Winnipeg, Canada 2.00 THETA $ 25.00 $ 1.11 $ 5.00 $ 2.00 Iowa I' 10.00 e.10 10.00 2.90 Iowa Z 10.00 2.00 Manitoba A ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 10.00 2.50 4.95 NoMinnesota A rth Dakota A 105.00 .00 3.00 Iowa B 5/00 5.00 2.10 4.52 ' $ 151x00 $ 35z0 ~ 23.08 Boulder, Colo $ 20.00 25.00 Cheyenne, Wyo. Colorado Springs, Colo. .~~~~~~~~~~ 25~00 Denver, Colo 152.0o Denver, Colo., Jr. Fort Collins, Colo 5.00 Hutchinson, Kan 75u0 Kansas City, Kan ' 20.00 Laramie, Wyo. ''-'''''''''' 5.00 Lawrence, Kan. .. . 25.00 Lincoln, Neb. . .. 30.00 Manhattan, Kan 65.00 Northeastern Wyo 5.00 Ogden, Utah 5.00 Omaha, Neb 50.00 Sioux Falls, S.D. 3.00 Pueblo, Colo 15.00 Salt Lake City, Utah 10.00 Vermillion, S.D. Wichita, Kan. ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ u~~ . 0 Falls City, Neb 1.00 IOTA 1.00 4.18 2.43 1.45 $ 55.00 13.10 Colorado A.." '. 50.00 $ 8.00 Colorado B 50.00 Kansas A "."."."." 20.00 7.00 Kansas B 75.00 Nebraska B 75z0 2.23 wyommmA ' . .. ' . 5.00 $ 300.00 $ 19..72 _ KAPPA Ardniore, Oklahoma o 10.00 $ Austin, Texas 50.00 15.00 Baton Rouge, Louisiana 5.00 Corpus Christi, Texas 50.00 Dallas, Texas ' ' " .' ' '. ' " 40.00 15.00 Fort Smith, Arkansas Fayetteville, Arkansas 10 5.00 Little Rock, Arkansas 15.00 Houston, Texas 150.00 15.00 10.00 Muskogee, Oklahoma ' '.. ' 5.00 1.00 New Orleans, Louisiana 35.00 Nita Stark Beaumont, Texas 100.00 15.00 Norman, Oklahoma Oklahoma City, Oklahoma 1010.00 0.00 15.00 6.45 Shreveport, Louisiana 10.00 15o0 Stillwater, Oklahoma .. . "."." 20.00 15.00 Texarkana, Texas-Arkansas ~~~~~~~~ 20.000 15.00 Tulsa, Oklahoma Wichita Falls, Texas 25.00 15.00 Bartlesville, Oklahoma 5.00 Brazos Valley, Texas . ' ' ' ' ' . ' 10.00 lake Charles, Louisiana 10.00 Midland, Texas 5.00 Paul's Valley, Oklahoma 5.00 Lubbock, Texas 5.00 McAlester, Oklahoma ~~~~~~~~~~~~ 10.00 5x0 Osceola, Arkansas "."." 5.00 5.00 5.00 Marked _._ Arkansas Texas A $ 100.00 $ Louisiana B " . '~ ' ' ' ' ' "." . ' ' 520.00 0.00 ~~x~ B ~=~~~~..~~~.~~~~~~~~~~~~ 20.00 6.04 Louisiana A 75/0 Oklahoma A 50.00 10.00 Oklahoma B 25^00 3.35 Texas r rn/m 1.74 $ 415.00 $ 15.09 </p>
      <pb ref="arr7110055_0007" seq="07" n="66-67  "/>
       <p>66 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI Alumna, Boise, Idaho $ 50.00 $ Bozeman, Montana 5.00 Butte-Anaconda, Montana 5.00 Calgary, Alberta 2.00 Corvallis, Oregon 2.50 Edmonton, Alberta 10.00 Eugene, Oregon 5.00 Everett, Washington 75.00 30.00 Portland, Oregon 100.00 Salem, Oregon 50.00 1.25 Spokane, Washington 25.00 3.25 Tacoma, Washington 75.00 2.44 Wenatchee, Washington 45.00 5.00 Yakima, Washington 10.00 Seattle, Washington 50.00 100.00 5.00 Medford, Oregon 25.00 Coos County, Oregon 5.00 Vancouver, B.C 10.00 Walla Walla, Washington 10.00 $ 559.50 130.00 $ 29.55 Mu Albuquerque, New. Mexico $ 5.00 $ $ Bakersfield, California 5.00 Berkeley, California 50.00 El Paso, Texas 5.00 1.00 Glendale, California 25.00 Long Beach, California 15.00 1.00 Los Angeles, California 38.00 210.00 Las Vegas, Nevada 1.00 1.00 Marin County, California 15.00 1.30 Reno, Nevada 12.00 Palo Alto, California 20.00 Pasadena, California 5.00 Phoenix, Arizona 5.00 3.57 San Diego, California 50.00 3.34 San Francisco, California 75.00 San Fernando, California 25.00 San Jose, California 35.00 San Mateo County, California 10.00 Santa Barbara-Ventura, California 10.00 5.00 San Bernardino, California 5.00 10.00 Santa Monica-Westwood, California 25.00 South Coast, California 20.00 5.00 Tucson, Arizona 5.00 Contra Costa, California 10.00 Centinela Valley, California 5.00 Roswell, New Mexico 5.00 Fresno, California 10.00 Honolulu, T.H: 5.00 Sacramento, California 20.00 Solano County, California 1.00 Santa Rosa-Valley of the Moon .. 10,00 $ 527.00 $ 210.00 $ 34.96Active $ 104.50 $ 23.50 Arizona A $ 25.00 $ 5.00 California B 20.00 California A 20.00 3.25 California r 100.00 8.00 Nevada A 10.00 3.00 California E 5.00 5.21 California Z 10.00 5.00 $ 190.00 29.46 3.75 Alberta A $ 2.00 $ 2.50 3.00 Idaho A S.00 Montana A 50.00 1.16 Oregon A 10.00 Oregon B 5.00 Washington B 15.00 2.00 Oregon r 10.00 6.45 Washington r 7.50 LAMBDA $ 8.00 5.00 7.00 1.00 ~ Can You Help? The Settlement School Committee needs a new manager for Arrow Craft, to fill the vacancy that will occur when Marian Mueller assumes the Directorship of the School. Do you know the right person? Also do you know Pi Phis who could become teachers at the Settlement School ? If so, please write to Mrs. Virginia Brackett Green, 2650 Sutherland Avenue, Indianapolis 5, Indiana. THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI 67 EXHIBIT A ARROWCRAFT SHOP STATEMENT OF PROFIT AND LOSS FISCAL YEAR ENDED MAY 31, 1954 Fiscal Year Amount Sales $145,304.43 Gross Profit-Wholesale $ 74,485.07 Add Supply Sales Profit ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' 226.82 $ 74,711.89 Commissions Allowed ' " . ' ' ' 27,697.10 Realized Gross Profit ' '..".".".".".".".".".'o 47,014.79 Expense: Salaries-Manager _ 3,169.00 Designing 4,451.54 Selling 4,867.31 Office 2,435.12 Utility 652.62 Selling and Shipping Supplies 802.63 Convention and Travel 134.65 Fuel 278.83 Lights 193.21 Miscellaneous 269.04 Car Expense 113.07 307.06 Office Expense .. . . 247.66 304.89 Maintenance 542.13 Telephone Transportation '~~~~~~~~~'~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 3593.24 4.38 Water . . ' ' ' ' " . ' ' ' " . ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' 30.48 Insurance, _ Insurance, Current Year _ TOTAL EXPENSE $ 19,246.86 Other Income: Less Expense: Rent 240.00 Salary .. . .' 1,315x0 Hotel Shop Net Profit $ 743.52 Purchase Discount 361.49 Savings Account-Interest 65.32 Sundry 15.27 TOTAL OTHER INCOME $ 1,185.60 NET INCOME $5-31-53 Fiscal Year % Amount 100.00% $132,734.69 100.00% $ 12,569.7 48.74 79,669.04 60.02 8,849.68 51.26% $ 53,065.65 $ 21,419.42 .16 53.75 .04 173.07 51.42% 53,119.40 40u2% 21,592.49 19.06 25,163.39 18.96 2,533.71 32.36% $ 27,956.01 21.06% $ 19,058.78 $ 3,480.96 $ 311.96 3.07 4,620.46 3.48 168.92 3.35 5,761.38 4.34 894.07 1.68 2,306.52 1.74 128.60 .45 650.04 .49 2.58 .55 1,063.62 .80 260.99 __ __ 134.65 .09 .19 267.50 .20 11.33 .13 161.13 .12 32.08 .19 371.33 .28 102.29 .08 105.05 .08 8.02 .21 277.94 .21 29.12 .17 163.76 .12 83.90 .21 142.35 .11 162.54 .37 21238 '16 329.75 .07 97.31 .07 4.07 .24 369.27 .28 14.89 .02 33.21 .02 2.73 1,000.00 1,000.00 1,000.00 .76 .76 1,000.00 13.25% $ 22,084.21 16.64% $ 2~37.35 $ 59.86 240.00 1,320.00 5.00 .51% ~ 678.66 .51m $ 64.86 .25 211.49 .16 150.00 .05 36.23 .03 29.09 .01 30.60 .02 15.33 ___ -82% $ 956.98 -72% $ 228.62 19.93% $ 6,828.78 5.'14% $ 22,124.75 ----------' 28,953.53 ---- 5-31-54 Increase % Decrease PRIVILEGE ==-RESPONSIBILITY Privilege never comes cheaply. The privilege of citizenship and of casting one's vote in a free election is no exception. Taking part in the democratic processes of government is too precious a prerogative to be exercised lightly. It is a duty which should be performed thoughtfully. The lever on the voting machine should not necessarily be pulled just because one's parentsor friends support a given party and its plat form ; the vote should be cast out of conviction for the rightness of the action. The price then for the privilege of the voting franchise is responsibility-responsibility for being an in-formed voter or responsibility for taking the consequences of irresponsible action. From release of Citizenship Committee N.P.C. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



