<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr7530199_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Finger, Lois Snyder</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Spring 1959</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr7530199_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1959</date>, News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Finger, Lois Snyder</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 198-201</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">40</note>
                        <note type="Folder">11</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 75, Number 3 (Spring 1959), Pages 198-201.</note>
			<note type="document">arr7530199_0000</note>


	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Changing Mission of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity for Women in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1944-1964</item>
                                <item>Summer crafts workshop</item>
                                <item>Education </item>
                                <item>Healthcare</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr7530199_0001" seq="01" n="198-199  "/>
       <p>THE UNIVERSITY OF TENNESSEE PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL, GATLINBURG, TENNESSEE Expenses Tuition: Full session $75.00. Half session $37.50. Room: Full session $24.00, $40.00, $48.00. Half session $12.00, $20.00, $24.00. Board: Full session $90.00. Half session $45.00. Ida A. Anders, Acting Dean of College of Home Economics, The University of Tennessee, and Marjorie Chalmers, RN, Resident Nurse, Pi Beta Phi Settlement School. Faculty Barbara McDonald, B.S., Artist-Craftsman of McDonald Ceramics, Gatlinburg. Pottery. Helen Worrall, Instructor of Enameling, Cincinnati Art Museum, with Kenneth Bates. Berta Frey, well known weaving instructor. C. Jane Glass, B.S., M.A., fornier college instructor, Artist-Craftsman of the Jane Glass Studio, Gatlinburg. Jewelry. Jean Hemphill, Textile and Craft Design. Marian G. Heard, B.S., M.A., Director of the Summer Craft Workshop. Professor of Craft Design, The University of Tennessee, Conductor of two Pi Beta Phi, University of Tennessee Foreign Craft Study Tours (European and Scandinavian Countries). Pi Phis and your friends come to the Workshop in Gatlinburg; work and study with craftsmen from various parts of our country; visit mountain craftsmen in their homes; earn credit in The University of Tennessee; take advantage of the "need" tax ruling which allows income tax deductions for expenditures made for education undertaken primarily for the maintaining or the improving of skills required in the individual's employment, trade or business. You will gain knowledge, new friends, pleasure all available in a well organized Summer Craft School valuable to the hobbyist and to the amateur artist as well as to the advanced artisan, to the teacher, to those wishing training in community service (for Red Cross, Scouts, and other youth organizations), and to workers in an important new field those who use the very latest therapy for treating the mentally ill by teaching ceramics and other crafts to mental patients. Come to Gatlinburg combine your vacation and your hobby at the Summer Craft Workshop! For brochure and further information write to SUMMER CRAFT WORKSHOP, PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL GATLINBURG, TENNESSEE n. FROM LITTLE PIGEON Edited by Lois Snyder Finger, Iowa Z DEAR PI PHIS EVERYWHERE: Do you remember the parts of the Initiation Ceremony which pledged you to assist in the support of the Settlement School ? Because no Grand Council and no Convention has seen fit to remove that pledge, it would seem that the obligation remains, and the boundless challenge for service still is ours. During the 46 years of its existence this unique project has not stood still. It has kept faith with us by providing the Fraternity with an inspiring "togetherness" ; it has become an increasingly vital factor in the lives of the mountain people ; and it is expanding in the field of Arts and Crafts until it is recognized, internationally, as an important crafts center which is contributing to American culture. The Settlement School should not be thought of as a school, only. It has become more than a school. It is a project which contributes to the well-being of the mountain people in six different fields. First, in the Educational Field, through our moral and supervisory support of the county school, along with the hiring of and paying the salaries of three teachers an expense which the county cannot afford at this time those of Music, Arts and Crafts, and Woodworking. Tennessee schools rate very low in the nation, and Sevier county very low in the state, so there is need to supplement the meagre county curriculum. Pi Phi buildings are used by the county, and in addition, the Fraternity maintains and supervises two dormitories for pupils who live far out in the hills, one for girls and one for boys. Second, in the Health and Emotional Field, through the Health Center and our nurse, Marjorie Chalmers, 1958 Convention Initiate, who last year administered for Pi Beta Phi 4000 office calls, 500 field visits, 2200 vaccinations and inoculations, 3000 examinations, 1200 chest X rays, and 161 Health talks. This one phase of our efforts in Gatlinburg has repaid us many times. To have been instrumental in helping just one club-footed baby to take its normal place in life is reward enough! Third, Economically, through our Arrowcraft work, by helping the mountain people, whose articles we sell, to be self-supporting and self-respecting. You will be amazed and pleased to know that during the last five years we have paid to our weavers and crafts-men $276,556.24. What a force Pi Beta Phi is! Fourth, in the Social Field, by supervising in our dormitories, group living and character building both of which carry over into mountain home-life. Last year 17 children lived in the dormitories. These children pay $5.00 a month, plus after school chores, which, of course, does not begin to cover the cost of caring for them. So, with the help of your gifts Pi Phi underwrites a high school education for mountain children. For some, the training in dining room service and in gardening provide the basis for a future livelihood. Fifth, in the Community Field. To create good public relations and so to contribute to better community service several staff members participate in one or more community projects the Community Chest, Civil Defense, Scout Counseling, P.T.A., church committees, Garden Club vice-president, and Chamber of Commerce president. Sixth, in the Spiritual Field, for Pi Phi's influence of high ideals and unselfish action has made its impact upon the people of that whole area for 49 years. Our seventh field of endeavor is the joint project with the University of Tennessee the Summer Craft Workshop when we use our plant to further this fast growing national interest, and to create a center of instruction for craft-minded students and professional people. Here, students enroll for college credit; teachers, for professional training; civic volunteers and group leaders for help in serving youth centers and veterans; hobbyists and physiotherapists to create and to study; and some come just for the love of arts and crafts. They have enrolled from every state in the union and from many foreign countries. In impressive numbers, each year they come all learning to respect Pi Beta Phi, and all becoming an enthusiastic part of this fraternity project. With increased funds 199 </p>
      <pb ref="arr7530199_0002" seq="02" n="200-201  "/>
       <p>200 THE ARROW OF Pi BETA PHI and facilities what a thrilling and far-reaching service this phase of Pi Phi work could become! In the summer, too, the University of Tennessee and Pi Beta Phi set up and conduct a Foreign Craft Tour. Do you know that when you contribute to the Settlement School you do not contribute to Arrowcraft ? Settlement School contributions go to maintain the buildings and grounds ; to pay the salaries of our maintenance people, our teachers, and our staff and to support the Health Center. You contribute to Arrowcraft, and so to the welfare of the mountain people, when you buy and sell Arrowcraft articles. When you hold an Arrowcraft sale and contribute the net profits of that sale you are contributing to all of the work in Gatlin-burg. Present day Settlement School work becomes more thrilling to Pi Phis as they learn more about it. The "What and Where" of the Settlement School, including information about programs, colored slides, memorial gifts, and the form to be used for legacies is to be had from Settlement School Committee Chairman. Some facts and fallacies follow. 1. The Settlement School is not "on the wane." Its field of assistance and influence is growing. 2. The Settlement School does not receive "state aid." 3. The Settlement School is not self-supporting, unless you consider "self-supporting" to mean that we ourselves alone are the sole support of our work in Gatlinburg. No other group contributes to its support. 4. The purchasing power of the dollar which you contribute is the same in Gatlinburg as it is in your home town. 5. Pi Phi is not "through in Gatlinburg." The vision of 49 years ago is lengthening to far distant horizons. The challenge is there and growing ; the thrill of achievement A weaving class at a Summer Craft Workshop THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI 2O in service (one of the reasons for founding Pi Beta Phi) as well as the burden, rests with us. With best wishes to each one of you for continued enthusiasm and happiness in Pi Beta Phi service, I am Most sincerely, LOIS SNYDER FINGER Publicity Chairman Settlement School Committee SETTLEMENT SCHOOL INFORMATION WHAT AND WHERE FOR PROGRAMS 1. Colored slides and script. Settlement School Chairman, Slides Distribution. * 2. "It Could Happen." Files Available at Central Office. 3. "A Visit to the Settlement School," 1958 Fall mailing. Available at Central Office. 4. A Brief History of the Settlement School in question and answer form. New edition, Winter 1958. Arrowcraft Shop. 20 each. 5. Current prize winning chapter program. 1958 Fall mailing. Available at Central Office. 6. Past prize winning chapter programs. Files. 7. News From Little Pigeon. THE ARROW Winter, Spring and Summer editions. 8. Annual Reports of Settlement School Committee Chairman, Director of Settlement School., and Treasurer of Settlement School. Fall ARROW. 9. Manual for Settlement School Chairman. New edition, Fall, 1958. FOR PUBLICITY 1. Glossy prints for press use. Settlement School Committee Chairman of Publicity, Editor, Little Pigeon News.* 2. Publicity articles for press use. Same as above.* 3. Postcard invitations for Arrowcraft sales. Arrowcraft Shop. 2 each. 4. Poster for Arrowcraft sales. Arrowcraft Shop. 250 each. 5. Blue paper bags. for Arrowcraft sales, wine trade-mark; small, medium, large. $1.00 per hundred and up. Arrowcraft Shop. 6. Summer Craft Workshop folders. Director of Settlement School. Spring. 7. Foreign Study Craft Tour folders. Same as above. Spring. MISCELLANEOUS 1. Legal form for legacies. Settlement School Committee Chairman.* 2. Magazine price list. Director of Magazine Agency. Central Office. 3. Information about Memorial Gifts (instead of flowers). Settlement School Committee Chairman. * * Consult Fraternity Directory in current ARROW for name and address of this chairman. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



