<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr7720027_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Little Pigeon News</title>
                        <author><name>Dix, Helen Boucher</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Winter 1960</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr7720027_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1960</date>, Little Pigeon News</title>
                        <author><name>Dix, Helen Boucher</name></author>
                        <extent>Page 26</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">40</note>
                        <note type="Folder">13</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 77, Number 2 (Winter 1960), Page 26.</note>
			<note type="document">arr7720027_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Meet Nevada Christian; The Virginia Green Patio</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Changing Mission of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity for Women in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1944-1964</item>
                                <item>Staff</item>
                                <item>Facilities</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr7720027_0001" seq="01" n="26-27  "/>
       <p>Lti/Pigeon Edited by Helen Boucher Dix, Ohio B Meet eva flan The Settlement School 'Committee is happy to introduce the new Manager of Arrowcraft. Nevada Semenza Christian (Mrs. Sutton), Nevada A, who comes to us from Los Altos, California, has a very interesting background. As an under-graduate at the University of Nevada she was a member of Phi Kappa Phi and graduated as gold medalist of her class. Following additional study at Stanford University she was a high school teacher for a short time, but far horizons beckoned and she left San Bernadino, California, to travel to the Far East where she became a feature writer for the China Press in Shanghai, China. There she met and married Sutton Christian, who was a colleague on the newspaper staff. After the Sino-Japanese conflict, the Christians returned to the United States where, during World War II, Nevada Christian directed the Office of Public Information for Pacific Area Division of the American Red Cross in San Francisco, California. For several years she and her husband were co-publishers of a daily newspaper in Mountain View, California. Six years ago our energetic new Manager of Arrowcraft organized the United Fund of Los Altos, California, and directed its fund raising efforts for several years. Her merchandising experience began as she worked in her father's store before her graduation from college. Sutton Christian, Nevada's husband, is a retired newspaperman, a member of a pioneer Tennessee family, and his hobby is historical research. He has written several very interesting articles for The Gatlinburg Press; articles which reveal the back-ground and family history of some of the fine craftsmen of the 'Gatlinburg area. These craftsmen have been associated with the Settlement School either as suppliers or as instructors of crafts, or both. Mrs. Christian's interest in the arts and crafts has been manifest throughout their travels which have taken them to Denmark, Norway, Spain, Portugal, Italy, and Mexico, in addition to their experience in China. On June 1, 1960, Nevada Christian arrived to assume her new duties as Manager of Arrowcraft at Pi Beta Phi Settlement School. After barely two weeks in which to become oriented at the Arrow-craft Shop she left for the 1960 Convention at Hot Springs, Arkansas, where many Pi Phis met her in the Arrowcraft display room off the lobby of The Arlington Hotel. With the capable help of our Di-rector of Settlement School, Marion Mueller, and the Pi Phi actives and alumnae who served as sales-ladies, Nevada managed to survive the confusion and excitement of Convention week to return to Gatlin-burg and the relatively normal (?) activity of Arrowcraft. A short two weeks later the Settlement School Committee arrived at the Mountain View Hotel for its annual meeting of eleven days of concentrated work. Following this came the frenzied preparations for shipping the largest amount of weaving and crafts ever to be sent so early to the clubs for their fall sales. Having weathered this rather rugged introduction to her duties with poise and capable interest, we feel sure that Nevada Semanza 'Christian will be a valuable and delightful addition to the Staff of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, and to the Gatlinburg community. We know that the clubs and chapters will find her most cooperative and helpful in making their Arrowcraft Sales a success. We all join in welcoming the Sutton Christians to Gatlinburg and the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School. 5he Virginia Teen atio There now is a Virginia Brackett Green Patio to go with our Red Barn: Due to unexpected gifts last spring, the Settlement School Committee was able to proceed with the plans for the hoped-for patio. A rock facing ties in with the stone stairwell of the Barn and rock wall terraces retain the hillside on the opposite side. The flooring is of flagstones set in concrete and a red wooden fence screens the patio from the second floor bedroom windows, for the patio is midway between the first and second levels of The Red Barn. The remainder of the leveled patio area is grass with the picnic tables located here. Mrs. Green, immediate past !Chairman of the Settlement School Committee, and her daughter, Carolyn, were present for the dedication picnic held on July 26, 1960. The many friends and correspondents of Elizabeth Waitt Rue, former Arrowcraft Manager, will be happy to know that she is managing the Arrowcraft Shop in The Mountain View Hotel. She is President of The Gatlinburg Garden Club this year. 4-.3-+ 26 FROM Edited by Mary Elizabeth Lasher Barnette, Ohio A NELL EZELL THOMAS, Shoe String Debut, Dot-race and Co., 44 pp. This is a slim volume full of chuckles, and while it isn't billed as being autobiographical, it exudes authenticity. Parents, especially parents of daughters, should find it starting a chain of recollections of their own tragi-comic experiences with their off-spring. From the moment Mary Katherine's family of moderate means acceded to her desire for a debut, ingenuity and a sense of humor became the tools of survival. Chiefly because of this Mrs. Thomas is successful in making her point that there can be certain lasting values manufactured from the frivolous, so long as a sense of proportion prevails. AUTHOR INTEREST: Nell Ezell (Mrs. Theodore Gaillard) Thomas, Oklahoma Alpha, a native of Texas and resident of San Antonio, has held a variety of creative jobs, among them fashion co-ordinator and columnist of the Austin (Tex.) American-Statesman. Currently she is the decorator for her husband's building firm. They have two daughters as well. Roger Conant, Mercer's Belles, The Journal of a Reporter, edited by LENNA A. DEUTSCH, University of Washington Press, 190 pp. Even the efforts of such leaders as Pi Phi's Carrie Chapman Catt have not emancipated women from being considered slightly ridiculous when openly in pursuit of a husband. Imagine then the reaction in 1865 when Asa Mercer, president of the territorial university in Seattle, appeared in the East to organize a project of female emigration to the Pacific Northwest. Magazines and newspapers of the period exploited the humorous angles fully, and it must have taken real courage to become one of the now famous Mercer Girls. There was, however, some serious recognition of the need for such a project. In the Washington Territory there were very few women, even already married ones, and consequently a dearth of material for both wives and teachers. On the other hand, in the East the Civil War had left women in the majority. The New York Times supported Asa Mercer, and when the actual journey began, its reporter Roger Conant went along, and the stories he wrote were subsequently published in the paper. How-ever, he also kept a diary, and it remained in private possession until 1954 when Lenna Deutsch and her husband heard of it by chance. Conant's descendants were agreeable to its publication, and this volume, edited and supplemented by Mrs. Deutsch is the entertaining result. Others, including Mercer himself and Harriet Stevens, one of the "Girls," published their versions of the Continental's voyage with its marriageable 400, but Mrs. Deutsch believes the Conant diary adds historically valuable sidelights from an unprejudiced observer. Devotees of American history should find this providing a light-hearted interlude in the study of the subject, and residents of the Pacific Northwest should greatly appreciate this contribution to the records of their own heritage. AUTHOR INTEREST: Lenna A. (Mrs. Her-man J.) Deutsch is a graduate of Washington State University where she was a member of Washington Beta. 9+ The Southern Highland Handicraft Guild held a 'Craftsman's Fair in Gatlinburg October 18-22. Marion Mueller was again the Local Arrangements Chairman and Marjorie Chalmers and Gene Redding were both on committees. This Fair received a lengthy write-up in The New York Times of Sunday, October 16, 1960. Eighteen blankets were purchased for The Red Barn with trading stamps sent by clubs and individuals. Please send your Top Value or S and H Green Stamps directly to Marion Mueller, Director of Settlement School. Winogene Redding, Settlement School Weaving Designer, whose hip was fractured in a fall last January, is recuperating from an operation performed September 17 in Boston. 27 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



