<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr7340231_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Dobler, Louise Wheelock</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Summer 1957</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr7340231_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1957</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Dobler, Louise Wheelock</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 231-235</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">40</note>
                        <note type="Folder">9</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 73, Number 4 (Summer 1957), Pages 231-235.</note>
			<note type="document">arr7340231_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">New Pi Phi Cook Book Features Smoky Mountain Section; Summer Craft Workshop</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Changing Mission of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity for Women in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1944-1964</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>
                                <item>Food</item>
                                <item>People</item>
                                <item>Diet</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr7340231_0001" seq="01" n="230-231  "/>
       <p>Our flewe$1 Chapter STUDENT UNION BUILDING, ALABAMA POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE * ALABAMA GAMMA, the 103rd chapter of Pi Beta Phi, was installed February 2, 1957, at Alabama Polytechnic Institute. Alabama Polytechnic [nstitute, better known simply as Auburn, is located n Auburn, Alabama, which is fifty-nine miles east )f Montgomery, the capital of Alabama. Auburn, the Loveliest village of the plains, was founded as a land-grant college in 1857. It was made co-educational in 1892. Since that date a superb school of Home Ecoaomics has been established. Other excellent schools It Auburn are the schools of Engineering, Art, Busiaess Administration, and Science and Literature. The campus of Auburn is quite beautiful. In memorial to the centennial anniversary a pool was 'milt in Ross Square, a park in front of Ross Chemical Building. The fraternity houses are scattered aver the campus, but a new fraternity row is being milt in a lovely section of Auburn. The twelve women's dormitories, which house the eleven sororities' chapter rooms, are very modern and funand :ional. Some of the festivities held on Auburn's campus Ire the Homecoming Game and crowning of the Homecoming queen, the O. D. K. Beauty Ball, where the twenty beauty semi-finalists are presented Ind the eight finalists are selected, the selection of :he twenty favorites for the Glomerate the schoolannual in which they are featured, skit night in which the fraternities and sororities each present a skit, and the Sigma Chi Derby. Among the honors which an Auburn co-ed may receive are: member-ship in Mortar Board, Alpha Lambda Delta, Fresh-man Women's Honorary Society, Dolphin Club, the honorary club for accomplished swimmers, and many other honorary organizations. Alabama Gamma was very fortunate to have Faye Anthony transfer from Florida State University and come to Auburn to act as our president. Faye was Miss F. S. U. last year and not only is she a very beautiful girl but also smart and capable. Alabama Gamma had a lovely installation and initiation. We were honored to have Mrs. Wild, Mrs. Speaker, Mrs. Parks and Mrs. Smmers present for the occasion. One of the highlights of the installation weekend was the presentation of the trophy to the pledge with the best scholarship, Jan Bishop. Nancy Lou Avara was chosen as the best pledge. The presentations were made at the formal banquet following installation and initiation. Alabama Gamma's actives, pledges and initiated alumnae are working hard to make their chapter another shining example of the fraternity that they love so much. SANDRA VAUGHN Use Pi Beta phi Magazine Agency 230 n.6 FROM LITTLE PIGEON Edited by Louise Wheelock Dobter, Washinc NEW PI PHI COOK BOOK FEATURES SMOKY MOUNTAIN SECTION " THE SMOKY MOUNTAIN section will be an in teresting feature in the new Pi Beta Phi Cook Book which will be available through the Arrow-craft Shop this summer. In addition to the recipes requested from the 270 alumnae clubs and official fraternity family, the Smoky Mountain chapter will have contributions from the Settlement School staff, Pi Phi weavers and native craftsmen who sell their handcrafts to Arrowcraft plus tempting dishes from long-time Gatlinburg friends of the Settlement School. When asked to tell something about the recipes and the people who contributed them, Mar-ion Mueller, Director of Settlement School, sent the following comments. PAST AND REPAST! Our Smoky Mountain chapter in our new Pi Beta Phi Cook Book is not one for the calorie-conscious. Traditionally, the Smokies are a land of superlatives, the recipes being no exception. Recipes have been submitted for this chapter from all walks of life by natives as well as those who have adopted this land of high horizons. By necessity the old folks' diet was a simple one, made from sources at hand. Spicewood tea, poke `sallet', pumpkin butter, sweet `pertater' butter, wild grape preserves, sulphur-steamed apples, gooseberry pot pie are a few of the `ole' memories. Not-too-old folks remember drying beans, pumpkin, fruit, and beef. `Soghrun lasses boilin' is an annual event in these modern times. A recipe for Blackberry Dumplings was submitted by Mrs. Elmer Kear, wife of the Arrowcraft broom maker for over twenty-five years. Christmas 1956 Mr. Kear sent a handmade cane of his de-sign and two of his brooms to President Eisenhower. He proudly showed me the thank-you note signed by Dwight D. Eisenhower. Biscuits are a `must' for young and old. One teen-age girl recently said she liked at least five biscuits with gravy and two more with jelly for breakfast. A favorite lunch might be soup beans, a chunk of onion, cornpone, and a glass of buttermilk. Plain ole cabbage with a hunk of meat is still a favorite. A few old-timers enjoy a good possum dinner with sweet `pertaters' and perhaps Stack Pie. Mary L. Ownby, one of our first weavers at Arrowcraft whose lovely stoles are worn by many Pi Phis, gave us the Virginia Green, Settlement School Committee chairm Mary L. Ownby, one of Arrowcrafts first weavers. 1 pegs on her porch which she uses as her warping recipe for this dessert which still finds its wa] table for young and old. Nellie Cook, one Arrowcraft girls, has sent a Sweet Potato PI Teen-agers like to hunt as much as gran Recently I heard an impressive conversatio teen-age girl and boy on the best way to kill (bear hunting is restricted, of course !) . Squis rabbit hunting are popular, too. Mrs. Orlie Watson (you all know Orlie wife Josie who wove for Arrowcraft over five years) says Orlie's favorite pickle is d with any kind of meat. Wanda Ogle Watso of Neal about whom you read in the last makes one of Neal's choice dishes, an old fa! apple relish which is served instead of sala wife of Carl Huskey, our woodcraft instruct also makes the wooden bowls and luggag for Arrowcraft, tells us how they used t( spicewood tea and sweeten with pumpkin Edna Cook, remembered from the Miami Convention, includes a favorite. To really see the area, one must climb Conte. After this accomplishment, Mrs. Jac (Pauline Whaling, Illinois Alpha) will s( (Continued on page 235) 231 </p>
      <pb ref="arr7340231_0002" seq="02" n="232-233  "/>
       <p>+ ARE You interested in crafts? Well, what are you planning to do this summer? It would be worth your while to give consideration to the Pi Beta phi-University of Tennessee Summer Craft Workshop at the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, June 10 to July 13. Workshop is planned for those who want to learn just for fun as well as for those who must learn to make a livelihood, earn college credit, or assist in mental or physical re-habilitation. Quotes from Pi Phis: Workshop was all I could ask it to be We learned to know our teachers, each an excellent craftsman in his own right, not only in classes, but also as friends. The enthusiasm and interest everyone had in her work was an inspiration and challenge to me. There was a warm, friendly, informal atmosphere in the school. . . . Our field trips to the workshops in the area and to the homes of the mountain people where Arrowcraft products are made, gave me a better understanding and appreciation of the altruistic work of our fraternity. . . . My Tennessee summer was one of the finest vacations. It offered me a chance to see another beautiful section of our country, at the same time giving me a chance to work at crafts with interesting girls and women from other parts of the country and foreign countries. If you are interested write for a bulletin to Summer Craft Workshop, P1 Beta Phi-University of Tennessee, Gatlinburg, Tennessee. STAFF Kenneth F. Bates, B.S., Instructor Cleveland Institute of Arts; author of Enameling Principles and Practice. C. Jane Glass, B.S., M.A., Designer-Craftsman of the Jane Glass Studio. Marian G. Heard, B.S., M.A., Director of Craft Workshop, Professor of Craft Design, The University of Tennessee. Frances Jeff ress, B.S., Dietitian; Supervisor of School Lunchroom Program, Crossett, Arkansas. Barbara McDonald, B.S., Designer-Craftsman of McDonald Ceramics, Gatlinburg. Lula Smith, B.S., M.A., Associate Professor, University of Iowa; Co-author of Contemporary Handweaving. Jean B. Stange, B,S., A.M., Assistant Professor of Related Art, The University of Nebraska. Beverly Wood, Texas Gamma and Nancy Jones, California Zeta, are the P1 Phi Graduate Assistants. ACCOMMODATIONS At the School: Dormitory room accommodatlon (5 to 7 per room), $12.00 for each half session, $24.00 for full session. Double room, $18.00 for each half session, $36.00 for full session. Single room $22.00 for each half session, $44.00 for full session. TUITION: EXPENSES $75.00 for full session. $37.50 for the half session. Materials and class fees extra. BOARD: It is required that persons having room accommodations at the school shall board at the school dining room at session rates. Meals are also available for guests and for those living in cabins, privat homes and guest houses. $90.00 for full session; $45.00 for half session. Single meals: 50 breakfast; 95 lunch; $1.45 dinner. For full session $ 24.00 to $ 36.00 to $ 44.00 90.00 75.00 $189.00 to $201.00 to $209.00 The Heritage of the Past Is the Seed That Brings Forth the Harvest of he Future ..lnscription on pedestal under Female Figure, Constitution Avenue West, The National Arthives, Washington, D.C. Triangle of Sigma Sigma Sigma Strnrner Cra/t W0kh0 Total cost fr half session Room $12.00 to $ 18.00 to$ 22.00 Board Tuition ;1 . . . :: . 4I;0] 45.00 37.50 $94.50 to $100.50 to $104.50 -4 2 </p>
      <pb ref="arr7340231_0003" seq="03" n="234-235  "/>
       <p>ROM ted by Mary Elizabeth Lasher Barnette, Ohio A IONA WALKER, Kappy , Oliver, Henry Holt and apany, 256 pp. he category of literature written specifically for young teens is a neglected one, understandably for the latter is an audience hard to please and laps harder to understand, one which blends child and the adult in a constantly varying mix-. Hence it signifies a measure of courage that . Walker chose to beam her first novel to this o 16 age group, and the measure of her success ae effort is to be found in decidedly favorable .ws as in the New York Times which used such is as, "new twists, amusing characters, crisp )gue, authentic Southern flavor," and "agreeacomedy." Thile the underlying theme, the before-andtransformation idea, is not new, it is always guing, and Mrs. Walker has put it in up-to-date s with an assist from modern psychology. re's also a good helping of common sense and sh of Cinderella in the book to make it both lesome from the standpoint of the examples !ts, and romantic in its appeal to the youthful er. Then Kappy Oliver from Philadelphia under-to convert her belligerently unattractive cousin from a "take me as I am, or else" attitude .rd nearly everyone, there is wide scope for her nuity and ample opportunity for the humorous ,tion of which Mrs. Walker makes so much. girls meet for the first time when both are sent heir families to spend several months in the ry City, North Carolina, home of their mutual in Bessie Plum, and both find it the broadening rience attractive Kappy anticipated when she d her journey South, though neither expected lumber and variety of surprises which resulted. zyone who has known a Till, and that takes in ally everyone, and has thought, "if only I could ny hands on that girl just once," is fair game his book. Since even those persons of exceplly high calibre abstract intelligence cannot or work in a vacuum, it follows that social Ligence is every bit as important to the well rated person. "Kappy Oliver" makes this point )ut moralizing, and the result is good entertain which contributes wisely to one's social in-.ence. JTHOR INTEREST: The mother of a teen-daughter and son, MONA (Mrs. Claibourne WALKER, Penna. Beta, found source material .er book walking right into her own home, and Vinone Ballingor Walker (Mrs. Claibourne W.) Mona Walker, Pennsylvania B she writes that this first book "was such fun to do and so satisfying in other ways that I am now working on another." Prior to this the Bucknell graduate has had short stories published, but this is her first book. FLORENCE MARIE TAYLOR, Night of 3:.i s, Poems, privately published. A specialist in verbal painting, Miss Taylor has gathered into this hard-bound volume poems which have been published in numerous magazines and newspapers. In addition to enjoying its literary value, Pi Phis, who buy the two dollar book, will have the satisfaction of knowing that twenty-five cents of each sale to or by a Pi Phi will go to the Indianapolis Alumna Club. Typical of her work is "The Garden of Peace" which describes a house deserted in a garden choked with weeds and then compares : 234 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI "And there are many places in the world Where blossoms of freedom, faith and truth decrease As words of hate and violence are hurled, And wars go on, and on, and never cease. If freedom's banner is to hang unfurled There must be spade work in the garden of peace." AUTHOR INTEREST: Indiana Gamma's FLORENCE MARIE TAYLOR does not limit herself to poetry, for over 125 publications have carried herfiction and articles as well. Currently she con( trates for the most part on material for busii publications. She is a member of the Worm Press Club of Indiana and of the Indianapolis bra of the National League of American Pen Won RANDOM NOTES : Another poetess, ANNA HARDING, Mich. Beta, has received Lyric M., zine's Quarterly Award for a sonnet publishes its winter issue. Last May this resident of Freder Md., was given third prize in the annual contesi the Pennsylvania Poetry Society. News from Little Pigeon (Continued from page 231) Conte Lodge pancakes, at least ten of 'em, with sausages, eggs and all the coffee you can drink. No, not too much after that five-mile hike ! Our own cook at Settlement School, Mrs. Lela Adams, treasures her very old recipe for Tennessee Cake, prize cake, of course, to claim the name of the state. One could not mention favorite recipes with-out including Country Fried Ham and Red-eye Gravy, perhaps a first choice for many. Biscuits and sourwood honey should be added in the same breath ! Recipes from the adopted Smoky Mountain folks are enticing. Tina McMorran, our Arrowcraft de-signer, submits her favorite recipe for Chop Suey and Almond Roca. Marjorie Chalmers, our nurse of twenty-one years, contributes some tempting favorites. Elizabeth Rue, manager of Arrowcraft, recommends a very special formula for cooking pork chops---a treat, she promises. The Plum Pudding is a holiday favorite of Marion Mueller. Edna Mc-Cutchan has managed our shop in the Mountain View Hotel for many years. Her recipes evidence alove for cookery. Henrietta McCutchan Huff i Missouri Beta who came here to teach, but v her marriage to Jim Huff, decided to become of the adopted. Lillian Hansen Howell (Kar Alpha) contributes some, too. Lillian served as sistant to the Director of Settlement School for 1 years and is now practicing her culinary art in own home. Lena Hodgen served as housekee at Settlement School for over ten years, but she capable of taking over the duties of cook w] necessary. Several of her specialties deserve consic ation. The Ham Loaf is tasty; I've tried it ! 7 is offered by Marian Heard who has directed Workshop for eleven years. University of Tenne: Dean Jess Harris' recipe for Hush Puppies is licious served with fish. Fish ! We have not rr tioned fish. Almost everyone loves to fish yo and old. Are you hungry? Can you smell the moun air ? Yes, do `cum' to the Smokies and we will some eatin' ! At least buy one of the new c books. Watch for the new Pi Phi Cookbook </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



