<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr7220105_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Dobler, Louise Wheelor</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Winter 1955</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr7220105_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1955</date>, News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Dobler, Louise Wheelor</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 105-106</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">40</note>
                        <note type="Folder">8</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 72, Number 2 (Winter 1955), Pages 105-106.</note>
			<note type="document">arr7220105_0000</note>


	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Changing Mission of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity for Women in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1944-1964</item>
                                <item>Nurses</item>
                                <item>Healthcare</item>
                                <item>Community outreach</item>
                                <item>Government</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr7220105_0001" seq="01" n="104-105  "/>
       <p>THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI tals. There were a dozen young children one of the DSt appealing being four year old Rickey White, Inadian born adopted son of an attractive Air )rce Colonel and his wife. To see Rickey salute e flag was a high light of the ceremonies. Participating in a naturalization ceremony and beming acquainted with those who take the Oath of llegiance to our country dramatized for the sorority embers the basic concepts of good citizenship they try to exemplify in campus and community life. Fraternity and sorority members have a little explored avenue of community service in many cities in the U. S. A. in connection with these naturalization ceremonies held there. Why not volunteer assistance to the U. S. Immigration and Naturalization Services and the local Bar Associations as did the N. P. C. Citizenship Committee in Washington D.C. ? 1 PHIS AT Zeta Siqrna Phi Convention mong visitors and delegates to the forty-sixth annual convention of Theta Sigma Phi were these members of Pi Beta Phi. hie sessions were held at the Hotel Chase in St. Louis, June 20-25th; and magazine editors, TV commentators, and foreign )rrespondents addressed the key meetings. acted left to right: Alice Townsend Barlow, Minnesota Alpha; Bonnie Thompson, Indiana Alpha; Beatrice Roehm Miller, 1diana Beta. handing left to right: Betty Ann Bixler, Indiana Gamma; Marilyn Mitchell, Nebraska Beta; Carol Christensen, North Dakota 1phti; Blanche Shirley Hayes, Illinois Zeta. ew5 FROM LITTLE PIGEON Edited -3ON DECEMBER 1, Marjorie Chalmers celebrates 20 years as the nurse in charge of health education and service at the Jennie Nicol Memorial Center in Gatlinburg. 1955 also marks the 35th year of Pi Phi's health program in the community. In the accompanying article Marjorie tells, in her inimitable way, some of the experiences and impressions of her work in the Smokies where she has made 21,798 field visits and has had 49,267 office calls. "They've been the stay of Izorie these many years." There had been a tea at Staff House honoring Grand Council, the Settlement School Committee, and the Province Officers. Izora and her granddaughter, Patsy, were leaving after visiting about two hours. She had been especially invited, for Izora has been. one of Arrowcraft's faithful weavers for nearly thirty years, and knew many of the "Pi Phi ladies" who were there. Pi Phi HAS been the "stay" of a great many Mrs. Mariorie Chalmers, R.N. in charge of the Jennie Nicol Health Center by Louise Wheelock Dobler, Washingto Gatlinburg folk "these many years." The inc family income has helped to pay for hon farms, and helped to educate the children, provided for an electric stove, a washer, or It has helped to pay the grocer, the doctor dentist. It has bought needed glasses. It has more than one permanent one of woma] greatest morale-builders; and when a woman a little home on a rocky farm doing things t way, she is surely entitled to all the morale build. For thirty-five years, Gatlinburg and its su ing area has had health service provided Fraternity. And as proof that that service h used and appreciated, there are records show our families continue to come children and children of those for whom the first recor, made. We have learned much of family characi We watch for tendencies to certain diseas know those who are subject to congenital and those who have had contact with tubes We know those who are having a run of ha. and those who are consistently "do-less." The stranger in our town might wonder drives along the wide road that leads to ff. "Why should this busy little resort town health center? Why not depend on the sery is given by the Department of Public Healt That, of course, is a good question. The tion would make it very clear that that servic leave much to be desired. Sevier County is lar, in some places, quite rough. We have nc health doctor, and the county nurse has me she can possibly do. She has about seventy in her charge. She inspects when she can once or twice a year. She gives no physical e: tions, and goes to each school but once oculation clinics. She does all the visitat crippled children and tubercular patients. S blood counts and gives preventive inoculai the office twice a week. In contrast, Pi Beta Phi Health Service is mate touch with the community. Our "wet are our pride and joy. Our school children familiar with our care as were their pare grand-parents. The Health Center has be, stay" in sickness and uncertainty, as well as in of health and hygiene. Now there are two doctors and a dentist in burg who have helped us carry the health 105 </p>
      <pb ref="arr7220105_0002" seq="02" n="106-107  "/>
       <p>THE ARROW OF N BETA PHI last ten years. But there are times when we give ething that cannot be received elsewhere. There families that have difficulty in providing the ,lute necessities of plain living, so there is nothing for medical service. In a city, taxes or community ;t may provide visiting nurse service. Here, we and on Pi Beta Phi. Vith first-aid we ward off many a serious in-ion. By early treatment we sometimes prevent a illness. We can take to the doctor children who !l at going without us. Through our various ics we have introduced the doctor as an interig and interested friend, and cooperation between and the families is greater. 'he Health Center is as much a part of daily as the school or store. Folks come for service or a as readily as they go to the shoe-man for repairs. ldren are not necessarily brought to us ; they come :heir own accord. Charlene and Anna Mae al-'s come in on their way to grandmother's house. ry, aged five, when sent to the store asks, "Don't Zed a shot ?" Ricky begs his father to bring his grown toys so that other little boys may have ri to play with, when they go to see "Miss =en" Mike came into the office the other morning. His L was scraped and bleeding from armpit to st. As I worked I asked questions. "Wreck, ce ?" "Nope." "Did you fall out of a tree again ?" 2p, clear from the top. Like-ta broke neck." 'hat did your mother say ?'A surprised look hed over the thin, freckled face, "Why, Lord ha' :cy, Marnie, I didn't go home. I came straight 2. ['he "least-un" fell in the creek and cut her knee. brother fetched her out and carried her to "th' se." Middle-sized brother scuttled to the house tell Mom. Mom called the office for particulars, [ "should she come for the young-uns, or would I bring them home ?" There were a few visits for clean dressings and the wound healed without infection. You can't get that type of service through public health, for it is just not permitted. You don't get physical examinations in the schools every year. You don't have health instruction with picture shows, nor classes for adults in first aid and home nursing. Participation in civic affairs seems important to our job. We believe most firmly that it is our duty to cooperate in anything and everything that will make living safer and more healthful, for the community as well as for the individual. We are very near to one of the nation's critical target areas. Knoxville, Alcoa, Oak Ridge and several TVA dams are less than fifty air miles away. Gatlinburg has been designated by the state coordinators as an evacuation center. The tourist facilities make it possible to house and feed large numbers of persons. With the Health center designated as a Command Post for the area, we have a great deal of planning to do. That planning has given us a membership on the State Advisory Committee for Women for Civil Defense, making it necessary for us to attend workshops about twice a year. The County Medical Association meets at the Health Center about once a month. We sit.in on the discussion of new drugs and treatments. We have movies on special surgical and medical procedures, as well as tape recordings of interesting lectures. We are a part of the professional life of the county, and can serve better because of it. There is much to do. We are forever busy. But the people of the community are being served as they have been from the long-ago beginnings. And the work of Phi Beta Phi moves forward according to the changing needs. It is, as it has always been, "the stay" of many folk "these many years." During the months of January, February and March, address all correspondence regarding Settlement School Slides to Mrs. Fred Archibald 830 West University Parkway Baltimore, Maryland MAINE ALPHA CHAPTER OF Pi BETA PHI Ce/tra1ei ~t~ JGcirfy q~th MAINE ALPHA Chapter of Pi Beta Phi celebrated on Saturday its founding thirty-five years ago on the campus of the University of Maine. From a local group known as Beta Phi, twenty-five girls became initiated into the National fraternity on May 25, 1920. Of this group two charter members, Mrs. Ardis Lancey Moore, Pittsfield, and Mrs. Madeline Eastman Cousins, Oldtown, were present for the festivities on the Maine campus. Honored guests of the chapter for the occasion were Mrs. Gladys Watkins Westcott, Amherst, Mass., and Mrs. Clara Parks Haggeman, West Hartford, Conn., Province President and Province Vice-President of Alpha Province East and Mrs. Hazel Sawyer Everett, South Port-land, Past-President of Alpha Province East and an active alumnae member of Maine Alpha for many years. Registration opened the events of the day followed by a Coffee at the Women's Lounge of the Union Building. A Welcome Meeting was conductedby Barbara Ilvonen, acting chapter president, which the activities of the present year for Ma Alpha were reviewed for Alumnae members. Sli^ of the Pi Beta Phi Convention held in Miami 1 summer were shown by Barbara Knox, past pp dent of active chapter and chapter delegate. , Chapter exhibits, historical data, photographs, a memoranda were on display during the day in Bumps Room. A display of beautiful hand-wol articles from the Arrowcraft Shop. of the Settlem School in the Smokey Mountains, the national pl anthropic project of the Fraternity, was also s( here. A luncheon was served at noon in Estabrt Hall, for all members of the active chapter a returning alumnae. In the afternoon a history of Maine Alpha ) presented by the active chapter and alumnae in Main Lounge of the Union Building. Under direction of Barbara Willey, introductions of yearly periods were made by Joan Williams a Left to Right: Mrs. Clara Parks Haggeman, Alpha Province East Vice-President; Mrs. Helen McElravy Buzzell, Retiring Presi of Eastern Maine Alumnae Club; Mrs. Gladys Watkins Westcott, Alpha Province East President; Miss Barbara Ilvonen, M Alpha Chapter President; Mrs. Hazel Sawyer Everett, for many years Alpha Province East President and Banquet Spec Mrs. Wilmarth Starr, Chapter Patroness. 107 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



