<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr7020131_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Dobler, Louise Wheelock</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>December 1953</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr7020131_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">December 1953</date>, News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Dobler, Louise Wheelock</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 131-132</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">40</note>
                        <note type="Folder">6</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 70, Number 2 (December 1953), Pages 131-132.</note>
			<note type="document">arr7020131_0000</note>


	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Changing Mission of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity for Women in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1944-1964</item>
                                <item>Staff quarters</item>
                                <item>People</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr7020131_0001" seq="01" n="130-131  "/>
       <p>30 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI AUTHOR INTEREST: As his wife writes, it would be difficult to find any man more losely connected to Pi Phi for more years," and hat, of course, is why Dr. Theiss' book is inluded in this column. His first wife, Mary Bar-el Theiss, was editor of the ARROW and grand ecretary ; his present wife, Anna Jackson Bran-on Theiss, was twice a province president, ;rand vice-president, circulation manager of the O.ROw, and first treasurer of the Settlement ,chool, and both his daughter, Mrs. Garner ames, and stepdaughter, Mrs. Myron Board-clan, are Pi Phis. Dr. Theiss, who has written )ver forty books, began writing on Charles A. )ana's New York Sun and eventually became )rofessor of journalism at Bucknell University, rom which he has recently retired.  RANDOM NOTES: In the last year JANE )AVIDSON, former Ohio Zeta president, has held research fellowship at the Mellon Institute, ittsburgh, and in the course of that produced series of articles on "Virus Hunters" for the 'ittsburgh Press. Her mother is Marie Bunnell )avidson (Mrs. P. B.), Montana A. -- Settlement School is given a fine tribute by ^TORTH CALLAHAN in his new book, Smoky Guntain Country, one of the American Folk-ways series edited by Erskine Caldwell and published by Duell, Sloan and Pearce-Little, Brown. Mr. Callahan grew up in the area and thus speaks with authority when he says, "the sorority officials take a realistic approach and do not talk down to the local people." Three pages are devoted to the school alone.  JULIA ELLEN ROGERS, a fifty-year Pi Phi, Iowa Z, has recently had her work, The Shell Book, first published in 1908, reprinted by the Charles T. Branford Company, Boston. It's richly illustrated in color and half-tones, and is attracting readers among a new generation of nature lovers. She now plans a similar re-launching for her The Tree Book. Two young Hunter College graduates have successfully established their own firm Caedmon Publishers, which the New York Herald Tribune says gives "literature a new third dimension." They are tape recording authors reading their own works and have found a ready market for their products. A recent Herald-Tribune photograph shows them recording with author KATHERINE ANNE PORTER, Maryland A, who had another book, Days Before, published last fall by Harecort. VOLUNTEER SERVICE BLANK Alumnce Have you leisure to contribute 'to Pi Beta Phi ? If you have, and if you have the desire to share in the joy of serving the Fraternity, please fill out this blank and send to the Grand President. NAME IN FULL ADDRESS CHAPTER AND YEAR ARE YOU A MEMBER OF AN ALUMNIE CLUB ? TYPE OF WORK PREFERRED ............................ ............................. ews FROM LITTLE PIGEON Edited by Louise Wheelock Dobler, Washington Beta '3CEREMONIES dedicating the new Ruth Bar rett Smith Staff House were held in Gatlin-burg, on Tuesday, June 2 3rd, at four o'clock in the afternoon. Present for the service were members of Grand Council, the Settlement School Committee members, and Province Presidents and Vice-Presidents in session for their annual summer meeting. They were joined by resident Pi Phis and long-time local friends of the school who gathered at this newest of our Pi Phi buildings as Katie McIntosh, Alabama B, and bookkeeper and assistant to the manager at Arrowcraft, played soft music on the piano which was borrowed from the PTA for the vacation months. Mrs. T. E. Smith of Atlanta, secretary of the Settlement School Committee, read an appropriate passage from the Bible, after which Mrs. Warren T. Smith of Brookings, Oregon, Chair-man of the Committee, presented the key to the house to Miss Ruth Dyer, Director of the School and head resident, who expressed the pleasure and gratitude of the staff for such a lovely, much-needed home. Mrs. Marjorie Chalmers, the nurse in charge of our program at the Jennie Nicol Health Center, added the thanks of the other resident staff members when she sang, "Bless This House." In accepting the home in the name of the Fraternity, our Grand President, Marianne Reid Wild, paid tribute to Ruth Barrett Smith for her years of loyalty and service to Pi Beta Phi, and formally declared that the house should be named in her honor. A closing prayer by Lucile Douglass Carson, Grand Secretary, invoking divine blessing and guidance on the house and its occupants, as well as the ideals which they represent was followed by the Lord's Prayer in unison and singing of the Anthem. In the social hour which concluded the dedication, guests were conducted through the house and served a most-welcome iced punch. Ruth Dean Barrett, the beloved Pi Phi for whom this house was named, was initiated into Iowa Gamma on June 6, 1909, where she was voted the most popular girl ever enrolled in school. On that same date in 1913, the year following her graduation and travel and study abroad, she was married to her college sweet-heart, Warren T. Smith, who has always been loyal and helpful Pi Phi husband. Today the: live in Brookings, Oregon, with the blue Pacifi, in their front yard, and not too far from thei son and daughter, Dick and Betty, who live wits their familes (including four favorite grand children) in Chehalis, Washington. In Los Angeles where they established thei first home, Ruth became active in the Alumna Ruth Barrett Smith, Iowa r, retiring chairman, Settlement School Committee. Club, serving as its president, and being in strumental in establishing the active chapter a U.C.L.A. Her interests through the years hav not been limited to Pi Phi, for she was active i] the work of Federated Club Women, served a a Gray Lady during the War years, and a: always willing worker for Bond drives an, Community Chest campaigns. When the convention of 1929 met in Paso dena at the Huntington she was a co-worker fa the Guide, and was elected assistant to th Grand Vice-President. In the Asbury Park Cor vention in 1931 she presided over an Alumni Session in the absence of Katherine Burr Telle: Grand Vice-President, and at the same conver tion she was elected to succeed Mrs. Teller a office which she efficiently and graciously hel until the Swampscott Convention of 1946. Following her retirement the Alumnae Df partment established the Ruth Barrett Smit Scholarship which is given each year in h( honor, and in 1947 Grand Council named h( 131 </p>
      <pb ref="arr7020131_0002" seq="02" n="132-133  "/>
       <p>32 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI Huff Photo New Staff House ) the chairmanship of the very important ettlement School Committee. Familiar with the :hoof and its needs and problems since she rst visited it in 1933, it was fitting for Ruth mith's regime to begin and complete plans for le long-needed new staff house. In this eneavor Warren's help was invaluable, and he avelled with her to Gatlinburg to give advice nd counsel. Completed and occupied, though scantily arnished, in the fall of 1952, the house pro-ides adequate and more convenient living uarters for our year-round resident staff, as Tell as the faculty members who teach at our ummer Workshops. It includes, on the ground oar, an entrance hall and coat closet ; a spacious ving room with fireplace ; a dining room largeenough for the workshop group, yet which can be made small enough for the regular family when the modernfold partition is installed to divide it; a convenient, airy, well-equipped kitchen; the bedroom-sitting room suite of the director, with a bath shared by the adjoining guest-bedroom; three other bedrooms, and a second bath. Upstairs are seven bedrooms, a sewing and pressing room, bath and shower rooms, and storage space. Generous gifts from individuals, clubs, and chapters have provided many of the first essential furnishings, but many others are needed before the "house" is really a "home." Your gift to the Ruth Barrett Smith Staff House will make sure that through the years a beloved Pi Phi is "so well remembered." On the last page of the September ARROW there appeared an in-correct notice about the Holt House Films. They may be obtained from Mrs. John C. Campbell, 926 E. First Avenue, Monmouth, Illinois. WASHINGTON, D.C., CITY PANHELLENIC Iceiuec1 at White ,JJotoe 4'ench Stuc ento onored '-FOUR French girls attending American colgram at the Sheraton Hotel. At three P.M. leges were received at the White House by they were met by Mme. Pierre Francfort, wife of Mrs. Eisenhower on May 14. The girls came to the Counselor of the French Embassy, represent. Washington for a gay week-end as guests of the ing Mme. Bonnet, who escorted them througl Washington City Panhellenic Association. the embassy and drove them to Mount Vernon. Among other things they had luncheon at the Friday evening the four girls were escorted by Speaker's Dining Room at the Capitol, were inyoung men from George Washington University terviewed on television, and saw the play "Arms to see the production "Arms and the Man." On and the Man" with escorts from George WashSaturday, May 16, the members of Panhellenic ington University. The French girls were Pauentertained them at luncheon at the Mayfair lette Renoe Ducatez, ' who is attending Sweet Restaurant, followed by another sightseeing tout Briar College Anita Kirgo, University of Delaof the embassies, Lincoln Memorial, Lee Man ware ; Monique Simone Klein, Hollins College sion and Arlington Cemetery. and Madeleine Viard, Bucknell University. The entire expense of their trip to Washing. Shortly after their arrival on Thursday, May ton was met by the Washington Panhellenic 14, the girls and 250 members of the 25 sororiAssociation through funds received from a bene. ties represented in the Washington Panhellenic fit tour of the French Embassy. The student! Association were received at the White House at will return to France this summer and the Wash. 12:50 P.M. by Mrs. Dwight Eisenhower. Folington Panhellenic felt that their Americar lowing this, they had luncheon at the Capitol experiences will be enriched by a visit to our with Speaker of the House Joseph Martin, Connation's Capital. gressman Arthur Younger, California and ConPi Phis in attendance: Mrs. William C. Dulin gressman Laurie Battle, Alabama. A visit to the Mrs. F. J. Homff, Mrs. O. F. Kotick, Mrs. B Senate was arranged through the courtesy of Harrison Lingo, Mrs. William R. Lockhart, Mis! Senator J. Allen Frear, Jr., of Delaware. ThursMary K. Lutz, Mrs. W. Kemp Menefee, Mrs day evening the girls were guests of the French Thomas H. Miller, Mrs. Arthur E. Nesbitt Club of the University of Maryland, sponsored Mrs. George C. Ober, Jr., Mrs. Charles E by Dr. Leonora Rosenfield. Pledger, Jr., Mrs. Reginald H. Pledger, Mrs Friday morning was spent in sightseeing the William E. Plummer, Mrs. Adrian M. Shields famous places in Washington, followed by a Mrs. Nell Anderson Spruce, Mrs. C. P. Trussell luncheon. The afternoon was very busy with a Mrs. Robert S. Wild. television appearance on Nancy Osgood's pro -+ Penn Help Week Provides 1,220 Man-Hours of Free Labor During 1952-1953 A campus wide fraternity "Help Week" program at the University of Pennsylvania provided 1,220 man-hours of free labor for community agencies during 1952-1953, a committee of the University's Interfraternity Council has reported to the Dean of Student Affairs. The report is given to members of the 19th Leadership School to show how Help Week has taken the place of Hell Week all over the country and is continuing to expand in program. The report read: "Harnessed for constructive service was a dynamo of student energy that might otherwise have been dissipated in the sort of hazing typical of old-fashioned `Hell Week,' which is on its way out at Pennsylvania as on most campuses." 133 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



