<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr7520139_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Finger, Lois Snyder</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Winter 1958</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr7520139_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1958</date>, News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Finger, Lois Snyder</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 136 and 139</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">40</note>
                        <note type="Folder">11</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 75, Number 2 (Winter 1958), Pages 136 and 139.</note>
			<note type="document">arr7520139_0000</note>


	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Changing Mission of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity for Women in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1944-1964</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>
                                <item>Promotion</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr7520139_0001" seq="01" n="136  "/>
       <p>ew. FROM LITTLE PIGEON Edited by Lois Snyder Finger, Iowa Z Under the trade name of "Arrowcraft," the traditional handwork of the mountain people near Gatlinburg, Tennessee, is in demand for its beauty of design and excellent workmanship, and it is a dependable source of income for scores of mountain families. Through the purchase and sale of this native handcraft, Pi Phis, everywhere, are proud to support a project which contributes both to the welfare of the mountain people and to American culture. 2auhie Jrienc10 Jprons ' APRONS, Patio (sketched) $3.50 Red, royal blue, Kelly green, marigold yellow, chocolate brown, black. Checked with white. Bordered pattern on bottom. DRESSY APRONS $3.50 White or pastels with metallic varieties in bands and stripes. Darker colors on black warp. Specify color preference. No duplicates. MOTHER and DAUGHTER APRONS $3.75-$2.65 Sheer pink or aqua with design. 5or Showero rthcIa 4nnitier4arie$ eu gJ TOTE BAGS (sketched) $3.50 Summer or winter colors. Pretty shades. OPEN SEAMLESS BAGS $4.00 New design in pattern and handles. Metallic and nubby threads for trim. ENVELOPE PURSE $1.35 Heavy white with silver metallic. "COQUETTE" PARTY BAGS $4.50 10% Fed. tax. Dainty colors in white and pastels, gold, silver and black. CLUTCH BAGS, Party style $3.50 Same materials and colors as above. -:.,\N\\\\\\X\%, \NN,k,'X\ ..., 136 FROM Pi Phi ~evt~ Edited by Mary Elizabeth Lasher Barnette, Ohio A RUTH FRANCHERE, Willa, The Story of Willa Lather's Growing Up, Thomas Y. Crowell Company, 169 pp. This delightful book, plainly written out of its author's love for the work and personality of one of the most decidedly American writers, has itself captured the essence of our country. By dealing with Willa Lather's formative years it appeals to a new reading audience for such classics as "0 Pioneers" and "My Antonia" and should stimulate .fresh interest in them. In fact' it's an invitation to learning in general, for no one, child or adult, can resist the appeal of Willa's eager, searching, questioning, and creative mind. To modern girls growing up Willa Cather should be a natural heroine, for the span of her life joins the romantic past to the challenging present, and her own accomplishments set an attractive standard worthy of emulation. It's a sprightly story too, for Willa Lather's own girlhood was as full of humor, warmly moving episodes, and excitement as one of her own novels. There are other provocative personalities, such as Professor Shindelmeisser, the music teacher, and Uncle William Ducker, who provided Willa with a much needed climate for learning, an atmosphere hard to come by in the Nebraska town of Red Cloud. Not the least of the personalities is Nebraska itself, for Mrs. Franchere writes lovingly, with a heart in tune with Willa's own, of dramatic Nebraska plains, sometimes swept with flowers, then abruptly blackened by deep frost. We join with our nine-year-old daughter in recommending "Willa" for mother-daughter reading this year. AUTHOR INTEREST: Ruth Myers (Mrs. Hoyt C.) Franchere, now a resident of Oswego, Oregon, where her husband heads the Department of Humanities at Portland State College, is a native of Waterloo, Iowa, graduate of the University of Iowa, member of Iowa Zeta. It was, she reports, the numerous childhood vacations spent with her grand-parents in Nebraska that established her feeling of identity with the Cather country and of kinship with the author herself. Mrs. Franchere has taught English composition at the University of Washington, University of Oregon and Portland State College. The Francheres have one daughter Julie. JACQUELINE JACKSON, The Pale face Redskins. Little, Brown and Company, 275 pp. Most persons would be amply content to have one creative talent, but Jacqueline Jackson now demonstrates that she has two, for she has executed the often humorous illustrations, which decorate this book, as well as written the lively narrative. The same daughter mentioned before assures us that this is just the sort of story that makes the reader want to get right in between the pages with the book's characters. After all, what could be more fun than belonging to one's own Indian tribe for an entire summer, fighting real battles with an inter-loping Boy Scout Camp, and finally making peace in traditional pipe-smoking fashion ? This book has that rare plus, a sense of humor, too, and that, we know, is a welcome quality to parents who read aloud to their own offspring. It also has joint boy-girl appeal from ages eight to twelve. AUTHOR INTEREST: Jacqueline Dougan (Mrs. Robert) Jackson, Wisconsin B, is a young woman of obviously remarkable energy. After at-tending Beloit College and marrying there, she went with her husband to the University of Michigan to study and there wrote her first, exceedingly amusing book, "Julie's Secret Sloth." This was followed by a year at Oxford University where the first of their three daughters was born. Now the family, which includes Damaris, Megan, and Gillian, is in New Haven where Mr. Jackson is an instructor at Yale College and Divinity School. RANDOM NOTES: While library browsing recently we spotted, and subsequently read, a 1956 novel, "Let My Name Stand Fair," by Missouri B's Shirley Seifert, a historical novelist of note. Unfortunately the book, her tenth novel, did not come to our attention at the time of publication, but it's good reading, and we commend it to your attention now. Briefly it's primarily a Revolutionary War story whose chief character is vivacious Caty Little-field Greene, wife of Washington's second-in-command General Nathanael Greene, and it presents most interestingly the domestic and social side of the war for freedom. The 414-page book was published by J. B. Lippincott Company. 4-* -3 139 </p>
      <pb ref="arr7520139_0002" seq="02" n="139  "/>
       <p>ew. FROM LITTLE PIGEON Edited by Lois Snyder Finger, Iowa Z Under the trade name of "Arrowcraft," the traditional handwork of the mountain people near Gatlinburg, Tennessee, is in demand for its beauty of design and excellent workmanship, and it is a dependable source of income for scores of mountain families. Through the purchase and sale of this native handcraft, Pi Phis, everywhere, are proud to support a project which contributes both to the welfare of the mountain people and to American culture. 2auhie Jrienc10 Jprons ' APRONS, Patio (sketched) $3.50 Red, royal blue, Kelly green, marigold yellow, chocolate brown, black. Checked with white. Bordered pattern on bottom. DRESSY APRONS $3.50 White or pastels with metallic varieties in bands and stripes. Darker colors on black warp. Specify color preference. No duplicates. MOTHER and DAUGHTER APRONS $3.75-$2.65 Sheer pink or aqua with design. 5or Showero rthcIa 4nnitier4arie$ eu gJ TOTE BAGS (sketched) $3.50 Summer or winter colors. Pretty shades. OPEN SEAMLESS BAGS $4.00 New design in pattern and handles. Metallic and nubby threads for trim. ENVELOPE PURSE $1.35 Heavy white with silver metallic. "COQUETTE" PARTY BAGS $4.50 10% Fed. tax. Dainty colors in white and pastels, gold, silver and black. CLUTCH BAGS, Party style $3.50 Same materials and colors as above. -:.,\N\\\\\\X\%, \NN,k,'X\ ..., 136 FROM Pi Phi ~evt~ Edited by Mary Elizabeth Lasher Barnette, Ohio A RUTH FRANCHERE, Willa, The Story of Willa Lather's Growing Up, Thomas Y. Crowell Company, 169 pp. This delightful book, plainly written out of its author's love for the work and personality of one of the most decidedly American writers, has itself captured the essence of our country. By dealing with Willa Lather's formative years it appeals to a new reading audience for such classics as "0 Pioneers" and "My Antonia" and should stimulate .fresh interest in them. In fact' it's an invitation to learning in general, for no one, child or adult, can resist the appeal of Willa's eager, searching, questioning, and creative mind. To modern girls growing up Willa Cather should be a natural heroine, for the span of her life joins the romantic past to the challenging present, and her own accomplishments set an attractive standard worthy of emulation. It's a sprightly story too, for Willa Lather's own girlhood was as full of humor, warmly moving episodes, and excitement as one of her own novels. There are other provocative personalities, such as Professor Shindelmeisser, the music teacher, and Uncle William Ducker, who provided Willa with a much needed climate for learning, an atmosphere hard to come by in the Nebraska town of Red Cloud. Not the least of the personalities is Nebraska itself, for Mrs. Franchere writes lovingly, with a heart in tune with Willa's own, of dramatic Nebraska plains, sometimes swept with flowers, then abruptly blackened by deep frost. We join with our nine-year-old daughter in recommending "Willa" for mother-daughter reading this year. AUTHOR INTEREST: Ruth Myers (Mrs. Hoyt C.) Franchere, now a resident of Oswego, Oregon, where her husband heads the Department of Humanities at Portland State College, is a native of Waterloo, Iowa, graduate of the University of Iowa, member of Iowa Zeta. It was, she reports, the numerous childhood vacations spent with her grand-parents in Nebraska that established her feeling of identity with the Cather country and of kinship with the author herself. Mrs. Franchere has taught English composition at the University of Washington, University of Oregon and Portland State College. The Francheres have one daughter Julie. JACQUELINE JACKSON, The Pale face Redskins. Little, Brown and Company, 275 pp. Most persons would be amply content to have one creative talent, but Jacqueline Jackson now demonstrates that she has two, for she has executed the often humorous illustrations, which decorate this book, as well as written the lively narrative. The same daughter mentioned before assures us that this is just the sort of story that makes the reader want to get right in between the pages with the book's characters. After all, what could be more fun than belonging to one's own Indian tribe for an entire summer, fighting real battles with an inter-loping Boy Scout Camp, and finally making peace in traditional pipe-smoking fashion ? This book has that rare plus, a sense of humor, too, and that, we know, is a welcome quality to parents who read aloud to their own offspring. It also has joint boy-girl appeal from ages eight to twelve. AUTHOR INTEREST: Jacqueline Dougan (Mrs. Robert) Jackson, Wisconsin B, is a young woman of obviously remarkable energy. After at-tending Beloit College and marrying there, she went with her husband to the University of Michigan to study and there wrote her first, exceedingly amusing book, "Julie's Secret Sloth." This was followed by a year at Oxford University where the first of their three daughters was born. Now the family, which includes Damaris, Megan, and Gillian, is in New Haven where Mr. Jackson is an instructor at Yale College and Divinity School. RANDOM NOTES: While library browsing recently we spotted, and subsequently read, a 1956 novel, "Let My Name Stand Fair," by Missouri B's Shirley Seifert, a historical novelist of note. Unfortunately the book, her tenth novel, did not come to our attention at the time of publication, but it's good reading, and we commend it to your attention now. Briefly it's primarily a Revolutionary War story whose chief character is vivacious Caty Little-field Greene, wife of Washington's second-in-command General Nathanael Greene, and it presents most interestingly the domestic and social side of the war for freedom. The 414-page book was published by J. B. Lippincott Company. 4-* -3 139 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



