<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr7410037_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Committee Reports</title>
                        <author><name>Green, Virginia Brackett</name></author>
                        <author><name>Mueller, Marion W. </name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Fall 1957</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr7410037_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1957</date>, Committee Reports</title>
                        <author><name>Green, Virginia Brackett</name></author>
                        <author><name>Mueller, Marion W. </name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 37-45</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">40</note>
                        <note type="Folder">10</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 74, Number 1 (Fall 1957), Pages 37-45.</note>
			<note type="document">arr7410037_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Chairman of Settlement School Committee; Settlement School Director's Report</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Changing Mission of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity for Women in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1944-1964</item>
                                <item>Funding</item>
                                <item>Dormitories</item>
                                <item>Healthcare</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr7410037_0001" seq="01" n="36-37  "/>
       <p>6 THE ARROW OF P1 BETA PHI PI PROVINCE lub No. Commissions Commissions Earned Per Earned Capita 19S5 Year 1956-57 -56 Commissions Earned Name of Club, Chapter, and Chairman 1956-57 604 Berkeley, Calif.-Mrs. Donald O. Horning $ 33.90 $ .43 $ 13.05 606 Centinela Valley-Mrs. D. J. Paisley 18.10 .67 4.70 608 Contra 'Costa, Calif.-Mrs. E. F. Crider 2.25 .17 16.95 610 Fresno, Calif.-Mrs. Bert Schwartz 27.30 .88 16.75 618 La Jolla, Calif.-Frances Phelps 17.38 .97 4.32 622 Long Beach, Calif.-Mrs. Richard Stratton 1.00 .02 1.00 624 Los Angeles, Calif.-Mrs. Harlan A. Dewell 57.19 .25 45.65 626 Marin County-Betty B. Brokaw 26.55 .47 34.05 628 Palo Alto, Calif.-Mrs. Edwin Harbordt 11,35 .18 29.82 630 Pasadena, Calif.-Mrs. James Hauser 124,55 .50 162.31 632 Phoenix, Ariz.-Mrs. Charles Read 71.85 1.38 26.25 634 Reno, Nev.-Mrs. R. C. Horton 13.25 .24 39.75 636 Sacramento, Calif.-Mrs. Robert Hopkins 31.60 .72 29.95 'Calif.-Mrs. 24.57 .61 36.10 638 San Bernardino, Perry A. Ratcliff 640 San Diego, Calif.-Mrs. Robert E. Honer 32.78 .34 14.40 642 San Fernando Valley, Calif.-Mrs. H. E. White 104.65 2.01 112.15 644 San Francisco, Calif.--Mrs. Stuart Armit 48.87 .87 24.40 646 San Jose, Calif._*Mrs. E. R. Heck 185.59 7.14 185.45 648 San Mateo 'County-Mrs. R. F. White 57.50 1.64 59.51 650 Santa Barbara-Ventura-Louise Dawson 17,12 .50 16.95 652 Santa Monica-Westwood Hills-Mrs. C. Vermaas 62.80 1.31 89.57 654 Solono County-Mrs. Howard Hodgden 10.98 1.10 24.88 656 South 'Coast-Iva Welsh 59.02 1.44 36.80 658 Tucson, Ariz.-Mrs. C. E. Mills 8.90 .16 19.60 660 Valley of the Moon---Mrs. Jack Germond 113.24 5.15 116.85 662 Yuba-Sutter, Calif.-Mrs. tanley Parkinson 10.50 .95 15.10 California B-Susan Straubel 5.40 .07 29.95 California r-Pat Franz 33.25 .52 49.65 California A-Patricia Houser 18.15 .32 25.20 California E-Mary Lee Foley 102.37 1.90 114.80 California Z----Jacqueline Frank 23.25 .58 28.60 Nevada A-Louella Matheus 12.27 .28 _ Arizona A-Pat Meeks 49.50 .62 100.10 TOTAL FOR PI PROVINCE FOR YEAR 1956-57 $1,416.98 Pi Province Alurnnm Club Commissions $1,172.79 Pi Province Active Chapter Commissions 244.19 TOTAL $1,416.98 Any sensible discussion of matters social must take into account the origins and ends of existing institutions. American college fraternities arose to satisfy the most fundamental of social instincts, the desire for community. Being gregarious creatures, we all feel in some degree the longing for congenial companionship. And as American colleges increased in enrollment, the need for community among the students became the more real. Our fraternities, some of which are a century and a quarter old, came into existence as social clubs and arrangements for companionable living. In this country, we never had anything very like the English collegiate system, in which the colleges of a university are at once private clubs and teaching bodies. For lack of Magdalen and Christ 'Church, Pembroke and Merton, our students developed clubs called fraternities, in which a small number of friends, united by some simple bonds of common belief and back-ground, might live together on a humane scale. Plan to come to Convention-New Ocean House, Swampscott, Massachusetts, June 22-June 28, 1958. Convention Guide: Ethel Sanford Adams (Mrs. Phillip), Boston, Massachusetts. From "The Defense of Fraternities" by RussELL KIRK. Committee Ieepot.st, CHAIRMAN OF SETTLEMENT SCHOOL COMMITTEE "It all depends on where you sit how you like the show" is a fact which we must admit many times if we are honest. It would be wonderful if each Pi Phi could sit in the seat of a member of the Settlement School Commit-tee at some time to get a close-up view of the amazing national philanthropy of the fraternity. The adjective is carefully chosen for one is constantly amazed at the many and varied opportunities which have opened up enabling Pi Beta Phi, through the Settlement School, to make an outstanding and unique contribution to the American way of life. Words are inadequate to do justice to the national project but this report will be an attempt to give you a clear view of your Settlement School during the last year. In a nutshell, Settlement School's contribution was Security but not in the limited sense which considers security in terms of money only. As someone recently pointed out, money alone does not make a person socially secure; there are at least five securities which combine to give that desirable status. Intellectual Security was the first emphasis of the Settlement School program and continued last year to be a vital concern. Mrs. Mueller, the Director, enjoyed the pleasant co-operation of educational leaders responsible for Pi Beta Phi schools and in turn, she gave of her time to assume leadership of the PTA Study Group and to give advice when called upon for such. Committed to the promotion of Arts and Crafts and Health, it was in line to furnish the teachers for Arts and Crafts, Music, Woodworking and Physical Education and Health. As has been pointed out so many times, the County can supply teachers for only the basic minimum requirements for the accredited school; so Pi Phi furnished the courses which developed appreciation and understanding so important in the life of a truly educated person. The Physical Education teacher, who coached football and basketball, was convinced the sports attracted and held many of the students who otherwise might have quit school. Mrs. Tuttle, the Music teacher, with the Girls' Glee Club served both the school and community and her plans for mixed singing groups will include more young people. For another year, Pi Phi dormitories made a high school education possible for boys and girls living too far from such a school to commute daily by school bus. Mrs. Mueller gave personal supervision to this group trying to help them find solutions to their problems which included bereavement, finances, and social adjustment. Besides the academic studies, the children learned through the work experiences afforded by the opportunity to earn part of the dorm expenses. This training prepared them for summer jobs and future careers as homemakers. Mrs. Mueller has an enlarged dorm program in mind but the lack of an Assistant will handicap her. Any Pi Phi who would like an interesting position full of variety and rewarding activities, should contact the Committee Chairman immediately, if she is unmarried and between the ages of 22 and 35 years. Pi Phi can look back with satisfaction on this far-reaching part of the program whereby through housing, the fraternity has given a boost to education. Hundreds of mountain children have been under the influence of the school staff during the many years they have lived in the dorms. Many have long since become parents, better ones we hope, and through them the Pi Phi influence continues through the years. A number bring their children for the experience in dorm living which they value in adult years. What difference would it have made to them today if Pi Phi had not come to Gatlinburg in 1912? Housing for students was not the only way in which education was aided. During the year, the Ruth Barrett Smith House lodged the resident staff and five to In a state where teachers' salaries have been for fraternity has helped to secure and hold faculty attractive, reasonable living was available to ma pay check go farther. Years ago, far-sighted leaders realized the full today is the best preparation for tomorrow; so they the Summer Craft Workshop in cooperation wi University of Tennessee and brought education on loge level to Gatlinburg, making full year-round the Settlement School facilities. Inadequate housin limited the Workshop in 1957, for even the livinfi at Teachers' Cottage was pressed into service as room to meet the demand. Many of those in attendan not afford tuition, supplies, travel costs, plus exi living accommodations found in a tourist town, an essential to supply reasonable room and board. T years ago the conversion of the elementary school bi into a dormitory was a temporary move. Each year as a school during the winter finds the job of con more back-breaking, costly, and less satisfactory act to Pi Phi standards. It is gratifying to have Stun novated Pollard, and Teachers' Cottages, for those to dormitory life. Success simmers down to maki most of what you are with what you have. The S Workshop instructors were successful in sending fo thusiastic craftsmen and it would be wonderful tc use of the red barn, which we have, to make it p for more to have the same opportunity for study Marian Heard, Tennessee Gamma, was the Wo Director to whom goes much of the credit for the of the project. Dean Jessie Harris of University o nessee and her staff contributed valuable assistance planning for this summer program. Kenneth Bab authority on Enameling, and Miss Lulu Smith, co. of "Contemporary Weaving," were popular members faculty. Jean Stange, University of Nebraska, I McDonald, and Jane Glass, both designer-craftsmer valuable additions to the teaching staff. It was exci see the foreign students grow to know the America of life as they worked side by side in the classes realize the friendly feelings as well as new skills cross the ocean and spread. International underst developed in such surroundings was the most effecti of education, and Pi Phi's outreach extended beyo shores of the USA. An encouraging thought is tl great majority will share the fruits of these days at shop with many others. The second Foreign Study Craft Tour was sal for the summer of 1957 and plans were well forn when the Suez crisis arose. Uncertainty as to what happen in the forthcoming months made it advise postpone the tour until 1958. The first one wa successful and all interested in further details write to Foreign Study Craft Tour, College of Hon nomics, University of Tennessee, Knoxville. Thus, Intellectual Security was fostered in manj but there is still a challenge to find a way to hell few remaining one room schools just a short dista of the main highway. Space does not permit the s the recent visit to one of these mountain schools, Ix Pi Phi would have been aroused to new efforts t the challenge, had she been on the trip. Health and Emotional Security are important a fraternity, through the Jennie Nicol Memorial Center, continued to render service to the mountai munity with a special concern for the children. Mr jorie Chalmers, registered nurse, set up the usual 37 </p>
      <pb ref="arr7410037_0002" seq="02" n="38-39  "/>
       <p>THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI maminations of football and basketball aspirants, the Ly clinic for T.B. as well as dental, and a weekly baby clinic. The children in the Pi Beta Phi schools rural schools were examined and health conditions 7ted to the parents. The annual typhoid booster and . preventive inoculations were given as they fell due. )ite of the tremendous amount of work involved, we happy to have a part in the Salk inoculation cam-1. The County Medical Association held its monthly ing at Health Center, and the blessings gained eighed the effort of preparing for them. Discussions, es, and talks by guest specialists helped Nurse Mar-to keep up with the ever-changing world of medicine also kept the name of Pi Phi fresh in the minds of nedical people who are concerned with the same sort salth program. Said Marjorie in her report, "To com-Ind to prevent illness and accident is sound. Health ital to an individual and to a community and our )nsibility grows as the community grows. In civil Ise, in flood and disaster, in epidemic and accident, 4ealth Center has a duty. And that duty, for top effi-:y, must be integrated with the planning of civic !rs. The maintaining of good public relations is an )rtant part of our service, and an active interest in nunity affairs is good business." The summary of for the year is recorded below, but how can one for credit, advice and suggestion, confidence and se-y? How can you evaluate the easing of a troubled SUMMARY OF WORK ld visits 493 ice calls 4141 vice given 3500 all pox vaccinations 225 tal typhoid inoculations 954 rnpleted typhoid series and boosters 741 tal triple vaccine inoculations 241 mpleted series and boosters 122 k vaccine inoculations 1222 erepeutic inoculations 221 alth talks 104 Scher-nurse conferences 149 eminations and inspections 3064 est X-Rays 1085 he need for Economic Security was early discovered attlement School and the Arrowcraft Shop was estabd to furnish a market for the native handcrafts. In this the mountain people had the opportunity to help (selves. Elizabeth Rue, the enthusiastic Manager of wcraft, reported orders and correspondence with 65 % le clubs and chapters. Once again enterprising, philanaic alumna supplied an outlet for the mountain smen. There were fifteen clubs deserving of special tion for these bought and paid for at least one thousand Lrs worth of Arrowcraft during the last fiscal year. 1paign-Urbana . .$2249.43 Cleveland, East $1355.66 Ind, Oregon 2028.47 Kansas City, 'Mo 1344.85 coma City 1941.40 Pasadena 1253.16 ,urgh 1658.72 South Bend 1249.41 aukee 1524.45 Seattle 1221.56 College, Pa . 1423.81 Denver 1122.18 1, Oregon 407.76 Tulsa 1089.26 Everett, Washington 1018.51 adena deserved to be listed last year and was accidentally ed. 7hile many other clubs did not make the above list .onor, their conscientious efforts added to the success ae Arrowcraft project; we could not do without them. that shoots best may sometimes miss the mark but hat shoots not at all, can never hit it." Because Arrow-had regular bills to meet, payment by the invoice encouraged, in fact, urged rather than the settlement he account at the end of the year. izabeth Rue and Tina McMorran, the Designer and !rvisor of Weaving, worked out an attractive new list for the coming year which will be appreciated ill chairmen. The new Cook Book will appear on it that book will be ordered through Arrowcraft Shop same as the other products. It will be ready for the fall sales. All of the clubs were invited to submit 5 choice recipes and as a result, the recipe committee had a difficult time choosing from the many tempting contributions. This committee deserves a vote of gratitude for an exacting task well-done. It took hours of concentration to make sure each participating group was represented in the book. Mrs. Helen Schuller Miller, chairman, Margaret Smith DeHoff, professor of Home Economics at Butler University and Dorothea White Flint, better known as Supervisor of Chapter Accounting, composed the committee of Home Ec majors which made the choice. Great appreciation is sent to all who co-operated in selling advertisements in the book to help underwrite the cost of publication. All profit will go to the Settlement School. Tina has designed some new place settings which will be attractive both in appearance and price. The new summer purse promises to meet the demand for one. Also Tina designed and wove a lovely afghan which the fraternity presented to Mamie Eisenhower for her Gettysburg home. Mrs. McMorran entertained in her lovely new home for the weavers who have woven 2 5 years or more for Arrowcraft. Three additional weavers qualified for 25 year pins and they were presented with them. It is timely that Pi Beta Phi expresses appreciation of Tina's nine years of creative service to Arrowcraft for after the first of the year, she will no longer be at Arrowcraft. Our best wishes follow her. Many members will be interested to learn that Arrowcraft will welcome Winogene Redding back to the staff as the designer-supervisor. Gene has given many years to Arrowcraft and pioneered with us in the earlier days of the project. It will be like coming home for she has many friends among the weavers as well as in the Burg. Last year during the summer tourist season, the Shop experimented with remaining open in the evening. The brief trial seemed to merit another try this year; so visitors this summer can visit Arrowcraft in the evening hours. Recently the Settlement School Committee was informed that Arrowcraft was one of the few is not the ONLY example of cottage industries in the United States. The government and the University of Tennessee sent distinguished guests to Arrowcraft from many lands and the staff escorted the visitors into the homes where the mountain people work as independent craftsmen aided by Pi Phis who provide a market for their handcrafts. Little did the fraternity anticipate 31 years ago when Arrowcraft was started, that out of its experience, Pi Beta Phi could make a valuable contribution to other parts of the world. Do Pi Phis begin to comprehend the Settlement School's contribution to Economic Security even beyond the Smoky Mountains? Social Security was an important by-product of Settlement School program. The experience of group living in the dormitories prepared the boys and girls to adjust to a world bigger than the family home. The assigned responsibilities proved that each had a needed service to render. By his conduct, each could merit friends and a respected place in his community. The athletic coach reported the team was not a winning team this year but that it rated recognition for good sportsmanship. Each of the Settlement School staff had a chance to help someone find Social Security and if you knew the stories you would be glad your support made this possible. Spiritual Security, the fifth one, was really the most important of all. When Pi Phi first came to the Burg, the natives were afraid the group wanted to introduce a religious sect. Soon it was realized that the Settlement School was motivated by spiritual ideals and by action, rather than through teaching and preaching, spiritual values were stressed. As is always true, one cannot help another without helping himself and Pi Phi brought distinction to the fraternity world as it sought to share. Memben have grown individually as they unselfishly gave of time and energy in support of the project. THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI When prices are high, money doesn't talk, it whispers; so the Committee, which is responsible for the operation of the Settlement School, was grateful for the alumnae club gifts which totaled $8,854.17. This was an increase of $392.44 over the previous year. The following nine clubs contributed $150 or more. Those marked (') made sizable increases in their gifts. St. Louis $800.00 *Milwaukee $250.00 Kansas City, Mo. . 500.00 Philadelphia 225.00 *Cleveland East 462.50 Indianapolis 210.00 *Wichita 350.00 Denver 175.00 *Everett $150.00 There were 10 Provinces in which the alumni clubs were 100% in support of Settlement School: Beta, Gamma, Delta, Epsilon, Zeta, Iota, Kappa, Lambda, Xi, Pi. The active chapters' gifts amounted to $2305.49 which was $70.72 less than received during the previous year. One reason for part of the deficit was the fact that gifts were sent to the wrong persons and received too late to be credited. Chapter gifts go to the treasurer of Settle ment School. The chairman, Central Office and Arrowcraft are all part of the Pi Phi organization and do hand over the money to the treasurer, but it is a waste of time and postage to make this necessary. The following nine Provinces were 100% in support of the project: Beta, Delta, Epsilon, Zeta, Theta, Iota, Kappa, Lambda, Mu. Three chapters gave $100 or more for their annual gift; it is interesting to note they were the three which did the same last year. Texas Gamma $150.00 Missouri Beta 100.00 Texas Alpha 100.00 These contributions were augmented by $9,142.75 from the Magazine Agency which was an increase of $34.16. Elsewhere will be printed the report which will give due credit to the faithful chairmen but they deserve a word of appreciation in this report. Many individuals and clubs sent Christmas gifts to the School and Health Center. A number of boxes of clothing were received; however only those in good condition should be sent. Money to purchase books for the Grace Coolidge Library was sent to the Director. These books were in memory of various Pi Phis. Individual gifts made it possible to buy a television for the dorm children at Christmas. The Memorial Fund grew this year with thoughtful friends sending gifts to Settlement School instead of flowers. This fund is allowed to grow until some special need arises. Several large gifts such as the $723 Rebecca White Memorial from Ann Arbor, the Bess Hecker Stipes Memorial of $97.50 from Champaign-Urbana and the $70.00 Memorial gift in memory of 5 members of the Columbus, Ohio Club, contributed by 13 friends, plus the many individual gifts will do something special at Settlement School. The legacy left by Bessie W. Brendel, a Pi Phi mi in memory of her daughter DeEtte Brendel was recc It was deposited in a Memorial Scholarship Fund an interest on the $2,934.62 will be given in scholarshi assist the mountain children when needed to con their education. The Arlington-Alexandria gave $300 for the Lois Brock Memorial Room in the Arts and Craft Bull This made possible the complete renovation of the with new flooring, paint and adequate lighting. F nately this improvement was made before Workshop in for jewelry classes. Mr. Balfour sent attractive , plates for the Staff House rooms and the Brock morial. Another unexpected gift, which solved a prol was a generous check with which to purchase flat-war Workshop. Mrs. Robert Davis from Pasadena in add sent a dozen sterling tea spoons for special tea pa Theresa Gibson Graham, who completed her terr Treasurer of Settlement School, gave a parting gift o other dozen sterling teaspoons. Theresa was a vale Committee member and will be missed. As the Committee worked on the budget, it was a of several important facts. Half a loaf is what yon: these days for the same money. Reliable statistics  $1 bought only as much food in 1956 as 41 bougi 1939. This is true for other commodities. Costs have in ,Gatlinburg the same as in all towns. The same gi money sent in 1939 will not begin to do the job in it did then. Old buildings need paint, repairs and Living costs require higher salaries. Schools are with the task of competing with industry's high sal to keep the teachers in the classroom. The LegisL voted a pay increase of $150 to each teacher. The sewe continues to cost 85% to 135% of the monthly 'c bill; the sewer was a needed improvement. The pavic Pi Phi Lane was a project which will pay for itself in 1 years and save man-power. The budget is the Committee's attempt to live b its yearnings. There is a challenge to meet the nee the rural area with a recreation program but the ( mittee must cut the pattern to fit the cloth. It is earnest hope that many will do as some of the clubs this spring in response to the Vice President's fine 1( They found ways to increase their gifts realizing tha budgets have had to increase and that Settlement Sc was no exception. Mrs. Richard James, formerly a Pro) President, is the new treasurer. She has "taking" wa3 let's give her a real work-out this year. Impression without expression is depression. It is hI that this report has given you a clearer impression of Settlement School and that you are thrilled to ha' part in such a far-reaching venture. Committee is, but "It all depends on where you sit how you like the shy VIRGINIA BRACKETT GREEN, Chaim, SETTLEMENT SCHOOL DIRECTOR'S REPORT "Howdy! Come and set awhile." Yes, this could be the greeting of many folks here in Settlement School area. Picturesque grammar is still in use by young and old. When roads come, the way of life of families living along highways changes somewhat from the way of life of families living in the more remote sections. However, when I visited recently in the home of one of our prospective dormitory girls who lives seven miles from the highway, there was a loom in one corner of the living room and television in another. Loom and television! What contrast! The old and the new meeting! And most families have a car of a sort. At Clinic this week Nurse Chalmers reported three mothers came in one car with their eleven children, only one of whom was in school! On our main street there are many neon signs,swimming pools, restaurants, ultra-modern motels, hotels. All this to accomodate the tourists who com the Smokies from all over the United States. Why do come? Of course, innumerable Pi Phis and friends to see Settlement School! Undoubtedly, the majestic b( of the mountains is an attraction. The new Civic C( attracts many conventions. As a consequence, there times when the traffic is bumper-to-bumper on our i street which is the only thoroughfare in the Burg. estimated by authorities that the traffic will double by 1 New highways are in the making. Gatlinburg hope relieve the traffic situation somehow in the near fu The history of Gatlinburg is a true American saga of period of less than one-hundred and fifty years. Yet, 1 is a certain enchantment of the area unlike any in the United States. </p>
      <pb ref="arr7410037_0003" seq="03" n="40-41  "/>
       <p>THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI ng Heritage Beta Phi has shared in this growth for forty-five Our Settlement School has developed out of a ;e of ideals. Yes, there have been many changes ;h the years. We hope, too, that in whatever way rogram develops, it will continue to enrich the )f all concerned. (Including Pi Beta Phis.) It is said re to show results is not the worst thing, but fail face the challenge." Yes, it is challenging and ng to be here at Settlement School. %tories / dormitories are examples of tangible evidence of plishments, also intangible evidences to be seen in )r perhaps never actually seen. Here, there are many experiences all summed up in a justifiable pride girls and boys who have gone out from the school. mhers' Cottage housed seven boys last year. None ad as students. However, interest in athletics pre-. Each was a true mountaineer. A Christmas. gift of a ion for boys and girls served as an attraction and 1 modernize our program. The five dollars required yard and room each month is difficult for some to 1. We do not want a spirit of charity, but a strong of responsibility developed. Not having an assistant Lst year, I worked more with the dormitory children, ruthfully, enjoyed every minute of my time with Center e resume of a year's work is always something of a ma. As Marjorie says there seems to be little differrom that of the year before, however, there is much intangible nature that is given in service. Examns for preschool children, football and basketball nts, dental clinic, Chest x-ray Clinic, weekly Baby s are routine each year. Salk vaccine inoculations Ise has been good. Seventy-one per cent of our stuhave had their final inoculation for polio and are mpletely protected as possible. One of the County is where Marjorie has served has gone with the tg of time. A new highway is going through the I grounds. Two other County schools' days are d to possibly two more years. Children will be com o consolidated schools. Come December, Marjorie have completed her twenty-first year at Settlement 1. veraft !titian of Arrowcraft and/or Settlement School has made in several publications this year, i.e. HOLI-, READER'S DIGEST, SPORTS ILLUSTRATED, FT HORIZONS, MILWAUKEE JOURNAL. Many guished guests and visitors come to our shop. Unedly, our shop is not only nationally known as a handcraft shop, but internationally known. The ern Highland Guild and Southern Highland Guild are well known. Arrowcraft, being a charter member Guild, is still active and a leader. umnae Clubs are the foundation of our Arrowcraft ess. It is with pride that we acknowledge the part :tubs have had in this national project of Pi Beta Fifteen Clubs paid over a thousand dollars to Arrow-within the fiscal year May 31, 1956 to May 31, Nearly sixty weavers bring their weaving to Arrow-each month. Arrowcraft is the main outlet for many men, and has been for many years. The people of area have demonstrated remarkable craftsmanship, .ularly in weaving, woodcarving, basketry, and pot Le resignation of our designer, Tina McMorran, will a fundamental change at Arrowcraft. After nine Tina is retiring, and will do free lance weaving in Direly mountain home nearby. Elizabeth Rue continues anager; Eunice Cole, bookkeeper; Edna Cook, Nella Cook (Hill as of June), Susie Maples (also assistant to the weaving director), and Nadine Grooms continue as native salesgirls. Charlotte Moyers replaces Ruby Watson who resigned as of last December. Ruby is now the proud mother of a baby girl. You ought to know that.. . Our maintenance staff is the same with the exception of a new housekeeper, Mrs. Malvinia Mc Allister. Lela Adams has completed her fourth year as cook. Orlie Watson claims thirty years as maintenance man, his son, Neal, approximately ten years. Richard Watson (minister by avocation) keeps us supplied with chickens, eggs, and vegetables. Mary Finger has come daily for four years to help with chores. Our largest maintenance job of the year was the paving of part of our lane. Some call it pi Phi Boulevard! At least it minimizes dust. There is much maintenance with twelve buildings and seventy-eight acres of land. The usual amount of entertainment was done at Staff House. We were hostesses to groups of Tennessee Gammas, Tennessee Betas, Little Pigeon Alumnae Club, Faculty of Pi Beta Phi, Southern Highland Guild Tennessee Division. Numerous Pi Phis passing through the area have toured the grounds. Many foreign individuals studying crafts come to our place. In fact, there is never a dull moment here. *Workshop Workshop for 1957 was literally bigger and better than ever. Twenty-seven states and seven foreigners from five foreign countries were represented in our personnel. There was one each from Pakistan, Iran, Finland, Puerto Rico, two Phillipines, and three from Thailand. It is amazing to see folks come from so many areas primarily to study crafts and learn new techniques. This certainly is an action program which helps develop physical, mental, moral stamina. One student admittedly came "for refreshment of spirit." A few come "just for fun," but the majority come for the "love of crafts." A new look.. . We cannot help dreaming of larger quarters for a Workshop dormitory. The younger girls are housed (eighteen or twenty of them) in a makeshift school building which was completed in 1913. Our red barn would make a wonderful dormitory to house these girls. The use of the barn could be extended to post-session work-shop. Each year there are several requests for courses later than our scheduled courses with the University of Tennessee. There are several competitive craft schools in the area, and in order to continue, Pi Phi must keep up in present standards of schools. Workshop was under the capable leadership of Marian Heard again for her twelfth summer. Because so many come several summers, we know there is something worth-while being offered. One girl had been here five summers when she was married. We thought surely that would end Annie's days at Workshop. However, for the last two summers she has managed her schedule so she could attend. When her husband came for her this year, he was so enthusiastic that I would not be surprised to see him take time from his engineering problems to enroll. Gifts A great big THANK YOU is extended to each donor. The list of donors will be printed elsewhere, but I wish to thank each one again. It is due to each of you that our national project of Pi Beta Phi survives. Each year the response increases. In order that there will not be too many duplications, we are asking that Christmas gifts be cleared through my office, if possible, by the end of October. A few packages have arrived without the name of the donor. We have to guess (or go into lengthy correspondence) if it was the Alum= Club from the postmark sending the gift. Being here one cannot help THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI realizing the magnitude of our Pi Beta Phi project in the mountains. School Pi Phi has supplemented the curriculum of the County with the addition of Music, Arts and Crafts, Woodcraft, Physical Education instructors. Approximately 600 students were in grades one through twelve. Carl Lewelling served capably as principal for the second year. The school is now Grade "A" of which we are very proud. The County is hoping to add a much-needed lunch-room before the school year ends. Also, additional space for classrooms will have to be provided by the County in the not too distant future. This is due to the consolidation of schools. Classification of English students will help many of the students both those going to college and the followers of picturesque grammar. Well, let's see In reading the above I trust I have given a word picture of your Settlement School to date, and that you will refer to this picture from time to time. Yes, you can be proud of this picture. It is yours. Of course, it would be much better if "you all would cum see us." Respectfully submitted, MARION W. MUELLER, Director ASSETS Current Assets: Cash Funds: 'Petty Cash $ 200.00 $ 200.00 Treasurers Cash on Deposit 28,010.01 35,719.78 Operating Cash Deposits 7,583.14 4,480.05 Savings Cash Deposits 5,772.80 5,860.44 Total 'Cash Funds $ 41,565.95 $ 46,260.27 Investments: Endowment 'Fund Securities $ 67,174.60 $ 68,903.72 General and Sinking Fund Securities 32,771.02 32,771.02 Total Investments $ 99,945.62 $101,674.74 Receivables: Due From Arrowcraft Customers ...$ 7,392.84 $ Due From Arrowcraft Weavers ... Total Receivables $ 7,392.84 $ 12,581.07 Inventories: Arrowcraft Merchandise ,Sc Materials $ 72,636.35 $ 63,951.88 Summer Workshop Materials 2,207.38 2,505.65 Total Inventories $ 74,843.73 $ 66,457.53 TOTAL CURRENT ASSETS $223,748.14 $226,973.61 Fixed Assets: Real Estate $ 5,427.35 $ 5,427.35 Buildings and Improvements 189,297.71 190,686.98 Equipment, Fixtures, Autos 45,384.10 46,372.26 $240,109.16 $242,486.59 Less: Provision for Depreciation 92,189.55 99,055.47 Members of the Committee Pi Beta Phi Settlement School Gatlinburg, Tennessee DEAR LADIES: We have audited the books, records, and support data of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, 'I nessee, year ended May 31, 1957, and present our ref of examination in the exhibits and schedules following. Our audit was in conformity with generally accec accounting standards and accordingly included such t, and confirmations as we considered necessary in instance. In our opinion, the financial position of your cc mittee's accountability together with the results of op( tions for the year ended May 31, 1957 are properly forth in the attached exhibits and schedules. Our audit indicated the usual high degree of dilige and cooperation by your committee in the discharge of obligation to Pi Beta Phi Fraternity. Very truly yours, JOHN W. DORNBLASER, C.P.A Member American Institute o, Certified Public Accountants EXHIBT LIABILITIES Current Liabilities: 5-31-1956 5-31-19! Employment, Sales and Excise Taxes ..$ 416.39 $ 79.'. TOTAL LIABILITIES $ 416.39 $ 791 Reserves Endowment Fund: Created by Annually Adding 75% of Active Chapter Contributions 67,174.60 68,901 Sinking Fund: Special Reserve for Additions to Buildings 15,000.00 15,00( Memorial Fund: Specified Memorial Contributions 725.29 72! General Fund General Fund Accountability 290,894.08 287,52 Analysis of General Fund: Balance 5-31-1956 Deduct: Net Loss 5-31-57 $ 1,640.58 Transfer to Endowment Fund 1,729.12 Balance 5-31-1957 $287,52, 5-31-1956 5-31-1957 9,325.99 3,255.08 Little Rock, Arkax July 6, 1957 PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL GATLINBURG, TENNESSEE 'COMPARATIVE BALANCE SHEET MAY 31, 1957 $290,89,, 3,361 TOTAL FIXED ASSETS $147,919.61 $143,431.12 Other Assets: Prepaid and Deferred Expense $ 2,542.61 $ 2,542.61 TOTAL ASSETS $374,210.36 $372,947.34 TOTAL LIABILITIES AND RESERVES.$374,210.36 $372,94: </p>
      <pb ref="arr7410037_0004" seq="04" n="42-43  "/>
       <p>ZETA PROVINCE CHAPTERS Indiana B Indiana r Indiana A Indiana E ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ Indiana u ZETA PROVINCE CLUBS Bloomington, Ind $ Columbus, Ind Ft. Wayne, Ind Franklin, Ind. .. . . Gary, Ind Hammond, Ind Indianapolis, Ind Lafayette, Ind. .. . Muncie, Ind Richmond, Ind South Bend-Mishawaka Southeastern Indiana Southwestern-Evanston z~~a~~~~~~ "~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ $ 146.00 IOTA PROVINCE CLUBS Avon, Ill. "."."."...' ' $ 20.00 Arlington Heights, ."..'.' 100.00 Champaign-Urbana 100.00 5.00 Chicago Business Women 5.00 10.00 Chicago North ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " 5.00 25.00 . 15.00 Chicago West Suburban ~~6 .5~0 Decatur, o~ Iu zxo 5.00 10.00 Illinois Fox River Valley 10.00 laof.ikestonTlill.le,. .111 ''''''''''''''' 15.00 7.50 ake County 2.00 Monmouth, 10.00 1rttohn 'srhoowrenshiffiWflopseaton 5.00 ....................... 135.00 North Shore, Jr 20.00 Oak Park-River Forest 100.00 Peoria, Ill. ' '' ' ' '' ''' ' ' ' ' '' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' 25.00 Rockford, Ill. . ~~~~ 15.00 South Suburban " ~ 310.00 0.00 40.00 75.00 KAPPA PROVINCE CHAPTERS $ 10.00 5.00 North Dakota A 30.00 Wisconsin A 50.00 Wisconsin B .~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 50.00 Wisconsin r 20.00 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI ipringfield, Ohio ~ 5.00 Tennessee B Tennessee ..`.,..'."...""..' oledo, Ohio ~~~ (50.00 Cleveland z~u ~m~~~5~o 10.00 $ 849.61 ETA PROVINCE CLUBS Blue Ridge, Tenn $ 2.00 C Chattanooga, Tenn. hapel Hill, N.C ~~~~~..~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ ~00 Charlotte, N.C 10.00 Columbia, S.C _ 5.00 Knoxville-Little Pigeon 10.00 10.00 Lexington, Ky. 25.00 Louisville, Ky. ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 50.00 10.00 Memphis, Tenn 22.50 25x0 Nashville, Tenn 20.00 ......... ....... 50.00 17.50 * $50.00 Received, Reported in Prior Year. DELTA PROVINCE CHAPTERS Maryland B ".".'m D.C. A Virginia A Virginia r West Virginia A DELTA PROVINCE CLUBS Va Baltimore, Md Charleston, Clarksburg, W.Va Fairmont, W.Va Morgantown, ~ Norfolk, Va Richmond, Va Roanoke, Va. 'j~'~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ EPSILON PROVINCE 'CHAPTERS Michigan A $ Michigan B Michigan r O Ontario B A EPSILON PROVINCE CLUBS Ann Arbor, Mich * Bloomfield Hills Detroit, Mich Flint, Mich Grand Rapids, Mich Grosse Pointe, Mich Jackson, Mich Lansing-East Lansing London, Ont Southwestern Michigan Toronto, -.. ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' THETA PROVINCE CHAPTERS Alabama A $ 10.00 Alabama B 10.00 Florida A 10.00 Florida B 10.00 Florida r Georgia A ~~~~~~~~~~.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 5.00 Alabama r ' ' ' ' ' ' " . ' ' " . ' ' ' ' ' ' ". " . ". ' ' ' ' ' 5.00 THETA PROVINCE 'CLUBS Athens, Ga. . . Atlanta, Ga 15.00 EijerEinnghaT.11. Ala: 10 5.00 6 Ft. Lauderdale, Fla. 10.00 25.00 Jacksonville, Fla ~~~~~~....~~~~~~~~ 10.00 20.00 3.00 15.00 Miami, Fla 64.86 10.00 Orlando-Winter Park 40.00 10.00 Pensacola, Fla. "."."."."."."...." 25.00 , Petersburg, ^~ 20.00 Tampa, Fla. "."."."."."."."."."." 10.00 $ 212.86 10.00 30.00 IOTA PROVINCE CHAPTERS 50.00 w 15.00 Illinois B-A 19.50 10.00 Illinois E 35.00 -25.00 Illinois Z Illinois H ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 154.00 5.00 5z0 Illinois e 25.00 2.00 5.00 4.00 .* 80.00 $ 453.00 ETA PROVINCE CHAPTERS Kentuckv A. ". ' " . ' ' ' ' ' o 20.00 North Carolina A North ~~7~^~ '~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~ ~ ~ ~ ~~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~0 South Carolina A Tennessee A </p>
      <pb ref="arr7410037_0005" seq="05" n="44-45  "/>
       <p>44 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI KAPPA PROVINCE CLUBS Beloit, Wis $ 25.00 Duluth-Superior 25.00 Fox River Valley, -~ 25.00 Grand Forks, N.D 2.50 Madison, Wis 25.00 Milwaukee, Wis 250.00 Minneapolis, Minn. St. Paul, Minn. . ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~~ ~~ ~~~ ~ ~~ ~ ~~ ~ ~~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ 2.006 $ 387.50 LAMBDA PROVINCE CHAPTERS Arkansas A * 20.00 Louisiana A 75.00 Louisiana B 20.00 Missouri A 60.00 Missouri 13 100.00 Missouri r 5.00 $ 280.06 LAMBDA PROVINCE CLUBS Baton Rouge, La. .".".".".".".".".'$ 5.00 Columbia, Mo 75.00 Fayetteville, Ark 10.00 Ft. Smith, Ark 1.00 Kansas 'City, Mo 500.00 Lake Charles, La 5.00 Little Rock, Ark. ' ' '' '' '' ' '' ' '' ' ' '' ' ' '' ' ' ' 10.00 Marked Tree, Ark 1.50 Mo 800.00 Shreveport, La 10.00 Springfield, Mo 15.00 Texarkana, Ark.-Tex 75.00 Tri State-Joplin ~~.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 10.00 Siloam Springs, 2.00 Pine Bluff, Ark 2.50 MU PROVINCE 'CHAPTERS Iowa A $ Iowa .13 5.00 Iowa r 10.00 Iowa Z 15.00 Kansas A ` 20.00 Kansas B Nebraska B ~ ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " . ' ' ' ' ' ' ' 175.00 0.00 MU 'PROVINCE 'CLUBS Ames, Iowa $ 25.00 Burlington, Iowa 3.00 Cedar Rapids, Iowa 50.00 Council Bluffs, Iowa 5.00 Des Moines, Iowa 100.00 Hutchinson, Kan 100.00 Indianola, Iowa 5.00 Iowa City, Iowa 5.00 Kansas City, Kan 20.00 Lawrence, Kan 25.00 Lincoln, Neb. Mt. Pleasant, Iowa ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 100.00 Manhattan, Kan 65z0 North Platte, Neb Omaha, Neb 60.00 Sioux City, Iowa 2.00 Sioux Falls, S.D. S.D 3.00 Topeka, Kan. Vermillion, S.D. .~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~5.00 W=him Kan " . . ' '.' ' .' ' . . ' 350o0 $ 938.00 NU PROVINCE CHAPTERS Oklahoma A $ 50.00 Oklahoma B ^~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~. ~~ 25.00 New Mexico Texas A 100.00 Texas B ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ '~" Texas A ...." '...' ".' 25.00Ardmore, Okla 25.00 Austin, Tex_ 50.00 Albuquerque, N.M 5.00 Brazos Valley, Tex 5.00 Bartlesville, Okla 5.00 Corpus Christi, Tex 50.00 Dallas, Tex 50.00 Ft. Worth, Tex. ''''''''''''''''' '''' 15.00 Grayson Countv, Texas 2.50 Houston, Tex 100.00 Lubbock, Tex 5.00 McAlester, Okla 2.50 Midland, Tex 10.00 Muskogee, Okla 5.00 Norman, Okla 10.00 Oklahoma 'City, Okla 100.00 Pauls v alley, Oklahoma Ponca 'City, Okla. ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ ~~ Sabine District-Beaumont ' ' ' ' " . ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " . ' " . zoo.on San Angelo, Tex _ Tex 15.00 Stillwater, Okla 20.00 Tulsa, Okla. Tyler, Tex. ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ ^.00G Roswell, N.M. ".".".".".".".".".".' 5.00 Waco, Tex. Wichita Falls, ~~'~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 15.00 El Paso, Tex. ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " . 5.00 XI PROVINCE CHAPTERS Colorado A $ Colorado B Colorado ~ ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ Montana A Utah A xzeRovoNcE CLUBS Boulder, Colo o 1.00 Bozeman, Mont. '''''''''' '''''''''' 5.00 Casper, Wyo 25.00 Cheyenne, Wyo. ' ' '' ' ' '' '' '' ' ' ' '' '' ' Colo. Colorado Springs, ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' '' ' ' ' ' '' '' ' ' ' 25.00 Denver, Colo 150.00 Denver, 'Colorado, . Jr 25.00 Ft. Collins, Colo 5.00 Laramie, Wyo 1.00 Ogden, Utah ".".'~~" . " . " . " .". " . " ." ~3 ~~~~~Colo. ~~.i~~'~..~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 220.00 $ 292.00 Wyoming PI PROVINCE CHAPTERS OMICRON PROVINCE CHAPTERS Idaho A ' '' ' ' ' '' ' ' ' ' ' ''' '' ' ' ' ' '' ' '' '' ' ' ' 25.00 Oregon A 28.49 Oregon B 5.00 Oregon 35.00 Washington A 15.00 Washington B 10.00 OMICRON PROVINCE CLUBS Boise, Idaho . ".".'."."."."."v 50.00 Coos County, Ore 5.00 Corvallis, Ore 5.00 Calgary, Alberta 2.00 Everett, Wash 150.00 Klamath Falls, Ore _ Medford, Ore 15.00 Olympia. Wash Portland. Ore. Richland-Tri City, .~~~ . ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ 100.00 25.00 Salem, Ore. Seattle, Wash. .. . ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 1035.00 25,0 ,SIpokane, Wash. _ acoma Wash Vancouver, B.C 5.00 Wenatchee, Wash. Yakima, Wash. ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ ~~ . 0 Bellevue, Wash 5.00 50.00 50.00 11.00 95.46 20.00 NU 'PROVINCE CLUBS $ _ "."."-'w 25o0 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI 45 California r " . ' ' . ' . . ' ' 25.00 California ' 30.00 California E ".'..' 5.00 California Z Nevada A Palo Alto, Calif. -* PI PROVINCE CLUBS Bakersfield, Calif. "."."."."."."."w 5.00 ....................... Calif 50.00 . 10.00 10.00 Fresno, Calif Calif 10.00 10.00 Honolulu, T. H 5.00 Lajolla, Calif 1.00 La 'Canada Valley, Calif Nev 5.00 Calif 1.00 15.00 Los Angeles, Calif. ~50.00 Mari` County, Calif 5.00 10.00 Pasadena, Calif. "."."."." 110.00 Phoenix, Ariz 5.00 Reno, Nev 10.00 Sacramento, Calif 10.00 San Bernardino Valley-Riverside 10.00 San Diego, Calif 50.00 San Fernando Valley-Encino 10.00 San Francisco 50.00 San 50.00 San Mateo 10.00 Santa Barbara-Ventura 10.00 Santa Monica 25.00 Solano County 5.00 South Coast-Laguna Beach 10.00 Tucson, Ariz. 5.00 Valle), of the Moon-Santa ~~~.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 10.00 Pasadena, jr. . Yuba-Sutter 5.00 Stockton, Calif 1.00 A sense of community is part of the primary needs of man. A community is satisfactory only when it is free: when its members feel that they belong voluntarily, and that their associates share common interests. College fraternities are one proven way to find satisfying community. A few of our universities and colleges, in very recent years, have established "house" systems analogous to the Oxford and Cambridge colleges, which seem to work reasonably well: but the fraternity, the college residential club, remains our principal American means for giving students a home in a college town. Fraternities are more important, indeed, than ever they were before: because the enrollments of most of our universities and colleges are now swollen to bursting-point, and the individual student is lost in a faceless mob of five or ten or even twenty thousand young people. Fraternity life is an important means of redeeming our colleges from the menace of the herd. By RUSSELL KIRK in "The Defense of Fraternities" Make use of your Pi Beta Phi magazine agency did you know that this year it made over $9,000 for the Settlement School? </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



