<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr8210013_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Gordon, Sally Wild</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Fall 1965</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr8210013_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1965</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Gordon, Sally Wild</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 13-16</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">41</note>
                        <note type="Folder">2</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 82, Number 1 (Fall 1965), Pages 13-16.</note>
			<note type="document">arr8210013_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Report on 21st Summer Craft Workshop; How About a Vacation Workshop This Year?</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>The Birth of Arrowmont, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1965-1979</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>
                                <item>Summer craft workshop</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr8210013_0001" seq="01" n="12-13  "/>
       <p>Arizona Beta's First Initiate is . Peggy Johnson Goldwater by Rusty Willard, Arizona Beta March 25, 1965, was a very special day for Arizona Beta at Arizona State University, Tempe, Arizona, and Mrs. Barry (Peggy) Goldwater. As honor initiate of Arizona Beta, Mrs. Goldwater became the first initiated member of the colony, chartered May 1, 1965. Peggy Goldwater was born Margaret Johnson, July 8, 1909, in Muncie, Indiana. She is the daughter of Ray Prescott Johnson, one of the founders of Borg-Warner Corporation. She graduated from Elmhurst High School in Muncie, and then attended Mt. Vernon Junior College in Washington, D.C. After Mt. Vernon, she studied dress design in New York City. On September 22, 1934, she and Barry M. Gold-water were married in Grace Episcopal Church, Muncie. Mrs. Goldwater has been very active in civic organizations in Phoenix, Arizona, where she and ex-Senator Goldwater have resided for many years. She has served as chairman of the education and nominating committees of the Junior League of Phoenix, Inc. She has given service to the Crippled Children's Hospital Clinic, the Veterans' Hospital, the Cerebral Palsy Clinic, St. Luke's Hospital of Visitors, the Social Service Center, and the Fine Arts Association. Perhaps her greatest contribution to a rapidly TEA FOR HONOR INITIATE-Special guests at the tea following Mrs. Barry Goldwater's initiation are pictured with her. They are Mrs. William H. Mansfield, Pi Beta Phi Grand President; Mrs. Henry Moore, Jr., Pi Beta Phi, Grand Treasurer; Mrs. Bernard Erskine, California Delta and sister of Mr. Goldwater; Mrs. Goldwater, and Mrs. Jack Byrd, Phoenix, Arizona, Alurnnce Club president. Peggy Johnson Goldwater growing community was her devoted effort to help found the Planned Parenthood Association of Phoenix. As a very civic-minded young woman, she began her three decades of service to this organization in 1937. The Planned Parenthood Association is predicated upon the conviction that every child should have love and security as a birthright, by al-ways knowing he is wanted by his parents. In Washington, D.C., while her husband served as U.S. Senator from Arizona (1952-1964), she was an advisory member of the Congressional Club, a volunteer for the Red Cross, and a member of the Ladies Senate Group. Being initiated into Arizona Beta climaxed many years of association with Pi Phi. Her sister-in-law, Mrs. Bernard (Caroline Goldwater) Erskine, California Delta, her daughter, who was an Arizona Alpha pledge, and her many admiring friends in Pi Phi introduced her to Pi Phi many years ago. Grand President, Alice Weber Mansfield, conducted the initiation ceremonies, and also attending was Mrs. Henry Moore, Grand Treasurer. As a very outstanding Arizonan, American, wife, and mother, Mrs. Goldwater is welcomed as an out-standing Pi Beta Phi. 12 News from Little Pigeon Edited by Sally Wild Gordon, Wisconsin Design of Happiness A design of happiness is etched in the face of Cora Morton, who has been weaving for Arrowcraft for almost 40 years. For the last 28 years she has woven only the Whig Rose pattern, and has a square of it on her loom in this picture. Both her mother and her daughter have woven for Arrowcraft. At Settlement School Our roots are deep in craft programs. S ince the beginning of Arrowcraft in 1925 we have been conscious of the value of crafts. Arrowcraft was. one of the earliest cottage industries and is a project of which all Pi Phis should be proud. 13 </p>
      <pb ref="arr8210013_0002" seq="02" n="14-15  "/>
       <p>Its most successful season . Report on 21st Summer Craft Workshop The 21st and most successful season of the Pi Beta Phi-University of Tennessee Craft Workshop was held from June 14th to July 17th, with a short session from July 19th to July 23rd, at the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School in Gatlinburg, Tennessee. If alumnae and active chapter members would examine the brochure sent the clubs and chapters describing this school, many more Pi Phis would take advantage of all the opportunities offered. The Workshop schedule is very flexible for the full session is divided into half sessions, each one complete in itself. The tuition for the session is $100.00, the half session $50.00, and the short session $25.00. Laboratory fees and materials are extra. It is possible to attend the full session for as little as $259.50, though this might mean rooming four or more in a room at the Red Barn. Double and single rooms are available at a slightly higher rate. Marian Heard, Pi Beta Phi convention initiate of 1958 and Director of this Craft Workshop, is Professor of Craft Design at the University of Tennessee. Her enthusiasm is an inspiration to all the students. The members of the staff are all experts in their field of art and crafts. This year it was possible to have Charles Bartley Jeffery, B.S., M.A., Director of Art Education at Shaker Heights Schools, Cleve-land, Ohio, give a course in Advanced Enameling during the short session. He is one of the top instructors in enameling in the country and the number that signed up for his class was far greater than the number that could be accommodated. This class drew many professional people, including an architect, a social worker, a dentist, an occupational therapist. In addition, there were craftsmen, teachers, a librarian, a real estate broker, an extension specialist in Home Furnishing, a farmer, students and house-wives. Next year's tentative plans call for three "name instructors" for this short session. This adds greatly to the expense of the Workshop, but the additional prestige these instructors give makes it very worth while. Graduate and under-graduate credit is given through the University of Tennessee. Classes may also be audited by those who are interested in them as a hobby. Six assistantships, covering tuition for one course, room and board, are offered in exchange for part-time work. Of the six assistants, three were Pi Phis and one the daughter of a Pi Phi. The Pi Phis were: Louise Bandy, Georgia Alpha, senior in art, University of Georgia; Patricia J. Crowley, New Mexico Alpha, Graduate student inart and crafts, University of New Mexico; Jo Hansen, Texas Gamma, senior in Applied Arts, Texas Technological College; and Elizabeth Starr Sullivan, daughter of Pi Phi, Mary Elizabeth Sullivan, and junior in Decorative Arts, University of California, Berkeley. The total class enrollment of 183 for all sessions of the 1965 Craft Workshop filled the classes and dormitories to capacity. Some, who came for the first session only, wanted to stay on for the second session, but in many cases it was impossible to accommodate them. Marion Mueller, Director of the Settlement School, turned her office into an attractive bed-room. The student who stayed there asked if she might reserve the same room for next year. Marion moved her office file to a niche in the Staff House and her typewriter into her own bedroom. As many beds as fire rules would permit were set up in the dormitories. This year an unusually large number of young girls attended the workshop. For the first time three high school students were accepted. One couple from Florida, both art teachers, lived in their trailer on the Settlement School property. The students came from 26 different states and from four foreign countries. Two foreign students, one from Jordan and one from Indonesia, are taking graduate work at the University of Tennessee and will return to their respective countries to teach at the college level. Two of the male students, one a florist from Illinois and the other a teacher from Utah, ate their meals at the Ruth Barrett Smith Staff House dining room with the dormitory students. The Staff House dining room was filled with enthusiastic students, some hurrying to finish their Pi Phi Workshop Assistants Louise Bandy, Georgia Alpha, .lo Hansen, Texas Gamma and Trish Crowley, New Mexico Alpha. 14 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI 183 enrolled Top Guest Instructor Many professional people attend `I 5 meal so they could return to the laboratory to work on their projects, some discussing their craft problems, and others relaxing a bit before getting back to their classes. These students are really dedicated to their work. They are at the Workshop to learn all they can in the short time they will be there. Many come with little experience, but leave with the great satisfaction of accomplishment. They have created something of their very own; an enamel dish, a silk screen design, a beautiful piece of jewelry, a woven piece of tweed for a suit, a coffee table with a mosaic top, a piece of stitchery, a set of windchirnes in ceramic. This experience will help those who are teaching the crafts to senior citizens, the occupational therapist in the large hospital, the recreational director of a school for the blind, the florist who is interested in creating ceramic bowls. "Why do we come to the Pi Beta Phi University of Tennessee Workshop ? Because of the congenial atmosphere of the school and the high standards which are expected." As a result, every student doeshis very best and so receives the greatest amount of benefit. This excellent summer Craft Workshop, the nucleus of our Centennial Project, is well established in one of the main Craft Centers in the United States, Gatlinburg, Tennessee. In order to keep our high standards and offer these opportunities in competition with the other fine craft schools, we must provide: Continued maintenance of the building and grounds An attractive environment Top instructors Ceramic wing for the Craft Center Building Better equipment This means great added expense. Please help the Settlement School prepare for our Centennial Project through increased contributions, greater magazine sales and larger Arrowcraft sales in 1965-66. 1965 Arrow Information Bulletin Available The Arrow Information Bulletin for 1965 is now available at the Pi Beta Phi Central Office in a limited quantity. Initiated members who wish to receive this Bulletin should fill in and mail the blank below. Maiden Name Chapter Class Married Name Address ............................... .................... ............................... (Give Zip Code Please) ............................................ i Mail this slip to the PI BETA PHI CENTRAL OFFICE, 112 South Hanley Rd., St. Louis, Missouri 63105 I Please send me a copy of: PLEASE PRINT -- - - ........... -- ARROW Information Bulletin Order Blank ............... ........... . . 1965 Information Bulletin ..... ..... ............................... .. ............................... ... ... ... </p>
      <pb ref="arr8210013_0003" seq="03" n="16-17  "/>
       <p>THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI Winter Pottery Workshop activity-Ken McDonald, pottery Instructor, left and Tom Ela, head ranger, Smokey Mountain National Park. How About a Vacation Workshop This Year? Since 1945, our Workshop, co-sponsored by the University of Tennessee, has grown to be one of the outstanding Craft Workshops in the country. In addition, we have added short workshops in the winter and spring. Five craft workshops were offered this past winter, each one scheduled for five days, with four hour classes. Fine local craftsmen conducted these classes in weaving, pottery, design, jewelry and stitchery. For a short vacation consider a week at one of these workshops in the early spring. Schedules may be obtained from Mrs. Marion Mueller, Director of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee. May L. Keller Award Each year a cash award of $25.00 is given to the chapter which submits the most outstanding original program given to inform members about the Settlement School Philanthropy. This award was named for May L. Keller, because she was a member of the committee which selected the site for the philanthro PY. This year the award was given to Iowa. Gamma, Iowa State University, at Ames, Iowa, for a very catchy informative program, "Jist Talkin'." Craft Workshop Scholarships Congratulation to the three Pi Beta Phi Alumnae Clubs which sent scholarship winners to the Craft Workshop this summer: The Albuquerque, New Mexico, Alumnae Club; The Chicago-West Suburban Alumnx Club ; The Buffalo, New York, Alumnae Club. Mrs. J. W. Normandeau of the Buffalo New York Alumnae Club requested some publicity pictures of the Settlement School, particularly of the Craft Workshop, so the scholarship committee could show these pictures to the girls being interviewed. They awarded a scholarship for room, board, and tuition for a half session to the Craft Workshop, to Miss Audrey Kennedy, a member of the occupation-al therapy department of Meyer Memorial Hospital. For Program Planning: Two Movies 1. Your Settlement School Today An Art and Craft Center. 1964 Convention Film 16 mm. color film with script 35 min. 2. Craftmen's Fair in Gatlinburg. 8 mm. color film with script 15 min. Color Slides The Art and Craft Center on the Settlement School property in the Smoky Mountains Movies and slides available through Mrs. Allen R. Rankin, 2185 Cambridge Blvd., Columbus, Ohio. Publicity and pictures for display available through Mrs. Carl Hensley, 1126 Fay Ave., Kemah, Texas 77565. Active Chapter Interest in Settlement School Diana Williams, Settlement School Chairman for Kansas Beta writes: "We have had several Pi Phi Nights devoted to Settlement School this year. I feel the most enjoyable and educational one was taken from the Settlement School Program Guide entitled, Tittle Rushee At My Knee,' written by Florida Alpha. The Philanthropy Chairman, the Magazine Chairman, and I worked on this program and believe it was well received by our chapter. We girls at Kansas Beta realize the necessity and importance of supporting the Settlement School. Many of us hope that someday we may have the opportunity to visit Gatlinburg." Meet Your Directors Director of Alumnae rograms The office of the Director of Alumnae Programs was newly created when Pi Beta Phi was reorganized in 1964 with the election of seven directors to assist Grand Council. This officer has been trying to evaluate the duties and do those things most helpful in the functioning of the alumnae department of Pi Beta Phi. Alumnae clubs need interesting, clever and educational programs along with the social types of entertainment used for their meetings. This office can act as an exchange for ideas for programming and all clubs can share in it by sending in outstanding programs presented and by requesting material in the files of this office. A letter was included in the spring mailing to alumnae club presidents giving a general outline of program suggestions for the program chairmen to use during the club year. The Director is glad to send detailed material on specific program requests. Copies of the monthly club letters and club re-ports of the Alumnae Province Presidents are sent to this Director and thus a close contact is maintained with them. All letters are acknowledged and through correspondence the successes as well as the problems are known and discussed. In the fall, each club sends a Year Book to the Director of Alumnae Programs and these are care-fully read, acknowledged, and sorted alphabetically into provinces, giving a very fine picture of the work of the alumnae clubs of Pi Beta Phi. In the spring, each club president sends a copy of the club's year end report or Questionnaire showing results of the year's accomplishments. With three hundred thirty-two alumnae clubs, this becomes quite a complete record of alumni work. The applications for the junior Group Scholar-ship which is given by donations from Junior Clubs, were handled by this officer this spring. Gladys Bon, present Director of Alumnae Pro-grams, attended Wyoming University at Laramie, Wyoming and was initiated into Wyoming Alpha chapter of Pi Beta Phi. She has brought alumnae club experience to this office since she had served as secretary, treasurer, Magazine Chairman, and twice as president of her club, during past years. Mrs. Bon has worked in many civic organizations in her home city of Casper, Wyoming. She was active in Girl Scout work and became a member of the Girl Scout Council. She was interested in politics when her husband was a member of the State Legislature. She served as president of the Republican Women's Club of Casper for two years, was a vice president of the State Republican Women's organi Gladys Phillips Ban zation, and represented Wyoming at the national Republican Women's Convention in Atlantic City, New jersey in 1960. Gladys Bon has been active for many years in St. Mark's Episcopal Church in Casper. She was recently Directress of their Altar Guild for two years. Mrs. Bon served from 1960-1964 as Alumnae Province President of Xi Province consisting of the states of Colorado, Montana, Utah and Wyoming. At the 1964 Convention in Victoria, British Columbia Gladys was elected Director of Alumnae Programs which office she is now holding. She has attended three national Pi Phi Conventions in Hot Springs, Arkansas, Washington, D.C. and Victoria, British Columbia and three Officer's Workshops, two in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, and one in St. Louis, Missouri this past June. Mrs. Bon's husband was educated in Switzerland, and was in the insurance business in Casper Wyoming until his death in 1958. She has two children a Pi Phi daughter, Jane Bon Swanton, Wyoming Alpha, who attended Mills College, Oakland California, and is a graduate of the Wyoming University. Her son, William Bon, graduated from New Mexico Military Junior College, attended University of New Mexico and Cornell University, Ithaca New York. He obtained his law degree from the Wyoming University, is a Sigma Chi, and is now a practicing attorney in Casper. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



