<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr8720007_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Beautiful, New Arrowmont</title>

                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Winter 1970</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr8720007_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1970</date>, Beautiful, New Arrowmont</title>

                        <extent>Pages 7-11</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">41</note>
                        <note type="Folder">7</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 87, Number 2 (Winter 1970), Pages 7-11.</note>
			<note type="document">arr8720007_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Arrowmont Dedication; Honors Guiding Spirit</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>The Birth of Arrowmont, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1965-1979</item>
                                <item>Facilities </item>
                                <item>People</item>
                                <item>Administrators</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr8720007_0001" seq="01" n="6-7  "/>
       <p>A hotel as magnificent as its name implies, Pi Phi's Convention hotel, the Hilton Palacio del Rio is indeed a palace on the river. Located in more than just the geographical center of historical San Antonio, the Palacio is situated next to her heart-the beautiful, winding San Antonio River. Bienvenido a San Antonio by NELL THOMAS BON VIVANT LUCIUS BEEBE, among other notables, proclaimed San Antonio to be one of America's three unique cities. Since this statement was made, numerous attractions like Hemisfair Plaza, our fabulous convention hotel and the River Walk have been added to the old historical landmarks of the Alamo, Spanish Governor's Palace, and Missions enhancing the flavor and color of this fascinating city. The Hilton Palacio Del Rio is located in the center of town beside the winding San Antonio River. From the east entrance of the hotel, Pi Phis may step out into the bustling traffic of a sophisticated city with modern stores and restaurants and from the west side walk down a few steps to the Paseo del Rio into quite an-other world where water taxis glide leisurely along, transporting visitors to the quaint shops and eating spots, the beautiful open air Arne-son Theatre, and La Vallita, a little city hidden in the heart of a big one. Two completely different atmospheres to choose from right at your hotel's door step. If you care to venture farther afield there is much more to see and enjoy. San Antonio is rich in military history with fine major installations where such legendary figures as Robert E. Lee, Sam Houston, Douglas MacArthur, and Dwight Eisenhower have been stationed. The Quadrangle at Ft. Sam Houston is the colorful home of a herd of albino deer, turkey, and peacocks who live contentedly among the old cannon and newly installed missiles. If wildlife enchants you, the Brackenridge Park Zoo is the second largest in the nation, where birds and animals thrive in natural settings. The Mexican Market in downtown San Antonio sells wares from Old Mexico and is perhaps more inclined to bargain with you, than the shops along the river. There is so much to see and do in San Antonio most Pi Phis will want to make a return visit. Hasta la Vista ! Looming over San Antonio's Convention Center is the 750 ft. Tower of the Americas. River boats from the hotel to this spot will be one of the fascinating features of the final Convention banquet. u ~ </p>
      <pb ref="arr8720007_0002" seq="02" n="8-9  "/>
       <p>wmont Dedication Dramatically lighted displays are featured in the Arrowmont Exhibit Gallery. A Purchase Exhibition organized by the Carroll Reece Museum, East Tennessee State University, and the Tennessee Artist-Craftsman's Association was on view in the Gallery during dedication week. Pictured in the West Atrium of the Emma Harper Turner Buil4ing are, from the left: Dr. Lura Odland, Dean of the College of Home Economics at the University of Tennessee and a member of the Arrowmont Board of Governors; Miss Jane McCormick, past Dean of Women; Dr. Charles Weaver, Chancellor of University of Tennessee; Miss Marian Heard, Professor of Related Arts and Di-rector of Arrowmont; Lucile McCutchan Woodworth, Executive Coordinator of Arrowmont and Arrowcraft. Honors Guiding Spirit Pr he day dawned bright, clear, and hot in Gatlinburg, Tenn., June 23, 1970, as the Grand Council, directors, province officers and the Board of Governors of Arrowmont gathered to attend the dedication of a dream. It was a day to be remembered by all who were present and it is a day to be remembered by Pi Phis everywhere. The building, airy, at-tractive and functional, is the second century project of The Fraternity, and was dedicated to Emma Harper Turner, one of the most dynamic members ever to wear the Pi Phi arrow. Mrs. Turner was Grand President from 1890-97, and founded and became the first president of the Alumnae Department. In 1910, as a member of the Washington, D.C. Alumna Club, she be-came the guiding spirit in establishing the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, outlining a plan for the establishment of the school in the Appalachian Mountains in honor of the Founders and the founding of The Fraternity. Completed last June at a cost of $650,000, the new classroom building contains 38,200 square feet of floor space. The varying floor levels were dictated by the topography of its site which is along a foothill of the Great Smokies. The series of functional levels are connected by ramps. The complex adjoins the former Craft Center, bringing the total studios to seven, all with outdoor working terraces. The Arrowmont Exhibit Gallery runs centrally between the studios and is 200 feet long with dramatic and effective lighting for art and craft exhibits. On the same le"vel are the auditorium and projection rooms. Dropping down a level are the library and the patio garden overlooking the mountains. On the lower level are offices, confefence rooms and supply areas. The enclosing structure is incombustible consisting of masonry walls faced with native stone, a steel roof frame and a fire resistant roof deck covered with cement asbestos shingles resembling slate that are expected to endure as long as the building itself. No individual has had a more effective role in shaping the dream of Arrowmont than its director, Marian Heard. A director of the summer craft workshops for the past 25 years, she has been associated with the University of Tennessee since 1936 and is Professor of Craft Design in the College of Home Economics. Special greetings and best wishes were extended during the dedication by Robert Gray, Director of Southern High-land Handicraft Guild, top; William L. Mills, Mayor of Gatlinburg, center; and Bruce Scheid, member of the Tennessee Arts Commission, bottom. Now that Arrowmont is a reality, her co-workers see Marian as Pi Phi's craft standard bearer into their second century of service. Arrowmont will follow the broad outlines of the vision of this brilliant designer of craft pro-grams. For her dedication to the craft world, for her untiring efforts in programming the new classroom building, and for her ever-present vision, the library-information center in the banding was named the Marian G. Heard Research Center. And so it is that Pi Beta Phi has built an institution that is designed to help people of all ages, all backgrounds, all social levels. Arrowmont is supported by Pi Beta Phi, and only Pi Beta Phi. No government agencies or other re-search agencies are involved in its funding. This is a project "perfectly timed with the increasing recognition by our government of all aspects of humanitarian and cultural endeavors." 9 </p>
      <pb ref="arr8720007_0003" seq="03" n="10-11  "/>
       <p>The Reverend Charles S. Maples D.D., First Baptist Church, Gatlinburg, who gave the invocation, chats with Henrietta McCutchan Huff, Arrowmont Board of Governors member from Gatlinburg. Elizabeth Yelm Kingman, retiring chairman of the Board of Governors, left, and Mrs. Pauline Gore are delighted with the new building. Mrs. Gore brought greetings from her husband, the Honorable Albert Gore, Senior United States Senator from Tennessee. Grand President Sarahlane Paulson Vanasse receives the keys to the Emma Harper Turner Building from architect Hubert Bebb of Gatlinburg. 10 BOG members Sarah Ruth Mullis and Dr. Odland, and U.T. Pi Phi Pam Phipps are served by Wane Huff Clabo, Iowa Gamma, who was a student at the Settlement School when it was first established. Board of. Governors member Geraldine Hall Dalton and incoming BOG chairman, Hesperia Aylesworth Henderson, admire one of the many wall hangings on display. Members of the Board of Governors are, left to right standing: Louise Rosser Kemp, Betty Bailey Hall, Christine Yerges Conaway, Hesperia Aylesworth Henderson, Mariantha James Williams, Lucile McCutchan Woodworth, Beth Olwin Dawson, Sarah Ruth Mullis, Betty Yelm Kingman, Allece Lock Garrard, S. Lucile Jennings, Geraldine Hall Dalton, Marian G.' Heard, Olivia Smith Moore. Seated: Carolyn Ottenger Kovener, Jean Dunbar Socolowski, Henrietta McCutchan Huff. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



