<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr8230015_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Gordon, Sally Wild</name></author>
                        <author><name>Truax, Camilla Bradley</name></author>
                        <author><name>Hensley, Eloise Glazner </name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Spring 1966</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr8230015_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1966</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Gordon, Sally Wild</name></author>
                        <author><name>Truax, Camilla Bradley</name></author>
                        <author><name>Hensley, Eloise Glazner </name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 15-18</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">41</note>
                        <note type="Folder">2</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 82, Number 3 (Spring 1966), Pages 15-18.</note>
			<note type="document">arr8230015_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">An Open Letter to All Pi Phis; Workshop Does It Again; Crafts Endorsed for Occupational Therapy; Houston Soars High with Arrowcraft Sales</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>The Birth of Arrowmont, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1965-1979</item>
                                <item>Summer craft workshop</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>
                                <item>Healthcare</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr8230015_0001" seq="01" n="14-15  "/>
       <p>Grand Forks Herald Photo by Colburn Hvidston When Greeks Stand Side by Side by Pat Gronowski, North Dakota Alpha President George W. Starcher of the University of North Dakota officially opens GREEK WEEK, 1965 by lighting a torch for the torchlight parade. "GREEK WEEK 1965" at the University of North Dakota was an extra special event this year because of the Greek March for Funds for the University Rehabilitation Center. A state supported institution, the rehab center is located on our campus and is available for use by the physically handicapped of our state. However, many people and doctors are not fully aware of the complete facilities that are offered by the rehab center. The Greek Week .Committee realized that here was an opportunity for us to acquaint not only local people, but North Dakotans as well, with the University Rehabilitation Center. With the help of Mr. Frank Brown, rehab administrator, Miss Judy Olson, president of Pi Beta Phi, headed this Service Project for GREEK WEEK 1965. Publicity was spread throughout the area by newspaper articles, radio interviews, and a full-page picture lay-out in the Sunday newspaper giving complete coverage to the forthcoming Armistice Day House-to-House solicitation. A torchlight parade opened the Greek Charity Drive. We Greeks began at the end of University Avenue from the Kappa Alpha Theta house, down to the Phi Delta Theta house, and to the home of the president of the university, Dr. George W. Starcher, Theta Chi, who officially opened Greek Week. Marching then to the Rehabilitation Center, we sang the Alma Mater before a most receptive audience of thirty! Then eleven hundred Greek members set out and canvassed the city of Grand Forks, collecting just pennies, nickels, and dimes. The money was counted and a check in the amount of twelve hundred dollars was presented to the Rehabilitation Center. In a letter to the UND newspaper The Dakota Student, Eugene Hotaling, Ed.D., Associate Professor of Education and Psychology at Valley City State College, Valley City, North Dakota, stated, "Last Thursday evening's march was important andsignificant for several reasons. One, it reflected the heart and soul of the college and university population of our country. Two, it was a witnessing of what the organized Greek fraternities and sororities accomplish when they get their Greek heads together and go out to accomplish something worth-while. Thirdly, it was a timely recognition by your students of those among us who need your help and support. My sincere congratulations to the Greeks of your campus." A banquet, attended by the members of the twelve fraternities and seven sororities at UND, officially closed GREEK WEEK 1965. A song was composed for the closing of Greek Week by Mr. Robert Van Voorhis, Tau Kappa Epsilon, Assistant Professor of Music at UND, and Miss Kay Torson, Delta Zeta, entitled, "When Greeks Stand Side by Side." Its significance alludes to our Greek System. Hymn to our fraternities; We raise our voices to thee. Our brotherhoods and sisterhoods Are joined by loyalty. To the same ideals that we hold dear We're bound together to serve Our campus and our community, As Greeks we're side by side. Standing side by side, Working hand in hand, In one common bond With Greeks throughout the land. The Unity that now is ours Will never fade away. "Greek" will live with all of us, Its spirit never will die. And we'll remember our college days When Greeks stood side by side. 14 News from Little Pigeon Edited by Sally Wild Gordon, Wisconsin A Design for The Future Inger Hansen, 17, of Fort Worth, Texas, works on a mosaic design in a Recreational Crafts class at the Pi Beta Phi Craft Workshop. Her creative endeavor is finding positive direction in an atmosphere and institution designed to fit the needs of the future. -". At Settlement School ... Our roots are deep in craft programs. ... Since the beginning of Arrowcraft in 192 we have been conscious of the value of crafts Arrowcraft was one of the earliest cottag^ industries and is a project of which all P Phis should be proud. 15 </p>
      <pb ref="arr8230015_0002" seq="02" n="16-17  "/>
       <p>An Open Letter to all Pi Phis . ... With a message of appreciation and invitation A Pi Beta Phi friend told me that she had been asked to make a contribution to a Pi Beta Phi fund and that it should be given on the basis of the question, "what has Pi Beta Phi meant to you ?" She gave the question a great deal of thought and decided that it had meant a great deal to her happiness and companionship on campus friendships through the years that had opened doors to wider friendship. Upon further consideration, she felt that it was all good and well to sit happily in a circle of secure friendship but the more important question to her was, "what does Pi Beta Phi mean to others ?" She found the answer in the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School philanthropy. Settlement School has provided better education and health for school children in the Gatlinburg Area for 54 years. It has provided opportunities for economic and cultural advancement for adults in the area. Because Settlement School offered education through high school, boys and girls were able to go on to college to gain a richer, fuller way of life. From education for children, Settlement School has evolved into an Art and Craft Center, offering adult education in the field of Crafts, and the promotion of native crafts through Arrowcraft Shop. Because the project progressed with the needs of the changing years, Pi Beta Phi means a great deal to thousands of students and adults. The Summer Craft Workshop, co-sponsored with the University of Tennessee, program has offered courses to over 1600 students in 21 years of service. These students are teachers and therapists, who have gone back to their communities to give the benefit of the skills and techniques learned in Workshop to thousands of other students and individuals. Because this friend appreciated the value to an individual to be able to study under a talented instructor who can inspire creative work, she made a contribution of $500.00. This sum was to be used to bring to Craft Workshop an outstanding person in the craft field. Last summer, Charles Bartley Jeffery, Director of Art Education, Shaker Heights School, Cleveland, an instructor in enameling, was brought to Workshop for the last week. The demand for his instruction was so great, the registration had to be closed, with many disappointed students. The need for opportunities to study under inspiring craftsmen is great. Pi Beta Phi is making an unmeasurable contribution to the culture of our country through its opportunity to offer this kind of inspiring instruction. The Members of the Settlement School Commit-tee wish to take this opportunity to express their sincere gratitude to the donor of this inspiring gift. The answer to the question, "what does Pi Beta Phi mean to others ?" is far reaching beyond personal friendships and beyond the community of Gatlin-burg, because the majority who have benefitted are non-members, all ages from 18 to 80, from almost every state in the union, from Canada and 14 different foreign countries. If you are as proud of this great contribution which Pi Beta Phi makes to the world, will you help make contributions through your chapter, your club or as an individual ? Will you help us make the 1966 Summer Craft Workshop the most successful one yet to be offered? I am proud to be the Chairman of the 1966 Settlement School Committee, Sincerely yours in Pi Beta Phi, DOROTHY COLEMAN THORMAN Workshop Does It Again by Camilla Bradley Truax, Louisiana Alpha "Craft Workshop in the Smokies" those were the words on the back cover of the 1965 Spring issue of THE ARROW that opened a whole new world for me. The classes in ceramics appealed most of all for here was an opportunity to develop a new skill that would fit right into my lifelong interest in horticul Camilla Truax checks her windchimes. THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI 17 ture. I have gardened for as long as I can remember and lectured and written on home gardening topics for almost thirty years. It was time for a new interest something creative in the field of art that I prayerfully hoped was not beyond my ability to acquire. But then, how could I lose? Two and a half weeks in the Smoky Mountains where some of the most fascinating plant life in this country abounds is an attraction per se. As it turned out, the classes were so absorbing from the first day when we handled clay, pounding and wedging, rolling and finally forming it into our own designs that there was little time for outside activities by any of the students. It was a privilege to be associated with so many people brought together by a common interesthandcrafts and to be directed by such skilled craftsmen. At once we knew that this was serious business, whether one was working for credit or merely auditing, as I was. The uninitiated cannot know with what fear and trepidation one puts her "firstborn" into an oven to be baked at 2300 degrees and the relief at seeing it emerge in one piece. When the windchimes really tinkled and the slitted, hollow owl glowed in the dark from a lighted candle concealed within, there was also an inner glow of pardonable pride in their creator. And when Instructor Anna Van Aken said, "That's ni-ice," in her inimitable way, well, there was a strong compulsion to return next year, friend husband willing. Crafts Endorsed For Occupational Therapy by Sally Wild Gordon Last June I was privileged to meet Virginia King at the Settlement School. Virginia is Chief of the Occupational Therapy Department, Metropolitan Hospital, New York City and Clinical Instructor in Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, New York, Medical College. In response to a request, she tells of the practical side of the Craft Workshop as she sees it as an occupational therapist. "Occupational Therapy is a many-faceted profession employing a variety of physical and mental skills. One of the most important skills essential in the training of all occupational therapists is the knowledge of certain art and craft activities and of their application to the rehabilitation of the physically or mentally handicapped. While learning the basic techniques of the handicrafts the student therapist is taught the principles of design, how to modify designs, the use of color and various materials within a craft, and quality in workmanship. A long look at the Weaving Studio. "As a student at the University of Tennessee in 1952 I majored in Home Economics and specialized in Related Art and Crafts. For several summers I attended the Pi Beta Phi University of Tennessee Craft Workshop in Gatlinburg. There I took required craft courses and had the rare opportunity of learning from some of the best craftsmen in the area and in the country. To observe the knowledge and skill which each instructor demonstrated in his own particular craft was most inspiring. Their standards of design and workmanship influenced me greatly and I came to appreciate the amount of time and care which has to be spent in creating a truly lovely craft item. "As an occupational therapist today, I often look back to those interesting and busy summers at the Pi Phi Workshop. When I entered Occupation Therapy School I was "one up" on most of the students in the knowledge of the basic crafts. This, undoubtedly, was due to my previous training in them. Not only did these courses help me as an occupational therapy student, but later as a practicing therapist they were invaluable when presenting and explaining a craft treatment program to my patients. Still later, when I took charge of an Occupational Therapy Department and supervised staff therapists, I impressed upon them the importance of good workmanship and proper craft techniques. So, the program at the Pi Beta Phi U. of T. Craft Workshop has played a large part in a positive and productive sequence of learning. The sound and thorough instruction I received in crafts has been of immeasurable benefit to me, to my staff and to our patients." We are proud, Virginia, that the Craft Work-shop was able to play a contributing part in your successful career. </p>
      <pb ref="arr8230015_0003" seq="03" n="18-19  "/>
       <p>Houston Club Soars High with Arrowcraft Sales by Eloise Glazner Hensley Oklahoma Beta Houston Alumnae set up shop for their successful Arrowcraft Sale. Seated is Mrs. Ralph Cantrell, chairman. Standing from the left are Mrs. George Merriman, Mrs. John Butteo, Mrs. Robert Braden and Mrs. Reece Anderson. The Houston Alumnae Club has learned that emphasis on progress means greater success in Arrow-craft sales. Progress, because the theme of its sale in November portrayed the Settlement School as it is today. Progress, as an additional day of sales was carried to the newly developed community surrounding the Manned Spacecraft Center where be-lief in the future and progress reign supreme. With faith and courage (not too unlike that of the Astronauts), the club determined to venture into the unknown with a sale of Arrowcraft so big and interesting that the whole community would be impressed with the importance of good art and craftsmanship. It all began with months-ahead planning to send the chairman, 'Charlie Cox Cantrell (Mrs. Ralph B.), Texas r, to Gatlinburg to shop for the sale while various groups of alumnae went to work creating in their special fields. Charlie's visits with the local craftsmen, with the work shop students in class, and with members of the Staff" gave her an insight which, when added to her natural enthusiasm, inspired everyone to great heights for a great purpose. The recreation room of St. Phillip's Presbyterian Church for one full day was a galaxy of beautiful pieces of art, beautiful ladies and a few men. In addition to the largest display of Arrow-craft ever shown in Houston, there were booths such as the Mothers' Club Kitchen, Pantry and decorative tiles; the junior Group's de coupage waste baskets and letter holders to match ; the Garden Club's aperns, de coupage panels, candle holders and fresh plants, and other Pi Phi groups with lovely hand-made children's clothes and Christmas Tree ornaments. Pi Phi workers wore wine and blue aprons withGreek letters of Pi Beta Phi, which were made by the Mother's Club. Several local artists were there demonstrating various crafts, such as decorative painting, tin flower making, papier machand furniture refinishing, rug hooking and the art of florentine flowers. Judith Williams Baizan (Mrs. Ernesto) , Michigan r, a well known portrait artist, who has painted her way from Grand Rapids to Havana to Houston, was featured as the "Quick-Draw Artist" who turned out portraits in pastels with customers in line all day. Possibly the busiest of all were the cooks and waitresses who prepared and served some 500 lunches from 11 A.M. to 3 P.M. Although the fee was small, as this was intended more as a courtesy to the shoppers, a nice profit was rewarding. The sale in the Clear Creek Area was held in a new shopping center across the street from the Manned Spacecraft Center. To add to the interest in crafts, a large display board told the story in pictures and clippings of Pi Beta Phi's progress in the Smokies from the one-roomed school to the present renowned Craft Workshops. A former workshop student, Lucille Glazner Matkin, Oklahoma B, was there with a display of her creations from work-shop. In all, it was truly a feature of Pi Beta Phi's progress with its unique and most successful philanthropy. Interest and enthusiasm was stimulated and many questions were answered. Of particular interest was the lady from Sweden, who was so happy to do all of her Christmas shopping for her family back in Sweden with gifts of authentic American crafts, which had been so difficult for her to find in the United States. And last, but not least, it was a tremendously successful sale financially. 18 Pi Phi's New Central Office Director With the advent of a new year, Pi Beta Phi also found a new Director of Central Office, Ruth Ann Bandy Edwards, (Mrs. Jon), a Missouri Beta. As efficient and cooperative as she is bright and attractive, Ruth Ann has spent a busy few months getting adjusted to her new responsibilities in Central Office. She is making an ever-widening circle of new friends through her quick and helpful response to all requests sent her way. Ruth Ann had been in Central Office a year and a half before assuming her new duties, following the resignation of Margaret LeSar Head. She had been in charge of the membership department since Au-gust, 1964. A native of Hillsboro, Illinois, she has lived in St. Louis since her graduation from Washington University in 1961. She has a Bachelor of Science degree in retailing. She transferred to Business School at Washington after one and a half years in its Art School, studying dress design. Before coming to Central Office, she worked as an assistant buyer in a St. Louis retail department store. Her hobbies are art, designing, clothing construction and antiquing. Another Missouri Beta Pi Phi, Caroline Barrere, Ruth Ann Bandy Edwards has recently joined the Office staff to take over Ruth Ann's former duties in the membership department. Pi Phi on University of Illinois Alumni Board by Aline Kinnison Sharp To be elected a Director of the tremendous University of Illinois Alumni Association is a great honor, and the Pittsburgh-South Hills Alumni Club is proud that Mary Jane Chandler Seamans (Mrs. Frank L.) has been chosen. Mary Jane is one of the few women on the Board, and will hold this office until 1968. Everything that Mary Jane joins she participates in very actively. She had an outstanding university record, majoring in English, and has been on many committees of the South Hills Club for Twenty-seven years. She served as President in 1943 and 1944. Among the civic organizations to which Mary Jane belongs are: Board Member of the Pittsburgh Garden Center for 12 years, Board Member of Florence Crittenton Home for 14 years, member of the St. Clair Hospital Harlequin Ball Committee for 10 years, and Board Member of Visiting Nurses Association of Allegheny County. She was chosen to be a member of the Fortnightly Review 'Club of Mt. Lebanon, a literary group of 40 women who meet to read and discuss papers on a chosen subject. Top Ohio State Scholars At the annual Panhellenic Scholarship Banquet at Ohio State, the Ohio Beta Pi Phis took top honors. The Pi Phi actives maintained the highest cumulative point hour ratio for the academic year of all twenty-one sororities, a 2.9482 out of a possible 4.0000. The average active point hour of all of the sororities combined was a 2.7698 for the academic year. Winning this honor was only the beginning that evening, for the highest award was also to be theirs. A silver punch bowl is awarded to the sorority which has the highest cumulative point hour for both actives and pledges combined. The magic number was a 2.8935 combined point hour as compared to a 2.7134, the all sorority average. At the same banquet, all of those in attendance were proud of our Panhellenic at Ohio State for it was announced that the O.S.U. 'Panhellenic was awarded the Fraternity Month Award, a national award presented biennially at the Panhellenic Con.-vention held this year at Williamsburg, Virginia. In a time of criticism of the Greek system, it is worth-while to consider its place on campus to strength-en its weaknesses and to continue to work for its continuance when its importance is reaffirmed. 19 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



