<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr8220023_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Gordon, Sally Wild</name></author>
                        <author><name>Kyle, Evelyn Peters</name></author>
                        <author><name>Barnette, Mary Elizabeth Lasher</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Winter 1965</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr8220023_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1965</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Gordon, Sally Wild</name></author>
                        <author><name>Kyle, Evelyn Peters</name></author>
                        <author><name>Barnette, Mary Elizabeth Lasher</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 23-26</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">41</note>
                        <note type="Folder">2</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 82, Number 2 (Winter 1965), Pages 23-26.</note>
			<note type="document">arr8220023_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Pillars of Progress; Craft Workshop Praise with Panhellenic Flavor; Craft Workshop Scholarship Success Story</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>The Birth of Arrowmont, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1965-1979</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>
                                <item>Facilities</item>
                                <item>Summer craft workshop</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr8220023_0001" seq="01" n="22-23  "/>
       <p>22 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI "Getting into college has become an end in itself, overlooking that the main objective is graduation four years hence," eliminate bunched up applications and as a result make the admissions process less frightening, less time-consuming, not to say, less costly. According to Harry C. Biser, director of the Ad-missions at Stephens College, "One of the real problems today is the complete lack of objectivity on the part of some students and their parents. Getting into college has become an end in itself, over-looking that the main objective is graduation four years hence." Only through a thoughtful family conference can a student and his parents begin to decide what kind of a school to consider at all. Later, consultation with the high school counselor can give further in-formation, plus an insight into the student's potentialities and interests from his high school record. There are books which help, too, such as one of the good compilations of accredited colleges, giving costs, programs of study, entrance requirements, strength of faculty. There are also catalogues and other literature in the hands of the counselor, perhaps giving the freshman class "profiles" of certain schools. When the field has been narrowed, the best way to evaluate is to make a visit to a few schools. The spring of the junior year is about the right time. Despite the number of touring high school students (Ohio Wesleyan University, for instance, which accepts a freshman class of 800, expected 3,000 high school visitors during 1964-1965), the schools manage to keep the welcome mat out. Usually a personal interview with Admissions is possible, plus a conference with someone on the staff in a student's field of interest, ending up with a campus tour. All that colleges ask in return is that visitors try to write ahead making a date for the visit and be well pre-pared (with high school transcript and available test scores) and reasonably brief with questions. Back home again, it is now, before a word has been written on any application blank, that the problem of admissions can best be tackled. Why not a clear-eyed look at the why of college choice? Perhaps the advice of President Vernon R. Alden of Ohio University is not amiss when he suggests seeking an education, not seeking entrance to a particular "name" college. It is true, many people seem tobe equating the name of the school with the quality of its education. Those who are really smart look more deeply than this. What they see is a long roster of colleges in the United States, all of which offer fine educational opportunities. It's true, some have names known to everyone; others have names less well known. Some have mailboxes overflowing with applications for entrance; others have mailboxes with plenty of room. The way is open for those students who want to fight through the crowd at Admissions, but open, too, (and much more widely open) for those willing to choose a more leisurely pace where standards are still good but competition is less keen. Whatever the choice, and even though on occasion the stories about admissions are frightening, for the student who has a modicum of intelligence and a large amount of perseverance, there's no need to be afraid. The situation is more hopeful than hopeless. Colleges today and tomorrow will surely have room for one more. Suggested Reading How To Get Into College, Frank H. Bowles (revised edition). E. P. Dutton and Co., Inc., 1960, paperback, $1.15. 185 pp. How To Prepare For College, Abraham H. Lass. Pocket Books, Inc., 1962, paperback, 95. 466 PP. Planning For College, Sidney Margolius. Avon Books, 1965, paperback, 75 . 304 pp. A Handbook for the Counselors of College Bound Students, published by the Association of College Admissions Counselors, 610 Church St., Evanston, Ill., 1964-66, soft-cover $5.00; hard-cover $6.00. The New American Guide to Colleges, Gene R. Hawes (second edition). The New American Library, 1962, paperback, 75. 349 pp. Lovejoy's Complete Guide to American Colleges and Universities, Clarence E. Lovejoy. Simon and Schuster, Inc., 1943, paperback, $3.50. 335 pp. Many additional books, similar to these, are avail-able in high school and public libraries. News from Little Pigeon Edited by Sally Wild Gordon, Wisconsin A Stitches for Our Times A visitor at the Pi Beta Phi Craft Center gazes intently at a handwoven pillow with de-sign in stitchery. On the wall three interesting stitchery techniques are shown-by ma-chine, an applique and three dimensional. The work represents one of the many arts and crafts courses offered at the Pi Beta Phi Craft Workshop, a program truly in step with our times. At Settlement School . Our roots are deep in craft programs. . Since the beginning of Arrowcraft in 1925 we have been conscious of the value of crafts. . . Arrowcraft was one of the earliest cottage industries and is a project of which all Pi Phis should be prow . 23 </p>
      <pb ref="arr8220023_0002" seq="02" n="24-25  "/>
       <p>Pillars of Progress by Evelyn Peters Kyle Grand Vice-President of Philanthropies Down the echoing corridors of our history of the last ninety-eight years are the supporting pillars of progress of Pi Beta Phi. John Ruskin said, "Let every dawn of morning be to you as the beginning of life and every setting sun be to you as its close; then let every one of these short lives leave its sure record of some kindly thing done for others, some goodly strength or knowledge gained for yourself." Surely some glimmer of this philosophy conveyed itself to the Swarthmore Convention of 1910, when Pi Beta Phi envisioned a Settlement School in the Tennessee mountains, in order that those who lived within that area might gain knowledge and strength. Now after fifty-three years we look back upon our achievements and forward to new accomplishments. The now thriving community of Gatlinburg can recall the one room school house and thirteen pupils, which grew to several buildings and grades one through twelve with an enrollment of eight hundred. It can remember the Health Center, which brought many needed services to the residents; the Arrowcraft Shop, which furnishd an outlet for beautiful native handicrafts fashioned by local weavers; and in 1945 the beginning of the Summer Craft Workshop co-sponsored by Pi Beta Phi and the University of Tennessee. The Settlement School of today is a very different place than the Settlement School of 1912. Today it provides two elementary teachers for music and arts and crafts, as the County has assumed more and Evelyn Peters Kyle more of the responsibility and operation of the school. Alumni Club and active chapter sales are the nucleus of arrowcraft support. Contributions from chapters and clubs also support the Red Barn program, and the Summer Craft Workshop. Formerly we were able to help the citizens of a given area. With the continuation of the internationally known Craft Workshop we have horizons unlimited. People from all walks of life and from many parts of the world may now enjoy its advantages, as we teach the preservation of native American crafts and Gatlinburg becomes an outstanding craft center. One of the most thrilling experiences is to be present at an Open House following the close of a session at Craft Workshop. The talent and expression displayed in the tangible results are almost beyond belief and definitely more than satisfying to one's artistic sense and inclination. The Settlement School today is concrete evidence that one of the kindest things we can do for others is to continue our strong support of a unique project that brings knowledge and strength to many people. It is one of Pi Beta Phi's greatest prides, the living memorial to our Founders, the "sure record of some kindly thing done for others," and a true pillar of progress. Craft Workshop Scholarship As has been its policy for the past twelve years, the Southern California Area Council of Pi Beta Phi is again offering a scholarship to any qualified active or alumna member in good standing of Pi Beta Phi for one full five week session of the 1966 Summer Craft Work-shop at Gatlinburg, Tenn. This scholarship includes room and board, tuition and partial transportation costs. Information and application blanks may be obtained by writing before April 1, 1966 to Mrs. John R. Andrews 119 No. Windsor Blvd. Los Angeles, Calif. 90004 -3 1966 Workshop Dates Dates for the 1966 Pi Beta Phi-University of Tennessee Summer Craft Workshop sessions are as follows: Full session June 13 July 15 First session June 13 June 27 Second session June 29 July 15 Short session July 18 July 22 24 Craft Workshop Praise with Panhellenic Flavor Sally David of La Grange, Illinois, a third year fine arts major at Millikin University, Decatur, and a member of Alpha Chi Omega sorority, attended the Summer Craft Workshop at the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School this past summer. She was the recipient of a scholarship awarded by the Chicago West Suburban Alumnae Club and she attended the full five weeks at the Workshop where she took courses in weaving and pottery. Miss David gave a most interesting report on her experiences to the Pi Phis at the home of the Alumnae Club president, Mrs. George H. Crane, Jr., in La Grange Park. "The total atmosphere was so artistic and this impressed me very much," Miss David reflected and went on to explain that "of the courses offered there, including weaving, textile design, jewelry, enameling, pottery, metal work and recreation crafts, a student can only manage two or three at the most during the summer. As a result, a means has been devised to enhance the artistic feeling a of the students' life there by having a constant change of displays of their work from the various courses throughout the meeting rooms and the dining hall. This stimulates everyone's interest in the entire artistic program. " She showed samples of the various weaving pat-terns she had made on the loom. Her four yard piece of navy and light blue wool and mohair tweed and the many interesting pieces of pottery she had created showed the high quality of work she accomplished at the Workshop. One of her most beautiful and unusual pieces was a relief picture made of clay and done from a sketch which she made at Andrew Bald, a lovely picnic spot in the mountains. It is gratifying to know that Miss David has applied for an assistantship at the Craft Workshop next summer, thus emphasizing her interest in our outstanding Pi Beta Phi University of Tennessee Craft Workshop program. Editorial Farewell to Pi Phi Health Center from the Gatlinburg Press Forty-five years ago, Miss Phyllis Higinbotham became the first graduate nurse at the Phi Beta Phi Settlement School. The feats that she accomplished can best be realized in a report she made: "In the many months without a doctor in the area, we were dependent on our own resources. We improvised splints, applied pressure bandages, used suction for snake bites and took care of axe cuts, gun-shot wounds, convulsions and bear scratches." In 1936 Mrs. Marjorie Chalmers took over the duties as head nurse at the Health Center. Since that time 26,115 field visits have been made, 71,673 office calls have been NATIONAL PARK PERSONNEL VISIT CRAFT CENTER September 14, was a busy day for the Pi Beta Phi Craft Center at Gatlinburg. The Center was a stop for a Craft Tour of the wives of the National Park Superintendents during a convention. Approximately 250 visitors viewed the work of the adult classes of late winter, spring and of summer workshop students. The exhibit of over 200 pieces included jewelry, enameling, silk screen, block print, vegetable dyeing, Castolite de-signs, weaving, stitchery, mosaics, rugs and pottery. Displayed with the crafts were different kinds of looms, a small spinning wheel, craft books, and craft magazines. Marion Mueller, Director of Settlement School is shown greeting the tour chairman, Mrs. John Morrell. treated and 36,216 shots have been given. Mrs. Chalmers, like Miss Higin'botham, made many of those field visits on horseback. And now the Pi Beta Phi Health Center, once the major medical facility for Gatlinburg, is no more. No fanfare, no bands. It left just as quietly as it came. It did not quit through necessity. The needs of the community have changed. The Sevier County Health Department will be taking over operation of the monthly Well Baby Clinic and the Immunization Clinic at the new Gatlinburg Medical Center. The adage you don't miss it until it's gone holds very true. We owe a very deep debt of thanks to all of the past workers and especially should we thank the present members of the school, the director, Mrs. Marion Mueller, the nurse, Mrs. Marjorie Chalmers, and all the others who have made the Settlement School the 'big success that it is. Summer ARROW Deadline Copy for the Summer ARROW should reach the editor by March 5. Alumni Club corresponding secretaries should send the name and address of club recommendation chairmen to the Pi Beta Phi Cen tral Office, 112 South Hanley Rd., St. Louis, Missouri 63105, in advance of this date. 25 </p>
      <pb ref="arr8220023_0003" seq="03" n="26-27  "/>
       <p>Buffalo Alumnae Club's Craft Workshop Scholarship Success Story by Mary Elizabeth Lusher Barnette, Ohio A The Summer Craft Workshop at Settlement School provided the "best craft instruction I've ever had" according to the enthusiastic report of occupational therapist Audrey Kennedy, winner of the first arts and crafts scholarship given by the Buffalo Alumnae club. Her experience justifies the club's 1964 decision to establish a new local project linked to the expanding Arts and Crafts in Gatlinburg. Miss Kennedy is employed at Buffalo's Meyer Memorial Hospital where she teaches crafts in the pulmonary division to patients afflicted with tuberculosis and emphysema. The scholarship was offered by letter through hospitals, churches, recreational centers, schools, and various service organizations, and the selection was made following written applications and personal interviews. Since her primary function is to discover and en-courage each patient's talent, the winner works in all types of crafts and wanted to expand her knowledge in areas where her experience had been limited. In Gatlinburg she concentrated on weaving and silk-screen design, earning three college credits in the intensive two-week session where she found the standards very high and the work equally satisfying. Initially Miss Kennedy, who plans to continue her college education this fall at the University of Buffalo night school, expected to teach, but in occupational therapy she feels she is "helping persons, who wouldn't have a chance any other way, to achieve the satisfaction of finding that they can be creative." In the hospital the crafts are begun as a diversional activity, developed further into avocations, and in many cases progress to prevocation preparation. When the illness or its aftermath prevents a person from returning to his former work, occupational therapy become the route to a new job suited to his limitations. Miss Kennedy has also worked with psychiatric patients using crafts as a diagnostic tool, and to relax patients and build their self-confidence. Supplementing the class work at Settlement School were field trips into the Tennessee mountains where the students observed the area's own craftsmen at work on pottery, weaving, broom-making, and wood-working using the materials at hand and producing truly creative design inspired by the surrounding nature. In the classroom the students were taught the techniques and then encouraged to seek design ideas on their field trips. Miss Kennedy found one she used later in silk screening drapery material whenshe observed an arrangement of knot-holes in a tree, and she finds she can provide the same sort of guidance in making patients aware of design and beauty around them. The craft school is unusual itself in its lack of a typically institutional structure, Miss Kennedy discovered. She found charm in the small buildings housing different crafts, in the common dining hall and dormitories decorated appropriately with hand-made crafts and fabrics, and in the beautiful countryside. There was a cosmopolitan atmosphere too, for the student body included persons from all sections of the United States and from both Indonesia and Jordan as well. It was an educational experience to observe how each person's designs reflected her own culture, the scholarship winner noted, and she found students and instructors alike generous in their sharing of experiences, training, and ideas far beyond the classroom period. The Buffalo Alumnae Club plans to repeat its tuition-room and board scholarship offer as often as possible, making it available to persons living in its area, in the belief that this is a distinctive means of serving both the community and Pi Beta Phi Fraternity. Attention: Art Majors Art and Crafts Majors Six graduate assistant Craft Workshop Scholar-ships are available for the 1966 Summer Craft Workshop, co-sponsored by Pi Beta Phi and the University of Tennessee. Tuition for one craft class, board, and room are offered in exchange for part-time work. Applicants should be seniors or graduates under twenty-five years of age. For further information on these scholarships write immediately to Mrs. Marion W. Mueller, Art and Craft Center, Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee 37738. All applications must be made by April 1, 1966. Coming in Spring ARROW Courses that will be offered in the 1966 Summer Craft Workshop sponsored by Pi Beta Phi and the University of Tennessee. 26 FROM pi phi pens Edited by Mary Elizabeth Lasher Barnette, Ohio A MARJORIE M. BEACH, First the Seed . . ., J. F. Rowny Press, Publishers, 264 pp. This is a travel book, but not in the ordinary sense. It's as much about a journey in search of a new approach to life as it is about the world's exotic lands and as much a Baedeker to mankind's inner differences as a guidebook to the labyrinths in its cities. In an earlier volume, The Mayor's Wife, Mrs. Beach described her role as the wife of the man who defeated the Pendergast machine in Kansas City, it was an arduous life, and both husband and wife had anticipated sharing an around-the-world holiday after which they would settle on the West Coast near the ocean. Albert Beach's sudden death ended that dream, but four months later Marjorie Beach was brought a legacy which gave her hope and, in time, goals. The mayor's chauffeur Henry Clay had saved the collection of maps on which Mayor Beach had planned the ocean journey and with them was a sack of sorghum corn seed Clay had given him with instructions to plant the seeds along the trip as "a little advertising for Missouri." "Mrs. Beach," said Henry Clay, "you must carry out the trip he had planned for you. Go 'round the world. Be sure and take them sorghum corn seeds with you." Though it was 1939 and the shadows of war to come were lengthening, within two weeks Mrs. Beach, with a pair of suitcases and the bag of seeds, was en route, and her intimate, friendly, often amusing chronicle carries the reader effortlessly with her. She planted her first seeds in a windowbox high above Paris streets. Others went in the ground near an oriental temple, on a mountain slope, and in other fertile spots in every country the author visited. Of greater significance, however, were the seeds of broader understanding, of new interests, and of wider goals that were nurtured by her journeys and the accompanying associations with all matter of people. Over twenty-five years later Marjorie Beach is still accomplishing, still giving, and her book, written to "show all those who have lost a loved one that they are still needed," should be especially meaningful reading for persons in need of encouragement. It is also good entertainment. AUTHOR INTEREST: Marjorie Marshall (Mrs. Albert I.) Beach, Kansas Alpha, fulfilled her husband's other goal and makes her home in Laguna Beach, Calif., where she is a factor in civic, religious, cultural, and charity circles just as she was in Kansas City. In lonely people she has found "a real purpose for living," and she has made her home overlooking the Pacific a haven for them. Helen R. Caswell, A Wind on the Road, D. Van Nostrand Company, Inc., 107 pp. As refreshing as its title, this book for pre-teens is a welcome change from the formula-series variety one sees too much of at this age level. Esther, the heroine, is a believable ten-year-old whose adventures are exciting enough to make good reading without being absurd. Furthermore, Mrs. Caswell herself created the blockprint illustrations, and thus there are none of the irritating discrepancies one often finds between an author's description of a thin, straight-haired girl and the illustrator's glamourous idealization of the character. In fact, the work of the artist-author enlivens the prose and contributes to the story line. Strong characterizations and vivid descriptions, especially of gypsy camp and of a 1910 family picnic near the McKenzie River in Oregon, the book's locale, enrich the presentation and give the reader something more than entertainment. AUTHOR INTEREST: Helen Rayburn (Mrs. Dwight) Caswell, Oregon Alpha, is the versatile mother of five, who majored in fine arts at the University of Oregon. She began painting after the first fifteen years of marriage, and since has become a professional portrait artist as well as a writer of narrative poetry, for which she won a James D. Phelan Award in 1958, magazine articles, and now a story for boys and girls. Her husband is a physicist, and their three-story home "cluttered with books, antiques, and projects" reveals the family's numerous interests, with special emphasis on music and travel. RANDOM NOTES: Gertrude Castellow (Mrs. Aaron) Ford, D.C. Alpha, whose book, A Rose By Any Name, was reviewed in the summer issue, is continuing her crusade in support of the Earl of Oxford as the true author of Shakespeare's plays and sonnets. In addition to speaking on the subject she has written and illustrated several poems, some answering directly the challengers of her theory. 27 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



