<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr8510023_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Arrow in the Smokies</title>
                        <author><name>Kingman, Elizabeth Yelm</name></author>
                        <author><name>Prince, Marion W. </name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Fall 1968</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr8510023_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1968</date>, Arrow in the Smokies</title>
                        <author><name>Kingman, Elizabeth Yelm</name></author>
                        <author><name>Prince, Marion W. </name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 22-24</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">41</note>
                        <note type="Folder">5</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 85, Number 1 (Fall 1968), Pages 22-24.</note>
			<note type="document">arr8510023_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Chairman, Board of Governors, Arrow in the Smokies; Director, Arrow in the Smokies</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>The Birth of Arrowmont, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1965-1979</item>
                                <item>Funding</item>
                                <item>Facilities</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr8510023_0001" seq="01" n="22-23  "/>
       <p>4PPOW iii the ~~nol~~e~ CHAIRMAN, BOARD OF GOVERNORS, ARROW IN THE SMOKIES The Settlement School began its new phase of development when it launched "Arrow in the Smokies" after the 1967 Convention. Three fine reports on the background of this project have been printed in the September, 1967, ARRow. One is the report of the Grand Vice President of Philanthropies, Evelyn Peters Kyle, and the other is the re-port of the outgoing Settlement School Chairman, Dorothy Coleman Thorman. The third is the report of the Settlement School Director, Marion Mueller Prince. These re-ports are milestones of fraternity history, fine resumes which present the hopes and ideals of the new phase, while also presenting the successes of the old. My work as Chair-man of the Board of Governors has been assisted by Dorothy Thorman and her Settlement School Committee in many instances of advice and help, and by Evelyn Kyle, whose support and knowledge has been invaluable. Marion Prince has given of herself and has extended her administration several months after she had hoped to retire. The new phase in the continuation of our philanthropy is progressing but cannot be hurried. Continuity in operation has been slowed somewhat by the advent of a new Board and changes in operating personnel. Mrs. Marjorie Chalmers took over the duties of Arrowcraft Manager in October, as a temporary position until a new manager could be found. Marion Mueller Prince (Mrs. Herbert), who has been Settlement School Director for a number of years, continued her administration after January 1, 1968, when it became apparent that there was no 'Pi Phi yet available to take over. The ability and devotion of these two Pi Phis, who were fulfilling the fraternity's special needs during this period, will be long remembered. My deep appreciation to them. Miss Marian Heard, as Director, again conducted a successful Craft Workshop in the summer of 1967. Subjects taught at this accredited Pi Beta Phi University of Tennessee summer program were: weaving, textile design, ceramics, enamelling, jewelry, recreational crafts, and stitchery. Miss Heard is Professor of Craft Design at the University of Tennessee. For many months she has spent additional time ' in planning the arrangements, equipment and innovations of the projected Arrow in the Smokies class-rooms, as well as other features. These have been incorporated in the recent architectural plans. We are fortunate that we have a Pi Phi of such creative talents. From my close association with the museum field and its publications I have become aware of the growing importance of the crafts as activities which enhance the very fabric of civilized society in all aspects. The new artistic ex-plosion has been making itself felt even more in the areas of advertising, industrial design, interior decoration. In addition, a growing awareness of creative projects which are based on artistic knowledge is reflected in increased attendance at museums in their tours and their arts and crafts classes, and is also reflected in the arts taught in the elementary schools of the nation. Arrow in the Smokies will become one of the few Craft Centers pioneering in the enrichment and promotion of Craft Design, while preserving the fine aspects of the traditional in crafts. Our new Resident Manager was found in April and took over her duties on June first. She is Mrs. Lucile Wood-worth, a Pi Phi of exceptional administrative knowledge and experience. She assumes both the duties of the past Settlement School Director and the Arrowcraft Manager. She will coordinate all administrative activities of Arrow in the Smokies under its Board of Governors. We have been fortunate that she became available this Spring. Our first Board of Governors' meeting took place July 12-14, 1968, at Gatlinburg, Tennessee. The Board members were appointed by the Vice President of Philanthropies over the winter months. A glance at the list of its Pi Phi members, published in the most recent Arrow, plus the University of Tennessee representatives, will indicate the fine caliber of this Board. Recent announcements by Grand Council have moved Evelyn Peters Kyle to Grand Alumnae Vice President and Orpha O'Rourke Coenen to Grand Vice President of Philanthropies. Mrs. Kyle's devotion and knowledge of our great philanthropy will surely spark much interest among Alumnae, and meanwhile we shall look forward to working with Mrs. 'Coenen and her special talents. After the Board of Governors' July meeting special cornmitttees and assignments can be announced. Mrs. Adin Hall has already been appointed to work with the Little Pigeon Awards. She is also Chairman of Ways and Means, working closely with the Board Chairman. Mrs. Floyd R. Hightower is, at present, circulating the special slide lectures on Arrow in the Smokies for Pi Phi groups. Mrs. James Huff will continue with Publicity and Public Relations in Gatlinburg. She has asked to be replaced as Secretary on the Executive Committee, so this position has been filled by Miss Lucille Jennings. Dean Lura Odlund, Dean of Home Economics Department, is also a member of the Executive Committee on the Board of Governors. Mr. Hubert Bebb, of Gatlinburg, was appointed the architect of the Arrow in the Smokies buildings, to be constructed as time and money becomes available. He is revising plans already drawn for a special exhibit wall, an architectural feature along the grass strip at the front of the Pi Beta Phi property adjoining the Arrowcraft Shop. Presently being reviewed by Grand Council is the completed drawings of the Classroom Building. The Arrowcraft Shop will also be enlarged in due course. There are delays in the actual ground breaking because of decisions that must be made carefully and priorities to be considered because of the care we must exercise in the spending of funds. Many "loose ends" can be tied together properly after our first meeting this summer. I hope that we can make a good start in helping Pi Phi realize its great plan for this unique Craft Center. Much creative planning has gone into this project long before my appearance as Chairman. As the ideas become forged into the goal envisioned, many of us are absorbing enthusiastically the spirit of this great philanthropy project. I am happy to be a part of it. Pi Phis everywhere, this is your project, and it is worthy of your dedicated support! ELIZABETH YELM KINGMAN DIRECTOR, ARROW IN THE SMOKIES Highways, expressways, and airlines lead to Gatlinburg via Knoxville. Gatlinburg, a mountain resort population of twenty-three hundred, is a tourist mecca with accommodations for thirteen thousand. The area attracts visitors to the adjoining Great Smoky Mountain National Park. An increasing attraction of many is crafts of the area. Few of these crafts are in evidence on Parkway, the arteryof Gatlinburg. However, Pi Beta Phi office and Arrowcraft Shop are on Parkway. The craft school area and Settlement School buildings are slightly and comfortably removed from the Parkway. In summary my last year at Settlement School, our Pi Beta Phi Memorial to our Founders, could well be ex-pressed in one sentence there has been constant effort to preserve the good of our past, in preparation for launching the project of the second century, ARROW IN THE SMOKIES. It has been a privilege and a pleasure to work with the many loyal Pi Phis and Clubs in this renowned project. Many friendships have developed through the years. Pi Phiroots are deep. There are many hours and years of devoted work of loyal Pi Phis in our Settlement School. My deepest appreciation is extended to each and every one. It is my sincere wish that these roots will grow into a large development that of ARROW IN THE SMOKIES. MARION W. PRINCE AssETS BALANCE SHEETS PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL May 31, 1968 LIABILITIES AND FUND BALANCES Current Funds Liabilities: General: Accounts payable $ 2,674.67 Due to Current Fund Re373.39 stricted Due to Pi Beta Phi Contingent 24,000.00 Fund Arrowcraft Shop and Magazine $ 1,813.92 Agency: Accounts payable Due to Current Fund General 34,959.11 Due to Centennial Fund 5,000.00 Fund balances: $ 40,375.14 General Arrowcraft Shop 136,578.45 Magazine Agency (deficit) (1,337.16) Restricted: $ 711.91 Matthew J. Wilson Income Fund: Fund balance at beginning of year Dividends 619.47 Library Fund: $ 866.94 Fund balance at beginning of year Craft books purchased 568.30 Current Funds General: Cash $ 21 ,229 .40 Accounts receivable 2,156.36 Craft supplies at cost 6,972.74 Prepaid expenses 2,105.59 Due from Arrowcraft Shop ($34,205.67) and Magazine Agency 34,959.11 $ 67,423.20 Arrowcraft Shop and Magazine Agency: Cash $ 28,462.71 Accounts receivable 19,670.65 Inventories at lower of cost (first in, first-out method) or market 128,880.96 177,014.32 $244,437.52 Restricted: Cash $ 1,256.63 Due from Current Fund General 373.39 1,630.02 $ 27,048.06 41,773.03 $ 68,821.09 175,616.43 298.64 $246,067.54 Special Funds Land Sale Fund: Cash $ 22,430.28 United States Treasury bills at cost (approximately equal to market) 199,854.14 Mortgage note receivable 8,246.14 $230,530.56 Centennial Fund: Cash $ 38,986.77 United States Treasury obligations at cost (approximately equal to market) 177,390.78 Due from Arrowcraft Shop 5,000.00 221,377.55 $451,908.11 Endowment Funds Settlement School Endowment Fund equity (10%) in Pi Beta Phi Trust securities at cost (approxi mate market value $102,000.00) $ 87,393.42 Brendel Scholarship Fund savings account 3,636.29 Matthew J. Wilson Fund corporate stock valued at market value at date of acquisition (approxi mate current market value $7,300.00) 8,430.38 $ 99,460.09 Invested in Plant at cost Land $ 1,521.35 Buildings and improvements 291,682.57 Furniture and equipment 73,673.10 Truck 2,753.50 $369,630.52 Construction in progress 3,122.08 $372,752.60 $246,067.54 Special Funds: Fund balances: Land Sale Fund $230,530.56 Centennial Fund 221,377.55 $451,908.11 Endowment Funds $ 87,393.42 Fund balances: Settlement School Endowment Fund. ...... $ 3,495.69 Brendel Scholarship Fund: Balance at beginning of year Interest earned 140.60 3,636.29 Matthew J. Wilson Fund: $ 6,181.25 Balance at beginning of year Additional shares received 2,249.13 8,430.38 $ 99,460.09 Invested in Plant $406,150.07 Balance at beginning of year Additions from: 7,380.04 Current Funds Land Sale Fund 4,268.48 $417,798.59 Less public school buildings aban45,045.99 doned $372,752.60 See note appearing on statements of income and expense and fund balance. </p>
      <pb ref="arr8510023_0002" seq="02" n="24-25  "/>
       <p>24 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI STATEMENTS OF INCOME AND EXPENSE AND FUND BALANCE PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL Year ended May 31, 1968 CURRENT FUNDS Income: Educational and general: Student fees $ 11,180.04 Interest and dividends Settle ment School Endowment Fund 3 , 609.26 Contributions: Clubs 12,578.30 Chapters 2,906.00 Pi Beta Phi 117,359.61 Other 643.39 Rent and other 9,643.88 Arrowcraft sales, less cost of sales 72 , 891.22 Magazine commissions 10,728.66 $241,540.36 Auxiliary enterprises: Craft supplies sales $ 7,132.08 Meals paid 9,202.12 Room rents paid 6,799.16 Other 37.25 23,170.61 $264,710.97 Expenses: Educational and general: Administration $ 19 , 354.15 Instructional 26 , 348.15 Operating and maintenance 52,956.47 Arrowcraft Shop 130,712 .07 Magazine Agency 22 , 045.95 $251,416.79 Auxiliary enterprises: Craft supplies $ 7,860.66 Dining hall 11,504.91 Housing 9,727.03 $ 29,092.60 280,509.39 LAND SALE FUND Income: Interest income: United States Treasury obliga tions $ 9,105.64 Monmouth College Trust 1,166.67 Mortgage note receivable 742.15 $ 11,014.46 Other 34.00 $ 11,048.46 Expenses: Ceramic wing construction $ 1,146.40 Architects' fees 3,122.08 Transfer to Settlement School Treasurer for Current Fund operations 4,510.00 8,778.48 Fund balance at beginning of year FUND BALANCE AT END OF YEAR CENTENNIAL FUND Income: Contributions.. . $ 19,097.54 Interest United States Treasury obligations 8,785.91 $ 27,883.45 Expense transfers to Settlement School Treasurer for Current Fund operations 42,202.67 EXCESS OF INCOME OVER EXPENSES $ 2,269.98 228,260.58 $230,530.56 EXCESS OF EXPENSES OVER INCOME ($ 15,798.42) EXCESS OF EXPENSE OVER INCOME ($ 14,319.22) Transfers from other Settlement School funds: Land Sale Fund Centennial Fund Fund balance at beginning of year.. FUND BALANCE AT END OF YEAR See note appearing on balance sheets. 4,510.00 42,202.67 46,712.67 $ 30,914.25 144,702.18 $175,616.43 Fund balance at beginning of year.. $108,648.69 Centennial Fund of Grand Treasurer Pi Beta Phi (contributions to June 30, 1966) transferred to Set tlement School Treasurer 127,048.08 235,696.77 FUND BALANCE AT END OF YEAR $221,377.55 NoTE Fund Accounting The accounts of the Settlement School are maintained on a fund basis of accounting appropriate to non-profit organizations. The for-mat of the financial statements displaying these funds for the year ended May 31, 1968, has been realigned to that which is appropriate for colleges and universities and, accordingly, no provision has been made for depreciation. On June 29, 1966, Internal Revenue Service indicated that certain activities of the Settlement School might be subject to federal income tax. Legal counsel is of the opinion that no liability for these income taxes exists, and if any is imposed, it would not materially affect the financial position of the Settlement School. Certain expenses paid from other funds of Pi Beta Phi are allocable to Settlement School and these financial statements reflect these expenses. Accountants' Report Pi Beta Phi Settlement School Committee, Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee. We have examined the balance sheets of the following funds of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School (a division of Pi Beta Phi) as of May 31, 1968, and the related statements of income and expense and fund balances for the year then ended:such tests of the accounting records and such other auditing procedures as we considered necessary in the circumstances. In our opinion, the accompanying balance sheets and statements of income and expense and fund balances pre-sent fairly the financial position of the funds (as described above) of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School at May 31, 1968, and the results of their operations for the year then ended, in conformity with generally accepted accounting principles applied on a basis consistent with that of the pre-ceding year except as further explained in note appearing above. Little Rock, Arkansas, August 5, 1968. Current Funds Land Sale Fund Centennial Fund Endowment Funds Invested in Plant Our examination was made in accordance with generally accepted auditing standards, and accordingly included Standin,g Committees CANADIAN PHILANTHROPIES COMMITTEE The Canadian Philanthropies Committee grew out of the Canadian Project Fund. The Committee administers two projects, the Loan Fund for Social Work students and the Northern Libraries Project and is responsible to the Vice President of Philanthropies. The inclusion of the new School of Social Welfare at the relatively new University of Calgary brings the number of schools to nine. This extension of the Fund was made possible by the redistribution of funds. The University of British Columbia and the University of Manitoba both agreed to release $500,00 so that a $1000.0!0 Loan Fund could begin in Calgary. A sum of $100.00 was sent to the Maritime School of Social Work where the fund is used extensively. Some of the schools have had some difficulty with unpaid loans but it is hoped that this money will eventually be repaid. At the 1967 Convention it was the unanimous decision of the Canadian delegates to adopt the Northern Library Project. Money is sent to supply books to the libraries of the Yukon and Northwest Territories. The Canadian Government supplies an adequate budget for the purchase of books but there is no money available for the extras that add so much to a library's usefulness, particularly, expensive reference volumes. In July, 1967, a cheque for $1000.00 was presented to the Commissioners of the Territories to be divided equally between the libraries. The library project has created considerable interest, especially, among the Actives. While some Alumnae groups still feel we should be adding more money to the Loan Fund, most are in agreement that it should be self-sustain-ing and that most of the money contributed should go to the libraries. Communications between groups so many miles apart in distance and in interests is difficult, but this is nothing new to you I am sure. I have tried to keep up interest with frequent letters and I have encouraged the expression of opinion. There was an excellent article on the Library Project in the ARROW and I hope this helped to create more interest. During the coming year I hope to establish terms of reference to act as a guideline for the next chairman. This week I am meeting with a representative of the Hamilton Club, which is responsible for the next chairman's appointment. This will give them an opportunity to become acquainted with the work of the committee. There are two areas where I would like to see some changes made. The GT2 form should have the Canadian Philanthropies 'Committee added so that there is no confusion as to where donations are to be sent. So many come to me and I must redirect them. The other is to find a suitable meeting time at Convention for discussion of the Philanthropies Committee problems with the Canadian delegates. We tried to do this at the Canadian breakfast, but this wasn't too satisfactory. I realize that to try to accommodate half a dozen people at a large convention is almost impossible, but perhaps there could be some workshop time available for this. My thanks to all those who have made it a pleasure to serve Pi Phi during the past year. RUBY WHITE TRAILL COMMITTEE ON CHAPERONS The Committee on Chaperons maintains personal records and employment contracts of all chapter house and lodge chaperons. It has authority to grant or deny the hiring of an individual chaperon. It serves as a contact between Grand Council, Alumnae Advisory Committees and Chapters in all matters related to the chaperon. It receives applications from persons desiring to serve as chapter house chaperons, and when requested in an advisory capacity for chapters seeking chaperons. In 1967-68, 74 chapters employed women serving as chaperons for the approximate 2950 undergraduate girls housed by Pi Beta Phi. The average chaperon age is 63 years and average service tenure is 3.6 years. The greater percentage are rated as "Superior" or "Very Good." The salary range is dependent on local situations. Due to a variety of reasons, most concerned with age and health, there is an annual turnover in chaperon person-nel. This Committee therefore welcomes the receipt of names and information regarding capable women interested in serving in this capacity. This may be accomplished by contacting the Chairman. This Committee expresses its sincere appreciation to Alumna Advisory Committees who work so closely with the chaperon and thus enhance the high degree of rapport and communication between the actives, alumnae and chaperons. The Chairman would like to acknowledge the devoted service of Mrs. Harriette Evans who has been with Iowa Zeta for 24 years and will return for the 1968-69 academic year. Sincere thanks is extended to Central Office which has processed the major mailing of this Committee. MARTHA COHAGEN STANHOPE CITIZENSHIP COMMITTEE Citizenship Committee Motion as reaffirmed by vote of the active and alumnx sessions of 1967 'Pi Beta Phi Convention followed the intent to become informed and participating citizens to know our great documents, the Declaration of Independence and the Constitution. As Chairman I attended the 1967 National Citizenship Conference proclaimed by the United States President held annually in Washington and across the nation during the week of September 17, Constitution Week. Attendance was larger than ever before recorded with delegates from many organizations. The theme 1967 was America's Oldest Legislative As-sembly. The First Assembly 1619, was held at Jamestown, Virginia. The program included naturalization proceedings and admittance of some 100 to the privilege of American citizen-ship, and was widely covered by the Associated Press. The presiding judge of the ceremonial naturalization proceedings charged the new citizens to know the American Constitution and follow the laws of their adoptive country. As delegate from Washington Alumnae Club to the District of Columbia Panhellenic Association I attend the monthly Naturalization Court. A detailed report of the 25 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



