<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr8610039_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Settlement School</title>
                        <author><name>Kingman, Elizabeth Yelm</name></author>
                        <author><name>Woodworth, Lucile McCutchan </name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Fall 1969</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr8610039_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1969</date>, Settlement School</title>
                        <author><name>Kingman, Elizabeth Yelm</name></author>
                        <author><name>Woodworth, Lucile McCutchan </name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 39-43</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">41</note>
                        <note type="Folder">5</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 86, Number 1 (Fall 1969), Pages 39-43.</note>
			<note type="document">arr8610039_0000</note>


	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>The Birth of Arrowmont, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1965-1979</item>
                                <item>Funding</item>
                                <item>Facilities</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr8610039_0001" seq="01" n="38-39  "/>
       <p>3 n THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI THE EIGHT HIGHEST TOTAL COMMISSIONS PER CHAPTER, 1968-69 Chapter Georgia A California E Mississippi B Texas A South Dakota .~.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ California Texas Minnesota A Chairman Amount 1968-69 Ginger Davis Linda Arobio 193.61 Pam Connor 132.42 Cynthia Ann Terrill 128.92 Joyce Delbridge '''''''''''''''''''''''''' 116.03 Dianna Dean Dana Dunn ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ ~~f Jane Gustafson 100.39 THE EIGHT HIGHEST TOTAL COMMISSIONS PER CLUB, 1968-69 St. Louis, Mo ' Denver, Colo. ... . Kansas City, Mo Little Pigeon, Tenn Houston, Texas Valley of the Moon, Calif Orlando-Winter Park, Fla Columbia, _~ Mrs. James Breckenridge 972.25 Mrs. John F. Boning 414.02 Mrs. A. E. Whiteside 292.58 Mrs. Ralph Lawson 178.19 Mrs. I. T. Burrell 169.57 Mrs. ~~2~ Houseman . Julian McFarland 159.44 Mrs. Harry Scurlock 133.15 THE EIGHT HIGHEST COMMISSIONS PER CAPITA FOR CHAPTERS, 1968-69 California E Georgia A Mississippi B California A ' ' ' ' '' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' '' ' ' '' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' Minnesota A South Dakota A Linda Arobio 2.98 Ginger Davis 2.37 Pam Connor 2.36 Dana Dunn 2.26 Jane Gustafson '' '' ' ' '' ' '' ' '' '' '' ' 1.89 Joyce Delbridge Cheryl McAnespie ~4 Ann Strohecker 1.33 THE EIGHT HIGHEST COMMISSIONS PER 'CAPITA FOR ALUMNA CLUBS, 1968-96 Little Pigeon, Tenn Minn Valley of the Moon, ~St. Paul, Minn Berkshire, Ma St. Louis, Mo Mrs. Ralph Lawson 11.88 Mrs. L. F. Bowman 4.40 Mrs. Julian McFarland 4.09 Mrs. David Park 4.03 Mrs. Gary Sarofoni 3.79 M~ James Breckenridge Eleanor Norris .~ ~ ~ ~~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~75 Mrs. Harry Scurlock 2.72 THE EIGHT HIGHEST DOLLAR INCREASES FOR ACTIVE CHAPTERS. 1968-69 ChaPter Indiana B Texas B California E California A Alabama A Mississippi B .~ ~~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~ ~~ ~ ~ ~~ ~~~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ Iowa Texas_A.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ Chairman Amount 1968-69 Deborah Childress $ 67.85 Jan Bauchman 61.20 Linda Arobio 54.01 Danna Dunn 43.65 Chris Faulk 43.44 Pam Connor Nancy Remmers .~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 243.10 8.32 Cynthia Terrill 35.24 Amount 1967-1968 .30 126.30 26.06 151.45 THE EIGHT HIGHEST DOLLAR INCREASES FOR ALUMNA CLUBS, 1968-69 Little Pigeon, Tenn St. Louis, Mo. Berkeley, Calif .......................... North Shore Junior Ventura County, Calif Birmingham, Ala 46.25 9.21 4,97 2.67 Mrs. Ralph Lawson ".".".".".".'w 97.66 Mrs. James Breckenridge 69.30 Mrs. Nancy Eckel 57.52 Mrs. Walter Issac 44.57 Mrs. Arlan Flake 44.24 Mrs. Ben Dunagan 42.58 Mrs. John Simms . ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 42.29 Mrs. Eleanor Norris 40.62 Settle/Milt School CHAIRMAN, BOARD OF GOVERNORS, ARROWMONT SCHOOL OF ARTS AND CRAFTS Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts is the name settled on after a week's deliberation at the Board of Governors' last July meeting, a period of thought for a few weeks afterward, and a final vote in the fall. We felt it was euphonious and can be known just by the single word to match the name Arrowcraft. The Summer Craft Workshop was a success in spite of limited facilities for classroom space. The director, Marian Heard, supervised a striking exhibit held in the Pottery and Weaving classroom building, on July 17. It was a fitting conclusion to our meetings and the ground breaking ceremonies, with delightful remarks by President Andrew Holt, of the University of Tennessee. Dean Lura Odland of the Home Economics School of the University of Tennessee, was hostess at a reception honoring her fellow governors at the conclusion of the festivities. Although we had not yet settled upon the right name, each governor re-turned home with the feeling that an institution of validity and good purpose would soon be a reality. Mrs. Thomas Garrard, a governor from Oklahoma, was so impressed with so many of the beautiful handmade objects produced by the Workshop, that she arranged a limed tour of some of them. They were seen in Oklahoma, Texas, New Mexico, Arizona, California, New York and Washington, D.C. In April, 1969, I made a trip to Gatlinburg for a meet-ing with the Grand Vice President of Philanthropies, Orpha Coenen, Executive Coordinator Lucile Woodworth, and Professor Marian Heard. The nearly completed Mall, with its beautiful stonework and cantilevered shelters, burst upon us, a fine relief and pleasant interpretation of space and greenery in contrast to the rows of stores along the street. The classroom building was taking shape, nestling down among the contours of the grassy plot back of the Pottery and Weaving Building. Mr. Hubert Bebb, the architect, showed us the model of the building and we were enchanted with its beauty of line, its distinctive simplicity, and its practical planning. There is plenty of parking space, too. The large hemlock tree was moved with success, and now thrives in front of the Administration building in a small plaza created for history exhibits. The stone gates to the school will be impressive when finished. Lucile Woodworth, in spite of a brief time away for illness, has continued to show her business and administrative ability in coordinating the operations of both Arrowmont and Arrowcraft. The knowledge and technical ability of Marian Heard is revealed in many details that appear in the ideas and plans of the physical school. It is wonderful to perceive the harmony of thought and action demonstrated by the "Triumvirate" of Lucile, Marian and Mr. Bebb as they work together. Pi Phi is fortunate! ELIZABETH YELM KINGMAN EXECUTIVE COORDINATOR, ARROWMONT AND ARROWCRAFT One year ago, your Executive Coordinator of Arrowmont arrived in Gatlinburg just in time for the opening of the 23rd Summer Craft Workshop. How wonderful if every Pi Phi could attend a workshop to see Professor Marian Heard's inspirational leadership, to feel the dedication of each teacher, and to be exposed to the enthusiasm of the students. All are just not students in the usual sense of the word as some are proficient craftsmen who have come for further training and knowledge. Our student body is composed of teachers, vocational rehabilitation workers, mental health therapists, senior citizens leaders, graduate students, regular college students, and then citizens and senior citizens. Their ages range from 16 to 80. During the three sessions, there were 72 students enrolled in each. Canada and England were represented as well as 32 of our United States. During this 1968 Craft Workshop, the Board of Governors arrived to organize and make plans for the future, the extended year round program for Arrowmont. How fortunate we feel here at the school to have such a capable and dedicated group of Pi Phis headed by Betty Kingman to work with us. We walked over the ground where the new building complex will be, each visualizing the future of the school, as we can be sure that the original committee did 57 years ago when the Settlement School had its be-ginning. What did this new Board of Governors visualize? 1) Additional housing units . . . on Pi Phi Hill .. . smaller units that can be opened and closed with a minimum of expense when registration is limited to smaller groups. 2) A Woodworking Studio . . . one of the first crafts taught in the early days of the Settlement School was woodworking. Many of the men who furnish crafts now for the Arrowcraft Shop learned at the early Pi Phi School. 3) A modern kitchen for Staff House to furnish food more economically and efficiently for those three meals each day that our hard working students and staff need. A school day starts at Arrowmont at 8 A.M. and ends at 9 or 10 P.M. Courses are concentrated, a 2 week session equalling a quarter of regular school. 4) An enlarged Arrowcraft Shop, both in working and sales space as well as in items produced and sold. Arrowcraft was an inherent part of the Settlement School and now can be even more a part of Arrowmont as our Resident Craftsmen Teachers will be able to produce and design for it. The Shop is al-ready an outstanding showroom and distribution point for beautiful handcrafted objects. The sales contribute to the economy of many craftsmen but these sales also help support Arrowmont. The hard work that is put into the Settlement School sales all over the country deserves the best in products but also needs new designs and larger inventories. These will come with growth. Our 1969 Summer Craft Workshop started June 18th and ended July 25th. The teachers who were under the direction of Professor Marian Heard were Ann S. Van Aken, Sandra Blain, Mary Frances Davidson, Richard. Daehnert, John T. Fix, Persis Grayson, Harry B. Hollander, Joan Paque, Sister Mary Remy, Bernice Stevens and Helen War-rail. It was a stimulating program despite our cramped quarters but the year 1970 will see Arrowmont in full production with studios and working quarters which will do justice to our able teachers, their inspired students, and our supporting Pi Phis. We are fortunate to have the academic backing of the University of Tennessee with Dean Lura Odland of the College of Home Economics acting on our Board of Governors. 39 </p>
      <pb ref="arr8610039_0002" seq="02" n="40-41  "/>
       <p>40 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI As this second summer program started for your Coordinator, she could look back on a busy year of orientation from which came many ideas and plans that can now be started. For example, in the Spring 1969 issue of The ARROW only one chapter letter mentioned Arrowmont, Pi Phi's philanthropy, so we plan this year to provide all province presidents with colored slides of the school to show on their visits to both active chapters and to alumni clubs ... visual exposure. We will bring the school to you since not all of you can come to Arrowmont. Your support is needed but we also want you to see how proud you can be of what you are supporting. In this world of unrest, you are contributing to a project which can help not only the United States but the whole world. Pi Beta Phi was founded not only for sisterhood but also for service to others. This has been an inspirational year for your coordinator.The people who should receive thanks for the help they have given are innumerable. Will each Pi Phi who has helped, even those who have just written a note of encouragement, know they have been part of this rewarding year. Since all can't be named, please understand when the staff here at Arrowmont and Arrowcraft are named . . Lela Adams, Faye Cook, Gene Hembree, Nella Hill, Susie King, Ruth Kenney, Flora Reagan, Judy Ward, Neal Watson, Richard Watson, Ruby Watson, Zanley Watson and my assistant, Nadine Whitted. Marjorie Chalmers and Elizabeth Rue are Pi Phis but they are on the staff and part of this wonderful group who have done everything that is humanly possible to help and advise the newcomer. We all welcome your suggestions and hope to continue to contribute our best to Pi Beta Phi. LUCILE MCCUTCHAN WOODWORTH LITTLE PIGEON AWARDS (1968-1969) Total contributions to Arrowmont which includes all Honorable Mention: Each gave $200. or more San Mateo, Calif. Arlington Heights, Ill. Contra Costa, Calif. Champaign-Urbana, Ill. There were also ten other clubs giving $10'0.00 or more in this category. checks, whether made out to Settlement School or Centen nial Fund: $23,128.79. 92 chapters gave $6,465.94 285 alumni clubs gave $16,662.85 Quiet Pigeons are given to the province officers whose clubs or chapters have contributed to Arrowmont 100%, 100 150 Milwaukee, Wis., $175.00 Westchester County, N.Y., $150.00 Honorable Mention: Austin, Tex. Bloomfield Hills, Mich. Tulsa, Okla. Five other clubs gave $100. in this category. Over 150 Kansas City, Mo., $1526.00 St. Louis, Mo., $1100.00 Pasadena, Calif., $1015.00 Honorable Mention: Houston, Tex., $760.00 Five other clubs gave over $100. in this cate gory. Chapters Clubs Alpha Beta Gamma Gamma Zeta Eta Iota Zeta Xi Pi North Pi South Soaring Pigeons are awarded to the clubs and chapters making the largest contributions to Arrowmont. Four chapters contributed over $250. and received Soaring Pigeons. Texas Gamma $401.00 A total of 45 clubs gave $100. or more. Missouri Beta $330.00 PURCHASES OF ARROWCRAFT ITEMS BY ALUMNIE CLUBS Texas Beta $300.00 Alabama Beta $251.50 246 clubs purchased Arrowcraft items during the past year. 43 clubs bought over $1,000. Soaring Pigeons were awarded to the following clubs: Sixteen other chapters gave $100. or over. Clubs receiving Soaring Pigeons Awards, according to the membership size of the clubs, in each of five categories are: 10 24 Manchester, Conn. Redlands, Calif. Honorable Mention: 10 24 Hattiesburg, Miss. Beloit, Wis. State College, Pa. Honorable Mention: Little Pigeon, Tenn. Anchorage, Alaska 25 49 Five clubs tied for first place with contributions of 2 5 49 Stillwater, Okla. with the largest purchase in sev $100.00 each eral years from any alumnae club $8,248.54. Harrisburg-Carlisle, Pa. Bozeman, Mont. $3,853.00 Richmond, Va. Honorable Mention: Park Ridge-Des Plains, Ill. Calgary, Alberta, Can. 50 99 Champaign-Urbana with second largest purchases Hutchinson, Kan. Camelback, Ariz. of any club this year $4,070.47 Second place: Hartford, Conn. Contra Costa, Calif. $3,141.76 Honorable Mention: Honorable Mention: (all purchased over $2,000. Bakersfield, Calif. in Arrowcraft items) Valley of the Moon, Calif. North Shore, Ill. 50 99 Nashville, Tenn., $800.00 Rockford, Ill. Lafayette, Ind. Rochester, N.Y., $350.00 Pittsburgh, South Hills, Pa. North Shore, Ill., $350.00 Beaumont, Tex. (Nita Hill Stark Club) THE ARROW OF N BETA PHI 41 100 150 Northern N.J. $2,564.66 Omaha, Neb. $1,947.31 Honorable Mention: Minneapolis, Minn. $1,553.87 Over 150 South Coast, Calif.-$2,399.24 Indianapolis, Ind.-$2,287.14 Honorable Mention: St. Louis, Mo. $2,193.66 ALUMNA CLUBS AWARDING SCHOLARSHIPS TO SUMMER CRAFT WORKSHOP 1968 1969 Both Years Westchester. County, N.Y. Beta Province Little Pigeon, Tenn. Eta Province South Suburban, Chicago, Ill. Iota Province Kansas City, Mo. Lambda Province (full session scholar-, ship) Oklahoma City, Okla. Nu North Province (two full session scholarships this year) Dallas, Tex. Nu North Province Houston, Tex. Nu South Province (two full scholarships each year) Spokane, Wash. Omicron Province (full session scholar-ship) counting principles applied on a basis consistent with that of the preceding year. Little Rock, Arkansas August 20, 1969 BALANCE SHEETS PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL ASSETS May 31, May 31, 1969 1968 Current Funds General: Cash $ 44,651.12 Accounts receivable 1 ,916.74 Craft supplies at cost 7,442.86 Prepaid expenses 5 ,889 .49 Due from Arrowcraft Shop 47 ,334.90 Due from Magazine Agency 1 ,342 .31 21,229.40 2,156.36 6,972.74 2,105.59 34,205.64 753.47 1968 Philadelphia Delco, Pa.-Beta Province South Coast, Calif.-Pi South Province Minnesota Alpha-Kappa Province (only chapter awarding a scholarship either year) 108,577.42 Arrowcraft Shop and Magazine Agency: Cash 16,302.48 Accounts receivable 21, 236.70 Inventories at lower of cost (first in, first-out method) or market 151, 534.7867,423.20 28,462.71 19,670.65 128,880.96 1969 Buffalo, N.Y.-Beta Province Northern N.J. Beta Province Denver, Colo. Xi Province two scholarships) Phoenix, Ariz. Pi South Province (full session scholar-ship) AUDITED FINANCIAL STATEMENTS PI BETA PM SETTLEMENT SCHOOL GATLINBURG, TENNESSEE May 31, 1969 Pi Beta Phi Settlement School Committee Pi Beta Phi Settlement School Gatlinburg, Tennessee We have examined the balance sheets of the following funds of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School (a division of Pi Beta Phi) as of May 31, 1969, and the related statements of income and expense and fund balances for the year then ended: Current Funds Land Sale Fund Centennial Fund Endowment Funds Invested in Plant Our examination was made in accordance with generally accepted auditing standards, and accordingly included such tests of the accounting records and such other auditing procedures as we considered necessary in the circumstances. We made a similar examination of the financial statements for the preceding year. In our opinion, the accompanying balance sheets and statements of income and expense and fund balances present fairly the financial position of the funds (as de-scribed above) of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School at May 31, 1969, and the results of their operations for the year then ended, in conformity with generally accepted ac 189,073.96 177,014.32 297,651.38 244,437.52 Restricted: Cash 2,379.26 1,256.63 Due from Current Fund General 373.39 373.39 2,752.65 1,630.02 $300,404.03 $246,067.54 Special funds Land Sale Fund: Cash $ 36,406.20 $ 22,430.28 United States Treasury bills at cost 199,854.14 Mortgage note receivable 8,246.14 36,406.20 230,530.56 Centennial Fund: Cash 46 ,953 .48 38 ,986 .77 United States Treasury obligations at cost (quoted market value: 1969 $120,908.92; 1968 $167,246.24) 127 ,900 .78 177,390.78 Corporate stock valued at market value at date of acquisition (approximate current market value $875.00) 1,162.50 Due from Arrowcraft Shop 5,000.00 5,000.00 181,016.76 221,377.55 $217,422.96 $451,908.11 LIABILITIES AND FUND BALANCES May 31, May 31, 1969 1968 Current Funds Liabilities: General: Accounts payable $ 3,261.19 Due to Current Fund Re stricted 373.39 Due to Pi Beta Phi Grand Treasurer 24,000.00 27,634.58 27,048.06 Arrowcraft Shop and Magazine Agency: Accounts payable 3,972.75 1,813.92 Due to Current Fund Gen eral 48,677.21 34,959.11 Due to Centennial Fund 5,000.00 5,000.00 57,649.96 41,773.03 2,674.67 373.39 24,000.00 </p>
      <pb ref="arr8610039_0003" seq="03" n="42-43  "/>
       <p>42 Fund balances: 80 ,942 .84 40,375.14 General.. . Arrowcraft Shop 134 , 478.43 136,578 .45 Magazine Agency (deficit) 3,054.43) ( 1,337.16) 212,366.84 175,616.43 297,651.38 244,437.52 Restricted: 1,331.38 711,91 Matthew J. Wilson Income Fund: Fund balance at beginning of year Dividends 313.65 619.47 1,645.03 1,331.38 Library Fund: 298.64 866.94 Fund balance at beginning of year Craft books purchased 568.30 298.64 298.64 Oklahoma City Alumnae Club Fund: Contribution 1,003.98 Scholarship award 195.00 808.98 2,752.65 1,630.02 $300,404.03 $246,067.54 Special Funds $ 36,406.20 $230,530.56 Fund balances: Land Sale Fund Centennial Fund 181,016.76 221,377.55 $217,422.96 $451,908.11 ASSETS May 31, May 31, 1969 Endowment Funds Settlement School Endowment Fund equity (10.775%) in Pi Beta Phi Trust securities at cost (approximate market value: 1969 $101,077.00; 1968 $102,000.00) . $ 87 ,343 .69 $ 87,393.42 Brendel Scholarship Fund savings 3,784.46 3,636.29 account.. .. .. Matthew J. Wilson Fund corporate 8,430.38 8,430.38 stock valued at market value at date of acquisition (approximate current market value: 1969 $8,430.00; 1968 $7,300.00) $ 99,558.53 $ 99,460.09 Invested in Plant at cost $ 1,521.35 $ 1,521.35 Land Buildings andamprovements 291, 682.57 291,682.57 Furniture and equipment 78,472 .08 73,673.10 Truck 2,753.50 2,753.50 374,429.50 369,630.52 Construction in Progress 198,887.07 3,122.08 $573,316.57 $372,752.60 LIABILITIES AND FUND BALANCES May 31, May 31, 1968 1969 Endowment Funds $ 87 ,393.42 $ 87,393.42 Fund balances: Settlement School Endowment Fund: Balance at beginning of year. . . Loss on disposal of securities. . . 49.73 87,343.69 87,393.42 Brendel Scholarship Fund: 3,636.29 3,495.69 Balance at beginning of year Interest earned 148.17 140.60 3,784.46 3,636.29 Matthew J. Wilson Fund 8,430 .38 8,430.38 $ 99,558.53 $ 99,460.09 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI Invested in Plant $372 ,752 .60 $406,150.07 Balance at beginning of year Additions from: 4,798.98 7,380.04 Current Funds Land Sale Fund 195,764.99 4,268.48 Less public school buildings 573,316.57 417,798.59 abandoned 45,045.99 $573,316.57 $372,752.60 NOTE. Fund Accounting The accounts of the Settlement School are maintained on a fund basis of accounting appropriate to non-profit organizations. The format of the financial statements displaying these funds is presented in a manner which is appropriate for colleges and universities and, accordingly, no provision has been made for depreciation. certain activities of the Settlement School might be subject to federal income tax. Legal counsel is of the opinion that no liability for these income taxes exists, and if any is imposed, it would not materially affect the financial position of the Settlement School. Certain expenses paid from other funds of Pi Beta Phi are allocable to Settlement School and these financial statements reflect these expenses. STATEMENT OF INCOME AND EXPENSE AND FUND BALANCE CURRENT FUNDS PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL Year ended May 31 1969 1968 Income Educational and general: Student fees.. . $ 10,471.50 $ 11,180.04 Interest and dividends Settlement School Endowment Fund 3,754.50 3,609.26 Contributions: Clubs 15 ,464 .25 12,578.30 N Beta Phi 10,601.52 10,935.18 Expenses allocable to Settlement School paid by other Pi Beta Phi Funds 82,602.85 106,424.43 Other 1,231.47 643.39 Rent and other 9,823.50 9,643.88 Arrowcraft sales, less cost of sales 75,930.77 72,891.22 Magazine commissions 10,586.55 10,728.66 224,260.34 241,540.36 Auxiliary enterprises: Craft supplies sales 8,289.26 7,132.08 Meals paid 8,288.20 9,202.12 Room rents paid 7,959.00 6,799.16 Other 28.25 37.25 24,564.71 23,170.61 248,825.05 264,710.97 Expenses Educational and general: Administration 35 , 319.38 19 , 354.15 Instructional 20, 968. 76 26,348 .15 Operating and maintenance 40,553.84 52,956.47 Arrowcraft Shop 120 ,086 .79 130,712.07 Magazine Agency 18,935.21 22,045.95 235,863.98 251,416.79 Auxiliary enterprises: Craft supplies 6,315.24 7,860.66 Dining hall 13,771.08 11,504.91 Housing 9,124.34 9,727.03 29,210.66 29,092.60 265,074.64 280,509.39 EXCESS OF EXPENSES OVER INCOME ( 16,249.59) ( 15,798.42) Transfers from other Settlement School Funds: Land Sale Fund 4,510.00 Centennial Fund 53,000.00 42,202.67 36,750.41 30,914.25 Fund balance at beginning of year 175,616.43 144,702.18 FUND BALANCE AT END OF YEAR $212,366.84 $175,616.43 See note appearing on balance sheets. On June 29, 1966, Internal Revenue Service indicated that 1968 Chapters 3,793.43 2,906.00 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI 43 STATEMENT OF INCOME AND EXPENSE AND FUND BALANCE PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL LAND SALE FUND Year ended May 31 1969 1968 Income Interest income: United States Treasury obliga tions $ 145.86 $ 9,105.64 Monmouth College Trust 1,000,00 1,166.67 Mortgage note receivable 494.77 742.15 1,640.63 11,014.46 Other 34.00 1,640.63 11,048.46 Expenses Ceramic wing construction 1,146.40 Multi-purpose classroom building and Pi Phi Mall 168,643.60 Architects' fees .... . 27,121 .39 3,122.08 Transfer to Current Funds 4,510.00 Fund balance at beginning of year.... 230,530.56 228,260.58 FUND BALANCE AT END OF YEAR. $ 36,406.20 $230,530.56 CENTENNIAL FUND Income Contributions Interest United States Treasury obligations Expense transfer to Current Funds. . EXCESS OF EXPENSE OVER INCOME Fund balance at beginning of year.... Centennial Fund of Grand Treasurer Pi Beta Phi (contributions through June 30, 1966) transferred to Settlement School Treasurer FUND BALANCE AT END OF YEAR $ 6,989.21 $ 19,097.54 5,650.00 8,785.91 12,639.21 27,883.45 53,000.00 42,202.67 ( 40,360.79) ( 14,319.22) 221,377.55 108,648.69 127,048.08 $181,016.76 $221,377.55 .--.--.-',-,---.=-----== 195, 764.99 8,778.48 _ See note appearing on balance sheets. EXCESS (DEFICIT) OF INCOME OVER EXPENSES ( 194,124.36) 2,269.98 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



