<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr8630015_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News of Arrowmont School of arts and crafts</title>
                        <author><name>Huff, Henrietta McCutchan</name></author>
                        <author><name>Williams`, Mariantha James</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Spring 1970</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr8630015_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1970</date>, News of Arrowmont School of arts and crafts</title>
                        <author><name>Huff, Henrietta McCutchan</name></author>
                        <author><name>Williams`, Mariantha James</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 15-19</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">41</note>
                        <note type="Folder">6</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 86, Number 3 (Spring 1970), Pages 15-19.</note>
			<note type="document">arr8630015_0000</note>


	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>The Birth of Arrowmont, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1965-1979</item>
                                <item>Facilities</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>
                                <item>Staff</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr8630015_0001" seq="01" n="14-15  "/>
       <p>Sing Praises Of Pledges As initiation time nears, the Pi Phis of Illinois Eta are taking a last look at the girls who will soon be our true sisters. After pledging last September, we knew we had an outstanding group of girls and they have certainly more than proved themselves over the semester. Al-though they numbered only fifteen, they certainly had enough enthusiasm for twice that many. Pledges were required to come over to the house to study three evenings a week, so they decided to surprise the actives. They all ordered Pi Phi pledge tee-shirts and came to study tables early so that they could serenade us with the songs they had learned. Added to this was a pizza party for the actives one Friday night. They were anxious to get involved in fraternity life, so our pledges organized a combination Halloween party and slumber party for the girls going through informal rush. Their interests were not entirely social. Theyby NANCY HILL, Illinois Eta began to direct their energy to volunteer work for the school and the community. In November, the university had an extremely large mailing, so the Pi Phi pledges volunteered to stuff envelopes for three days in their spare time. They also organized themselves to collect for the Arthritis Foundation. The greatest thing these pledges have done is to come up with a cumulative grade point aver-age of 3.05 on a four point scale. Grades ranged from 2.4 to 3.7. At the beginning of November the scholarship chairman had put the pledges on a new program calling for a mini-mum of 18 study hours per week. For this group it has certainly paid of. This is the first time in ten years that all of the pledges have made grades to be initiated. When these fifteen girls become initiates they will certainly continue to radiate energy and enthusiasm. They are all infected with the spirit of Pi Beta Phi. Mr. Soule Is Surprise Visitor by KAY TUCKER, Virginia Gamma Last fall, while touring historic Williams-burg, Virginia, Cleon Soule, son of Inez Smith Soule, met two young Virginia Gammas who directed him and Mrs. Soule around the colonial capital. Upon discovering that Mr. Soule was a "born Pi Phi," the girls invited the Soules to have dinner with the Pi Phi chapter at William and Mary. The Pi Phis were greatly entertained by their honored guests, and after dinner, the Soules stayed to observe one of Pi Phi's most enjoyable events a candlelight. Cleon Soule did not forget the Virginia Gamma Pi Phis, and sent us a beautiful Christmas card in which he revealed a secret he and Mrs. Soule had been in Williamsburg on their honeymoon. Cleon Soule, son of Inez Smith Soule, with Lynda Murphy, president of Virginia Gamma. 14 News of The Great Smoky Mountains Gatlinburg, Tennessee 37738 Edited by HENRIETTA MCCUTCHAN HUFF Missouri Beta Stonemason Charles Ogle sets the final cover stone in place for the Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts. The special ceremony to lay the cornerstone was held last October 18, 1969. 15 </p>
      <pb ref="arr8630015_0002" seq="02" n="16-17  "/>
       <p>October Highlight A Cornerstone Is Laid 0 n October 18, 1969, a brisk fall morning in Gatlinburg, a special ceremony was held to lay the cornerstone of the Pi Beta Phi Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts. Present were the Arrowmont Board of Governors, the Pi Beta Phi Grand Council, faculty members from the University of Tennessee, and Pi Phis from the Gatlinburg area and across the nation. Autumn color in the surrounding hills made an inspiring background for this important event. Elizabeth )(elm Kingman, Chairman of the Board of Governors, was Mistress of Ceremonies. An invocation was given by the Reverend Vance Eastridge, pastor of the Gatlinburg First United Methodist Church. Professor Marian Heard, Director of Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, spoke about the "giant steps" that had been taken toward the establishment of the school. In 1912 Pi Beta Phi became involved in education and welfare by setting up a school and health service in Gatlinburg. In 1915 the largest cottage weaving industry in the country began to develop. Arrowcraft Shop was founded in 1925, and promised a bright future in arts and crafts. In 1945 Gatlinburg assumed educational responsibilities, and the University of Tennessee helped to establish Summer Craft Work-shops. Laying a cornerstone for Arrowmont means we now move toward a year-round arts and crafts program which will open in June, 1970. Miss Marian Heard, Director of Arrowmont, speaks to guests of the "giant steps" that have been made in the creation of the school. by MARIANTHA JAMES WILLIAMS Board of Governors Other speakers were Sarah Holmes Hunt, Grand Vice President of Philanthropies, and Mayor William Mills of Gatlinburg. Each told in turn what Arrowmont means to every Pi Beta Phi, and what Arrowmont means to the community of Gatlinburg and education. Charles Ogle, the stone mason, asked Sally Vanasse, Grand President, Olivia Moore, treasurer of Arrowmont, Dean Lura Odland, Home Economics Department of the University of Tennessee and member of the Board of Governors and Mayor Mills of Gatlinburg to assist with the trowel in laying the cornerstone. A sealed lead box was placed inside the corner-stone. The box contained the following items: Arrowcraft Catalogue, 1969; Arrowcraft History; lists of officers of Pi Beta Phi, Board of Governors of Arrowmont, and the personnel of the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School and the Arrowcraft Shop; a Whig Rose bookmark from the Arrow-craft Shop; a March 13, 1969 feature story from the Gatlinburg Mountain Press; several other booklets telling the history of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity and the School; the 10th Annual Let-ter of Dean Odland to alumni of the University of Tennessee. Louise Rosser Kemp closed the ceremony with a benediction. Lucile McCutchan Wood-worth, business manager of Arrowcraft and Arrowmont, was eager to show guests through the construction area to view the beginnings of studios for jewelry design, recreational crafts, textile decoration and enameling, plus exhibit galleries, an auditorium, a library, offices, conference rooms, and a sales supply room. The new Arrowmont Building adjoins the present Craft Center, at present housing the ceramic and weaving studios. The Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts will open in June of 1970 for the year-round program of workshops, accredited by the University of Tennessee. Dedication of the new building and the school itself is promised for June. This is another "giant step" in the near future for Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, and for Pi Beta Phi. Sally Vanasse, Grand President, takes a trowel to help lay the cornerstone. Members of the Board of Governors consider the fashion in headgear for this special occasion. Left to right-Carolyn Ottenger Kovener, Mariantha James Williams, and Olivia Smith Moore. The formalities of laying the cornerstone are over and building is going up. But at least one rather large question remains. Will we be able to have a permanent roof over these classrooms? Much depends on Pi Phis around the world. If each Pi Phi buys at least one $1.00 shingle, a permanent roof would be possible. Will you help? 17 </p>
      <pb ref="arr8630015_0003" seq="03" n="18-19  "/>
       <p>Craft Teacher Is Summer Student Miss SARAH LAWSON, a 1969 summer student in Recreational Crafts at Arrowmont, is shown teaching art to a second grade child who is in traction. Miss Lawson was awarded a scholarship for the 1969 Summer Workshop by the Pi Beta Phi Sarah Lawson Alumnae Club of Gatlinburg because she is very important to the handicapped and hospitalized children in East Tennessee. She teaches crafts to children in grades 1-12 who are patients in hospitals in the Knoxville area. "A unique experience" she says of her work last summer with students from foreign countries. In the past years, over 17 foreign countries have been represented during Summer Workshops. .Remember .. Counsel for Pi Beta Phi advises that bequests by wills or gifts made to Arrowmont are considered by the Internal Revenue Service to be tax deductible. It is suggested that the bequest or gift for Arrowmont be made to "Pi Beta Phi Settlement School (Arrowmont) ." Contributions or gifts can made in forms other than cash, also. WANTED 8 Graduate Assistants for 1970 Summer Workshop WhO_Actives or graduates with some art or craft background What--Room and board, plus one craft class free, in exchange for work as assistant to Director of Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts. When Apply NOW Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Gatlinburg, Tenn. 37738 Barbara Wehr, a Pi Phi from Minneapolis, Minn., is pictured at the loom in her weaving class. Barbara has been an assistant to the director for two summers, 1968 and 1969. Looking on are Miss Marian Heard, left, Director of Arrowmont School, and Mrs. Lucile Woodworth, Executive Coordinator of Arrowmont and Arrowcraft. Barbara enjoyed every minute at Arrowmont and hopes many Pi Phi collegians will apply to work as an assistant. 18 Pi Beta Phi alumni joined with Mrs. Clifford M. Hardin (center), wife of the U.S. Secretary of Agriculture, when the Craft Tour was in Washington, D.C. last October. With Mrs. Hardin, Indiana Delta, are, front from the left, Mrs. Austin Doyle, Jr., Mrs. William C. Dulin, Gamma Alumnce Province President, Mrs. Hardin, Mrs. Robert Wild, Mrs. Ringo Di Masso. Back row: Mrs. George Sampson, Mrs. B. Harrison Lingo, Mrs. J. W. Cassidy, Mrs. James D. Pewitt, Mrs. Henry Johnson, Mrs. Val Sherman. Arrowcraft Featured In Washington CRAFTS on display at the Cooperative Crafts Exhibit in Washington, D.C., during the month of October, included many from the Arrowcraft Shop. The shop is a member of the Southern Highland Handicraft Guild, Asheville, N.C. a non-profit educational organization formed in 1930 by representatives of a few craft centers scattered through the mountain area. The Guild's purpose like that of the Arrowcraft Shop is to preserve the highland heritage of craftsmanship, a vital part of the cultural, economic, educational and social pattern of mountain life. This year will see the culmination of a half century's dreams and work by Pi Beta Phi and the craftsmen of the region, since over a million dollars has been invested to create a year-round arts and crafts center and educational facility in Gatlinburg. Crafts shown from this shop at the exhibit in the U.S. Department of Agriculture included weavings, baskets, dolls, and brooms. They joined handcrafted items from cooperatives andguilds in 32 states as one of the activities for Co-op Month 1969 in Washington. The Third Annual Cooperative Crafts Exhibit was sponsored by the National Steering Committee for Co-op Month 1969 as one of the feature representatives of government departments and agencies and national cooperative organizations serve on the committee. Visitors to the craft exhibit received information telling about Arrowmont, how and why it was founded, and giving plans for the future. For Slides of Arrowmont Actives should contact their Province President. Alumnae Clubs should contact the Alumnae Province President. 19 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



