<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr8720039_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News of Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts</title>
                        <author><name>Fullerton, Carolyn</name></author>
                        <author><name>Bushnell Lehner, Eleanor</name></author>
                        <author><name>Swan, Pat</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Winter 1970</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr8720039_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1970</date>, News of Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts</title>
                        <author><name>Fullerton, Carolyn</name></author>
                        <author><name>Bushnell Lehner, Eleanor</name></author>
                        <author><name>Swan, Pat</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 39-44</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">41</note>
                        <note type="Folder">7</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 87, Number 2 (Winter 1970), Pages 39-44.</note>
			<note type="document">arr8720039_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Arrowmont Means New Awareness; Student Likes Intensive Work; Kathy's Tours Foster Pi Phi Pride; Cerebral Palsy Victim is Popular Student; Arrowmont Benefits Reach Far Afield; Dori and Devony Share Enthusiasm; Works on Thesis</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>The Birth of Arrowmont, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1965-1979</item>
                                <item>People</item>
                                <item>Arts</item>
                                <item>Students</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr8720039_0001" seq="01" n="38-39  "/>
       <p>Five Surprises For Happy Julie by DARLA WANDTKE Ohio Epsilon OHIO EPSILON'S Julie Burns was probably the most excited, surprised, and proud Pi Phi in the nation last April. The California Alpha Scholarship Award was the first deserved award given to Julie that month, only to be followed by the Outstanding Junior Award given by the Julie Burns alumnae at the Founders Day Banquet. Julie only had time to recover from this excitement when she found she had been elected president of the College of Education. Thinking her good luck could never hold out, she never suspected she would be tapped for Peppers Women's Honorary. After having so many unexpected moments, Julie turned her last surprise into one on the chapter. Julie had a candlelight she had been given an engagement ring. Unusual as it seems, all this took place within ten days in April. Thanks to sisters like Julie, Ohio Epsilon is always full of excitement. This summer, proud Illinois Eta Pi Phis watched one of their sisters, Paula Collins, compete and be named as a finalist in the Miss Illinois Contest. Paula, a senior elementary education major from Beecher City, represented the city of Effingham. The beauty contest winner spent most of her summer working with teachable mentally handicapped children in a summer day camp. Upon graduation she hopes to pursue her Masters degree in Special Education. Freshman Pledge Is Miss North Dakota WHEN Nancy Jean Tangen became a pledge of North Dakota Alpha along with 29 other girls, there was a special beauty and poise to Nancy. So, as a freshman she entered the Miss Grand Forks pageant, swept all the judges' eyes and became a title holder of Grand Forks. Nancy, 18, Miss Grand Forks, swept talent and swimsuit competition and was crowned Miss North Dakota 1970 one Saturday night at Bismarck. She is a University of North Dakota sophomore and was runnerup in last year's Miss U.S. Durum contest. Now that she is busy with all the added duties of a beauty this year, we as her sisters wish her the best of everything. 38 News of Pictured above is a close-up view of the impressive entrance to the Emma Harper Turner Building at Arrowmont school of its and crafts '446, The Great Smoky Mountains Gatlinburg, Tennessee 37738 39 </p>
      <pb ref="arr8720039_0002" seq="02" n="40-41  "/>
       <p>Pat Rush Fullerton, studying textile design under Sister Mary Remy, is shown dipping her material in the dye-adding another color to her design. Arrowmont Means New Awareness by CAROLYN "PAT" FULLERTON Redlands Alumna Club A SUMMER month at Arrowmont ! What does it mean ? To me, a teacher of Arts and Crafts at Red-lands High School, it meant a whole new focus on the world. Here we forgot that crippling trap of categorizing people according to generation. We were too involved in appreciating what each person did. It meant an 18-hour daily dose of beauty .. in the design of the spacious new building whose laboratories had been so knowledgeably planned that tables, sinks, power outlets, tools, supplies, storage areas were all right where we needed them . . . in the straightforward use of structural materials such as cinder block, stone, wood, even fiber insulation slabs, all left in their natural state to give richness of contrast in texture patterns . . . in the exhibits, both the highly organized Tennessee Craft Guild objects and the informal displays of the works of former students and instructors that provided a constant feast of beauty in every room and corridor. It meant a new awareness and love of colors and materials and a new excitement in the de-signs and uses to which the materials had been put. It meant the fun of learning a whole new bevy of skills. It meant plenty of time to saturate ourselves in the learning process. (The labs were open from seven a.m. until midnight six days a week. The instructors were available for assistance far beyond the 150-minute class periods.) We did not have the maddening frustration of getting deeply involved only to have a clanging bell announce: "Time to stop . . . put it away." We were involved not only in our own projects but also in those of our fellow students who provided a healthy portion of our learning and stimulation. We cared what each one did. We were all caught up in the current of experimentation and could hardly turn it off. With the help of our instructors we acquired new eyes to see design, new courage to try the untried, and humor to make the whole learning process a ball. My Arrowmont experience will revitalize my own teaching and enrich the lives of all who attend my classes. Arrowmont kiln is filled with student-made pottery that has been glaze-fired. WANTED 8 Graduate Assistants for 1971 Summer Workshop WhO Actives or graduates with some art or craft background WhatRoom and board, plus one craft class free, in exchange for work as assistant to Director of Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts. When--Apply NOW Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Gatlinburg, Term. 37738 Student Likes Intensive Work WHAT DO students like about Arrowmont? The answers to this question were many and varied, and from time to time, The ARROW will quote a few, as space permits. "A series of `intensive' workshops is a good idea. It enables people with heavy schedules to enroll. The whole idea of fostering `quality' art is extremely important, especially today when schools are beginning to cut art programs be-cause of financial stress. Quality art is not the result of hit and miss, entertaining busy work. Only through projects like this one can the interest and taste of viewers and participants be raised to the point that they cry out loudly for expansion, not diminishment, of this important area of education. Pi Beta Phi is doing the world a great service. KEEP UP THE GOOD WORK." Kathy Lambert, Graduate Assistant, 1970 Kathy's Tours Foster Pi Phi Pride KATHY LAMBERT, Kentucky Beta, was a graduate assistant at Arrowmont during the 1970 summer session. Kathy received her B.A. in art (textile design) from the University of Kentucky last spring, and went to Arrowmont to learn more about the crafts, especially weaving. She felt that she could also learn first hand about the Pi Phi philanthropy and that this would be most rewarding. According to Kathy, "Working as an assistant is sometimes difficult, but it serves as an opportunity to meet more of the other students. I had a feeling of pride in Pi Beta Phi whenever I gave visitors a tour of the school." Kathy hopes eventually to earn an M.F.A. degree, and teach weaving on the college level. At the Arrowmont dedication, a silver tray formerly be-longing to the D.C. Alpha chapter house was presented to Arrowmont. Here Grand Vice President of Philanthropies, Sarah Holmes Hunt, accepts it from Grand President Emeritus, Marianne Reid Wild, and Gamma Alumnae Province President, Maurine Stuart Dunn. </p>
      <pb ref="arr8720039_0003" seq="03" n="42-43  "/>
       <p>Cerebral Palsy Victim Is Popular Student by ELEANOR BUSHNELL LEHNER DENNIS JACKSON. of Los Angeles wears a ceramic medallion created for him by fellow students to celebrate the completion of his session at Arrowmont. Dennis, the assistant recreation director for the Los Angeles County Crippled Children's Society, was awarded a scholarship to Arrowmont by the Los Angeles Alumnee Club. Both walking and talking are difficult for Dennis because he has been a victim of cerebral palsy since birth. But his constant cheerfulness and his ability to make others feel at ease made him one of the most popular students on the Arrowmont scene. The medallion his friends gave to him dubbed him "Dennis the Clay Menace" because of activities in the pottery lab. When Dennis was a youngster he attended a Crippled Children's Society camp. Later he offered his services as a volunteer and discovered that he enjoyed the work. Now he holds a bachelor's degree in sociology and a master's in recreation from California State College, and his primary job is the planning of recreational activities for young crippled adults. Dennis makes light of his personal difficul-An article about Shaheda Khanam of Dacca, East Pakistan, which appeared in the Summer, 1970, ARROW, mentioned the colorful saris she wore to the delight of her fellow students. As one of them exclaimed, "She wore a different sari every single day." For students learning weaving and textile design this was a special bonus. Here she is in the sari she wore to the dedication of the Emma Harper Turner building. Shaheda spent the entire summer at Arrowmont, working toward her Masters in Crafts from U.T. ties. "Look," he says, "we've all got something to give. So what are you going to do about it ? hide it under other things you don't have ? You must face the fact that you've got this particular thing. Then you can accept it. The secret, if there is one, is to care about life . . to care about people. I do." In return, it was quite evident at Arrowmont, that people care about Dennis. 42 Arrowmont Benefits Reach Far Afield by PAT KELLY SWAN Upsilon Province President How MANY years have you been a Pi Phi ? For me, after a membership of 23 years, the words Gatlinburg, Settlement School, and Arrowmont have a very real meaning. How I wish all of you could experience what I did when I attended Arrowmont this past June. We as Pi Beta Phis have so much, a unique philanthropy in "our" Arrowmont. The building is beautiful and every need to facilitate the finest kind of an arts and crafts center has been included in its planning. How exciting it was to attend the first session ever held in this magnificent setting. How proud I was to be a Pi Phi and to be involved and surrounded with others who were interested in gaining new ideas and knowledge in the fields of crafts. The unusual wall hangings from the looms, the contemporary designs in the jewelry lab, the perfection done by the enamelists, the rich batik and hand printed fabrics from the textile department, and of course the warm earthy glazes from the kiln. To be a part of this could not help but awake and stimulate creativity. The benefits of Arrowmont are far reaching. The borders of Tennessee are no longer the limits of its students. For example, during my session there were two Roman Catholic Sisters from Louisiana who are teachers at a retarded children's home. A craft instructor from Ohio who worked with senior citizens was attending through a Pi Beta Phi alumnae scholarship. The Los Angeles Alumnae Club sent a representative from their local Easter Seal Foundation. Orphan children in Selma, Ala. were to have many new projects to make upon the return of their hobby teacher. How satisfying it is to know that Arrowmont is giving so many persons new inspiration for themselves and their pupils. To create beauty for pleasure and for others allows a per-son, regardless of age, the gratification of a purposeful life. Arrowcraft alumnae sales make it possible to keep the volume of business large enough in the Gatlinburg shop to support many of the south-ern craftsmen who make our merchandise. Be-cause of this, it is more important than ever for Pat Swan stands beside the silk screen she made using Mt. Hood, Oregon, as her theme. Pat attended the first two-week session of Arrowmont last summer. us as individuals to support this outstanding project. All profit from local sales go to Arrowmont, but this is not enough to support the school. Your donations and bequests will truly benefit so many those in the field of education and those individuals who by their own choice cannot help but create beautiful crafts after at-tending a workshop at Arrowmont. Design and Textile Design instructor, Sister Mary Remy, presented the first program in the new auditorium. As chairman of the art department at Mount Mary College in Milwaukee, she recently returned from a year's leave of absence during which she explored the art crafts of Finland on a Fulbright Research Grant. Students and guests were invited to a showing of color slides illustrating her findings. 43 </p>
      <pb ref="arr8720039_0004" seq="04" n="44-45  "/>
       <p>Dori Lehner, left, displays a wall hanging and tote bag she created in the beginning weaving class. Devony Lehner, right, poses with some of the ceramic pieces she created in the beginning pottery class. Dori and Devony Share Enthusiasm Two SISTERS from Los Angeles, the daughters of Pi Phi's national public relations chair-man, Eleanor Bushnell Lehner, were enthusiastic 1970 summer workshop students. Doriana, a Stanford graduate, was initiated into Phi Beta Kappa, and then boarded a midnight plane in order to arrive at Arrowmont in time for the opening of the summer session. An anthropology major, an international folk dancing expert who has given demonstration performances for underprivileged and handicapped groups, and a teacher of piano to blind children, Dori at-tended Arrowmont to acquire a knowledge of crafts to augment the services she can offer toothers. Devony Lehner, Dori's sister and a Stanford junior, flew with her to Gatlinburg to attend the first summer session. Also an anthropology major, Devony is a skillful photographer who provided several photographs for this issue and for promotional bulletins. After four weeks of classes, the sisters were sent to Asheville, N.C., to set up the Arrowmont display at the five day Craftsman's Fair of the Southern Highlands. Accompanying them on this project were students Joann Alspaugh of Knoxville and Susan Homer of New Canaan, Conn. Works On Thesis BARBARA GAGE of Southfield, Mich., is not a Pi Phi. But her interest in Arrowmont is so great that she has chosen for her thesis topic for her Master's Degree at the University of Tennessee: "An Historical Study of the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School." The study will deal with "the founding of the school and the development of its various programs to meet the educational, financial and health needs of the people of the Gatlinburg Community." Barbara received her Bachelor of Science from Michigan State University in Home Eco-nomics Education. She became interested in the school when she first attended the Craft Work-shop in 1962. Since then she has attended work-shops in 1964, 1969, and again last summer, 1970. Since the fall of 1969 Barbara has been at-tending the University of Tennessee where she has been working for her Master's Degree in Related Arts, Crafts and Interior Design. She hopes to finish the thesis and receive her degree in December, after which she plans to return to MiChigan to teach crafts in a junior high school. 44 Chapter "Patients" Aid Disaster Drill by GEORGIA PATTERSON Kansas Beta Saturday, May 2, the Kansas Beta chapter ran a practice disaster drill with the local St. Mary's Hospital. The drill was used to test the speed and accuracy of hospital and ambulance personnel in emergency situations such as tornados. Injuries of the mock tornado victims ranged from dead-on-arrival, concussions, internal in-juries, and pregnant women, to broken arms and legs. When the ambulances arrived, the victims were sprawled out on the lawn with cards Freshman Camp Counselors Chosen by KRIs CARLSON, Minnesota Alpha For the past thirty years it has been a tradition at the University of Minnesota to sponsor a weekend retreat known as Freshman Camp. This is held one weekend toward the latter part of the summer and is offered to all freshman and transfer students. The main purpose of the camp is to provide the students with numerous experiences that may have some bearing on their future feelings toward university life. There are seven freshman camps and several student counselors to a camp who combine their talents and ideas to make each camp a success. One of the key factors in making the camp a valuable experience are the highly qualified student counselors. A detailed process is used by the university in selecting those students. who will become the camp counselors best suited for the job. This selection takes place many months prior to the initial camp, followed by many hours discussing new ideas which will be beneficial for the camp. The students are encouraged to participate in the various phases of the program. The schedule includes everything from guest speakers, to dances, skits and informal discussions. These camps in the past have resulted in excellent indoctrination experiences for incoming fresh-man. Minnesota Alpha is extremely proud of the Pi Phis that are involved in this program.around their necks telling the ambulance drivers what injuries each girl had. The ambulances took each of us to the hospital in order of the seriousness of our injuries. On stretchers, we were transported from the ambulances through the emergency entrances of the hospital to the waiting area where doctors and nurses examined us. Then, the doctors ordered each victim to the part of the hospital where she would get the best care. The internal injury cases were sent into surgery, the pregnant women went to the maternity ward, and the dead-on-arrival girls were even transported to the morgue! The chapter had a great time helping out St. Mary's Hospital and is already looking forward to being "patients" again next spring ! Epsilon Pledge Award To Honor Candy Armstrong The May meeting of the Clearwater, Florida, Alumnae Club, will remain in the memory of at least one member for a long time. Candace Secor Armstrong, former Theta Alumnae Province President, was the surprise honoree at the meeting. In her honor, the Clearwater club will be awarding a Revere silver bowl, the Candace Armstrong Bowl, to the Epsilon pledge class with the highest grades and proficiency in fraternity service and education. It will be a traveling award, and the recipient will be selected annually by the province president. To further the surprise, the bowl was presented by Candy's daughter, Delynn Armstrong Barton, Alabama Alpha, a member of the Tampa Alumnae Club. Candy resigned as Theta Alumnae Province President when her husband, Jim, was seriously injured in a car wreck in September, 1968. Her love and loyalty to Pi Phi dates back to college days. She transferred to Rollins for her junior year as Florida Gamma was installed by Amy B. Onken, to be the first affiliate of the new chap-ter. She was elected president her senior year. She held many offices, including president, in the Orlando Club. She moved to Largo as the Clearwater Club was chartered and has been on its board in some capacity ever since, having served two years as president. 45 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



