<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr8110055_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Alumnae Letters</title>
                        <author><name>Capen, Mrs. Edward K.</name></author>
                        <author><name>Huff, Pauline Whaling</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Fall 1964</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr8110055_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1964</date>, Alumnae Letters</title>
                        <author><name>Capen, Mrs. Edward K.</name></author>
                        <author><name>Huff, Pauline Whaling</name></author>
                        <extent>Page 54</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">41</note>
                        <note type="Folder">1</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 81, Number 1 (Fall 1964), Page 54.</note>
			<note type="document">arr8110055_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Knoxville; Little Pigeon</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Changing Mission of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity for Women in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1944-1964</item>
                                <item>Community</item>
                                <item>Activities</item>
                                <item>People</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr8110055_0001" seq="01" n="54-55  "/>
       <p>54 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI and alumnae living in the Chattanooga area. In February, our regular meeting was well attended, with Alice Alsobrook reporting on the house corporation. Plans were made for a casserole sup-per to be held in March in honor of Alumnae Province President Marguerite Hickey and a member of our club, Mrs. Fred J. Flint, who was selected Mrs. Chattanooga and later Mrs. Tennessee. On April 25, our Founders' Day luncheon, held at Fairyland Club, was well attended. We ended the year with a meeting on May 12, at which time we honored graduating seniors and in-stalled new officers. The Signal Mountain Area Group had their four scheduled coffees, with a speaker at each. In August the speaker was Linda Ricketts, active rush chairman; in October, Edna Bunn, Chattanooga Alumnee Club President; in January, 'Marguerite Hickey, Eta Province Alumnae President; and in March, Betty Blocker, charter member of Tennessee A. JOAN HILL HANKS LEXINGTON For the 1963-64 season, the Lexington Alumnae Club met every month from September through May, with the exception of December. The meetings opened with a pot luck supper for the new pledges at the chapter house. In October, a joint meeting was held with the actives, pledges, and mothers of Kentucky Be Besides becoming better acquainted, the opportunity was available for all to Christmas shop through a Settlement School sale, and alumnae and mothers had the chance to see one of the skits used by the actives in rushing. In January, the club had a potluck supper in honor of Marguerite Hickey, Eta Province Alumnae President. The group was most grateful to Mrs. Hickey for her many helpful ideas on improving the club and suggestions for money making projects. Our money making project for this year was a benefit bridge party at a local country club. This was most successful, as well as enjoyable. April was a busy month, with Founders' Day celebrated jointly with Kentucky A and Kentucky B at a local country club, and a senior farewell supper. Aside from meetings, several members devoted a great deal of their time to planning the new chapter house at the University of Kentucky. Phyllis Foster Parker worked many hours with the architects, assisting in the drafting of floor plans that resulted in everything a college girl could desire in her college home. Ground for the new house was broken in the spring of 1964, and construction is underway, with the completion date set for January, 1965. NANCY F. HARRIS KNOXVILLE From the picnic for the new pledges and actives in September to the supper given for the graduating seniors in May, the Knoxville Alumna: Club feels it has had a most successful year. Something new has been added in several ways this year to stir up interest and enthusiasm. The first was the organization of a group meeting in the daytime once a month for a covered dish luncheon. Those who attended were interested alumnae who found it impossible to attend night meetings. A member of the regular night group also attended each month to bring information on their activities. Though the group is still small, these meetings were looked forward to both for fellowship and delicious food. The year's biggest project came in November. To attract Christmas shoppers, an A-frame type chalet was designed and constructed by able and willing husbands of our alumnae group. Ronald Reid was responsible for the architectural plans, while William A. Akers, with the help of other husbands, did the constructing. The chalet was set upon the Mall in downtown Knoxville and stocked with merchandise from the Settlement School and quick snacks for the busy shoppers. To add atmosphere, actives from our University of Tennessee chapter were dressed in appropriate costumes and circulated through the crowds. Special chairmen for these events were: Mrs. Keith R. Leech, food; Mrs. Herbert P. Neff, Jr., Settlement School items; Mrs. John N. Christopher, costumes; Mrs. William Booker and Mrs. Charles S. Vesel, publicity. If cooperation means success, the project would have shown a tremendous profit, but one item over which we had no control hampered the sales and that was the weather. Though plagued by rain each time we opened, still enough was sold to show a small profit. Our faith in this idea has not been shaken so the chalet is stored away, while plans are being made to try again next year. The third new interest factor added this year was a mid-year news letter written by our president, Mrs. Paul C. Helton, and mailed to all area alumni with an up-to-date summary of all that happened during the year and outlining the plans for the remainder of the year. This was appreciated by alumnre who find it impossible to attend meetings regularly. Other outstanding meetings of the year included a joint meeting with the local mother's club. This has become an annual affair, which fosters interest in our active chapter. Our Founders' Day luncheon was made a success due to the fact that we were joined by the Little Pigeon Alumnae from Gatlinburg, as well as our active chapter from the University of Tennessee. The actives were in charge of the program, which included a sk't in honor of the "Founder of the Year." To close the year, the daytime group is joining the regularalumnae group for a covered dish luncheon. We all have big hopes and plans for next year. MRS. EDWARD K. CAPEN LITTLE PIGEON Little Pigeon Alum= Club has a very pleasant and cooperative year. One of the outstanding attractions of the fall season was the Craftsman's 'Fair. Our club was delighted to contribute to Settlement School a colored movie, directed by Barbara McCroskey and edited by Marjorie Chalmers. It is available for all clubs. The members were pleased to entertain Marguerite Bacon Hickey, our alumnae province president, with a potluck supper in November. She brought us many helpful ideas and encouraged us in our successes. This was also the night for the preview for the craft film and script. She found it very praise worthy. The annual Spring style show was given March 21 at Huff House, the recreational building of Mountain View Hotel. Marion Webb Mueller was chairman of this event for the second year. Every member made an important contribution toward the success of this show, our only money making project of the year. Two Knoxville shops provided the clothes, which were worn by local women and children. There were prizes for men, women, and children, and refreshments for all. In December, at the annual Christmas party for the boys and girls in the Settlement School dormitory, a box of candy was given to each and a badminton set for all. This year our club joined the Knoxville Club to celebrate Founders' Day, at a luncheon at the Andrew Johnson Hotel. Elizabeth Waitt Rue and Dorothy Harper Davis, both of Iowa-l' and initiated in the same pledge class fifty years ago, received special recognition. PAULINE WHALING HUFF LOUISVILLE An enjoyable Kentucky A-Louisville Alumnae Club card party, at the chapter house, where alumnae members met the new pledges on an informal basis, began our busy year. President Anne Shulhafer Vanderburgh awarded Settlement School articles as prizes for highest scores. Our October program, presented by Sue McGee Baker, concerned constructing Christmas decorations for the home. We felt that early instruction of creative ideas was ideal for those of us who wished to work on these festive touches in November. Autumn was brightened for the Pi Beta Phis by the annual Settlement School and handicraft sale, for which we not only utilized Gatlin-burg products, but also employed the skills of our alumnae in producing beautiful cloth, paper, pottery, and food items to sell. Two notable events occurred in January. Our alumnae province president, Marguerite Bacon Hickey, visited one of our meetings, and the University of Louisville-Dayton game was followed by a lovely party, at the home of Janet McWilliam Smith. A new committee was established in February to carry out plans for commissioning an artist to paint the late Emma J. Woerner's portrait for a Louisville public school, which is being named in honor of this beloved Pi Beta Phi humanitarian. Funds are now being accepted from any who wish to contribute to what we consider one of the most important projects in the history of our club. Following our February business meeting, a "Guess-What" auction, a successful innovation of bidding on boxes containing different prizes ranging from twenty-five cent items upward, was both hilarious and financially rewarding. Our Founders' Day luncheon, in April, was followed by another activity with the Kentuuky A's in June, the senior fare-well dinner, held at the home of Ethel Krieger Dering, at which the seniors were given presents by the collegiates, after an impressive ceremony. MARY BEVERLY SPITZER MEMPHIS The 'Memphais Alumnae Club has taken on a special air of enthusiasm since the installation of the new active chapter at Memphis State University, and appropriately opened the year with a coffee at the new Panhellenic Building on campus. With Joanne Hagen Murdock as president, the club has over fifty members this year and has begun plans to form a junior group, which will, meet at night. Eta Alumnae Province President Marguerite Bacon Hickey visited Memphis for our November meeting, when we entertained the new pledge class. After an informal dinner at the home of Elizabeth Eddy Dameron, the pledges serenaded the group then rushed back to the dormitory before curfew. In December, husbands of the members were guests of honor at the annual Christmas party. At the potluck luncheon in February, everyone was making plans for the telephone bridge, which was the club's fund raising project for the year. Throughout the month of March, members entertained one or more tables of bridge in their homes. Guests were charged $1 and, after each party, the highest scores were telephoned to the chairman, Sara Cook Green. At the end of the month, gift certificates of $5, $10, and $15 were presented to the three women with the highest scores. A great deal of the success of the project was due to the many members who joined together having larger groups. Two very ambitious mem THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI 55 bers, Peg Proctor Garrecht and Mae Keller Weiss, served lunch to eight tables of bridge on two consecutive days. The Founders' Day banquet was shared with the Tennessee Actives. Awards were presented and the new officers were in-stalled. The year's activities ended with a picnic at the summer home of Lu Brown Gruenberg on Coro Lake. NATALIE FISHER WATSON NASHVILLE Lake in October, fifty-seven members gathered at the home of Pat Sayers for the annual membership coffee. Our honored guests, Julia Heard, wife of Vanderbilt University's new chancellor, and Idanelle McMurray, new headmistress of Harbeth Hall, were given a special welcome by President Barbara Fridrich. November was devoted to plans and preparations for the third annual Pi Beta Phi Christmas Village, under the capable leader-ship of Mary Jane Evers and Ellen White 'Dillon. This year the active chapter had a Christmas wrapping booth and their profits went into a fund for furnishings for the new chapter house being built, which will be completed by fall. In January, the club enjoyed a visit from Alumnae Province President Marguerite Bacon Hickey, who talked on "Aims of Pi Beta Phi Alumnie Clubs." Nancy Fawn Diehl invited the club to her home for the February meeting. With great pleasure and pride, alumna: presented the Christmas village check of $2100 to Dr. Freeman McConnell, of the Bill Wilkerson Hearing and Speech Center. March found members trying to learn to be better cooks, with a delightful and informative meeting at the Martha White Testing Kitchens. In April, the club enjoyed a wonderful Founders' Day banquet, directed by Peggy Wade Elam. Toasts by Idanelle Mc-Murray, skits by the active chapter, and presentation of scholarship awards, by Elizabeth Marshall, highlighted the evening. New officers were installed in May and the Nashville Alumna` Club looks forward to a wonderful year under their Leadership. SARAH TODD HYMAN THETA PROVINCE ATLANTA A buffet supper, with Atlanta actives as guests, began the 1963-64 year of the Atlanta Alumnae Club. Tickets for a local department store gift certificate were sold, drawing to be held at the December meeting. October found everyone having a delightful dinner and meeting with Alumnae Province President Kathryn Leutwiler Tanton. She gave a very enlightening talk on nationwide fraternity problems. Arrowcraft articles helped us with our Christmas shopping, at the November meeting. Mrs. Miriam Wilson, Jr., head of the crafts department for the Atlanta Parks and 'Recreation Department, and Mrs. Gloria Kidd Brown, a residential designer, were guest speakers. Both of these ladies have attended the Settlement School summer workshops, and some of their beautiful arts and crafts were on display, showing some of the activities taught at the workshops. December was a busy month for all of us. The regular meeting was a small gift exchange Christmas party. A drawing for the $100 gift certificate was held, with Mrs. Aliene West being the winner. The mother-daughter tea, held at the home of Mrs. Jack Fraser, was a time for getting acquainted with the actives, pledges, and their mothers. March is the month for election of officers. 'Margaret Quante presented the history and constitution of Pi Beta Phi in a very clever and interesting way by using bingo cards. A Founders' Day banquet was held in April, with Judge Elmo Holt, of the Fulton County Juvenile Court, giving an excellent speech. Georgia A actives were guests and gave a history skit, which was chosen to be given at Convention. The May picnic brought to an end the Atlanta Alumme Club's activities for the year. Installation of new officers was held at this time. MRS. WENDELL W. GISH BIRMINGHAM In September, the Birmingham Alum= Club assisted Alabama A in two special rush parties, called "Angel Parties." Summer party plans were laid for in and out of town active members. The private home of one alumna almost burst at the seams when seventy-eight actives and alumnae attended the Loyalty Day dinner. Monthly night and day group meetings were well attended. Meetings varied with old and new ideas. Members brought baking and good outgrown children's clothing to the 'September meeting for an auction sale, which netted $70. March was set aside for a repeat sale. A raffle, with saving stamps from, Loyalty Day dinner purchases, along with a .50 lunch charge, augmented the treasury. The Arrowcraft sale was held in an attractive woods setting of a church, with refreshments. Theta Alumnae Province President Kathryn Lautwiler Tanton's informative talks to the fraternity were given in October, after lunch with the day group and dinner with the night group. The Christmas lunch and February dinner dance have become annual affairs. Both were held at Vestavia Country Club. The night group planned the Founders' Day banquet, with guest speaker Robert Garrison of Sigma Chi Fraternity. He spoke on how certain groups were trying to destroy the fraternity system. The local Panhellenic scholarship fund raised money by a lunch and fashion show, at the Birmingham Country Club, in February. The May picnic, in the lake setting of the cottage of two alumnae, has become the traditional way to end the year. NANCY BAKER LYNN CLEARWATER Virginia Whitney Harding has enthusiastically led the Clear-water Alumnae Club through many activities this year. Her success is most eloquently expressed by the tribute from members who voted unanimously to re-elect her for another year. Our monthly informal morning cooky-shine bridge or knitting meetings continue to be grand gatherings for the new and old members. These are scheduled to continue through the summer again this year. Bridge being very popular here, members held bridge sessions in their homes to raise funds for the Settlement School, during the month of October. Clearwater alumna: groups, representing about twenty women's fraternities, accepted the national pattern of Panhellenic and joined in a general rush party in June. The party was lovely, but somewhat disappointing in that a relatively small percentage of eligible girls came to find out about the various aspects of being a fraternity woman. In the fall, we were informed by Rollins College, Florida r, that they had pledged Lucy Anderson, who will make an outstanding Pi Beta Phi. October brought a visit from Theta Province Alumnie President Kathryn Leutwiler Tanton, who had as her guide Theta Province President Mary Jane Stein Derringer. After the meeting, Mary Jane spoke about her recent visit to Florida B and described renovations in the chapter house. She also gave a brief resume of the activities of other chapters. Entertaining husbands took precedence over everything in January and the many who came to the lovely dinner agreed that Betty Moyle Champeau was an organizer par excellence. In February, Kathryn Lage Wiley and Nadine James Carlisle were honored in being among the ten best dressed women in Clear-water. Kay was our alumna` club president last year and Nadine is taking over the post of rush chairman for the coming year. Celebration of Founders' Day took place at a luncheon April 25, which honored our five Golden Arrow members: Alice Howe Barry, Margaret Gordon Furd, Louise Osman Hinchcliff, Lucille Hunt Petrie, and Vivian M. Smith. Our inactive list of Golden Arrow members include: Irene Gould Albertson, Helen Taylor Aldrich, and Lena Dunning Kirby. ELIZABETH ADELL MCCORD FORT LAUDERDALE A feeling of responsibility to fraternity was instilled in the members of the Fort Lauderdale Alum= Club, at the September meeting, by Kathryn Leutwiler Tanton, alumnae province president. Under the capable leadership of two presidents, Margaret Jelstrom and Marilyn Johnston, club members met this responsibility in several ways. Working with other alum= groups in the Fort Lauderdale Panhellenic Club, members of Pi Beta Phi were instrumental in planning and carrying out programs for welcoming and entertaining the thousands of college students who visited our city in March. Utilizing a new approach, club members, working under Cynthia Blake, set up displays of Settlement School products in a major department store. The consensus was that this method could be used profitably in the future. In December, a cocktail dinner party was held honoring active members and their escorts. Alum= club members and their husbands enjoyed meeting active members from every state chapter and several out of state representatives. All, club members worked to make this night a memorable one for the visiting actives. Club members also worked together, under the guidance of Marilyn Johnston, to make the nine monthly programs interesting and entertaining. The schedule included a fashion show, a Halloween party, and an original skit. The traditional Founders' Day ceremony was celebrated with a luncheon for both the Fort Lauderdale and Hollywood Alumnae Clubs. Officers for the 1964-1965 year were installed. These new officers joined with the rest of the club to end the year's activities with a family picnic. It has been a good year for the Fort Lauderdale Alurnnw Club of Pi Beta Phi. It is the consensus of opinion that the club has accomplished much of what it set out to do. The members look forward with enthusiasm to the challenge of next year. JESSIE F. MILLIKAN GAINESVILLE This is our second year as an organization. Nancy Hawbeker Gilbert was our president this year. Our first meeting was a fall get-together, at the home of Margaret Thorpe Hart, to meet the new people who had come to Gainesville during the summer. On October 29, we held our first Settlement School sale, which </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



