<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr8110023_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Praise for the Past and Vision for the Future</title>

                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Fall 1964</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr8110023_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1964</date>, Praise for the Past and Vision for the Future</title>

                        <extent>Pages 23-24</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">41</note>
                        <note type="Folder">1</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 81, Number 1 (Fall 1964), Pages 23-24.</note>
			<note type="document">arr8110023_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Praise for the Past and Vision for the Future; Creative Arts and Crafts Center Chosen as Centennial Project</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Changing Mission of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity for Women in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1944-1964</item>
                                <item>Settlement Schools</item>
                                <item>Staff</item>
                                <item>People</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr8110023_0001" seq="01" n="22-23  "/>
       <p>Chapter Service National Award Winners Sara Mieher Mimsi Sass Delta and Lambda province chapter service award winners shared the national award in 1964. Mimsi Sass, D. C. Alpha and Sara Mieher, Mississippi Beta, earned the recognition on the basis of their outstanding leadership and tireless devo-tion to detail in all areas of chapter organization and work. Both winners have served their chapters as presidents and have maintained high scholarship records in spite of their heavy loads of responsibility as chapter officers. CONVENTION SPEAKER (Continued from page 13) cism about the all-sorority average, which is consistently higher than the all-women's average, when there is idle chatter by fraternity women about the extensive examination files maintained in the house, when faculty advisors are asked to adjust an academic schedule so that a pledge can make her grades for initiation, when a chapter requires that members take reduced academic loads in order to raise the grade point average, and when the practice of taking incomplete grades in difficult schedules is advocated or condoned. This is not the best practice in my opinion. "The mean level of the ability of college students has been going up and the serious scholars, at least in my observation, in many instances are shunning affiliation with fraternities because they believe that the many chapter functions are anachronistic and the archaic activities promoted by fraternities will interfere with the real purpose of higher education. As Maria Leonard, the Founder of AlphaLambda Delta, national scholastic society for fresh-man women, has said, "Education is not something you get, it is something that you become." I would like to voice the old fashioned sentiment that I hope you are getting it in a becoming way. "In the matter of development of leadership, the disjointed nature of the large campus is pain-fully apparent. On a campus of 12,000 students less than one-half of one percent will attain positions of conspicuous leadership, by dedication and meticulous attention to the student power structure. The contribution of leadership will be through the small friendship group of the fraternity, with sincere and reasoned cooperation with other groups holding similar aims. .. I close with a quotation from the eminent scientist Einstein who said to youth : "Try not to become a person of success only but a person of value. The world is demanding this of youth to-day because a different world cannot be built by indifferent people." "May this be your individual as well as your chapter creed." 22 Praise for the Past and Vision for the Future Standing at a crossroads in the area of philanthropic service in 1964, Pi Beta Phi members at-tending the 44th biennial Convention heard their 52-year old philanthropy, the Settlement School de-scribed as "the most important philanthropic venture ever undertaken by a fraternity" and also listened to suggestions for a new development in philanthropy that could "be an ideal opportunity to provide continued leadership in the utilization of human resources through a judicious, sound, yet in-spired program." Those statements came in talks made during the Settlement School program by Miss Marian Heard, University of Tennessee professor of Arts and Crafts, and director of the Pi Beta Phi-UT Summer Craft Workshop, and Dr. Lura M. Odland, Dean of the College of Home Economics of the University of Tennessee. Miss Heard . Miss Heard dealt both with the past and the future. "I come to you from a wonderful section of the country that you all know, that is very dear to your hearts, from a valley in the Smokies, from Gatlin-burg, the site where your sorority sisters, desiring to serve mankind, established the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School. From this site, this launching pad, many successful ventures have been placed into orbit, some to orbit only locally, some of national significance, some of international significance. ". . . Without doubt, your Fraternity's Settlement School, with all its ramifications, is the most important philanthropic venture ever undertaken by a fraternity. ". . Health and education were your primary purposes but you were very flexible, wise and appreciative of the heritage and culture of the mountain people. You enlarged the scope of your influence to a cottage industry and later, the Arrow-craft Shop. ". . Let's think of what the Arrowcraft Shop has meant to the Pi Beta Phi sorority. Every piece bought at the Arrowcraft Shop carries the Pi Phi tag. What better advertisement all over the United States and foreign countries ? The annual alum= sale has been a cohesive force some common goal to work for. People in the community take away a story plus a concrete object, which is always a credit to the Pi Phis. ". . In 1945, there was a desire on the part of the Pi Beta Phi Fraternity to extend their training and extend their influence in the craft field even more so than locally or through the Arrowcraft Shop. And so by combining with the University of Tennessee, a craft workshop was started. We havenever had less than thirty States represented at our workshop. We have had people from 43 different states and 13 foreign countries. ". . We have teachers from all levels, specialists who work with the blind, who work with the deaf . . . people who work with women in prisons. We have people who work with the aged or geriatrics. We have people who have trained with us and who have gone in later and studied and concentrated on working with crippled children. ". . These are a few things that you put into orbit. You have been very successful with them. But I would like you to face: what's our future? You pioneered very successfully. We hope that you will wish to pioneer again. ". . We would like to propose a great creative craft and art center at Gatlinburg. You have a great investment there. You have a reputation for absolute excellence. You have the highest standards in your craft workshop. You have the appreciation of the people in the community who realize that if it had not been for the Pi Beta Phi School and the education they were able to obtain there, they would not enjoy the position they do in the community. You have a craft climate which has never been known since the country became industrialized. You are in an area where more crafts are indigenous to the area than any other part of the United States. You are in an area where our Southern Highland Guild is the largest area guild of any one in the United States. ". . . This creative craft center would be a much, much different thing than the craft workshop carried on five or six weeks in the summer. This would be a year-round project, not classes all year round, but there would be times when nationally known craftsmen would come and teach for the very fine proficient craftsmen of this country.. .There would be times when we could have credit people come. There would be times when people would come and go back to communities to work with the blind, the deaf, the crippled, all areas . . . they are all demanding craft people. . . . So again, you are blessed with a wonderful opportunity to do a service to mankind, a field that is wide open. Some organization is going to meet this challenge, this dream. We hope with the wonderful pioneering work that you have done previously to this that it will be the fraternity which has done so much in promoting the crafts, in adding to the cultural climate of the area in which they settled. Dean Odland . Dean Odland spoke of the University of Tennessee's association with Pi Beta Phi in the Craft 23 </p>
      <pb ref="arr8110023_0002" seq="02" n="24-25  "/>
       <p>24 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI Workshop and reaffirmed the University's interest in such a project. .. I would like to cite a few faCts and figures in regard to the Pi Phi-UT Craft Center in Gatlinburg, Tennessee. The center is recognized as a serious and studious program. The participants include students of arts and crafts, high school and college instructors, occupational therapists, commercial artists, extension agents and specialists, as well as independent craftsmen. Also, an international reputation has been established through students from seventeen countries, including India, Greece, Turkey, Indonesia, Fin-land, Iran, Thailand and Pakistan also Hawaii, Puerto Rico and the Philippine Islands. The State Department, the International Cooperation Agency, the Federal AID, ICA and other groups regularly schedule visits to Gatlinburg for those students and visitors who are interested in the development of sound craft programs for their native countries. A talky of participants over the years indicates that approximately 3,000 students have enrolled in the Craft Center program, including over 100 International students from many countries around the world. It would seem interesting, almost imperative to obtain some census of the extent to which these 3,000 students have spread the influence of the Craft Workshop program of Pi Beta Phi, throughout the country and throughout the world at all socio-economic, age and activity levels. "This is an era of growth and development in all human undertakings. While we have spectacular developments in the sciences, with communication technology and space studies, we have reason to wonder if we are making equally spectacular progress in our realms of understanding of human re-sources and needs. . There would seem to be a unique opportunity here for a contribution in the field of Crafts. It would seem too, that with a historical background of successful pioneering on the part of Pi Beta Phi in the area of Craft development programs, there would be an ideal opportunity to provide continued leadership in the utilization of human resources through judicious, sound, yet inspired programs. "I do speak for the University of Tennessee in our support of our mutual interest in the further development of such programs. We have enjoyedand appreciated the opportunity to work with you through the years we would be pleased to continue with program development for future undertakings. ". . . We are revising curricula and research and service programs to adapt to changing times and concepts. It is appropriate too, to investigate any means, instructional research or extended services whereby we might enhance the Craft Center pro-gram. ". . From the University of Tennessee, President Holt, Vice President Spivey, Vice President Read and Dean Hilton Smith of our Graduate School wish me to extend greetings and encouragement in our undertakings of mutual interest . . . we all consider this program to be one quite in keeping with our "reaching for greatness" in an academic atmosphere, with the leadership provided by the Pi Beta Phi Fraternity and our major representative, Miss Heard. "The good we do, whether it be in a chapter house, in the university or in the world, lives after us. May the spirit that fostered the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School in the beginning, support continuing programs through the years to come so that the entire work may act as a leaven to help not only the Pi Phis but the fraternity spirit from one end of this great nation to its uttermost bounds which now include the world." Three future Pi Phi alumnae smile their approval at some proposed plans for future developments at the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School site in Gatlinburg-plans that are expected to lead to the development of an Arts and Crafts Center as the Centinnial Project. 4 Arrow Information Bulletin Available The 1964 Arrow Information Bulletin containing convention minutes and reports of national officers and committee chairmen is now available to members of the Fraternity. A copy may be obtained by sending a request to Central Office with the following information: 1. Maiden name, active chapter and class. 2. Married name and address. Are You an Inactiue Pi Phi? This Page is for Your in ormation! Pi Phis active in chapters and alumnae clubs will are unable to be present at the regular fall meet-hear the report concerning the new centennial fund ings. Of course all interested Pi Phis are invited project at the meetings this fall. This detailed exto read on. planation is for the information of those who Creative Arts and Crafts Center Chosen as Centennial Project The 44th Biennial Convention of Pi Beta Phi, meeting at Victoria, B.C., Canada, voted to celebrate Pi Beta Phi's Centennial by establishing a center for education in the field of arts and crafts at Gatlinburg, Tennessee.By 1967, a gradual phasing out of some parts of the Settlement School pro-gram will have been effected and other parts will have been incorporated in the new centennial project. This center will have a four-fold purpose. It will provide training for therapists and volunteers working with physically and mentally handicapped. It will provide further education for professionals and educators in the field of arts and crafts. It will provide an introduction to ways of using leisure time in a creative manner to many who seek to en-rich their lives. It will provide a show-case and training center to other countries as to how creative crafts native to a country can be preserved and developed. Our Summer Workshop in Gatlinburg has al-ready attracted people from many foreign countries, top craftsmen from our own country and those working in hospitals and rehabilitation centers with mentally and physically handicapped.Our new centennial project will make these courses available on a quarterly basis, and those who want college credit will receive it from the University of Tennessee. All those who, for a variety of reasons, will be seeking to learn more about creative arts and crafts will be brought together in an already established atmosphere of excellent craftsmanship. As Pi Phi's Centennial Fund provides for the buildings, equipment and personnel for our new project, our birthday will be celebrated by all thosewhose lives will be enriched by this program. Many will profit directly by coming to the center them-selves, but there will be even more who will feel the influence of our birthday fund when those who have learned at the center return to their own communities to teach. They may teach children to appreciate the beauty in this world and to create beauty themselves, or they may teach injured muscles to work again, or they may teach dulled minds to recognize their surroundings and become alert to reality, or they may teach senior citizens to use their days creatively and productively, or they may teach a community to become aware of the possibilities of creative talent among its own citizens and the advisability of preserving the pat-terns of its heritage. The possibilities of increased enrichment of lives in a variety of areas are unlimited and exciting. Our fund is still small, only $85,000. If each Pi Phi throughout the fraternity will contribute to our one-hundredth birthday party, our new project will begin in a manner worthy of our first one-hundred years. It has been suggested that each Pi Phi send $1.00 for each year of the 100 years which she has shared with Pi Phi; that is, a dollar for each year from the date of her initiation to 1967. Or each Pi Phi might send $1.00 for each of the twelve founders. These donations may be made in one sum, or pledged over a three-year period. Whether you are a dollar-a-year Pi Phi, or a dollar-a-founder Pi Phi, do be a loyal Pi Phi and give joyously. Join those Pi Phis from ocean to ocean who are contributing to the Centennial Fund and help make the celebration of our first one-hundred years a glorious one. ---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- Donations may be sent to the Centennial Fund Treaslirer: Mrs. Theodore N. Shreve, 417 Leyden St., Denver, Colo. Please fill in the following information and mail it with your contribution. Maiden name Married name Chapter Address .. . City State Zip Code Closest Alumnae club 25 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



