<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr8320033_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Gordon, Sally Wild</name></author>
                        <author><name>Eddy, Susan</name></author>
                        <author><name>Mintich, Mary</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Winter 1966</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr8320033_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1966</date>, News From Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Gordon, Sally Wild</name></author>
                        <author><name>Eddy, Susan</name></author>
                        <author><name>Mintich, Mary</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 33-37</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">41</note>
                        <note type="Folder">3</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 83, Number 2 (Winter 1966), Pages 33-37.</note>
			<note type="document">arr8320033_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">What Is Settlement School?; Pi Beta Phi Scholarships to 1966 Workshop; Workshop Valuable Help; Inspiration in the Smokies; An Artist's Touch for Centennial Party</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>The Birth of Arrowmont, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1965-1979</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>
                                <item>Summer craft workshop</item>
                                <item>Funding</item>
                                <item>Students</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr8320033_0001" seq="01" n="32-33  "/>
       <p>Florida Beta Pi Phi Is Hos pits s First Woman Chief of Staff from the Marion (County Florida) Sentinel When Dr. Margaret Palmer assumed the position of chief of staff at Munroe Memoria'. Hospital (Ocala, Florida) last fall, she became the first woman physician ever elected to the high position. She faces the problems of the office with the same frank, clear-headed approach that has made her one of the most respected physicians in Marion County and is fully aware that the additional duties of the position will practically eliminate the small amount of free time she has now. What she does not say is that the position of chief of staff is an elective one, voted on by the physicians on the staff of the hospital. This is added proof that practicing physicians and surgeons in Marion County have long held Dr. Palmer in es-teem and have high regard for her ability, with absolutely no prejudice against her because she is a woman in what is generally regarded as a "man's world." Dr. Palmer underscores her every reference to Munroe Memorial Hospital with a tone of pride pride in the progress it has made since she became the first woman to practice medicine in Marion County in 1953, in the growth of the physical structure, in its modern facilities and equipment, in the excellency of the staff physicians and surgeons, in the people of Marion County through the hospital board of trustees, for the support that has made this progress possible. And last, but not least, she reflects pride in the attitudes which have permitted the smooth transition from a segregated hospital to an integrated one. The chief of staff also serves as chairman of the hospital's executive and credentials committee, and presides over the monthly staff meetings and any additional emergency meetings that are called. It is the duty of the chairman of the executive commit-tee to bring before the staff any problems that pre-sent themselves at the hospital. As chairman of the credentials committee, the chief of staff must decide, with the committee, on the eligibility of each staff member and his ability to perform required functions in the hospital. It is this committee that also decides the qualifications of any staff applications. Dr. Palmer, who has served previously as secretary-treasurer of the hospital staff, is fully cognizant of the many problems and needs of the hospital, and feels it's something of a record that there has been little, if any, disagreement between the hospital staff and its trustees. Since Margaret Palmer returned to her hometown to practice she has also noted with satisfaction the expansion of the Marion County medical profession and the highly qualified physicians and specialists that have been attracted to Ocala. With a smile Dr. Palmer notes that of all the influx of doctors, only one other woman physician resides in Ocala, Dr. Gertrude Warner, the pathologist at the hospital. Which brings up the inevitable question why are so few women in the medical profession ? Weighing her words carefully, Dr. Palmer says that women are the one human resource that can be most readily tapped to meet the enormous demands for health care and that anyone with scientific leaning, regardless of sex, should consider the medical profession. She believes that the rigidity of the average medical course, especially the intern and residency years, the attitude of "a woman's place is in the home," and the fact that the practice of medicine is exhaustingly demanding both physically and emotionally, retard the recruitment of women in medicine more than any sex barrier or prejudice. "I honestly dislike the word `dedicated' but is there a substitute? You have to want to be a doctor so much that nothing and no one can deter you if you don't then the practice of medicine will never be a rewarding effort which it is to me. You live with the telephone, you know 24 hours a day, every day of the week, except when you change with another doctor for a long weekend or sparse vacations and get where no phone is in reach," says Dr. Palmer. Did she determine when she was very young that she would be a doctor ? "It makes a nice story," she grins, "But it's not fact. The fact is I loved going to school. I entered Florida State College for Women (FSU) as a chemistry major, changed to zoology when I transferred to Duke University in 1945, graduated from Duke in 1947 with an A.B. in zoology, and it was then I think I decided to go into medicine." (Dr. Palmer was not only a Florida Beta Pi Phi, but also affiliated with North Carolina Beta at Duke.) Nevertheless, the determined Miss Palmer en-rolled at Emory and graduated in 1951 as Dr. Margaret Palmer. There were four other girls in medical school with her all four graduated and all four are doctors today. Dr. Palmer is not the only Pi Phi in her family. Her sister, also a Florida Beta, Mrs. Frederick Swindal lives in Tampa. 32 News from tittle Pigeon Edited by Sally Wild Gordon, Wisconsin A At Settlement School . ...Our roots are deep in craft programs. ...On the foundation of Arrowcraft, which began in 1925, we have built toward a bright future in art and crafts. . . .The new Craft Center is part of that future and opens the door to new accomplishments that will be a source of pride to all Pi Phis. Learning a Craft Beverly Lewis, Virginia Delta Pi Phi from Norfolk, Virginia and a student at Old Dominion College, learns the craft of enameling at the 1965 Craft Workshop, which she attended as the recipient of the Virginia Alpha Craft Workshop Scholarship. </p>
      <pb ref="arr8320033_0002" seq="02" n="34-35  "/>
       <p>What Is Settlement School? The May L. Keller Award Program 1966 by Susan Eddy, Iowa Alpha (based on Peanuts' "What Is Happiness?") Settlement School is a national altruistic project. Settlement School is a memorial to our twelve Founders, who established the first women's fraternity, April 28, 1867. Settlement School is opportunity offered by Pi Beta Phi to others, to help themselves. Settlement School is education in the field of art and craft. Settlement School is togetherness shared by students from all parts of the United States and foreign countries, when attending Craft Workshop. Settlement School is the first philanthropic project supported by a fraternity, giving financial support through the active chapters and alumnae clubs, to expand the educational program. Settlement School is Arrowcraft Shop, a market for hand weaving and crafts. Settlement School is Summer Craft workshop, a workshop co-sponsored by the University of Tennessee and Pi Beta Phi, where creative ability is ex-pressed. Settlement School is happiness in helping others to help them-selves. Settlement School is the 1967 Centennial Project Pi Beta Phi Art and Craft Center. Impressions of a Pi Phi Delegate Maxine Goldback, President of the Pasadena Alumnae Club, included the following paragraph in her Fall letter to the club members. "Pi Phis met and renewed their pledges of faith and fellowship at the 45th Biennial Convention in Gatlinburg this summer. Could I have but one wish, it would be that each of you could have shared in this experience. A dream of mine came true, that I was visiting our Settlement School. Oh yes, the village has become a tourist mecca, but once one leaves the main street with the neon lights, teeming crowds and tourist attractions to stand on Pi Phi property beside the original Log Cabin and look out across the meadow to the mountains, her imagination soon carries her back across the years to the time when Pi Phi first came to this valley and began this project beside the Little Pigeon River. One is most proud when the progress of the Settlement School is seen, the praise of the local residents is heard and a look into the future shows the results which will be achieved by our Centennial Project." 34 Pi Beta Phi Sponsored Scholarships to 1966 Workshop Albuquerque Alumnae Club Martha Dawson, a student teacher from Corsicana, Texas, for the full session. Berkeley Alumnae Club $7 5 toward an assistant scholarship in memory of Mrs. Elizabeth Sullivan. Buffalo Alumnae Club Mrs. Gladys Del Principe, a Recreation leader from Alden, New York, for the short session. Houston Alumnae Club Mrs. Thomas E. Holmes, art and crafts coordinator for senior citizens in Houston, Texas, for the second session. Southern California Area Council Kay Kauzlarich, Colorado Alpha, a student from Littleton, Colorado, for the full session. Virginia Alpha Beverly L. Lewis, Virginia Delta, a student from Norfolk, Virginia. 4 Is your club interested in sponsoring such a worth-while project? How can you raise the money for a scholarship fund and how do you choose the scholar-ship winner? Some clubs designate a certain amount from the profits of their benefit and some clubs have special affairs to raise the money for the scholarship. In the case of the Southern California Area Council, each Pi Phi Alumnx Club in the Council contributes a certain amount per club membership. Decide whether this scholarship should be open to Pi Beta Phis, actives and/or alumnae, or to anystudents or adults interested in art and crafts, teachers in recreational centers, therapists working with the handicapped and in hospitals, etc. Pi Phi scholarship winners to date include undergraduate and graduate students, teachers, an art and crafts coordinator, a recreation leader, an hospital therapist, both Pi Phis and non-Pi Phis (including an Alpha Chi Omega) . The Scholarship Committee of the Houston Club sent letters to the directors of the different agencies in the city, explaining that they were interested in sending to the Pi Phi summer Workshop either a trained employee or a volunteer worker who would return to Houston to do craft work. Their selection this year was Mrs. Thomas E. Holmes, the art and crafts coordinator at Helena House, a senior citizens' center. The Southern California Area Council Committee sends its explanatory letter to all the Province Presidents so that the information can be circulated to both actives and alumnae. Any interested Pi Phis can then apply for an application blank. Applications should include the name, address, age, school status, profession, why the applicant wishes to take this training and how she expects to apply it. Request letters of recommendation. Have a deadline so that the selection of your winner can be made in plenty of time for enrollment at the 1967 Summer Craft Workshop. Workshop Valuable Help by Mary Mintich of Belmont, North Carolina I believe the life of each of us is enriched by participation in a comprehensive art program. This, plus a teacher shortage, led me to a senior high school art room five years ago only to discover I wasn't prepared to teach all those things in which I believe. My young family prevented me from going a great distance for months of study and there has been no adequate craft instruction within one hundred miles of Charlotte, North Carolina. It is impossible to express what three sessions at the Pi Beta Phi Craft Workshop have meant to my students and to me. In the process of learning I have developed into a producing and exhibiting craftsman and have found tremendous personal satisfaction. Even my painting has improved because concepts, attitudes, design and awareness are taught and nourished there, in addition to the techniques of the craftsman. My students strongly prefer crafts to two dimensional work and have won national honors each year since I first brought this interest back to them from Gatlinburg. Some of them will be craftsmen, others will develop crafts as an avocation, but all will at all times be more aware, more appreciative and discriminating as adults and consumers. Each art teacher I have encouraged to attend the Craft Workshop has returned a better teacher. The influence of the Craft Workshop clearly extends far beyond the range of those fortunate enough to study there. We are all looking forward to its in-creased growth and development. Mary Mintich working on silver pin. </p>
      <pb ref="arr8320033_0003" seq="03" n="36-37  "/>
       <p>Glen Kaufman instructs Gladis Kiser in weaving. Inspiration in the Smokies An article in the National Geographic Magazine inspired Gladis Graham Kiser and her husband to visit the Smoky Mountains in 1932. One of the memorable spots they visited was the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School in Gatlinburg. Some years later and after many trips back to the Smokies, Mrs. Kiser learned that the University of Tennessee was co-sponsoring a summer Craft Workshop with Pi Beta Phi at the Settlement School. Jane Glass, a craftsman from Gatlinburg and an instructor at the Workshop, gave a jewelry course at the YMCA in Birmingham. Mrs. Kiser was so enthused that she made plans to enroll the following summer at the Pi Phi Workshop in Gatlinburg. Over the years Mrs. Kiser has developed from an elementary art teacher to a junior high, then senior high art teacher and now is supervisor of art for the Jefferson County Schools in Alabama. She feels the greatest value of the workshop is the very high quality of the instructors and their unwillingness to accept below first quality techniques or designs. The student is forced to develop an awareness of nature with her patterns of texture and design and is encouraged to use God-given ideas to incorporate in her own work. In her own professional life Mrs. Kiser has been able to use every technique and idea. Gladis Kiser wants every Pi Phi who has had a part in making this workshop possible to know how much the school has meant to her and hopes each Pi Phi can become a student, for, as she says, "You would be surprised what you can accomplish." Study Grants to 1966 Workshop Four Illinois women were able to take advantage of the Summer Craft Workshop through Study Grants from the State of Illinois: Marguerite Hug, Director of Recreation at the School For The Blind in Jacksonville, Illinois, through the Department of Children and Family Service; Maybell Wenke and Mildred Stensvaag of Moline, Illinois through the Department of Mental Health; Mrs. Arthur John-son through the State Hospital at Galesburg. The State of Louisiana Rehabilitation at Baton Rouge sent Evelyn Wilsford of the University of Tennessee at Knoxville, Tennessee. Outstanding Contributions Through Arrowcraft Sales, benefits and other special events, four Alumnae Clubs were able to con-tribute $1000 or over to the Settlement School. Congratulations and a Little Pigeon Award went to: Houston, Tex., Junior and Senior Clubs-$1200.00 Kansas City, Mo., Junior and Senior Clubs $1000.00 St. Louis, Mo., Junior and Senior Clubs-$1000.00 Pasadena, Calif., Junior and Senior Clubs $1000.00 Honorable mention: North Shore, Ill. $600.00 Attention: Art Majors Art and Crafts Majors Seven graduate assistant Craft Workshop Scholarships are available for the 1967 Summer Craft Workshop, co-sponsored by Pi Beta Phi and the University of Tennessee. Tuition for one craft class, board, and room offered in exchange for part-time work. Applicants should be seniors or graduates under twenty-five years of age. For further information on these scholarships write immediately to Mrs. Marion W. Mueller, Art and Craft Center, Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee 37738. All applications must be made by April 1, 1967. The Settlement School Still Needs Your Support Through the years the Settlement School and the Craft Workshop have developed through your voluntary contributions. During this 100th year of Pi Beta Phi your sup-port will still be needed, for it is upon a solid foundation of the Settlement School and the Craft Workshop that the Centennial Fund Project will be established. 36 An Artist's Touch for Centennial Party With the Pi Beta Phi spotlight on Centennial this year, Los Angeles Pi Phi alumnae chose a unique way to begin this auspicious year with a party that brought the paintings of one of their talented members together with Arrowcraft Center items. Marion Hewlett Pike, California alumna, internationally acclaimed portrait artist, graciously provided a special exhibit of her paintings for the affair at the home of Mrs. Donald Moulton. Hand-crafted goods from the Pi Beta Phi Craft Center were attractively displayed for sale and admiring at the party, which attracted wide and enthusiastic participation. Mrs. Pike, who painted the impression of California Governor Ronald Reagan which appeared on the cover of the October 7, 1966 issue of Time magazine, was on hand for the party. Mrs. Pike, who has been honored as a Woman of the Year by the Los Angeles Times will have a one-woman show at the Marlborough Gallery in New York City in April, 1967. Her portrait of Los Angeles Symphony conductor Zubin Mehta is permanently exhibited in the Dorothy Chandler (California Alpha) Pavilion of the Los Angeles Music Center. Described by Time as ". . . a 5 ft., 2-in. dynamo whose canvases often turn out to be bigger than she is," she has filled commissions for Art Connoisseur Norton Simon and his family, Bob Hope, Washing-ton's National Gallery Director John Walker, Louvre Conservator Magdeleine Hours and Swiss sculptor Alberto Giacometti. Marion Hewlett Pike, right, California Alpha, discusses her paintings with Eleanor Bushnell Lehner, Florida Beta and Georgia Alpha, at the morning party where the paintings were exhibited as the Los Angeles Alumnae Club ushered in the Centennial year. Los Angeles Times photo In addition to the painting exhibit and arrow-craft display and sale, the affair featured exhibits of materials pertaining to the Pi Beta Phi Centennial Project. Eleanor Bushnell Lehner (Mrs. George F. J.), a Florida Beta and chairman of the Los Angeles Alumni Club headed the committee arranging the party. Working with her were Mrs. Jean Bobst Venable, club president; Mrs. Patricia Wright Bercel; Mrs. Louisa von Klein Smid Witt Mrs. Joann Putnam Beasley ; Mrs. Sally Kirby Quinley; Mrs. Mar-ion Coe Palmer and Mrs. Sherill Mason Smith. Special guests at the occasion were Grand Vice President of Philanthropies, 'Evelyn Peters Kyle; Lois Snyder Finer, past Grand Secretary; Mary Em-rich Van Buren, Pi South Province President; Isabel Mulholland Cramer, Centennial Fund Committee member. SLink For Friendships by Carolyn Steel, Virginia Delta I never realized how much a sorority could mean until this summer. Since I was just initiated last May I couldn't possibly know all the advantages of being a member of a national women's fraternity, but it didn't take long to find out. This summer a group of Pi Phi's moved to Virginia Beach to find employment and relaxation. The first two people I met were Tri-Delts from the University of Kentucky. A while later another Tri-Delt from the University of South Carolina came and also some from William and Mary. As the summer progressed more and more sorority girls arrived. The next two that I met were Alpha Xis from East Carolina and there was also one girl who was a Kappa Alpha Theta at William and Mary. There were some Chi Omegas from Transylvania. To top it off, there were nine Pi Phis. The entire summer seemed like one huge intersorority convention. The fact that we were in different sororities did not alienate us, but it somehow made us closer. We became sisters in one wonderful Panhellenic summer sorority. We didn't compete with each other because there was no need to. We merely enjoyed the broadening of our Greek friendships. There was a time when I thought Pi Phi was the only sorority in America, and that we should live in "peaceful co-existence" with all other sororities. Now I know that it is possible to live in complete harmony with them (except maybe during rush!) because of the wonderful, lasting friendships that I made this summer. Now I am not only proud to be a Pi Phi but a fraternity woman. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



