<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr8130015_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Gordon, Sally Wild</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Spring 1965</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr8130015_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1965</date>, News from Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Gordon, Sally Wild</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 14-15</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">41</note>
                        <note type="Folder">1</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 81, Number 3 (Spring 1965), Pages 14-15.</note>
			<note type="document">arr8130015_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">High Honor Accorded Jessie Harris by UT; Winning Program Presented; Workshop is Praise; Settlement School Visitors</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>The Birth of Arrowmont, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1965-1979</item>
                                <item>Programs</item>
                                <item>People</item>
                                <item>Staff</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr8130015_0001" seq="01" n="14-15  "/>
       <p>News from Little P geon High Honor Accorded Jessie Harris by UT Jessie Wooten Harris, first Dean of the University of Tennessee College of Home Economics, was accorded a high honor by the University in October, 1964, when the new Jessie Harris Home Economics Building was dedicated. At the dedication program recognition was made of Dean Emeritus Harris's leadership in guiding the University of Tennessee Home Economics program to a position of national eminence in her 32 years of service. Dean Harris, 1936 Pi Beta Phi convention initiate, was honored by the faculty of the UT Home Economics Department and the Settlement School Staff with a tea at the Pi Beta Phi staff house. Miss Harris has seen the Pi Beta Phi Craft Workshop program develop to its present position of productivity and service, having been a founder of the project. She served as the University representative in the organization and was a faithful promoter of the project through the years until her retirement. Winning Program Presented Members of the North Shore Junior Alumnae Club met at the Northwestern University chapter house of Illinois Espilon last fall and expressed much interest in the award winning Settlement School program that was written by the chapter's Settlement School program chairman, Judy Weed. Illinois Epsilon's original program won the 1964 May L. Keller Settlement School Award. The pro-gram covers the many phases and accomplishments of the Settlement School and future developments at the School site in Gatlinburg, Tenn. This honor for Illinois Epsilon and the enjoyable evening it afforded for both chapter members and the North Shore Junior Alumnae serves as a re-minder that the time is near at hand for submission of Settlement School programs for consideration in the selection of a 1965 May L. Keller Award winner. The award carries a $25 cash gift and goes to the chapter which submits the most outstanding pro-gram given to inform members about the Settlement School philanthropy. Copies of programs to be considered for the awards should be sent by May 1st to: Mrs. Floyd H. Thorman 1221 Elm Street Winnetka, Illinois 60093Edited by Sally Wild Gordon, Wisconsin A Workshop Is Praised The Albuquerque Alumnae Club Scholarship to the Summer Craft Workshop is not limited to members of Pi Beta Phi. Last year it was won by Hellyn Moore, talented University of New Mexico craft major. Her enthusiastic letter of appreciation for the opportunity to study in the Craft Workshop will undoubtedly serve as an inspiration to others. She wrote in part .. . "I am a senior crafts major at the University of New Mexico. Last spring the Pi Beta Phi Scholar-ship was offered to all craft majors. After looking at the brochures about the Workshop, I became quite interested, so I submitted examples of my craft work and letters of recommendation to the Pi Phi jury. "I feel quite fortunate that I was chosen to at-tend the workshop. The experience was most beneficial and I was tremendously impressed with the excellent quality and amazing quantity of work done. "The skills learned have already been of great value to me and two articles I made there were exhibited in a Contemporary Craftsmen of New Mexico show last fall. I know that I will continue to benefit as I further my study of crafts in graduate school. "There is much more to be said about how really excellent I felt the instruction was. I have given two talks here concerning my summer, one to the Crafts Department and one to the Pi Phi chapter and I think the listeners were as impressed as I was with the Workshop and the work done there." Wanted Pi Phis! Work scholarships will be available for art or crafts students graduate or undergraduate at the Pi Beta Phi University of Tennessee Craft Workshop in the Smokies at Gatlinburg, Tennessee in the summer of 1965. Check the dates for the Workshop in this issue of THE ARROW. If interested, write to Settlement School Chairman, Mrs. Floyd M. Thor-man, 1221 Elm St., Winnetka, Illinois. Workshop Information See the back cover of this issue of THE ARROW for complete information on courses and dates for the 1965 Pi Beta Phi-University of Tennessee Summer Craft Workshop. 14 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI 15 Settlement School Di-rector Marion Mueller explains the historical background of the Grace Coolidge collection to Tennessee Alpha and Tennessee Gamma Pi Phis. Settlement School Visitors... Pi Beta Phi groups, such as these from Tennessee Gamma and Tennessee Alpha, who can visit the Settlement School are indeed fortunate. Throughout the year, except in mid-winter, Pi Phis, educational or religious groups may have retreats or workshops at the Red Barn. Reservations are usually made several weeks in advance. All Phi Phis are invited to tour the school when in the area. Mrs. Meuller discusses architects sketches which show a possible development and expansion of the Craft program. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



