<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr8940015_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News of Arrowmont School of arts and crafts</title>
                        <author><name>Mahone, Melinda Key </name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Summer 1973</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr8940015_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1973</date>, News of Arrowmont School of arts and crafts</title>
                        <author><name>Mahone, Melinda Key </name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 15-21</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">41</note>
                        <note type="Folder">9</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 89, Number 4 (Summer 1973), Pages 15-21.</note>
			<note type="document">arr8940015_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Arrowmont Identified; Workshop Brings 135 to Arrowmont; Helen Lewis Plans Gatlinburg Retirement;Scholarship Recipient Lauds Arrowmont; Arrowmont Secretaries Agree On Advantages of Their Ideal Jobs; Scholarship Money Covers Four Weeks</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>The Birth of Arrowmont, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1965-1979</item>
                                <item>Staff</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>
                                <item>Students</item>
                                <item>People</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr8940015_0001" seq="01" n="14-15  "/>
       <p>High School Day Is Each year at the University of Southern California, rush is a function involving a great deal of pressure and competition for sorority members as well as rushees. Until recently, it seemed that the situation would remain exactly as it al-ways had, leaving no time for rushees to get to know sorority girls outside of the demands of a rush situation. All of that was changed this year when Diana Billings, California Gamma, Pan Diana Billings, .California Gamma hellenic rush chairman on the U.S.C. campus, came up with the idea of a High School Day, a program in which girls from high schools in the Los Angeles area could meet and talk with sorority members in a non-rush environment. Diana referred to her own feelings as a fresh-man in explaining her idea. "I always used to stereotype sorority girls until I came up on a weekend and visited a house they were doing normal things and all were fun, different individuals. I wanted this for other girls to know how real a sorority is." Over fifteen hundred invitations were sent out to girls who had expressed an interest in joining a sorority, as well as to all freshman girls accepted at the university to date. Girls who had inquired about sororities but were not necessarily bound for U.S.C. were included in the program as well.ush Innovation On Saturday, March 31, two hundred and ten girls attended High School Day. The event was held at the Lambda Chi Alpha fraternity house and featured a slide show of sorority girls in both candid and posed shots. The slide show was presented with a brief talk on sorority and campus life given by Diana and the Panhellenic president. The talk stressed the love shared in a sorority and within Panhellenic. The importance of the individual within the structure of sorority living was also highlighted. Sorority life was presented as one of many life styles to choose from in a college environment, but as a unique sharing experience. After the slide presentation, the girls were split into twelve groups, each going to one of the twelve sorority houses on the campus, where they enjoyed do-it-yourself sundaes with the members of various sororities. High School Day was an innovative and successful event for both the active sorority members and potential rushees. The members of the California Gamma chapter are proud of the fact that the inspiration and initiative for the idea came from one of our own members. Mother, Daughter Share Initiation Day For the first time in Texas Alpha history, the traditions of initiation experienced some changes. Early in the year, the chapter voted to initiate the junior members of the pledge class in November rather than in March. The chapter also voted to initiate a mother and daughter simultaneously. On "junior" initiation day, Sallie Griffis and her mother, Dorothy Warner Griffis, made their pledges to the chapter together. Mrs. Griffis be-came an honorary initiate of Texas Alpha. A Pi Phi pledge during college days, Mrs. Griffis was never initiated because of her marriage. How-ever, due to her many contributions to Pi Beta Phi, it was voted by the chapter and the alumna, and approved by Grand Council that she be initiated with her daughter in November last year. It was indeed a first for the chapter and was a moving experience for a mother and daughter to share together. 14 News of The Great Smoky Mountains Gatlinburg, Tennessee 37738 school of arts and crafts -N.. Staff members of the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School in former years, now living in Gatlinburg, were invited to a luncheon at the Ruth Barrett Smith Staff House by the Arrowmont Board of Governors while the Board was in Gatlin-burg for is annual meeting. Seated are Mattie Huff Clabo, Iowa Gamma, elementary school teacher 1928-29, 1934-39; Miss Winogene Redding, weaving instructor 1925-33, 1958-62; Mrs. Marjorie Chalmers, Illinois Beta-Delta, nurse 1935-65; Stella Sue Huff Cox, Tennessee Gamma, 7th, 8th grades and high school English teacher, 1934-39, and high school English teacher 1955-73. Standing are Henrietta McCutchan Huff, Missouri Beta, elementary school teacher 1928-31; Pauline Whaling Huff, 7th, 8th, and high school English teacher, 1932-34; Frances Moore Mattil, nurse 1928-32; Mrs. Tina McMorran, weaving instructor 1948-58; Mrs. Dorothy Lexau, kindergarten teacher 1926-27; O. J. Mattil, Smith-Hughes agriculture teacher and wood-working instructor 1922-34; Miss Eva Hathaway, Iowa Gamma, grade school teacher at the Sugarlands School 1927-33. 15 </p>
      <pb ref="arr8940015_0002" seq="02" n="16-17  "/>
       <p>rrowmont Identi:ed Have you ever been to Gatlinburg, Tennessee? Gatlinburg is a small tourist town which lies at the foot of the Great Smoky Mountains National Park. Each year 8 million visitors pass through this small town. Many of them miss seeing our legacy to mankind the Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts. The Arrowmont School is the continuation of a teaching tradition started by our Fraternity in 1912. Arrowmont School (3) is open during the summer months and teaches courses ranging from textiles and spinning to jewelry and woodwork. The students are of many different ages and many different backgrounds. These students have one thing in common, however, they love to create and to be useful. The atmosphere here lends itself to creativity. The Fraternity has about 50 acres of undeveloped land where students and faculty can enjoy the beauty and serenity of the mountains. Yet they are only a few steps away from downtown Gatlinburg should they prefer a change of pace. Arrowmont is located in the heart of down-town Gatlinburg. The Arrowcraft Shop (1) is a retail store which sells only handmade area crafts. The Administrator's Office (2) is located on the main street. Mrs. Helen Lewis has been the Administrator of Arrowmont since October, 1971. She does a marvelous job of "ruling" this 67 acre domain. The present Arrowmont building (3) was completed in 1970. The Staff House (4) is just as the name implies, the house where the staff lives. This presently includes Mrs. Lewis, the Administrator, and Mrs. Riddle, Assistant Administrator. The Staff House is also the dining room for summer school. The dining room can seat 104 people. Students who attend summer school at Arrowmont are not always lucky enough to find housing on campus. There is a definite need for more dormitories. As the picture clearly shows there is land to build on but we have no money to build with. The ultimate goal of our Fraternity is to make Arrowmont a year around school. In order to accomplish this there must be more housing. There are three rustic houses which are used as dormitories, they are Stuart (5), Pollard (6), and Teachers (7). The Red by MELINDA KEY MAHONE Board of Governors Barn (8) located very close to the Staff House was remodeled in 1949 to provide housing for students. Thus we have a new school which can accommodate 134 students and housing facilities for only 80 students. At the present time the urgent need is for more housing. As you tour the country this summer, come to Gatlinburg and tour Arrowmo4t. Mrs. Lewis or Mrs. Riddle will be happy to 'show you around. Each Pi Phi should learn to appreciate what her Fraternity is doing to bridge the generation gap, and we should all strive to make Arrowmont a school which operates all through the year. Workshop Brings 135 to Arrowmont During the first week in April, Arrowmont and the Department of Crafts and Interior De-sign of the University of Tennessee presented a workshop for the Art In Home Economics Association. Co-chairmen for the event were Arrowmont's Director, Marian G. Heard, and David Van Dommelen, Associate Professor from Pennsylvania State University. Undergraduate students, graduate students, and faculty members from colleges of home economics all across the country and Canada filled the nine different craft classes. The members of the organization were so enthusiastic that they voted to hold another workshop at Arrowmont some time next spring. There were 135 people registered as students, plus 17 staff and faculty members. Since school housing facilities are limited, many of these people had to find housing at nearby motels. Hopefully Arrowmont can continue to host such workshops and conferences in increasing numbers in the future. 17 </p>
      <pb ref="arr8940015_0003" seq="03" n="18-19  "/>
       <p>elen e is lans Gatlinburg Retirement Helen Anderson Lewis, Kentucky Alpha, came to Gatlinburg in October, 1971, to accept a temporary appointment as administrator of Arrowmont and Arrowcraft. In April, 1972, she agreed to stay on as administrator until Sep tember 1, 1973. Those who have come to know Helen in Gatlinburg are happy to learn that she plans to live on in Gatlinburg after her retirement in September. Helen has given many years of service to Pi Phi. Her career as a loyal Pi Phi started when she was a charter member of Kentucky Alpha at the University of Louisville, serving as treasurer and as vice president. After graduation, Helen immediately became active in the Louisville Alumnm Club, and following her marriage to Benjamin Lewis, moved to Indianapolis where she continued to be active in the Fraternity, serving as treasurer and vice president of the Indianapolis club. After nine years as vice president of the old Delta Province (during which she and her family moved to Detroit), Helen became province president, making frequent visits to the Indiana and Michigan chapters. In 1950 Helen was elected to Grand Council as director of rushing and pledge training, andin 1958 became director of membership. While on Grand Council she served as NPC alternate and evolved the colonization plan which is still in practice. In 1960, she left Grand Council to serve as national convention guide, where she served until 1970. During the years as an officer, she was in charge of or assisted at the colonization of the following chapters: Alabama Beta and Gamma, Texas Delta, Colorado Gamma, Michigan Delta, Kentucky Beta, and Ohio Eta. She at-tended installations of Ohio Eta, Indiana Zeta, Michigan Delta, Ohio Zeta, Kentucky Beta, Michigan Gamma, and Indiana Epsilon. Helen has attended 19 conventions and has visited approximately 75 chapters. Helen is proud of her two married daughters, one a Pi Phi, and her eight grandchildren. Along with her interest in her family and Pi Phi, Helen, an accomplished pianist, has found time for her music and church work, for gardening, knitting, and bridge. She is not always serious, either, but can be counted on to join in the fun and frivolity when the occasion arises. In fact, the life that Helen leads exemplifies the ideals of Pi Phi. Helen Lewis indulges herself with a few quiet moments of relaxation in the living room of Staff House. 18 Mary Rae, Curator of School Programs for the Milwaukee Art Center, works on two displays for her FIBERS: CON-TEMPORARY REVIVALS exhibition at the Center. Scholarship Recipient Lauds Arrowmont Mary Rae, Milwaukee, Wisc., was the recipient of the Brendel Scholarship to Arrowmont for the 1972 Summer Workshop. Mary is Curator of School Programs for the Milwaukee Art Center. As such she gives color slide presentations in schools, and develops instructional art resources for educators. In response to a request for her thoughts on Arrowmont, Mary wrote, "I was so pleased to have received the Brendel Scholarship. "I have been doing some textile printing since my session at Arrowmont; however, the greatest help has been in my work here in the Milwaukee Art Center. The whole environment at Arrowmont, and even the indirect inspiration derived from other work being done there, has given me increased understanding and appreciation of contemporary crafts that has been directly applied to the in-class presentations (color slide lectures) that I give in the Milwaukee area schools. Specifically, my courses in textile printing and craft media have helped me with my program entitled "Fibers," a program showing the contemporary fabric constructionsand textile designs of Wisconsin design-craftsmen. "More recently, on March 23, 1973, the Milwaukee Art Center opened an exhibition entitled FIBERS: CONTEMPORARY REVIVALS which I planned as an educational exhibition for school groups as well as the general public. The exhibition features the contemporary works of nine Wisconsin artist craftsmen working in the fiber media. Three of them, Joan Michaels Paque, Sister Remy Revor, and Richard Daehnert, have been instructors at Arrowmont. The fiber techniques are illustrated and explained with reference to their historic origins on instructional panels that accompany the contemporary pieces. From this exhibition, another instructional resource will be developed in the form of color slides with an accompanying text to be used by teachers. My in-class presentation, "Fibers," will be revived also. "With this exhibition we hope to spread the same enthusiasm for the fiber field as was exuded at Arrowmont last summer !" 19 </p>
      <pb ref="arr8940015_0004" seq="04" n="20-21  "/>
       <p>Arrowmont's three efficient secretaries are, L to R: Sharon Huskey, Teresa Coons, and Sue Robbins. Arrowmont Secretaries Agree On Advantages o f Their Ideal Jobs What could be more ideal than working at Arrowmont in the beautiful mountains of Tennessee ? The three secretaries at the school agree that there's really nothing that could be more ideal. Sharon Huskey has worked full time as a secretary since June, 1971. She has lived in Gatlin-burg all of her life, and attended the eight grades of the Pi Beta Phi School. After graduating from Gatlinburg-Pittman High, she at-tended Arrowmont for three summers, the third summer as a Graduate Assistant. Teresa Coons calls Dayton, Ohio, her home. After attending college in Dayton, she attended craft courses at Arrowmont for three summers. She liked it so well that she applied for full time work and she has been a secretary since February, 1972. Teresa lives at Staff House. Sue Robbins lives in Sevierville, 13 miles north of Gatlinburg. She is bookkeeper and secretary to the Administrator, Helen Lewis, and spends most of her time at the Administration Office on the main street. Sue also assists Sharon and Teresa at Arrowmont. She is new at her job, having arrived in February, 1973, but she has caught on quickly to the variety of work she does at the two buildings. If you should visit Arrowmont, the Administrator or any of the girls will be happy to take you on a tour of your philanthropy. Scholarship Money Covers Four Weeks The 1972 recipient of the Virginia Alpha Craft Workshop Scholarship was Kassie Laughlin, Iowa Beta. By astute management of scholarship money, Kassie was able to spend four weeks at Arrowmont. Her enthusiastic evaluation of the school is as follows. "Arrowmont for me is a very `special' place. It is that little niche away from the regular pat-tern of life where you can go to live, learn, and share with others. I went to Arrowmont last summer with many expectations, all of which came true in a very real way. "As a Pi Phi, I'm so proud to be able to call Arrowmont ours. Until you visit the school, you can't imagine what Arrowmont is all about. I was there for most of the summer and I hardly had my fill. It is such a special place because there seems to be this feeling of caring for others. I especially enjoyed the instructors because they were so helpful as teachers and so inspiring as artists and craftsmen. Another interesting factor was the. wide range of ages and occupations of the people attending Arrowmont. I think I enjoyed that the most because, as you would be learning in the classroom, you would also be sharing ideas with all of these people. Aside from the people, the natural and beautiful surroundings of Arrowmont are enough to inspire anyone! "I wish every Pi Phi could visit Arrowmont. The school has so much to offer. It is more than just a part of our history, when it started out as the Settlement School. Arrowmont is a very real place thriving on the Arts and Crafts. Kassie Laughlin, Iowa Beta 20 Eleven scholarship recipients attended the second and third sessions of the 1972 Summer Workshop at Arrowmont. Standing at the entrance to the new classroom building; above, are those who attended the second session. L to R: Mary Rae, winner of the Brendel Scholarship; Kassie Laughlin, Virginia Alpha Scholarship; Irene Duke, partial scholarship from the Jacksonville Alumnce Club via the Arthritis Foundation; Denyse Johnson,,, scholarship from Contra Costa (Calif.) Alumnce Club; Catherine Umstot, partial scholarship from Jacksonville (Fla.) Alumnce Club; Andrea Singleton, scholarship from the Buffalo (N.Y.) Alumnce Club; Arlene Finarchiarro, Wilmington (Del.) Aumnce,Club scholarship. Administrator Helen Lewis, below left, poses with scholarship recipients who attended the third session of the 1972 Summer Craft Workshop. From Mrs. Lewis, L to R: Eleanor Kirk, Ohio Delta; Karen Mullen, scholarship from Mid-Cities (Texas) Alumnce Club; Kassie Laughlin, Virginia Alpha Scholarship; Susan Wheelock, Massachusetts Alpha, partial scholarship from Massachusetts Alpha and Boston West Suburban Alumnce Club; Jean Juhlin, scholarship from the Chicago South Suburban Club. 21 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



