<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr9110023_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Pi Beta Phi Settlement School</title>
                        <author><name>Vollmar, Helen Deppe</name></author>
                        <author><name>Riddle, Caroline M.</name></author>
                        <author><name>Lewis, Helen A.</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Fall 1974</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr9110023_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1974</date>, Pi Beta Phi Settlement School</title>
                        <author><name>Vollmar, Helen Deppe</name></author>
                        <author><name>Riddle, Caroline M.</name></author>
                        <author><name>Lewis, Helen A.</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 22-26</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">41</note>
                        <note type="Folder">11</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 91, Number 1 (Fall 1974), Pages 22-26.</note>
			<note type="document">arr9110023_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Chairman, Board of Governors, Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts; Administrator, Pi Beta Phi Settlement School; Arrowmont and Arrowcraft Awards 1973-1974; </note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>The Birth of Arrowmont, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1965-1979</item>
                                <item>Facilities</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>
                                <item>Funding</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr9110023_0001" seq="01" n="22-23  "/>
       <p>PitctPh, Sett/ern/Mt SChOOl CHAIRMAN, BOARD OF GOVERNORSi ARROWMONT SCHOOL OF ARTS AND CRAFTS lie 1973-74 year got off to a good start with a very cessful Arrowmont Night at Convention. Wilma Dyke-n, author and lecturer, gave a most inspirational speech lut Arrowmont. She was given a standing ovation. )ur position in Gatlinburg continues to be one of rect and leadership. Business and professional leaders re luncheon guests of the Board of Governors when y met in Gatlinburg for the annual meeting in Ocper, 1973. A ten week craft course for the local resi-Its, which met one evening a week, was given last ing starting in February. The response was good with enrollment of forty-two. Me summer session for 1973 was again most success-with 953 students attending from 42 states and 3 eign countries. Paul Rossiter, retired manager of the ,ubleday Book Store in New Orleans, established a )k store at Arrowmont. He returned for the summer 1974 and enlarged his inventory. Because of limited using, many students were forced to live off campus and dng facilities were inadequate. Hopefully with the tallation of a commercial dishwasher and disposal, s situation will be relieved somewhat, this coming nmer facilitating two-shift dining. The 1974 summer sion included three two week sessions and four one ek sessions under the direction of Marian Heard, Di-tor. Additional specialized craft workshops have num-!ed four during the year. It is hoped that these will itinue to increase each year bringing us closer to our al of a year round school. The Red Barn continues be popular for rental by various groups. Caroline Riddle, Florida Beta, became the new adnistrator for Arrowmont and Arrowcraft on September 1974, having worked since spring with the retiring ministrator, Helen Lewis. Mrs. Riddle brings to the r a strong background in art education, personnel adnistration, and philanthropic service. The annual meeting of the Board of Governors was Ed at Gatlinburg, October 4-7, 1973. New members of the and are Cecile Kendall of Corpus Christi, Tex., Mary Jean wler of Houston, Tex., and Helen Lewis, 'Gatlinburg, no. Retiring were Betty Hall, Henrietta 'Huff, Betty King-.n, and Miss Olivia Moore. A donation to Arrowmont was .de by the Board honoring Miss Olivia for her many years service to Pi Beta Phi. The Board also presented Helen wis with a pewter pitcher upon her retirement as administor. The individual members of the Board have functioned ,1I in their particular capacities. A General Mills coupon to has been launched to provide funds for the purchase needed potter's wheels and looms for Arrowmont. ease save coupons and give to your club Arrowcraft airman or send to Cecile Kendall, 4305 O'Grady, ,rpus Christi, Texas, 78413. The coupons are found in General Mills (Betty Crocker) products. An exciting Arrowcraft Design Award contest has been :ablished open to non-Pi Phis as well as Pi Phis to courage new designs for Arrowcraft items. Details of contest were published in the summer ARROW issue, 74. A highlight of the year was the meeting of the 'ademics Standards 'Committee held at the University of Tennessee at Knoxville two days prior to the annual Board of Governors meeting. This included a briefing of accreditation procedures of the university and graduate school, plus requirements for certification of courses and faculty for Arrowmont. This review further demonstrated the high standards required by the University of Tennessee which must be met by Arrowmont School of Crafts. The meeting was of mutual benefit in under-standing one another's structure and endeavors. The Arrowmont group was entertained at luncheon and at a dinner party at the Faculty Club and was given an in-depth tour of the campus followed by an informal coffee with students and faculty. A visit to the active chapter's quarters completed the visit. Grand Council, whose meeting followed the BOG meeting, met jointly with the Board for their final meeting on October 7, 1973. Lists of Arrowmont students and staff attending the 1974 summer session will again be divided into provinces and sent to clubs through APPs and PPs. Clubs and chapters are urged to invite the students for programs. Hand-out leaflets with pertinent facts about Arrowmont and Arrowcraft have been printed to be given along with Arrow-craft sales. They must be ordered from Gatlinburg. A generous cash donation from Marian Heard and Sandy Blain assisted with the building of a much desired salt kiln for the ceramics department. The fascia board around the Emma Harper Turner building has been contracted for completion. The frame cottage on the grounds, occupied by Mr. Orlie Watson until his death last year, has been refurbished and will be used by Arrowmont assistants. The $4000 gift of the Dallas Club honoring one of their members, Edythe Mulveyhill Brack, former Grand Council member and devoted Pi Phi, will enable the establishment of a photographic studio at Arrowmont. An interim visit to Gatlinburg in early March was made by Sarah Hunt and the Chairman of the Board of Governors. Vandalism is on the uptrend there and various methods for better security were discussed. Arrowcraft has enjoyed a prosperous year, despite shortages and inflation. However, price increases will be necessary and a new catalogue will be forthcoming. Despite the energy crunch and the uncertain economic conditions ahead, we dare to be optimistic about the coming year. Marian Heard reports she is having a good response to the 1974 Arrowmont brochure. The Chamber of Commerce says that, because of the close proximity of Gatlinburg to neighboring states tourists will come. To carry optimism still further, as an ever-increasing number of members learn more about how their great heritage at Gatlinburg is contributing to today's world through Arrowmont, they will make it their Favorite Philanthropy. The Chairman wishes to express her gratitude to the members of the Board of Governors, Grand Council, Central Office, and the staff of Arrowmont and Arrow-craft for their assistance on her behalf during the past year. HELEN DEPPE VOLLMAR ADMINISTRATOR, PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL The months since I assumed responsibility for .the two mponents of our Settlement School in Gatlinburg have been busy ones indeed. I have been grateful to my predecessor, Helen Lewis, that each facet of the work turned 22 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI 2 over to me finances, personnel, maintenance, public relations, 'Pi Phi relationships, all was in a healthy state of operation and carefully recorded for reference. The annual meeting of the Board of Governors early in October, 1973, afforded my initial opportunity to know members and to learn the responsibilities of each. Cec Kendall and Mary Jean Fowler, both new members, bring to the committee transferable, valued experience. The meeting of the Grand Council in the Red Barn was a similar opportunity to meet those who had been only names to me before. October, too, was the time of the Southern Highland Handicraft Guild fair in Gatlinburg. Arrowmont and the University of Tennessee provided an outstanding educational exhibit in the entryway. Many persons were housed on our campus and an open house was held in the Library on Friday evening for all participants. In November Faye Cook, who is in charge of shipping for Arrowcraft, and I made a trip to Cookeville to visit the Upper Cumberland Craft Center of Mr. John Max-well. We purchased wooden items for the shop, toured his facilities, and saw his dulcimers being made. Faye, Nella Hill, and I also attended the annual Chamber of Commerce dinner on behalf of Arrowmont and Arrowcraft. November 9 to 11, 1973, marked the National Art Education Mini-Workshop on the Arrowmont campus. At Christmas time a luncheon was held at the Staff House for all the Settlement School employees and it was wonderful to sit down together as a family. Small tree ornaments from Arrowcraft were sent to the classrooms at the Pi Beta Phi Elementary School, so, that they may know of our continued interest and concern. Last spring three special workshops were held on the Arrowmont campus: Tennessee Crafts Workshop March 21-23, 1974 Environmental Arts Conference April 2-5, 1974 Southern Highland Handicraft Guild Workshop and Annual Meeting April 24-27, 19'74 Food service and housing were provided for all four workshops held this year. For the Southern Highland Guild meeting a beautiful buffet supper was served in the Library for some 200 persons. Thanks to the continued support from our alumnae clubs and chapters, several major projects were under-taken this year: the installation of the fascia board on Arrowmont, completing at last the magnificent structure; the installation of a commercial dishwasher in the Staff House kitchen (all summer school students will benefit from this!) ; and maintenance measure for Staff House, Watson House, and Arrowcraft Shop. Watson House was for many years the home of the Orlie Watson family. It has been remodeled and re-furbished and last summer housed 8 graduate students, relieving 8 beds for other summer school students. Ample housing continues to be our most pressing need for the school. Arrowmont continues to offer a wide variety of courses for persons of all ages and all walks of life. Woodworking and kiln building were first offered in the summer of 1973. In 1974 we added glaze calculation. In 1975, thanks to the generous gift from the Dallas Alumnae Club, honoring Edythe Brack, we will be able to offer a course in photography. Arrowmont worked with the Great Smoky Mountain National Park to provide craftsmen to give demonstrations at the Sugarlands Visitors Center during summer months. Our. graduate assistants gave demonstrations in weaving and pottery. Mrs. Rossetter gave such effective demonstrations and talks on spinning that she came back at the invitation of the Park to demonstrate for the Park Interpreters meeting. Her husband, Paul Rossetter, who had managed a bookstore in New Orleans before his retirement, managed our Arrowmont Bookstore last summer. He ordered craftbooks recommended by the instructors and students we. delighted to be able to purchase on-the-spot books whi( were discussed in class. The store provided a valuab addition to our school. One other contribution which cannot be passed over that of Helen Russell who has come to Arrowmoi summer after summer to catalog our craft library. La year she and her husband contributed some beautifu substantial new library shelves. We are indeed indebt( to both of them in many ways. The University of Tennessee continues to work close and supportively with Arrowrnont. In October, Lu. Odland, Dean of the College of Home Economics, ho tessed a meeting of the Academic Standards Committ^ on the Knoxville campus. Marian Heard, Helen Vollrna Lucile Jennings, Betty Hall, and I met with Universi officials for a most informative exchange and for a r newed understanding of our mutual co-operation. Dean Odland later asked Dr. Hitchcock in the Foc Systems Administration Department of the University work with me on a remodeling plan for the Staff Hou kitchen. Three graduate students, under her supervisio have been assigned to this project and have made sever trips to Gatlinburg to study our operation and needs. Gifts from clubs and chapters have made possible ti purchase of looms and potters' wheels. The San Matl Club has given money for a carousel-recorder to better t( the Arrowmont story to visitors to the school. To ea^ club and each chapter and each Pi Phi who has remer bered and given to our philanthropy here in Gatlinbu we are grateful indeed. Arrowcraft continues to operate smoothly and profitabl thanks to our loyal, hardworking girls and to our clu and chapters. As of last May, 249 clubs sold Arrowcraft; 4 chapters. Club sales to May this year totalled $168,008.7 chapter sales, $5,348,09. Due to many price changes from increased maters and labor costs, a new, bright Arrowcraft catalog will published this summer. There will be several new wov, items, the result of suggestions from Pi Phis! An Arrowcraft Design Award has been initiated and currently being publicized to clubs, chapters, schools al colleges. Each of three awards is a $100.00 design pt chase, the designs becoming the property of Arrowm for production and marketing. It is hoped that this awa will serve two purposes: better understanding and newed interest in Arrowcraft by Pi Phis and as a soul of fresh, new design ideas for Arrowcraft. The inform tion flyer can be obtained by writing the Administrate Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tenness 37738. On May 8 sixteen weavers were honored by a tea the Staff House. Nella Hill presented sterling silver Stun Nye pins to each weaver completing 25 years of weavi for Arrowcraft. Currently seventy weavers, some moth^ and 'daughters, weave for Arrowcraft. In the past 20 yes some 25 such pins have been awarded, but an event hon^ ing the weavers had not been held since 1966. One weal at the tea, Mae Lethco, first wove for Arrowcraft in 19.2 Also, for the first time in a number of years Arro craft offered a course for the Gatlinburg community. Fo one women and one lone man signed up for 10 we( of textile techniques during the winter exploring st: crafts as: batik, tie-dye, printing, stitchery, quilting, lo( ing, twining, etc. We hope to offer similar courses nl winter. I cannot complete my report without a word of gn tude for the cordiality that has been extended to me the members of the Board of Governors, Grand Couni Settlement School employees, the members of the Lit Pigeon Alumna Club, and the community of Gatl burg itself. All have made the' transition to my w( with Arrowmont and Arrowcraft warm, comfortable a pleasant. CAROLINE M. RIDDLI </p>
      <pb ref="arr9110023_0002" seq="02" n="24-25  "/>
       <p>THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI ARROWMONT AND ARROWCRAFT AWARDS 1973-1974 ROWMONT trance Club contributions according to size categories 1 25 First: Four clubs tied, Oak Park-River Forest, IL; Black Hills, SD; Everett, WA; Stockton, CA; $150 each Second: Three clubs tied, Hampton Roads, VA; Little Pigeon, TN; Youngstown-Warren, OH; $100 each 5 50 First: Amarillo, TX, $500 Second: Hinsdale Township, IL, $350 Third: Rochester, NY, $325 Honorable Mention: Chicago South Suburban, IL; Olympia, WA; San Jose, CA; $200 each 1 75 First: Champaign-Urbana, IL, $1,000 Second: Arlington Heights, IL, $585 Third: Two clubs tied, Philadelphia Main Line, PA and St. Paul, MN, $500 each 5 100 First: San Mateo, CA, $750 Second: Contra Costa, CA, $450 Third, Sacramento, CA, $450 1 150 First, Los Angeles, CA, $2,035 Second: Three clubs tied, Bloomfield Hills, MI; Nashville, TN; North Shore, IL; $700 each Third: Tulsa, OK $550 Honorable Mention: Washington, DC; Cleve-land East, OH; Omaha, NE; over $400 each er 150 First: Dallas, TX, $4,050 Second: St. Louis, MO, $3,904 Third: Houston, TX, $3,157.50 Honorable Mention: Pasadena, CA; over $1,000 Two hundred and seventy-nine alumnae clubs gave 8,004.61 to Arrowmont during the past year. These ores represent club contributions only and do not in-[de any money received from other sources. apter contributions First: Montana Alpha, $205.44 Second: Two chapters tied, Louisiana Alpha; Texas Gamma, $150 each Third: California Eta, $125 (new chapter) Honorable Mention: Illinois Beta-Delta; Louisiana Beta; Missouri Beta; New Mexico Beta; $100 each. ZROWCRAFT ubs making the largest purchases according to size categories 0 25 First: Bozeman, MT, $2,006.70 Second: Stockton, CA, $1,732.63 Third: Jersey Shore, NJ, $1,400.00 Honorable Mention: Albany, NY; Springfield, OH; Marshall, TX; Black Hills, SD; Casper, WY; Everett, WA; Yuba Sutter, CA; all over $1,000 26 50 First: Stillwater, OK, $4,500.00 Second: Marin County, CA, $2,604.05 Third: Whittier Area, CA, $2,247.79 Honorable Mention: Olympia, WA; over $2,000 51 75 First: Honolulu, HA, $6,844.42 Second: Champaign-Urbana, IL, $4,397.79 Third: St. Paul, MN, $4,259.18 Honorable Mention: Cleveland West, OH; Arlington Heights, IL; over $3,000' 76 100 First: Sacramento, CA, $2,767.14 Second: Contra Costa, CA, $2,403.94 Third: Portland, OR, $1,942.18 Honorable Mention: Northern Virginia; Fort Wayne, IN; Minneapolis, MN; over $1,000 101 150 First: Wichita, KS, $2,576.34 Second: Bloomfield Hills, MI, $2,521.42 Third: Washington, DC, $1,876.03 Honorable Mention: Northern New Jersey; Cleveland East, OH; North Shore, IL; Omaha, NE; Tucson, AZ; Reno, NV; over $1,000 over 150 First, Houston, TX, $7,073.14 Second: St. Louis, MO, $2,531.65 Third: Pasadena, CA, $1,112.09 Honorable Mention: Kansas City, MO; Oklahoma City, OK; Denver, CO; South Coast, CA; all over $1,000 Two hundred twenty-seven alumnae clubs purchased $178,204; 4 pockets purchased $2,150.82, and 7 Pi Phi groups (not chartered alumnae clubs) purchased $719,78. Sixty-seven clubs purchased over $1,000. Chapters making the largest purchases 1. Iowa Gamma $725.51 7. Virginia $242.73 Gamma 2. Oklahoma Alpha 557.30 8. Ohio zeta 228.83 3. Texas Delta 404.41 9. Indiana 228.23 4. Maryland Epsilon Beta 320.18 10. North Dakota 5. Iowa zeta 304.65 Alpha 220.67 6. California 249.99 Delta HELEN A. LEwIs Board of Governors Chairman, Awards Committee AUDITED FINANCIAL STATEMENTS PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL GATLINBURG, TENNESSEE May 31, 1974 and 1973 ACCOUNTANTS' REPORT Beta Phi Settlement School Committee Beta Phi Settlement School Winburg, Tennessee We have examined the statements of financial condition of May 31, 1974 and 1973 and the related statements of venues and expenditures and changes in fund balances r the years then ended of the following funds of Pi Beta i Settlement School (a division of Pi Beta Phi Frarnity): Current Funds Endowment Funds Invested in Plant Special Fund Wisconsin Alpha Trust Our examinations were made in accordance with generally accepted auditing standards, and accordingly included such tests of the accounting records and such other auditing procedures as we considered necessary in the circumstances. In our opinion, subject to the outcome of the income tax matter referred to in Note D, the aforemeni ioned financial statements present fairly the financial position of the funds (as described above) of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School at May 31, 1974 and 1973, and the results of their operations and changes in fund balances for the years then ended, in conformity with generally accepted accounting principles applied on a consistent basis. Little Rock, Arkansas July 30, 1974 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI 25 STATEMENT OF FINANCIAL CONDITION CURRENT FUNDS PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL May 31 1974 1973 ASSETS Unrestricted: General: Cash $169,035 $107,907 Craft supplies at cost 20,322 19,519 Prepaid expenses 9,950 9,187 Due from Arrowcraft Shop 41,327 65,266 Due from Magazine Agency 3,231 2,631 243,865 204,510 Arrowcraft Shop and Magazine Agency: Cash 30,350 26,790 Accounts receivable 30,525 24,839 Inventories at lower of cost (first-in, first-out method) or market 240,522 233,582 301,397 285,211 Restricted: Due from current fund unrestricted.. 1,171 926 $546,433 $490,647 LIABILITIES AND FUND BALANCES Liabilities: Unrestricted: General: Accounts payable $ 28,996 $ 23,021 Due to current fund restricted 1,171 926 Due to Pi Beta Phi Grand Trea surer Note B 303,705 303,705 333,872 327,652 Arrowcraft Shop and Magazine Agency: Accounts payable 230 922 Due to current fund general 44,58 67,897 44,788 68,819 Fund Balances: Unrestricted: General (deficit) ( 89,621) ( 123,143) Arrowcraft Shop 255,528 216 ,020 Magazine Agency 695 373 166,602 93,250 Restricted: Matthew J. Wilson income fund. . . . 993 687 Library fund 178 239STATEMENT OF REVENUES AND EXPENDITURES AND CHANGES IN FUND BALANCES CURRENT FUNDS PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL Year Ended May 31 1974 1973 Unrestricted: Revenues: Educational and general: Student fees.... . $ 69,468 $ 56,931 Interest and dividends Settlement School Endowment Fund 538 528 Interest Wisconsin Alpha Trust , . 1,872 Contributions: Clubs 46,493 47,770 Chapters 2,804 2,603 Pi Beta Phi 6,291 11,665 Expenses allocable to Settlement School paid by other Pi Beta Phi Funds 85,407 82,194 Other 15,267 5,668 Rent and other 14,153 11,947 Arrowcraft sales, less costs of sales 126,476 117,416 Magazine commissions 9,4.04 9,349 378,173 346,071 Auxiliary enterprises: Craft supplies sales 24,424 27,090 Meals and room rents paid students and faculty 75,029 61,864 Meals and room rents paid guests and groups 8,184 4,604 107,637 93,558 485,810 439,629 Expenditures: Educational and general: Administration 118 , 620 107, 414 Instructional 43 , 193 34,34C Operating and maintenance 46,522 40,69! Arrowcraft Shop 129 ,351 118,911 Magazine Agency 11,031 11,46! 348,717 312,823 Auxiliary enterprises: Craft supplies 16,018 18,790 Dining hall 36,478 31,213 Housing 11,576 9,629 64,072 59,632 1,171 926 412,789 372,45! EXCESS OF REVENUES OVER EXPENDI TURES-UNRESTRICTED 73,021 67,174 Transfer from Library Fund 331 1,121 73,352 68,301 Unrestricted fund balance at beginning of year 93,250 24,945 UNRESTRICTED FUND BALANCE AT END OF YEAR 166,602 93,25( Restricted: Revenues: Dividends Matthew J. Wilson Income Fund 306 30t Contributions Library Fund 270 611 Contingent liability Note D 167,773 94,176 $546,433 $490,647 See notes to financial statements. STATEMENT OF REVENUES AND EXPENDITURES AND CHANGES IN FUND BALANCE ENDOWMENT FUNDS AND INVESTED IN PLANT PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL Year Ended May 31 1974 1973 Endowment Funds Settlement School EndowmentFund: Gain on disposal of securities... $ 11 $ Balance at beginning of year. . . 5,512 5,523 5,512 267 228 500 ( 110) 200)EXCESS OF REVENUES OVER EXPENDI TURES-RESTRICTED 576 Transfer to Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts 331 1,12' 245 20. Restricted fund balance at beginning of year 926 1,12(. RESTRICTED FUND BALANCE AT END OF YEAR 1,171 92, 291 5,221 Brendel Scholarship Fund: Interest earned Contributions Awards (deduction) $167,773 $ 94,17 EXCESS OF REVENUES OVER Ex PENDITURES Balance at beginning of year 157 528 4,847 4,319 See notes to financial statements. 5,004 4,847 Matthew J. Wilson Fund Balance at beginning and end of year. . . 8,430 8,430 $ 18,957 $ 18,789 ....... Invested in Plant Additions from current funds $ 17,540 $ 6,107 Balance at beginning of year 1,208,752 1,202,645 See notes to financial statements. $1,226,292 $1,208,752 </p>
      <pb ref="arr9110023_0003" seq="03" n="26-27  "/>
       <p>THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI STATEMENT OF FINANCIAL CONDITION ENDOWMENT FUNDS AND INVESTED IN PLANT PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL May 31 1974 1973 $ 5,523 $ 5,512 5,004 4,847 8,430 8 ,430 18,957 $ 18,789 $ 1,521 $ 1,521 1,102,814 1,097,674 117,404 106 ,804 4,553 2,753 $1,226,292 $1,208,752 $ 5,523 $ 5,512 5,004 4,847 8,430 8,430 $ 18,957 $ 18,789 $1,226,292 $1,208,752 notes to financial statements. STATEMENT OF FINANCIAL CONDITION SPECIAL FUND WISCONSIN ALPHA TRUST PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL AssETs ............................................. % Federal Farm Loan Bonds (market value .37,207) $142,233 FUND BALANCE :onsin Alpha Trust Note C $142 ,233 notes to financial statements. STATEMENT OF REVENUES AND EXPENDITURES AND CHANGES IN FUND BALANCE SPECIAL FUND WISCONSIN ALPHA TRUST PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL Year ended May 31, 1974 WISCONSIN ALPHA TRUST 3t assets received Note C $I42,233 rest income 9 ,919 152 ,152 3t expenses ( 558) asfer to. Arrowmont ( 1, 872 ) to Elvehjem Art Center ( 7,489) 9,919 FUND BALANCE AT END OF YEAR $142 ,233 notes to financial statement NOTES TO FINANCIAL STATEMENTS PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL Years ended May 31, 1974 and 1973 NOTE A Significant Accounting Policies The accounts of the Settlement School are maintained on a fund basis of accounting appropriate to not-for-profit organizations. The current funds are used to account for transactions related to the instructional programs of the School and the auxiliary activities which provide services to the students, faculty and public. The Endowment Funds are used to account for gifts which allow only the income thereon to be expended. The Invested In Plant Fund contains the transactions relating to investment in property and equipment. The Special Fund is described in Note C. The format of the financial statements displaying these funds is presented in a manner which is appropriate for colleges and universities. In accordance with generally accepted accounting principles for colleges and universities, no provision has been made for depreciation of buildings and equipment. Certain expenses paid from other funds of Pi Beta Phi are allocable to Settlement School and are included as in-come and expenses in these financial statements. NOTE B--Due to Pi Beta Phi Grand Treasurer Advances to Settlement School were made as a loan for the purpose of paying a portion of the construction costs of a classroom building to be known as Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts. The loan bears interest at 5% due annually. There is no stated due date for the loan principal. NoTE C--Wisconsin Alpha Trust The Wisconsin Alpha Trust agreement dated December 5. 1972, proVides that Arrowmont School Division of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School hold certain properties in trust and distribtite income from those properties in the following manner. At the end of the first year, 80% of the net income shall go to the Elvehjem Art Center and 20% to Arrowmont. In subsequent years, 80% of the net income shall paid to Arrowmont and 20% used for purposes of continuing education of Pi Beta Phi alumnae. Assets of the Trust at May 31, 1974 consisted of a $233 savings account and $142,000 of 7.35% Federal Farm Loan Bonds. The initial term of the Trust is for five years and one month. Four additional periods of five years each may be extended by Wisconsin Alpha. The trust agreement provides that all assets be fully paid over to Wisconsin Alpha or its successor immediately upon establishment of an undergraduate chapter of Pi Beta Phi on the campus of the University of Wisconsin, Madison, Wisconsin. NoTE D Contingent Liability The Settlement School has received a notice of income tax deficiencies from the Internal Revenue Service for years ended May 31, 1961 through May 31, 1968, which amounted to approximately $60,000, including penalties. The Internal Revenue Service contends that the Arrow-craft Shop income is not related to the tax exempt purpose of Settlement School and is, therefore, subject to income taxation. The Settlement School does not agree with this position and plans to pursue the matter in court. The out-come cannot he determined at this time and no provision has been made for any liability in connection with this matter. AssETs awment Funds ttlernent School Endowment Fund equity (.70%) in Pi Beta Phi Trust securities at cost (approximate market value : 19 74 $5 , 751; 19 73 $6,897).r rendel Scholarship Fund savings ac count.... . atthew J. Wilson Fund corporate stock valued at market value at date of acquisition (approximate market value: 1974 $7,880; 1973 $8,645) sled in Plant at cost snd uildings and improvements arniture and equipment rucks FUND BALANCES owment Funds q.tlement School Endowment Fund rendel Scholarship Fund :atthew J. Wilson Fund ESTED IN PLANT May 31 1974 $ 233 142,000 Staniinq C2omm,ittee6 CANADIAN PHILANTHROPIES COMMITTEE Libraries in Canada's northland continued to benefit, thanks to the generous contributions of Pi Phis in both Canada and the United States. In 1973 the sum of $450 was sent to the library services in the Yukon Territories and an equal amount to the library services in the North-west Territories. This money has enabled one librarian to employ a person who speaks and reads Greenland Eskimo to translate the titles and summarize the contents of some recently acquired books written in Greenland Eskimo. The library of periodicals, pamphlets, and books, started, by Pi Phi contributions, in the Indian Brother-hood centres in the Yukon has been given government approval and will now receive funds from this source. Once again Pi Phis contributions have pioneered the wayin new projects. The libraries in the north appreciate o support for it enables them to undertake activities f which no government monies are available. The loan funds for social work students which t Canadian Project established at nine Canadian univer ties are currently under study. While some universiti consider the funds to be useful, others have not ma use of the funds for some time. Presently, more than h the total money in the fund is on deposit in banks. We are grateful for the loyal support of the ma clubs, chapters, and individuals who have contributed the Canadian Project and who have helped to ke "Arrow in the Arctic" vital and alive. CAROL CHILDERHOSE MCGONIGAL ALUM COMMITTEE FOR CONTINUING EDUCATION The Alumnae Committee for Continuing Education was appointed by Grand Council in March, 1974. For some time there had been talk in the Alumnae Department, and within Grand Council, on assistance to alumnae to create interest in continuing education. Soon after Wisconsin Alpha gave up its charter on the University of Wisconsin campus, the Wisconsin Alpha Trust Fund was established. Continuing education scholar-ships will benefit from a portion of the income of this trust. The many loyal members of Wisconsin Alpha of Pi Beta Phi hope that these funds will help Pi Phis in furthering their education and that this will help in perpetuating Wisconsin Alpha as well as Pi Beta Phi. The committee consists of three alumnae. Those serving are Polly Hackett Burns, Illinois Eta; Lindsey Farnham Siegfried, Ohio Beta; and the chairman, Aileen Welgan, Alberta Alpha. In the brief time that this committee has been woi ing together, ideas have been shared on the mundane a philosophical levels. Communication has been by Lett This offers its own unique demands. A formal report recommendations has been sent to Grand Council 1 their consideration. Included are recommendations on a of recipients; amount of scholarship; length of schol: ship; criteria; need and goal; publicity, implementatic involvement of alumna club; etc. My sincere thanks to each committee member for I efforts. Much has been accomplished, much is ahe Each of us feels the excitement of being involved in new worthwhile project for Pi Beta Phi. AILEEN AYLSWORTH WELGAN EMMA HARPER TURNER MEMORIAL FUNDS COMMITTEE For twenty-eight years the Emma Harper Turner Memorial Funds project has been one of the truly "shining things" of Pi Beta Phi. Established by vote of the Swampscott Convention in 1946 with an appropriation of $50,000 from general Fraternity funds, it was set up with a dual purpose. The principal of the fund was to be used for loans to chapters for building and remodeling purposes. The interest on these loans was to be used to lend assistance to some of our alumnae who, through tragedy, accidents, advanced age, prolonged illness, etc., were carrying heavy burdens almost too great to be borne. This committee, composed of three alumnae appointed by Grand Council, is in no way concerned with chapter house loans. Its sole function is to process grants to alumnae in need of special assistance. Since 1950 the principal has been augmented annually by contributions from alumnae clubs (primarily), active chapters, and individuals. Several clubs, in addition to their regular donation to this fund, send an extra gift honoring the memory of a beloved member who has died. As this is a relatively small project, the amount of each of these gifts of love is necessarily limited so that as many alumnae as possible can be helped. Since its inception in 1948 eighty-four alumnae have received grants; More than half of them have been Golden Arrows, seven of them having worn the Arrow from sixty to seventy years. Grants are of two types: (1) Emergency grants, given in one check and ordinarily granted only once; (2) Monthly grants on a continuing basis for as long as the ne exists. Emergency grants are usually given to young alumnae facing almost over-whelming burdens. In instance can the Fraternity assume all or even a ma portion of the expenses which may be involved. But es rather small grants can help lighten the load and give lift to the spirit in the knowledge that Pi Beta Phi concerned about them in "friendship unending." Among our older alumnae the need is usually fox continuing monthly grant to supplement a slender incox Most of them have a small income, barely enough to co the minimum of living expenses, but nothing for em gencies or for the little extras which can make a ; and often lonely life easier to endure.. By our small gi of love we bring sunshine into drab lives, give them dignity which comes from having a little money of th own, and provide a few small comforts or pleasures. 'I surprise, the joy, of knowing that their Fraternity s cares about them seems to mean as much as the ba, needed money. One elderly alumna seems to have sumn up the feeling of most of them upon receipt of their f gift, "When I saw the check -I knew it came strait from heaven !" Another once wrote, "I clutched the ch, to my heart and let the tears roll down." Ten alumnae have received grants during the past ye three of them were new grants. Five of them are Got( Arrows whose initiation dates range from 1907-19 These gifts are always given in confidence. Only the 1 alumnae involved in processing the grants and the Gr% 27 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



