<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr9030017_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News of Arrowmont the Craft School and Arrocraft the Cottage Industry</title>
                        <author><name>Lehner, Elanor Bushnell</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Spring 1974</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr9030017_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1974</date>, News of Arrowmont the Craft School and Arrocraft the Cottage Industry</title>
                        <author><name>Lehner, Elanor Bushnell</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 17-21</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">41</note>
                        <note type="Folder">10</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 90, Number 3 (Spring 1974), Pages 17-21.</note>
			<note type="document">arr9030017_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Just What Did You Buy?; An Invitation to Arrowmont; Florida Gammas Have Reunion at Red Barn; Arrowmont International; BOG's Participate in Academic Meeting</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>The Birth of Arrowmont, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1965-1979</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>
                                <item>People</item>
                                <item>Staff</item>
                                <item>Administrators</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr9030017_0001" seq="01" n="16-17  "/>
       <p>Tennis Champ Defeats Male Challenger by ANDREA S. BLETZINGER Fox River Valley Club In this year of challenges, of women declaring their rights in all areas including sports, Wisconsin's Ann Stanton Grant, Arizona A, gained national attention when she took up the gauntlet, played and defeated Bob Lindwall, Manitowoc, on the tennis courts. The petite Ann Stanton Grant, Appleton, Wisconsin homemaker, who declared her age might as well have been worn like a number on a foot-ball player's uniform, could not deny her 44 years. Every Wisconsin newspaper mentioned it. Active in the sport through her college years at the University of Arizona where she became a member of Arizona Alpha, she stopped playing after marriage and not until the family moved to Appleton in the 1960s did she return to the game. With the enthusiasm she gives to many other activities, including participation in the Fox River Valley Alumnae Club and on the advisory board for the Lawrence University active chapter, she soon found herself in singlesand doubles women's programs at the Fox Cities Racquet Club and played with her husband in couples tournaments as well. She finally reached a point where she had to budget her time playing tennis to fit her busy schedule as housewife, den mother for the youngest of her five children, and all the handicraft projects she enjoys. She knits one or two sweaters a month during the winter, does crewel work, papier tole, and decoupage. Her family calls it all "Mother's mental health pro-gram." She also makes most of her own clothes including her tennis dresses. All her friends and many other tennis buffs gathered in June to watch her play Bob Lind-wall. They felt concern through the first set which she lost, but being one who likes challenge, she came back strong in the second and won both the second and third sets, thus gaining the day. "It was one of the toughest competitions I've ever been in," she told. "After that first set when Lindwall won, I really wanted to beat him." The challenger asked for a return match on his home grounds in Manitowoc and again Ann Grant was the winner. After her first win she gained state-wide coverage in newspapers, even made the New York Times as her friends in Connecticut, where the Grants had lived before coming to Apple-ton, noted and sent her clippings. During the past summer Mrs. Grant was ranked sixth in the state among women over 35 and fourth among women over 40. She played in several tournaments throughout the state over the summer months. Earns Scholarship Susan McKellar, Florida Beta, has been awarded the Florida Home Economics Association Scholarship. The selection was based on scholarship, activities, and a grade point average of 3.8. Susan's activities include Village Vamps, Union Program Council, AHEA, FHEA, and Omicron Nu honorary. Edited by ELEANOR BUSHNELL I Board of Students, staff members, and visitors at Arrowmont can pass from level to level on a ramp that is itself a work of art. The student in the lower hallway of the Emma Harper Turner classroom building seems almost obscured by the beauty surrounding her. the craft school the cottage Inc The Great Smoky Mountains Gatlinburg, Tennessee 37738 17' </p>
      <pb ref="arr9030017_0002" seq="02" n="18-19  "/>
       <p>Just hat Did You Buy? Future Arrowcraft customers will better understand and appreciate the value of their purchases, thanks to a newsy handout prepared at the recommendation of the Board of Governors. The flyer, which may be ordered from the Arrowcraft Shop, may be placed in the bag with an Arrowcraft purchase, or used as a hand-out at club sales. Even Pi Phis may appreciate this simple explanation of the Settlement School-Arrowcraft-Arrowmont relationship. "Thank you for your Arrowcraft purchase. "Perhaps you would be interested to know something of the history and background of Arrowcraft. "In 1912, as a memorial to its Founders, the Pi Beta Phi Fraternity established a Settlement School in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, in the foot-hills of the Great Smoky Mountains. It brought educational and health facilities to the region and, by 1925, provided the Arrowcraft Shop, as an outlet for the craftsmen producing in their homes. "Arrowcraft, one of the first cottage industries in the United States, grew and expanded. Products were sold by the shop in Gatlinburg and by chapter and alumna, clubs across the country. Today some sixty weavers, and many other craftsmen, market their work through the efforts of Pi Beta Phi. It continues to provide the finest weaving and craftsmanship to be found in the area. "In 1945 summer craft workshops were inaugurated in conjunction with the University of Tennessee. College accreditation was offered. From this foundation, and a continuing interest in crafts, evolved the Arrowmont School of Crafts, which provides expert instruction, during the summer months, to both beginning and advanced students in a variety of crafts. "Funds derived from Arrowcraft sales benefit mountain craftsmen and also help to support the Arrowmont School of Crafts." An Invitation to Arrowmont On Arrowmont Night at the 1973 Pi Beta Phi Convention, the following song was introduced by the Pi Phi Chorus, directed by Music Chairman Mary Swanson Engle. When it had ended the audience demanded an instant replay. The melody is the popular Lerner-Loewe tune, "Camelot, The words are by BOG member Eleanor Lehner. It doesn't matter what your occupation Or what the type of habitat you haunt We offer you a cordial invitation To Arrowmont. .. . It doesn't matter if you feel uncertain Or if you know exactly what you want We offer you a peek behind the curtain At Arrowmont. Arrowmont! Arrowmont! It has a magic of its own And at Arrowmont! Arrowmont! Enchanted dreams are sown. . It doesn't matter if you don't feel ready And don't know what to do at Arrowmont, You'll never know until You cultivate a skill But what a thrill that skill will bring To you at Arrowmont ! 18 Florida Gammas Have Reunion at Red Barn Florida Gammas gathered at the Red Barn on the Arrowmont campus last September from as far away as California, Illinois, and Florida. There were twelve Pi Phis plus one husband. Some had not seen each other for over 40 years. What excitement such a gathering generated and what fun was had during that week, discovering the Arrowmont Arts and Crafts School, browsing and buying in the Arrowcraft Shop, riding the aerial tram and the ski lift to the top for a beautiful panoramic view of the mountains, hiking the trail that leads up the mountain in back of the Red Barn (a delightful experience!) and sight-seeing the Smoky Mountains National Park. Caroline Riddle inspired the reunion, and the women were most grateful to her and to Arrowmont for the opportunity. The experience deepened friendships as well as appreciation of what is being accomplished in Gatlinburg. Pi Phis have every right to take great pride in their sponsorship. Every alumna should experience such a re Enjoying coffee in the Staff House dining room: (I to r) Helen Draughon, Peg Lofroos, Frances Williams, Mary Louise Wilkerson, and Mary Zimmerman. union with former college mates in the charming and comfortable Red Barn and view the handsome Arrowmont School building. To catch the spirit, one really needs to make a visit. Why not try it ? Rollins College classmates from a number of years back held a reunion in Gatlinburg recently. Those attending included, back row (I to r) Caroline Riddle, Florida Beta, Arrowmont-ArrowcrtIft Administrator; Ruth Haddock; Leila Larkin; Peg Lofroos and Dickie Colado, Florida Gamma; Helen Draughon, Florida Beta; Mary Fisher Zimmerman and Damaris Wilson, Florida Gamma; Marian Heard, Tennessee Alpha, Director of Arrowmont, 2nd from right. Front row (I to r) Helen McIntosh; Mary Louise Wilkerson; Katherine Sloan, Diane Carnes and Frances Williams, Florida Gam-ma; and Henrietta Huff, Missouri Beta, representing Little Pigeon Alumnae Club of Gatlinburg and Arrowmont Board of Governors. 19. </p>
      <pb ref="arr9030017_0003" seq="03" n="20-21  "/>
       <p>Arrowmont International Charles Counts, Arrowmont pottery instructor (center, above) demonstrated a primitive method of firing ceramics to his classes. The clay is placed in the midst of a pile of brush and wood. Branches are placed on top and a fire is lit. Counts, who has made an intensive study of pottery-making among primitive peoples, commented, "We're not sure just how this kiln process works so well ... but it does." Counts maintains a studio in Rising Fawn, Ga., and is president of African Craftsmen in America, Inc. He will soon return to Nigeria to continue his studies of African techniques. One of his associates: British potter Michael Cardew, who has also taught at Arrowmont, recently toured the United States with Nigerian potters Ladi Kwali and C. Kofi Athey, demonstrating unique African methods. The idea for this originated during a meeting at Arrowmont. They now plan to invite textile craftsmen to the States. Sister Consolata Agytong of Ghana studied textiles and basketry during the 1973 Arrowmont summer session. The Gatlinburg Rotary Club granted her a scholarship to make this possible. In the photo, right, she is shown with Arrowmont graduate assistant Sharon Heidlingsfelder. 20 BOGs Participate in cademic Meeting (EDITOR'S NOTE: The following report was prepared by Caroline Riddle, Arrowmont Administrator, with the assistance of Betty Hall, former BOG chairman.) Just prior to the Arrowmont Board of Governors meeting in Gatlinburg, Dean Lura Odland, College of Home Economics, invited BOG members to spend 24 hours on the University of Tennessee campus and meet with the Academic Standards Committee. Helen Vollmar, chairman of the Board, Lucile Jennings, chair-man of the Settlement School property committee, Betty Hall, past chairman of the Board, and Caroline Riddle, new Settlement School Administrator, accepted the invitation and experienced a thoroughly planned and stimulating 24 hours. Activities opened with a luncheon at the Faculty Club and then moved to the Conference Room in the Home Economics Building for the Academic Standards Committee meeting. Dr. Odland presided and introduced in turn the participants and speakers: Dr. Walter Herndon, Vice Chancellor for Academic Affairs; Dr. Margaret Perry, Dean for Graduate Studies ; Dr. Robbie Blakemore, Chairperson, Related Arts, Crafts, and Interior Design Department; Lucile Jennings, who spoke from a student view-point; Mr. Ronald Leadbetter, Asst. Legal Counsel; Dr. John McDow, Dean, Mr. Jim Clark and Mr. David Thomas from Admissions and Records; Caroline Riddle; Marian Heard, Arrowmont Director; and Helen Vollmar. This was only the second meeting of this Standards Committee, the first having been held in 1969. Dr. Herndon spoke of the university's overall accrediting through the South-ern Association, and then the accrediting of each college within the university. He posed two questions briefly: "Are we using our re-sources as well as we might ?" and "Have we charted a course ?" Both of these related to Arrowmont, as well as to the university. Mr. Leadbetter interpreted the Letter of Understanding between U.T. and Pi Beta Phi. Mr. McDow spoke particularly of transcripts and records, explaining the new term C.E.U., meaning Continuing Education Units. This is a flexible unit of measure for non-credit activities and may be used to record an individual's participation in formal classes, courses, pro-grams, and informal, non-traditional modes of non-credit education. Miss Heard spoke of her hopes for Arrowmont. She pointed out that U.T. assists Arrowmont by offering no craft courses on their own campuses during the summer. She spoke of last summer's Arrowmont successes and growth, of projected courses in marketing and photography, of craft tours to Southwest United States and to Europe, and of the dream of a year-round school. In the evening there was dinner at the Faculty Club, where the guests included Mrs. Nancy Reese, wife of the new Chancellor of the University of Tennessee; Sister Remy Revor and Dr. Jim Darrow who taught at Arrowmont last summer ; Jane Martin and Jan Henley, rep-resenting the Pi Phi chapter on campus; Mrs. Calvin Scott, president of the Knoxville Pi Beta Phi Alumnae Club, and many students who had attended Arrowmont. The following day Dean Odland had arranged an in-depth tour of the campus, con-ducted by Sandy Blain, assistant professor at U.T. and assistant director at Arrowmont. This included brief visits to various departments of the College of Home Economics: Crafts and Interior Design where Marian Heard was working with a stitchery class ; Textiles and Clothing; Food Science and Food Systems Administration; Nutrition; Child Development, Family Relationships, Home Management and Family Economics; and Home Management Department. Each speaker explained his own department's concept of its role in relation to the changing needs of society. These visits were followed by an informal coffee with students and faculty. The BOGs enjoyed seeing familiar faces and meeting those at the University who have worked so closely with Pi Beta Phi. Because of these mutual efforts, Arrowmont has become an exciting, highly regarded School of Crafts. Helen Deppe Vollmar, Chairman of the Board of Governors, chats with Jan Henley and Jane Martin, officers of Tennessee Gamma. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



