<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr9240101_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Fraternity Forum</title>

                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Summer 1976</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr9240101_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1976</date>, Fraternity Forum</title>

                        <extent>Page 100</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">41</note>
                        <note type="Folder">12</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 92, Number 4 (Summer 1976), Page 100.</note>
			<note type="document">arr9240101_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Sell Arrowcraft</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>The Birth of Arrowmont, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1965-1979</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>
                                <item>Funding</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr9240101_0001" seq="01" n="100-101  "/>
       <p>100 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI was given by the'Fraternity education interest group, on the Pi Phi philantropy, Arrowmont. This was especially beneficial because Arrowmont is located in our home state of Tennessee. The slides showed the complete facility the grounds, classrooms, equipment, and dormitories. The slide show inspired our chapter to plan a weekend retreat to Arrowmont, only four hours away. The whole idea of a philanthropy became more poignant when chapter members observed Arrowmont in operation and saw for themselves why Arrowmont, located in the beautiful mountains of Tennessee, has such a national appeal. Our two representatives gained helpful ideas from the Convention workshop on chapter organization and structure. One of the most effective ideas which our officers initiated at the beginning of the year was a stricter following of parliamentary procedure. This insured more efficiency during chapter meetings and better communication between officers and other members. After elections this spring, we held an officer training workshop for all new and old officers. During these sessions, new officers learned the general responsibilities of being a Pi Phi officer, as well as the specific duties of their individual offices. This not only enabled the new officers to find out first hand about problems they might encounter, but also gave them a chance to get together as a group. Our rush chairman brought back several new ideas for rush this year. A new and more efficient method of voting was instituted and some small changes made in third round to make it more personal for the rushee. The whole experience of Convention helped our two representatives gain better insight into the operation of Tennessee Beta as one chapter of a national organization. New ideas added much enthusiasm and proved to be extremely beneficial for the chapter as a whole. ASHLEY ROWE, CAROL SCHEER Sell Arrowcraft TENNESSEE GAMMA Our chapter delegate, Becky Dunn, came back to U T this fall with many new and exciting ideas for our chapter that she gathered at Convention '75. We all were eager to try out some of the new ideas, but we were hampered by fall rush for a while. Therefore we had to put some of eagerness into rush. We began putting the ideas to work as soon as we got our new pledges from fall rush. Our pledge trainers, Amelea Whitman and Charlotte Carr, implemented some improved methods of Fraternity orientation. Aiding in the Fraternity orientation program was Becky Dunn who constructed a local pledge book. Previously we only used a national one. Judging from surveys taken during the year everyone thought that our new Fraternity orientation program greatly improved the pledges' awareness of our history, the actives in the chapter, and general university life. Another fall event was an Arrowcraft sale organized by Jan Cox. Since Knoxville is so close to Gatlinburg, knowlledge of Pi Phi crafts is locally widespread. Because of this knowledge and our publicity, the same was very successful. This was our first Arrowcraft sale. We now plan to make it an annual event. As far as weekly meetings go, we have improved immenselv. We now have formal meetings every other week as opposed to two formal meetings a week that we formerly had. We also made another improvement in meet-ings. We are now using parliamentary procedure in our meetings. Previously we attempted to use it only in formal meetings. This wasn't even entirely successful. Since we have enforced parliamentary procedures we have cut our meeting times in half. Our meetings are now more organized and orderly. As the Convention suggested we have implemented our officer training program. At the beginning of winter, we held an officer training workshop. This was soon after our new officers were installed and was a great help. It also started our chapter working toward similar goals. These are the main ways that Tennessee Gamma has implemented ideas from Convention '75. These ideas have greatly improved our chapter throughout the year. The enthusiasm that Becky Dunn brought back with her definitely rubbed off on the other members of Tennessee Gamma. Most of the ideas that were brought back to us, even those not mentioned above, have been extremely successful. Interest Groups Stronger TENNESSEE DELTA Tennessee Delta has benefited greatly from Convention. One of the many ideas that has proven successful is the use of other actives for chairing interest groups instead of the vice presidents. We also implemented ideas from Convention to start making our interest groups strong again. Another successful idea was the use of the nominating committee for slating and interviewing future officers. This proved to be more productive because those being interviewed were more open with the committee than with executive council, our previously used system. To help these new officers, we have learned how to run and operate an effective officer workshop. We have used the idea of more appointed offices and have used this to delegate responsibility more towards the active chapter than solely on executive council. A program that has improved is officer training through closer relationships with outgoing officers. Arrowboard and the vice president of moral advancement have become more active from tips picked up at Convention. Spirit and morale has been boosted within the chapter. And because of more competent officers and a more spirited Arrow-board and active chapter we have a great pledge class and have not lost any because of unhappiness with sorority life. Our pledges have also become more aware of Fraternity heritage and education because of the change in the final pledge tests. Officers have taken an increased interest in their jobs and have been striving to do them better and better. We have bettered our scholarhip, our attitude, and our chapter. We learned a lot at Convention, more than I can write about. Most important was realizing the concept of "National." Seeing and talking to Grand Council helped us to realize that it is more than an address to write to. Be-cause of this, our correspondence is better and more personal, which helps with the realization that we are a national Fraternity. MARTHA COLEY Hold Chapter Retreats TEXAS BETA Texas Beta is implementing Convention '75 ideas through our interest groups and at chapter re THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI 101 treats. The enthusiasm brought back from Convention was felt by many of the other officers and through them we have been able to generate it throughout the chapter. The reason we had the officers spread the enthusiasm was be-cause it was easiest for them to do this in their interest groups. One of the biggest programs initiated was that of more group retreats. In the previous years, Texas Beta has had retreats only during one day. We usually had one retreat a semester in which the actives and pledges were able to get together for a picnic and skits, but no workshops were usually done. In the fall, Texas Beta had an overnight re-treat away from campus, when we had well organized group workshops and talk sessions. The retreat helped to unify the chapter and in the process made it more organized and informed. This semester the pledges also had an overnight retreat with the same general group workshops. The next day, the rest of the active chapter joined the pledges for skits and songs. The other programs that have been used from Convention '75 are rush ideas and songs. Rotation groups in rush were used once again and new songs initiated. The success of Convention '75 has been felt throughout the chapter and we hope to use more ideas in the near future. CAROLINE THOMPSON Enthusiasm Spreads TEXAS GAMMA The enthusiasm generated at Convention '75 has definitely spread throughout the Texas Gamma chapter! Our delegate, Teddi Crager, and Jill Brown, alternate delegate, found it hard to describe the warmth and genuine friendship received from the many Pi Phis they met from all over the United States and Canada. Receiving the high honor of the Balfour Cup not only gave the chapter pride and honor, but encouraged everyone to strive just as hard this year in every aspect of chapter participation. This spirit was generated during rush in the fall and has definitely brought us even closer together. Our thirty-eight new initiates soon felt this atmosphere of pride and sisterhood in the chapter and have definitely added a fresh, exciting spark to all of the activities and friendships. The chapter has come to a better understanding of the workings of Pi Beta Phi and has a broader concept of the many chapters in the nation and Canada their differences as well as the many similarities and traditions we all hold dear. Our pledge program has become better organized this year by following a well-prepared schedule for each activity and event. One of the major changes in Texas Gamma is the revision of the office of vice president of social advancement. Whereas we formerly stressed the office as that of a social chairman planning functions for the chapter, it is now organized as it was designed to be. We now stress the office as one of coordinator for rush, social, and pledge activities, having a rush chairman, social chairman, and pledge trainer work under her. The many workshops held at Convention gave the chap-ter several good ideas we plan to incorporate in our up-coming retreat and rush next fall. However, the most beneficial aspect of Convention was the experiences and friendships gained from all Pi Phis working toward the common goal of harmony and sisterhood. TEDDI CRAGERStarts Standards Board TEXAS DELTA Convention was a rewarding experience for me as a Pi Phi but also as an individual. It was my hope to convey to the chapter the exciting things I had learned. In six short days I had seen the love and friendship that only Pi Phi could give. Many of us at Texas Delta were going through a period of apathy. I believe that this is a problem shared by many chapters, but being at Convention gave me a spark of enthusiasm and excitement for the coming years. Of all the new ideas that were shared at Convention, the most beneficial was that of beginning a standards board within our chapter. Some time ago, Texas Delta had a standards board but through the years it had lost its effectiveness. Other Pi Phi chapters at Convention had efficiently operating standards boards and their organizations served as guidelines for our new board. At the present time, our standards board is working diligently to formulate rules. Rush is another area of improvement which is being credited to Convention. Texas Delta had a successful fall rush but is looking foward to an even better one in 1976. Many of the workshops at Convention were geared toward rush and membership selection. We hope to use some of the ideas to formulate new guidelines for membership selection. Many other chapters have specific guidelines which they adhere to during voting. We will be implementing their ideas in our '76 rush. The third and final area which benefited from Conven tion was in chapter finances. While at a workshop, I was told about a method of billing members which has been implemented in our chapter. At the beginning of each school year, our treasurer sends a letter to each parent indicating our chapter budget and how we will be spending our funds. At the end of the letter is a form which we ask parents to fill out and return to the treasurer. The form indicates whether the parent wishes to have their daughter's bill sent to them or to the daughter. This approach allows parents to see how their daughter's dues are being spent and the bill is usually paid quickly. It seems impossible to acknowledge all the contributions that Convention made to our chapter. I wish that every member could have spent at least one day at Convention and seen a great Fraternity at work. But most importantly was the satisfaction and sisterhood found there. I hope that the enthusiasm I gained at Convention will be felt by every Texas Delta during some of her active affiliation. If a Pi Phi Convention can accomplish this in one girl, then perhaps it can start a chain reaction in every active and alumnae member. PATTI FLETCHER Voting Procedure Changed UTAH ALPHA Unfortunately, as I went through my notes on Convention I didn't find too many ideas that the Utah Alpha chapter picked up on. I attribute this mainly to two reasons. 1) That only 21 girls out of 75 live in the sorority house and unity and consistent enthusiasm is hard to come by. 2) Because the girls who went to Convention never really sat down and went over all the notes gathered from Convention. We did change our voting procedure this year which proved to be much better. This year we each were given a </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



