<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr9320037_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News of Arrowmont the Craft School and Arrocraft the Cottage Industry</title>
                        <author><name>Persche, Mary Alice Barber</name></author>
                        <author><name>Daniels, Stephanie </name></author>
                        <author><name>Waterman fr. Knoxville, photos, Natalie </name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Winter 1976</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr9320037_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1976</date>, News of Arrowmont the Craft School and Arrocraft the Cottage Industry</title>
                        <author><name>Persche, Mary Alice Barber</name></author>
                        <author><name>Daniels, Stephanie </name></author>
                        <author><name>Waterman fr. Knoxville, photos, Natalie </name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 37-42</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">41</note>
                        <note type="Folder">13</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 93, Number 2 (Winter 1976), Pages 37-42.</note>
			<note type="document">arr9320037_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Brack Photography Studio Opens; Slides Ready, Canada; Former Assistant Returns with Hubby</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>The Birth of Arrowmont, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1965-1979</item>
                                <item>Facilities</item>
                                <item>Construction</item>
                                <item>Summer Crafts Workshop</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr9320037_0001" seq="01" n="36-37  "/>
       <p>Radio Career Is Aim of Missourian by SHARON MANES, Missouri Alpha Writing, producing, and broadcasting a one hour news-feature radio show are all routine for Diane Campbell, Missouri Alpha. Diane is a sophomore beginning her third semester at KCCU, a university owned and operated radio station serving the Columbia community. With a double major of broadcast journal-ism and political science, Diane combines her interests of public relations and law. In high school, she developed an extensive background in speech and an avid interest in news. Her future plans include hosting her own talk show. Before Diane could broadcast, her voice was tested for the "air," and she learned to operate the station's equipment. She started as a newswriter and broadcaster and quickly advanced to news producer the following semester. As news producer she was responsible for everything that was aired, even sports and weather. Diane programmed the 15 minute show in addition to writing and broad-casting the news. Now, Diane has her own hour-long show during which she presents news and feature stories along with editorials. The program is broadcast every Wednesday morning from 8 to 9 a.m., prime time for the area. Candy Reynolds, Tennessee Alpha Tennis Champ Earns National Rankings by CATHY BRIDGERS, Tennessee Alpha Tennessee Alpha Pi Phis are mighty proud of tennis star Candy Reynolds. Not only has Candy received the Most Valuable Women's Tennis Player Award for two years, she is also president of the Health and Physical Education Club and co-captain of the Women's Tennis Team. Candy went to SMU her freshman year, and in 1973 she was USTA Women's National Amateur Grass Court Champion. In 1974 Candy transferred to UTC and was on the USTA Junior Wightman Cup Squad 1974-75. During her sophomore and junior years she represented UTC in the state AIAW women's collegiate championship and won the regional championship in 1976. In 1975 she was ranked #4 in women's collegiate tennis players. This year Candy was a member of the USTA Junior Federation Squad and won the USTA Women's National Amateur Clay Court Championship for singles and doubles. Candy's current rankings, including professionals, are #1 in the south in women's singles and doubles, #7 in the U.S. women's doubles, and #47 in U.S. women's singles. 36 Edited by MARY ALICE BARBER PERSCHE Board of Governors Sandy Sanderson, Houston, Tex., beginning photography student, gets down-to-earth in learning the rudiments of her new-found art form. She was snapped in this position by another student, Natalie Water-man, Knoxville, Tenn., who is credited with taking all of the pictures accompanying the article on Arrowmont's photography studio. The Great Smoky Mountains Gatlinburg, Tennessee 37738 37 </p>
      <pb ref="arr9320037_0002" seq="02" n="38-39  "/>
       <p>Photography Studio Opens THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI pension has been added to the urriculum classes in photog f artisans to be able to suitably heir pottery, jewelry, textiles, other art objects for marketing poses has resulted in the estabnew studio and laboratories at 'he Edythe Brack Photography y classes were held for the first its year's summer session, June 7 st 13. both beginners and advanced students were conducted in sions. The beginning course k and white continuous tone film development techniques, and enlargement procedures. Advanced projects offered instruction in special graphic techniques and photo manipulation. The new facility was designed by Dr. William J. Lauer, assistant dean of the School of Architecture at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville. Construction was handled by Ray King Construction Company, Pigeon Forge, Tenn. The studio and laboratories consist of three main rooms, divided into smaller enclosures for individual use in developing film and making prints or enlargements. The work-rooms also contain film drying cabinets, storage lockers, and complete facilities to accommodate 14 students at a time. Equipment includes eight enlargers, easels, print timers, washing sinks, a print dryer, dry-mount press and other equipment neededin photographic processing. A major contribution towards construction of the new photographic studio and laboratories came from the St. Louis (Mo.) Alumnae Club in the amount of $19,000. Another $5,000 was donated by the Dallas (Tex.) Alumnae Club to purchase equipment for the facility. Edythe Brack, for whom the studio is named, is a former member of Grand Council and a member of the Dallas Alumnae Club. This latest addition to the Arrowmont curriculum boasted an impressive staff of instructors. Included were Robert Hansen, instructor at the School of Visual Arts and the Below, photography students become real clock watchers in the lab. Student Sandy Sanderson watches the seconds tick by during a critical film developing process. Matt Gibson, a music teacher from Waupun, Wis., isn't preparing to take a shower with his clothes on. The cubicle is used for drying strips of exposed and developed film. Assoc. Professor of Art in Photog-"ennessee State University, explains print dryer to Emma Jostes Keller, rid member of the St. Louis Alumnae tially funded the new photography r Director Marian Heard and Arrow-~tor Riddle look on. Left, a finished enlargement of a black and white photo is examined by student Audrey Dick, Cincinnati, Ohio. 39 New School, and official photographer for the American Crafts Council in New York; Donald Scott Harter, workshop leader, graphic designer and freelance photographer at the Limited Press Studio, Madison, Wis.; Earl Iverson, assistant professor of Design and Photography at the University of Kansas, Lawrence, Kans., Jack Schrader, associate professor of Art in Photography at East Tennessee State University, Johnson City, Tenn., and Conrad Reinhardt, communications specialist at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville. Photography courses were planned for the Gatlinburg community this fall and winter. Above, two heads are better than one when it comes to selecting one photograph over another. Instructor Jack Schrader shares his expertise with student Alis Franzblau, Tampa, Fla. Joie Kotzen, below, Sarasota, Fla., hangs out, not the Monday wash, but freshly developed negatives that are hung by clothespins to air-dry on the patio outside the lab. </p>
      <pb ref="arr9320037_0003" seq="03" n="40-41  "/>
       <p>40 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI Barbara Crawford, Oklahoma Beta, created this Ikat weaving. Admiring it are (I to r) Renee Bergeron, Baton Rouge A.C. scholarship recipient; Anna Osborne, Louisiana Beta, Mu North Province scholar-ship winner; Sharon Patrick, Delta Kappa Gamma scholarship, Arizona Alpha; Tony Caetano, Morin County, Calif., scholarship student; Mary Ellen John-son, Florida Delta; the artist, Barbara Crawford. Henry Perram, Lafayette, La., who studied advanced weaving on scholarship awarded by the Lafayette A.C., teaches the elderly and emotionally handicapped as a volunteer. Susan Somerfield, Gatlin-burg, was an Alspaugh scholarship winner who spent most of the summer taking courses at Arrowmont. She is a recent high school graduate and wants to make crafts her career. Slides R ea y, Canada by STEPHANIE DANIELS, Ontario Alpha Three cheers for the Canadian chapters! At last, after waiting all these years, we finally have our very own, real live, true wine and blue set of slides of the famous Arrowmont. As I was fortunate to attend Arrowmont last summer on the Virginia Alpha Scholarship, I was able to compose a vivid array of slides of inside, outside, and all around Arrowmont. My next step was to produce a dialogue to accompany this slide series. This entire set of slides is available to all Canadian chapters, as well as alumnae clubs, upon request. The only way to see the true beauty of Arrowmont and the Smokey Mountains is to go there to see it. Since not everyone can do that, these slides will be just about as good. Hope-fully with these appealing pictures, more and more Canadian Pi Phis will take a week or two and visit the best southern hospitality around! To reserve the slide series, Canadian clubs and chapters should write to: Arrowmont Slides, Ontario Alpha, Pi Beta Phi 220 Beverly Street, Toronto M5T 1Z3 Ontario, Canada Gathered at the Conversation Circle are (seated, I to r) Helen Hasbrouck, Wyoming Alpha; Marian Heard; Caroline Riddle; Eryn Plimper, Corpus Christi A.C. scholarship recipient; Helen Russell, Arrowmont librarian. Standing are Annette Crawford, Texas Beta, Dallas A.C. scholarship; Laura Vandervoort, Tennessee Beta; Mary Cassily, Louisiana Alpha; Mary Ellen Johnson; Helen Lewis, Kentucky Alpha. Former Assistant } eturns With Hubby Donna and Norman Burns of Bryan, Ohio, acquired the "Arrowmont Experience" while enrolled as students during this year's summer session. Donna took beginning photography, while Norm, a dentist familiar with gold and silver fillings, studied beginning jewelry. Donna described their "experience" as a married couple, living and working among classmates who were either considerably younger or older than they were. "For me, it all started back in 1954," Donna recalls. "I had graduated from Ohio State University with a Bachelor of Science degree in fine arts education. As an Ohio Beta, I was familiar with the Pi Phi Settlement School and craft workshop because I had read about them in The ARROW . "Prospects for summer employment at home were dim so I decided to apply for a job at the Settlement School as a graduate assistant. Accepted, I took off on my maiden trip to Gatlinburg that June. I remember the bus rounding the corner and my first view of the staff house and its rolling landscape. It was beautiful. "The Chamber of Commerce and a parking lot now sit on what was part of this expanse of lawn. Trying to remember what took place 22 years ago is a real problem for someone who has difficulty remembering what happened just yesterday." Donna Burns remembered meeting her "boss" for the first time, and her fellow-assistants. "I couldn't understand at the time why everyone held the school's director, Miss Marian Heard, in such reverence. I soon learned, and it has been reaffirmed even more now that I've returned after so long an absence as a student. Never has there been a person more sincere or more dedicated to promoting the crafts throughout mid-America than Marian Heard." It was a "fun" summer, according to Donna's recollection. The living quarters for the assistants were in classrooms of the old elementary school building. The desks had been removed and small cots, a single dresser and a clothes rack were all that had been provided for the convenience and comfort of the assistants. For recreation they would watch the mice and snakes that came to visit on occasion. But, they were young, she recalls, and they loved it. Donna Burns, above, scans a strip of film with a trained eye in selecting just the right one to print. Below, dentist husband Norman sticks out his tongue and says "oh" as a piece of jewelry he's making starts to take shape. 41 </p>
      <pb ref="arr9320037_0004" seq="04" n="42-43  "/>
       <p>42 THE ARROW OF P1 BETA PHI camera and started the course "cold turkey," so to speak. I never doubted for a moment that I wouldn't emerge an expert by the end of the week. That speaks for the kind of teachers Marian Heard hires. They're not only good at what they teach, but they know how to instruct beginners or advanced students with equally outstanding results." Both Donna and Norm found the physical facilities at Arrowmont far improved over what they were during Donna's earlier visits. They never dreamed that they would become so absorbed in their projects that they would remain in their respective laboratories until the mid-night closing time every night. Donna admitted that she was more appre hensive about her husband's participation than her own. After all, he had never attended a school of this type before. She was afraid he might get bored, or object to spending his vacation in this way. "The very first day he met other couples at breakfast like Louise and Bill Davis from Indianapolis, Ind., Bill had been a research chemist with the Eli Lilly Co. for 38 years and both had come to Arrowmont for the past four years. This summer they were taking advanced jewelry and electroforming. "In class, Norm met Larry Kassman from North Miami Beach, Fla., whose wife Tina was taking a class in weaving. He also met Sarah "Sis" Mullis from Atlanta and Martin Mueller from Santiago, Chile. There were people from all walks of life and all parts of the world linked together by a common bond a thirst for learning and the joy of accomplishment." Donna and Norm Burns are looking forward to another summer at Arrowmont. They've found something they can share together and with others ... the Arrowmont Experience. After Donna and Norm were married a few years, she talked him into making a spur-ofthe-minute trip to Gatlinburg to show him where she had spent that first summer after graduation. Norm didn't (and still doesn't) believe that it's ever necessary to make advance reservations for motel accommodations. He hadn't known about Gatlinburg in the summer, especially on a Fourth of July week-end. "Our Our dilemma provided one more reason why we have a soft spot in our hearts for Arrowmont and Miss Heard," Donna said. "After fighting the traffic for several hours and stopping at every motel in town, we finally realized there wasn't a room available anywhere. People already were asleep in their cars everywhere in town. "It was 2 a. m. when we knocked on the door of the staff house and got Marian Heard out of bed. She set up two cots in the dining room of the teachers' cottage and we bedded down until morning when we found motel accommodations for the remainder of the week." Donna's and Norm's Arrowmont experience was sidetracked temporarily after that trip. They were busily bringing up their three children. But they did try, though unsuccessfully, to revisit Gatlinburg and Arrowmont. Then, three years ago a sister Pi Phi, Linda Poorman Behringer, provided the impetus that took both girls to Arrowmont for a two week stay. "My interest didn't wane," Donna added, "and Norm listened to me extol the merits of Arrowmont for three solid years before succumbing to its spell. "I had since returned to teaching art in a local high school, and felt the need for a good refresher course. We could only spend a week this time, so the photography course for me and jewelry making for Norm fit into that schedule, " Donna continued. "I had never used any camera more sophisticated than a Brownie Kodak or Instamatic," she confided, "so I borrowed a 35 millimeter Pi Phi students and a scholarship winner smile at the Conversation Circle. They are (I to r) Dorothy Adams, Texas Alpha; Lisa Drumm, on scholarship from Akron A.C.; Elizabeth Yarbrough, Arkansas Alpha; Donna Burns, Ohio Beta; "Sis" Mullis, South Carolina Alpha. Dr. Burns, in his enthusiasm upon his return home from a week at Arrowmont as a student, "sold"two other couples on taking courses next summer when the Burnses plan to attend again. Attends Conference At White House To recognize the worthwhile efforts of mil-lions of school volunteers, 90 leaders in volunteers-in-education throughout the United States were invited to participate in a conference on School Volunteerism at the White House, Washington, D.C., in September. As director of the ADDitions School Volunteer Program of Orange County (Fla.) public schools and as coordinator of eight southeast-ern states in Region IV of the National School Volunteer Programs, Inc. (NSVP), Eleanor Yothers Fisher, Florida Beta, attended the conference. She served as state NSVP coordinator for the past three years and designed and implemented the ADDitions program now in its sixth year. The program has won the annual Walt Disney $1,000 Award for Community Service in Education twice. Last year 1,643 volunteers, men and women from ages 16 to 91, contributed 65,759 hours in Orange County schools. Eleanor is very active in Orlando civic affairs, as well as in the Orlando-Winter Park Pi Phi Alumnae Club. Last year she was one of six central Florida women chosen as "beautiful activists" by the Germaine Monteil-Burdine's community recognition project, an annual event honoring women in volunteer fields. The Wizard Rushes, Rushees Are Wizzed Last spring, as a group of Washington Gam-ma Pi Phis watched the Wizard of Oz for probably the fifteenth time, out popped the idea of modeling a rush party along that theme. With chapter approval, a large group of creators brainstormed, the end product of which was an innovative and highly successful rush party. The chapter room was decorated with large scenes from the story, and the rushers donned ruffled jumpers and puffed sleeve blouses. Adding to the effect was fanciful makeup consisting of Raggedy Ann-like eyes and bright red circles on the cheeks. While the talk was flowing freely from rusher to rushee, a knock announced the arrival of a visitor Dorothy herself, as she would be today. Due to the comic talent of Judy Beeman, pledge class president for 1975, Dorothy seemed older, but equally magnetic, and hysterically funny. During the course of the skit, more old friends appeared: the Tin Woodman, played by Marla Seese, the Scare-crow, played by Judy Stein, and the Cowardly Lion, played by Betsy Campbell. The rushees made it clear they thoroughly enjoyed themselves, and the members of Washington Gamma were thrilled to call it a success! 6*i; Two Pi Phis from Newton, Kan., attended the national Republication convention in Kansas City last August. Showing off their souvenirs are Sue Harper Ice, Kansas Alpha, an alternate delegate, and Marion Sears Button, Kansas Beta, a delegate. 43 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



