<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr9440009_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Arrowmont the craft school and the cottage industry</title>
                        <author><name>Persche, Mary Alice Barlow </name></author>
                        <author><name>McGee, Amy </name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Summer 1978</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr9440009_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1978</date>, Arrowmont the craft school and the cottage industry</title>
                        <author><name>Persche, Mary Alice Barlow </name></author>
                        <author><name>McGee, Amy </name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 9-13</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">41</note>
                        <note type="Folder">14</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 94, Number 4 (Summer 1978), Pages 9-13.</note>
			<note type="document">arr9440009_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Arrowmont Logo is Simple, Elegant; Arrowcraft Shop Opens Display Gallery; Weaving Family Spans Generations; Quilt is Winner In Magazine Contest; Program Sparks Interest In Arrowmont</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>The Birth of Arrowmont, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1965-1979</item>
                                <item>People</item>
                                <item>Weaving</item>
                                <item>Coverlets</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr9440009_0001" seq="01" n="8-9  "/>
       <p>Jackson Alums Honor Golden Arrows The Jackson (Miss.) Pi Phi alums love their Golden Arrow members and to prove it they held a special meeting honoring the three who had been sisters for fifty years or more. Lighting a candle as she introduced each honoree and presenting them with a long stemmed carnation tied with a silver-blue bow, Kathleen Ward Hirsch conducted a beautiful program relating highlights of the lives and activities of each Golden Pi Phi. Initiated in 1918 by Missouri Gamma, Amelia Ruxton Purser led in seniority. Amelia is a retired school teacher and is active in the First Baptist Church. Running a close second was Marguerite Miller Miesse, who was initiated in 1919 into Kansas Beta. One of the founders of the Jack-son Alumnae Club, Marguerite has a Pi Phi daughter. The "youngster" of the three was Mildred Garber Burster with her 1922 initiation by Illinois Beta-Delta. A retired librarian, Mil by FRANCES CROOKES REBMANN limiamamiusnat [Iss Golden Arrows honored by their Jackson, Miss., Alumnae Club recently are, I-r, Mildred Garber Burster, Marguerite Miller Miesse, and Amelia Buxton Purser. dred also has a second generation Pi Phi. Club president Sybil Marty Cheesman concluded the program by presenting engraved charms as mementos of the evening and especially as tokens of love from the club. "Snow-In" Strengthens Sisterhood Ties by PEGGY MONAGLE, Indiana Delta to help our house mother, Mrs. LeVor, prepare meals. Other sisters pitched in and did K.P. The maids couldn't come in either, so we all shared the work of keeping our house clean. We played cards and backgammon, watched T.V., some prayed together, some played the piano and sang together, we all talked a lot and clowned around together. Some of our braver sisters had fun toboganning at nearby Slater Hill. Sisterly teamwork gradually dug cars out from under huge drifts, resulting in frozen hair and even frozen eyelashes, but a warm friendly spirit of togetherness. Food delivery trucks couldn't get through the snow, but when the cars were freed, girls gladly went shopping for supplies. Feeding 80 girls takes a lot of food! Gradually, West Lafayette dug itself out and things returned to normal. We are glad for the experiences that we shared. We learned more about our fellow Pi Phis, and our sorority sisterhood was greatly enriched and deepened. Indiana Deltas had a unique and enjoyable opportunity to take time out, let their hair down, and enjoy each other's company last winter. A blizzard hit Purdue on the evening of January 25th and didn't quit until it dumped 121/2 inches of badly drifted snow, completely immobilizing the community and closing the university for two days! Governor Bowen termed the blizzard a "disaster," but for the students, the snow-in provided a great four day vacation. Nobody could go anywhere, but we found that we were all in the same boat and made the best of it. When school was cancelled, all of the usual pressures from classes, commitments, and books were lifted, and spirits soared. The bonds of sorority sisterhood were strengthened as we realized we had nobody to lean on but ourselves. But, who could be better? Due to road conditions, neither the cooks nor the waiters could come in, so dietetics majors and amateur gourmet chefs volunteered 8 Edited by MARY ALICE BARLOW PERSCHE Board of Governors Arrowmont's New Logo News of The Great Smoky Mountains Gatlinburg, Tennessee 37738 9 </p>
      <pb ref="arr9440009_0002" seq="02" n="10-11  "/>
       <p>Arrowmont Logo Is Simple, Elegant A simple and elegant symbol is the new Arrowmont School logo created by Designer-Instructor Patrick Bourke. Utilizing the first letter of the school's name, the logo represents the nature of the Arrowmont Experience, which is the sharing of one's skills, one's philosophy; in other words, one's art. Ray Pierotti, Arrowmont Director, states that it also represents the mountains about the school, the high place that learning and education hold in the philosophy and preferred giving of the Pi Phis. The circle in the arm ofthe A represents the center of learning, the circle of the conference table, the gathering together of all peoples, regardless of race and creed. The new logo is being used on letterheads, brochures, signs. Bourke, currently instructor and Chairman of Communications and Humanities, St. Clair Community College, Port Huron, Mich., is on the staff of the 1978 Arrowmont summer session. Arrowcraft Shop Opens Display Gallery There was much excitement this spring at Arrowcraft Shop, Gatlinburg, with the opening of a new exhibition and sales gallery featuring the contemporary works of regional craftspeople. The Arrowcraft Gallery opened March 25 with a multi-media exhibition of wood, pottery, weaving, jewelry, enamels, puppets, and fiber art. Caroline Riddle, Administrator of Arrowmont and Arrowcraft, who established the gallery, has chosen Bette Raymond as its director. Bette, a member of the Southern Highland Handicraft Guild as a vegetable dyer, has taught spinning and dyeing at area workshops and recently has been manager of the Twelve Designer Craftsmen Shop, Pigeon Forge, Tenn. r 7eaving Family Spans Generations Weaving can become a family affair that often spans several generations. It's true particularly in the Wilson family which has had four generations of weavers supplying items for Arrowcraft Shop customers. Ruth Wilson, a 30-year weaver, was pre-ceded by her mother who wove until she was 82 years old. Ruth learned from her brother and sister-in-law. Ruth's daughters, Ruby Whaley and Sue Ogle, add another generation to the weaving clan, and a still younger age group is represented by Connie Cole, Ruby Whaley's daughter, and Tim Wilson, a nephew of Ruby and Sue. For many of the weavers their salary is their livelihood, used to maintain their homes. Each weaver has her own unique skills and specializes in weaving particular products. Some prefer the patterned design while others like the simple design. Weavers own their own looms, but the shop assists them in purchasing if needed. They are issued yarn at Arrowcraft and given a pattern to take home to begin weaving in quantity, but always knowing that quality is the most important because of Arrowcraft's high standard in hand weaving. It takes about six to 12 hours to put the warp on the loom before beginning to weave; usually 80 to 100 yards of warp are put on the loom at once. It is threaded into the loom ac-cording to the design to be woven. After several pieces are woven, the weaver can take them off the loom; they are then ready to sew and press before bringing to Arrowcraft. Tim Wilson (second from left) delivers family-made products to the Arrowcraft Shop along with Alvin and Rodney Shults. Tim weaves coasters; Alvin makes eyeglass cases; Rodney weaves Weftwind mats, and Tim's mother, Eula Wilson, weaves bath mats. Receiving the finished merchandise is Cathy Graves; Nella Hill, Arrowcraft Shop manager and weaving designer, stands by to give out new yarns. Connie Cole obtains yarn from weaving assistant Cathy Graves. Connie weaves Weftwind mats, using 100 yards of warp at a time. Ruby Whaley (above left) makes potholders and fringe napkins after balling a skein of vegetable-dyed yarn. Ruby's mother, Ruth Wilson (above right) winds a bob-bin at the hi wheel before starting to weave bibs, hot mats, potholders, and Whig Rose mats, her specialty. Below Christine Shults and Sue Ogle put on 85 yards of cotton warp for pocket aprons. There are three looms in operation at the Shults' home. </p>
      <pb ref="arr9440009_0003" seq="03" n="12-13  "/>
       <p>Quilt Is Winner New Business Is Result of Challenge Magazine "Necessity is the mother of invention," so the saying goes. And Faye Cook and her sister, Veryl Monhollen, both Arrowcraft staff members, recognized a need when Arrowcraft's catalog listed a number of craft items for sale that the shop was unable to obtain from local craftsmen. Faye challenged Veryl's sons to provide the wooden items. Veryl and her husband, Lee, have three talented and energetic sons Roger, Randell, and Jeff. They also had a large building on their property that formerly had been a chicken house. The building soon was converted into a woodworking shop; a business license was obtained, and a name chosen for the business. So, Middlecreek Crafts came into existence. Lee and sons enrolled in a design class at Arrowmont taught by Mrs. Doris Bartels. The four fledgling craftsmen started supplying Arrowcraft Shop with the items it needed most. Soon their line expanded to include nap-kin rings, cutting boards, wall brackets, and flower plaques. As Middlecreek Crafts became known, orders came from Berea College, Berea, Ky., and the World of Wood Carvers in the Ozarks. The men also were invited to a craftsman's fair in Gatlinburg. Needless to say, the new business is flourishing, and the Monhollens' three sons found that they could no longer devote only evenings to their new avocation. They have left their other employment to spend full time at Middlecreek Crafts. Loyalty to Arrowcraft Shop, which presented the opportunity that launched them into business, has prompted the new craftsmen to process its orders first. They also weave shoulder totes for Arrowcraft when needed. Congratulations to Administrator Caroline Riddle whose beautiful quilted montage depicting Settlement School and the Appalachian crafts was one of 51 winners in a recent Good Housekeeping Great Quilt Contest! A full-page color picture of her detailed quilt and directions for making a similar quilt or wall hanging appeared in the March 1978 issue of Good Housekeeping magazine. The contest, which drew 9,954 entries, was sponsored by Good Housekeeping, the U. S. Historical Society and the Museum of American Folk Art. Winners represented each state and the District of Columbia. Caroline's entry was the Tennessee winner. Many may remember seeing Caroline's quilted montage on display at the Pi Phi convention in Minneapolis, Minn., where it drew much favorable comment. One block represents Arrowmont showing Red Barn, Staff House, Arrowmont School, Arrowcraft Shop, cottages, Little Pigeon River, and the Great Smoky Mountains. Other blocks include a Whig Rose mat woven by Arrowcraft weavers, a braided rug made from her own vegetable dyed wools, and a corn husk doll. There are several pieces made by Nurse Marjorie Chalmers as a gift to Caroline. Also, there is a woven piece by Tina McMorran, an Arrowcraft weaving designer for many years; a square showing a Great Smoky Mountain bear sewn by Helen Lewis, former Grand Council and BOGs member; and a square depicting an iron made by Lela Adams, former Settlement School housemother and now Staff House cook. Pi Phis and others from across the country have written Caroline in recognition of the excellent design and the fine publicity. To Compile Registry A registry of Pi Phis who are practicing craftsmen is being compiled at Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts. The information will be made accessible to gallery owners, museum and educational program directors. To be included, artists /craftsmen should send a resume (including Pi Phi chapter andinitiation date), two 35 mm slides of them-selves at work, and up to five slides showing individual examples of their craft. The slides become the property of Arrowmont Board of Governors. Craftsmen are reminded not to submit the actual samples of their work. The resume and slides should be submitted to the attention of Ray Pierotti, Director, Arrowmont, Box 567, Gatlinburg, Tenn. 37738. 12 Progr Interest In Arrowmont by AmY MCGEE, Alabama Beta As part of an effort to learn more about Pi Phi philanthropies and to foster closer relations with the Tuscaloosa Alumnae Club, Alabama Beta had a joint program with the alums on Arrowmont. The program started with a slide presentation of the Arrowcraft Shop, the Pi Phi Mall, and Arrowmont School itself. Examples of all the different kinds of crafts taught and the varied make-up of Arrowmont students were brought out in the presentation. Featured in the program was an account by Mrs. Melba Hollingsworth, a Tuscaloosa High School art teacher, of her experiences from three summers' work at Arrowmont. Mrs. Hollingsworth praised the faculty at the school as being "the cream of the crop around the world." She told how the teachers were truly interested in their students' work, citing as an example one professor who stayed in the lab from 8:00 a.m. until midnight to give extra help to his students. "Another strong point of Arrowmont is the fact that a beginner can learn from a world-renowned craftsman, along with students who may have studios of their own," Mrs. Hollingsworth said. A greal deal is expected of Arrowmont students, with an average of ten to twelve hours each day being spent working on projects in the labs. But time is found also to enjoy the beauty of the surrounding countryside, as when Mrs. Hollingsworth's ceramic class met at five o'clock one morning to watch a sunrise in the mountains. King Tut R e turns The King Tut fever sweeping the country landed at the California Gamma house and all the girls were caught up in the excitement. Suzie Nora started the interest when she acquired tickets for the whole house to view the Egyptian exhibit, and added a book on the artifacts to the Cal Gamma library. Then Songfest chairman, Nancy Meyer, announced the theme for Cal Gamma's entry in the spring musicale was to be "The Return of King Tut." Songfest awards prizes for the best costuming, best dancing, best music, and overall best entry. L to R: Sid Quarks, President of Alabama Beta, Mrs. Melba Hollingsworth, Beverly Doddridge and Mrs. Elsie Gribbin admire Mrs. Hollingsworth's quilted batik made during her course at Arrowmont. Trackster Trains Hard by SHARON GRAY, Missouri Alpha As a college junior, Lisa Cantwell has more than one career to worry about. Lisa, an energetic young lady from Branson, Mo., is entering her third year as a member of the University of Missouri Women's Track Team. After a successful high school career in which she captured first in both her conference and district division, and was a state competitor in hurdles, the 440 yard dash, and the 880 yard run, Lisa decided to run collegiately. As a returning letterwoman, Lisa again faces the trials of daily practice sessions. In the mornings she runs four miles in addition to the quarter-mile intervals she runs in the after-noon. Her program also entails intensive weight training and strict dieting. This marks her third year as a cross-country runner and her second as a member of the indoor-outdoor track team. This year during indoor track, Lisa concentrated her efforts on the 600 yard dash. During outdoor season, she participated in the half-mile run. Last year Lisa, along with three other girls, qualified fo Nationals in the two-mile relay. Thus far, tl-' has been the highlight of Lisa's affiliation w the M.U. Women's Track Team. 13 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



