<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr9430019_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Arrowmont the craft school and the cottage industry</title>
                        <author><name>Persche, Mary Alice Barber</name></author>
                        <author><name>Goertz, Roxann</name></author>
                        <author><name>Scott, Jean Wirths</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Spring 1978</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr9430019_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1978</date>, Arrowmont the craft school and the cottage industry</title>
                        <author><name>Persche, Mary Alice Barber</name></author>
                        <author><name>Goertz, Roxann</name></author>
                        <author><name>Scott, Jean Wirths</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 19-23</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">41</note>
                        <note type="Folder">14</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 94, Number 3 (Spring 1978), Pages 19-23.</note>
			<note type="document">arr9430019_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Seminar Studies School Future; We Love You, Marian Heard!; Topaz - Another Arrowmont Student; What is Arrowmont?; Workshop Is Scheduled For Interested Alumnae</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>The Birth of Arrowmont, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1965-1979</item>
                                <item>People</item>
                                <item>Summer Craft Workshops</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr9430019_0001" seq="01" n="18-19  "/>
       <p>Music Mayor Works With Osmonds Senior Barbara Lacke, Iowa Gamma, spent a funfilled summer in Hollywood, Calif., and she owes it all to a Pi Phi. Barb is a music composition major at Iowa State University and she spent last summer as assistant music supervisor for the "Donny and Marie" Osmond show. An Iowa Gamma Pi Phi who graduated two years ago had worked as the receptionist for the Osmonds and had become good friends with Tommy Wolf, the music supervisor for the show. She mentioned Barb to him and he asked for Barb's resume and a tape of original compositions. He gave his consent, for Barb to work for him and arrangements were made for her to receive college credit for her work. Barb was in on the first five productions for the current season and she attended production meetings, vocal and instrumental rehearsals, and all recording and taping sessions. Besides re-cataloging their entire sheet music library for the past two seasons, she arranged music and also took music off records and tapes when the sheet music was not available. She says that one of the most beneficial aspects of the experience was that "I had my first real look at the inside makings of a big time production and I learned more in two months than I did last year at school. I learned things that they can't teach you in the class It's in one door and right into another for Barb Locke behind the scenes in Hollywood. room. I now also have a more realistic concept of just how hard it's really going to be when I head out there after graduation." Barb has been very active in campus musical organizations including serving as president of Sigma Alpha Iota and composer and director of an original music score for an educational film now being distributed all over the United States. Barb's entry in the song contest for last summer's Pi Phi national Convention, "And Here We are," won the Best Original Song. This spring she will be music director for Stars Over Veishea, a musical celebrating Veishea '78, the largest student-run campus activity in the nation. ATTENTION ALUMS! HOUSE DIRECTORS NEEDED To help our chapters and their Advisors in hiring House Directors (Housemothers), we are trying to compile a file of prospective employees. If you are interested in being a Pi Phi House Director or know someone who is qualified, please send the following information to Director of Alumnae Advisory Committees: Mrs. E. Clifford Crane 625 Marview Terrace Cincinnati, Ohio 45231 NAME ADDRESS Previous Experience (if any) Fraternity Affiliation (if any) Areas or States in which you would work Additional information will be sent on receipt of this form. 18 Edited by MARY ALICE BARBER PERSCHE Board of Governors Dr. George F. J. Lehner, Temple Terrace, Fla., helps facilitate the flow of ideas during a Development Seminar session in the Arrowmont Library. News of The Great Smoky Mountains Gatlinburg, Tennessee 37738 the craft school the cottage industry 19 </p>
      <pb ref="arr9430019_0002" seq="02" n="20-21  "/>
       <p>Seminar Studies School Future Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts in Gatlinburg was the scene of a Development Seminar last Oct. 24-26. Its purpose dealt with the future what it holds for the craft world, for Arrowmont School, for Arrowcraft Shop, and the entire Settlement School complex. Participants also explored ways in which Pi Beta Phi can most effectively manage its resources and establish short-term as well as long range goals. Grand Council and the Board of Governors felt that many questions pertaining to the future needed answers at this time. It also was felt that assistance in obtaining these answers was needed from outside the Fraternity and from professionals who could lend particular expertise in solving related problems. The participants who were invited to the Seminar came to Gatlinburg and shared with Pi Beta Phi their advice, ideas, opinions, and projections for the future. Represented were experts in craft merchandising, fine arts, problems of the handicapped, conference centers, recreation and year-round camps, land planning and development, as well as the Gatlinburg community. Attending as ex officio participants were officers of the Pi Beta Phi Fraternity, representatives of the Arrowmont Board of Governors, and faculty members from the University of Tennessee. Two and one-half days of intense dialogue and discussion were moderated by Dr. George Lehner. Participants worked in small teams as well as larger groups to examine a variety of topics such as Arrowmont programming and Arrowcraft products. The vast number of suggestions and proposals generated throughout the Seminar will be studied and evaluated by the Board of Governors and used in establishing annual and long range goals. In addition to the many obvious tangible benefits gained from the Seminar, there were numerous intangible ones such as the climate of cooperation and genuine concern which was evidenced throughout the meetings. One participant was heard to say that he now understood what was meant by the expression an Arrowmont experience! In a letter to all the Seminar participants following the conclusion of the meetings, "Sis" Mullis, Chaiftnan of the Board of Governors, aptly expressed her sentiments: "I do not know," she wrote, "that I am capable of putting into words how I felt after all of you left and the Seminar was over. There was a deep feeling of gratitude, knowing how busy you are, that you would take days off from your work to come to Gatlinburg. There was a sense of amazement that such a group of outstanding people in their own fields could come together and in two and one-half days become such a cohesive force . . . the Seminar has been everything we had hoped it would be." Dr. Harry Day, President of the Spring Hill Center in Minnesota, and Tom Bacchefti, Executive Director of the Tennessee Arts Commission, ponder a fine point relative to Settlement School's future planning. Laura Sanborn, owner with her husband of Sanborn Western Camps in Colorado, attended the Seminar. Laura is a Colorado Alpha Pi Phi. 20 Dorothy Farley, Director of Craft Alliance in St. Louis, Mo., attended the Seminar. Robert Wilson from the Graduate School of Planning at the University of Tennessee; J. W. Soloman, Director of the General Services Administration in Washington; and Glenn Whistler, Director of the Gatlinburg Chamber of Commerce. "We Love You, Marian Heard!" by ROXANN GOERTZ, Minnesota Alpha "We love you Marian Heard!" resounded throughout Arrowmont Auditorium as Marian Heard, who was retiring as Director of Arrowmont School, stepped in for her regular weekly assembly with students and faculty one Thursday in July. Each of the over 150 students, faculty, and staff members turned toward her as Marian stood at the back of the room, and they created a sea of Marian Heard faces they wore T-shirts and waved banners, all printed with an image of Ms. Heard. It was a rousing standing ovation. The Arrowmont student assistants and some staff members had, with a great deal of trouble in trying to keep their operation secret, printed the shirts and planned the surprise honoring Ms. Heard. Ms. Heard's name evokes many fond Arrowmont memories, not only among the faculty and staff who have worked very closely with her over the years, but also from Arrowmont students who have returned summer after summer and have enjoyed her spirited leader-ship, dedication, and friendliness. Honoring Ms. Heard at the 1977 National Convention, the numerous other ways she has been recognized as a very special and talented person, as well as Marian Heard T-shirt Day were only small recognitions and thank-yous to a woman who has contributed so much to Arrowmont and to all of the work she has done in many capacities. "We love you Marian Heard!" Dr, Donald Wyckoff, Crafts Organizational consultant, and Rose Resnick, from the California League for the Handicapped. Marian Heard, retiring Director of Arrowmont, with Dr. Lehner, Development Seminar moderator. 21 </p>
      <pb ref="arr9430019_0003" seq="03" n="22-23  "/>
       <p>Topaz Another Arrowmont Student by JEAN WIRTHS SCOTT, Grand Vice President, Philanthropies Topaz is a familiar sight to many of Arrowmont's summer students. He makes his way carefully down the steep rain-soaked steps from student housing, he leads his constant companion through the doors of Arrowmont, up the ramps and into the fiber studio; he lies quietly at her feet as she twines and loops fibers into a beautifully crafted wall hanging; he makes his way across the path and into Staff House for the three meals served there each day. Topaz is a Golden Retriever Guide Dog. His companion and friend is Martha Cowden from Dayton, Ohio. The summer of 1977 was the third year for Topaz as an Arrowmont "student." It was the sixth year for Martha. Martha has watched the growth of Arrowmont since 1972 in the early years as a sighted student and, for the last three years, through the eyes of Topaz. Martha's training in crafts began at Arrowmont. She had first attended Western College in Oxford, Ohio. Gatlinburg was an area familiar to the Cowden family as they summered each year at a family home in the Great Smokey Mountains. Martha says, "It's the atmosphere and friendly quality of the surroundings and people that bring me back each year." She has the highest praise for the caliber of instructors who are attracted by Arrowmont to teach there each summer. Because of her interest in both spinning and weaving, Martha attended three sessions in 1976 and two sessions in 1977. She'll be back this summer. With new techniques learned and with the perfection of her own skills, Martha has gone from Arrowmont to teach crafts to other blind students as a volunteer for Good Will Industries. Last fall, she joined a craft co-op in suburban Dayton. There she gives both her time in management and her own crafted objects for display and sale at a new shop located in a warehouse compound of artists' shops. Martha's ability as a fine craftsman was recognized last summer when two of her pieces in macrame were chosen from juried slides for the National Exhibit of Art by the Blind in Philadelphia. Martha was one of 39 Martha Cowden, Topaz's companion and friend. craftsmen chosen who represented 14 states and her work was selected from over 300 entries. More than 60,000 people viewed the show. The hours of learning and working put in each day by Arrowmont summer students are long, tedious and often grueling. For the dedicated student, the studio rarely closes before midnight. One of Martha's class projects was an intricately twined wall hanging in variegated tones of blue and grey carefully knotted and looped to give a three dimensional shape. Enough of a challenge for the most dedicated student! But Martha's interest went beyond the classroom projects and secretly at night after the studio was closed, she and Topaz sat in her room using other newly perfected techniques to form a coiled basket as a surprise for her instructor. Martha's instructor, Edward Lambert, an instructor at The University of Georgia and a producing craftsman from Athens, praised Martha's ability. "She is an inspiration to all of the students both beginner and advanced. " Was it difficult for Topaz to become acclimated at Arrowmont? Martha's answer was quickly, "No." Martha already knew her way around the Arrowmont campus and buildings (Continued next page) 22 What Arrowmont? Have you ever considered a retreat at Arrowmont in the Great Smoky Mountains? Pi Phi chapters, alumnae clubs, and outside groups have chosen Arrowmont and the Red Barn as a favorite place for retreat in the fall, winter, and spring months. Last March, 20 members of South Carolina Alpha enjoyed themselves at Arrowmont. Reminiscing about her weekend, Phyllis Smith wrote: " 'Arrowmont.' Visions of yearly projects fill the mind; scenes of hard work and hard earnings sent to a complex somewhere in the Great Smoky Mountains. There's more to it we at South Carolina Alpha can testify in Arrowmont' s behalf. "What is Arrowmont? Arrowmont is much more than simply a few buildings nestled in the heart of Gatlinburg, Tenn. Arrowmont is a state of mind no Pi Phi should miss experiencing. "Arrowmont is driving for hours and arriving at a group of buildings that somehow already seem familiar, and suddenly realizing Workshop Is Scheduled For Interested Alumnae The Arrowmont Board of Governors is offering Arrowcraft chairmen and other interested Pi Phi alumnae an opportunity to learn first-hand about Arrowcraft and Arrowmont. A workshop is scheduled for Tuesday, May 2, to Friday, May 5, at Arrowmont, Gatlinburg, Tenn. There will be workshops on ordering, pricing, displaying and the promotion of Arrowcraft; on the use of Arrowmont facilities, and the history of Settlement School. There will be tours of the facilities, the craftsmen's studios and homes as well as weaving demonstrations. Accommodations will be in the Red Barn and the cottages. Each participant will pay $55 for room and board plus the cost of her transportation. Judy Dawson, WIDE TRAVEL, 917 Lloyd Center, Portland, Ore. 97232, is handling reservations.why yes, we've seen the pictures. Yet, this is heritage; this is the child of years of work in what must have initially seemed unyielding mountain ways and ever slothful progress. This is a part of us and we are a part of it. This is the product of a collective effort which has endured the struggle and brought a market to craftsmen, a school to children and inspiration to all who enter its grounds. "Arrowmont is touring the crafts school and feeling your soul respond to the aura of creative initiative which dwells within it; watching the panorama of artistic endeavor unfold before the picture screen of your mind; sensing the hopes and the accomplishments of people from all spheres of the world combined in one complete and self-reliant whole; be-coming aware of the importance of learning and teaching, of the communion of giving and taking and seeing it exhibited in the attitudes of those around you. "Arrowmont is climbing a mountain at sunrise and returning at sunset, the owner of a strange sense of something akin to awe, of something akin to humility, of something latticed with strands of aspiration and en-twined with strings of imagination. It is reveling totally in the rugged mountain terrain the same mountains that greeted the founders of Arrowmont and of Settlement School who carried their dreams into the Gatlinburg valley community years ago. -Today, we are a part of it, and we are proud to help make it possible." Topaz . . (Continued from preceding page) from her days as a sighted student and it was she who taught Topaz the ways of a student. Now Topaz is the expert as he guides his friend from dorm to class to meals and back again to class. The "in" attire for 1977 students was specially designed T-shirts bearing either the Arrowmont letters or a likeness of Director Marian Heard. Not to be outdone by others, Topaz walked the halls of Arrowmont on the last day of classes sporting his own T-shirt (a gift from the students) with the large stylized ARROWMONT letters across the back. There was a slight look of embarassment on his face to be so attired but pride shown on the faces of all others who readily accepted Topaz as "just another Arrowmont student." 23 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



