<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr9220027_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News of Arrowmont the Craft Schol and Arrowcraft the Cottage Industry</title>
                        <author><name>Lehner, Elanor Bushnell</name></author>
                        <author><name>Mahone, Melinda </name></author>
                        <author><name>Senner, Geraldine DeBenedetti</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Winter 1975</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr9220027_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1975</date>, News of Arrowmont the Craft Schol and Arrowcraft the Cottage Industry</title>
                        <author><name>Lehner, Elanor Bushnell</name></author>
                        <author><name>Mahone, Melinda </name></author>
                        <author><name>Senner, Geraldine DeBenedetti</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 27-34</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">41</note>
                        <note type="Folder">12</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 92, Number 2 (Winter 1975), Pages 27-34.</note>
			<note type="document">arr9220027_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Arrowmont Hosts International Symposium; Meet Mary Helen-New Board of Governors' Chairman; It Doesn't Matter If You Feel Uncertain; Or If You Know Exactly What You Want; We Offer You A Peek Behind The Curtain; AT ARROWMONT; Hawaii No Ka Oi or Win With Arrowcraft</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>The Birth of Arrowmont, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1965-1979</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>
                                <item>Administrators</item>
                                <item>People</item>
                                <item>Sales</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr9220027_0001" seq="01" n="26-27  "/>
       <p>New Editor Handles Alum Club Letters An active Pi Beta Phi alumna with a degree in journalism those were two of the qualifications that caught the eye when a new Alumna= Club Letter Editor was needed for The ARROW. Holding those qualifications, and many more, was Lindsey Farn ham Siegfried of Terrace Park, Ohio. Lindsey grew up in Cincinnati, at-tended Northwestern University, and was graduated from Ohio State University in 1960. She pledged Pi Phi at Ohio State, following in the footsteps of her mother, Dorothy Russell Farnham, and two aunts, Helen Russell Mitchell and Mary Russell Dye. She received her BA in journalism from Ohio State, and spent the next two years traveling as a market research investigator for Procter and Gamble. She was then hired by that company as a staff assistant in the advertising department. The company was also responsible for husband, John, since they met while both were traveling for P. and G. The Siegfried household is definitely male oriented, since there are now three sons Gregg, 11 , Brett, 9, and Kevin, 6. Even the dog, a schnoodle (schnauzer-poodle) named Pepper, is male! Lindsey has been active in the Cincinnati Alumnae Club for ten years, serving in a number of offices, including president. She was chairman of the club's first Ladies' Domino Tournament which she learned about at the San Antonio Convention. They are now planning their fourth tourney. Currently Lindsey is chairman of the Decorators' Show House, the major Junior League fund raiser in Cincinnati. In addition to her ARROW job, she is a member of the Pi Phi Alumni Committee for Continuing Education. In her spare time, Lindsey has a catering business with .a friend a niece of Amy B. Onken. They fix gourmet luncheons, brunches, dinner parties, etc., and have fed everyone "from pro football players to Gloria Vanderbilt." But that's another story ! News of The Great Smoky Mountains Gatlinburg, Tennessee 37738 Iowa Gammas found a way to remember each others' major fields and to have fun doing it. Last spring each came to dinner dressed in an outfit representing her major. Shrewd businesswomen, television directors, fashion designers, and many others dined and laughed at the inspired idea. Pictured are Anne Huene, Roxanne Beale, Nora Schroeder, Marcia Eckert, Carla Boots, Amy Becker, Mary Lynn Meyer. Group Advances In Cultural Department by PATrI KING, California Eta The Pi Phis of California Eta have missed out, for the past year and a half, on the educational and cultural enrichment area of mental advancement. So, to make up for lost time, two cultural activities were planned during the summer in order to get off to a good start in the fall. We began our "pre"-cultural experience at the Dorothy Chandler Pavilion in the Los Angeles Music Center. About thirteen of us were thoroughly delighted with Nanette Fa-bray's performance in the musical comedy "Wonderful Town." Our next excursion took us to the Holly-wood Bowl Special bus. The evening started out on the right foot (?) when the V.P. Mental, who was in charge of the tickets, realized that she had left them in the trunk of the car back in Long Beach. However, with a little convincing (and a glance through group ticket sale files) we managed to enter the Bowl with plenty of time left to enjoy our picnic dinners (the thing to bring to the Bowl). The program consisted of two choral master-pieces, one by Bach and one by Faure. The evening ended happily although we must admit we preferred the food and good conversation to the performance. Edited by ELEANOR BUSHN Bo A student-designed silk-screen print portrays the motto featured in the 1975 Arrowmont coi which foreshadowed the second U.S. International Ceramic Symposium, he!d at Arrowmont fr September 16, 1975. Here Marian Heard and Caroline Riddle, Arrowmont Director and Adrr it as a banner. a d c7 n a bond be desn the pellet of the r 1 art 4 the craftsman a d be x5.wn the peoples of the w Its ~i %am maroon isa bond b+,ha psopla :.;x,. "Ite art af the cry',: r s a bond be we the Jeuplaa a 'the weriL Ire art the craftsman is a bond haiween # pimple oph w ril + the a-aft:mer is al-and. hsb.esm the rupee ter* le art of the craftsman Ma band be wean the polies of is endand 27 26 </p>
      <pb ref="arr9220027_0002" seq="02" n="28-29  "/>
       <p>. """" .".... .... ceramic artists from Australia, nada, Hungary, Nigeria, the and Wales arrived at Arrowmont 1975, to spend a month together hteen tons of day into original ,n was the second International ^osium to be held in the United )jective, as expressed by Arrow-) Director Sandra Blain, was to me and a physical setting for Efferent backgrounds to observe, cork, to verbalize, and to discuss of communication." auspices of the International 2eramics with support from the national Ceramic Symposiums, the ntly sponsored by the National Endowment for the Arts, Arrowmont, and. the Tennessee Arts Commission. In honor of the occasion Tennessee Governor Ray Blanton declared the months of August and September International Ceramic Months in his state. Greetings arrived from President Gerald Ford and from Ms. Nancy Hanks, Chairman of the National Endowment for the Arts. On behalf of Arrowmont the visiting craftsmen were welcomed by Administrator Caroline Riddle and by Ms. Blain, who served as I.C.S. Coordinator and as Arrowmont representative to the symposium. Councilman Earl Ogle and Mrs. Glen Bullock represented Gatlinburg and the Tennessee Arts Commission, respectively, in greeting the visitors. Until September 15 the participants remained in seclusion, sharing ideas, opinions and orientations as they explored new materials, techniques and concepts. Working side by side, they expressed their individual responses through the medium of clay, transforming it into a variety of distinctive creations some decorative, some utilitarian. In the words of Kurt Spurey, Austrian potter and Director of I.C.S., Each one did his throwing, shaping, casting, designing, rejecting or elaborating, glazing and firing. The basic idea can, perhaps, be best expressed in the form of a paradox: very individualistic togetherness. Working side by side turns into working together. Friendly discussions go on during the entire creative process. What an interplay! Opinions are clashing, new orientations are emerging, and most important communion breaks through isolation." This intensive period of creative activity culminated in a special exhibit of art works which opened with an invitational preview and banquet on September 15 and remained on display in the Arrowmont Gallery through November 10, after which time some items were selected for permanent collections and others for traveling shows by Arts Commission officials. Oldrich Asenbryl, who was born in Czechoslovakia and now lives in Wales, is shown as he throws the body for a porcelain tea pot. The decorative pots from his production studio reflect a departure from the traditional concept of an English tea pot. Pmont Hosts International uium THE WHITE HOUSE WASIIINOTON Vail, Colorado August 13, 1975 Mrs. Ford and I take great pleasure in welcoming all who attend the Second U.S. International Ceramic Symposium. Bringing together ceramic artists from all over the world, this event gives public recognition to ceramic art while at the same time strengthening international friendship and goodwill. We welcome this opportunity to applaud the talented exhibitors and to salute the organizers of the Symposium for their important contribution to the advancement of one of the oldest, most creative and useful art forms in the world. ,*h4l eir/11 28 Carmen Dionyse of Belgium has won many awards for her sculptural works which represent human forms, usually heads with partial bodies and simplified features. Through shape, surface quality, and subtle co!ora-Con her dynamic figures reflect a quality of mystery. Here she is using a paddle to modify a shape. But, according to Lewis Snyder, President of the U.S. I.C.S., aside from the works created, "For the delegates, the true values are the thoughts, ideas, and developments from this experience, the attitudes and opinions fostered by observing, the information, techniques, materials, and processes discovered among participants. Attitudes and developments are hastened by the catalyst of the Symposium itself. This is what the Symposium is really about." (A member of the Symposium Planning Committee, Mr. Snyder is also Director of Crafts for the TAG.) Participants, selected on the basis of their professional backgrounds, their contributions to the ceramic arts, and their willingness to communicate and to be receptive to new ideas and disciplines, were as follows: AUSTRALIA Joan Campbell, Perth, member Australia Council (for the Arts). Best known for large, sculptural forms, her work is represented in major exhibitions and viewed in many publications. BELGIUM Carmen Dionyse, Gent, professor of art at "PHICO," Hasselt Superior Institute of Fine Art and at "KASK," the Royal Academy of Fine Art. Recipient of many prestigious international awards. CANADA Victor Brosz, professor of ceramics and department chairman at the Univer</p>
      <pb ref="arr9220027_0003" seq="03" n="30-31  "/>
       <p>Marc Hansen, a Western Michigan University professor of art, is widely known for his use of crystalline glazes on fine porcelain traditional bottle forms. Here he is trimming a bottle which will be glazed and then fired in a controlled oxidizing atmosphere. When finished, crystals of 'varying sizes and colors will appear to be floating on the glazed surface. sity of Calgary, Alberta. Helped to organize the 1974 Calgary International Exhibition. Represented in many international shows. HUNGARY Sandor Horvath, designer for a ceramic tile factory. NIGERIA Abasiya Ahuwan, Zaria, N.C.S., instructor at Ahmadu Bello University. By showing that Western-educated craftsmen make pots in primitive ways, he hopes to en-courage Nigerian potters who feel threatened by increasing technology. WALES Oldrich Asenbryl, originally from Czechoslovakia and trained as a plaster mold maker in a factory. Operates a production pottery studio. UNITED STATES Sandra Blain, assistant professor of ceramics, University of Tennessee, Joan Campbell of Australia constructs monumental cube and ovoid forms which emphasize subtle textural variations. She utilizes a very porous stoneware clay body which she scrapes and pierces to achieve a unique surface quality. Here she works on a large slab construction which will be raku fired in a kiln built around it. Knoxville, and Assistant Director of Arrowmont. Member Symposium Planning Commit-tee. Joe Bova, assistant professor of ceramics, Louisiana State University, Baton Rouge. Member Symposium Planning Committee. Michael Cohen, production potter, Amherst, Massachusetts. James Darrow, assistant professor of ceramics, University of Tennessee, Knoxville and member Symposium Planning Committee. Marc Hansen, professor of art, Western Michigan University, Kalamazoo. Robert Winokur, instructor at Tyler School of Art, Temple University, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. Additional members of the Planning Committee were Susan Peterson, Hunter College, New York and Cynthia Bringle, Penland School of Crafts, Penland, North Carolina. Two new designs were winners in the Arrowcraft Design competition. A bright Christmas hanging features mini-Santas and tiny bells on a stylized tree. The colors-red, green, and white, of course. The Bridge Party set, right, woven of linen and cotton, consists of a covered score rcrd and numbers for each table. Meet Mary Helen- New Board of Governors' Chairman by MELINDA MAHONE, B4O.G. The annual Arrowmont Board of Governors meeting in Gatlinburg each October brings excitement, hard work, and new faces. The Board consists of thirteen Pi Phis scattered through-out the United States. Beginning in October, Mary Helen Holliday became chairman of the Arrowmont Board of Governors, to serve for the next two years. Mary Helen, Texas Alpha, received her A Fashion Note . Arrowcraft shared the spotlight on Arrowmont Night at Convention. As one of the trio of featured speakers, Sarah Ruth ("Sis") Mullis, Board of Governors Co-Chairman, wore a hostess skirt especially woven for the occasion. The pink border on the white skirt featured a design adapted from the diamond pattern which Arrowcraft weavers have used for years on table mats and tote bags. This skirt was in the designing process for about six weeks. Handwoven skirts can be ordered from the Arrowcraft Shop in a variety of designs and color combinations. B.A. and M.A. from the University of Texas and after teaching high school English for two years, married Jim Holliday. While living in Texas, Mary Helen continued her interest in Pi Phi by being a member of the Dallas Alumnx Club. She and Jim also began raising their family three daughters. In 1954, the Hollidays moved to Jackson, Miss. Mary Helen wasted little time getting involved in Pi Phi work. The Jackson Alumnae Club was soon rechartered and Mary Helen served in various offices in the club, including the presidency. For several years she was the Mississippi State Recommendations Chairman. She also served as secretary of the Mississippi Beta House Corporation and was fortunate to have a fine assistant in her husband who was instrumental in planning and building the new chapter house. After living sixteen years in Mississippi, Jim and Mary Helen were transferred back to Dallas. One year later, 1971, Mary Helen be-came Pi North Alumnae Province President. That fall an officers' workshop was held in Gatlinburg and the lady from the southwest fell in love with Arrowmont and the mountains of the southeast. A few months later Jim and Mary Helen were transferred again, this time to California. One year after her first visit to Gatlinburg, Mary Helen returned to visit the school she loved Arrowmont----as a member of its Board of Governors. In 1973 Mary Helen was elected secretary of the Board and served in that capacity until the present. The Holliday family is all grown up now. Jim and Mary Helen are proud grandparents of three grandsons and one granddaughter. Mary Helen continues to work hard for Pi Phi. She is an active member of the San Mateo (Calif.) Alumnae Club. Her husband loves Pi Phi also, and has been a tremendous asset to Mary Helen and the Fraternity. The Arrowmont Board of Governors is in-deed proud to have Mary Helen Holliday as its new chairman. 31 11 </p>
      <pb ref="arr9220027_0004" seq="04" n="32-33  "/>
       <p>32 It Doesn't Matter if You Feel Uncertain Among Pi Phi collegians who enrolled at Arrowmont for 1975 summer courses were Beth Brower, Ohio Epsilon; Nancy Spangler, Ohio Zeta; Jean Helfrich, Ohio Epsilon; Marti Gilbert, Michigan Alpha; Cissy West, Tennessee Delta; Anna Osborne, Louisiana Beta; and Barbara Crawford, Oklahoma Beta, who worked as a student assistant for five weeks. We Offer You a Peek Behind The Curtain Students on the firing line waiting to consign their creations to the kiln. 1975 Ceramics courses were taught by Charles Counts, B.A., M.F.A.; James S. Darrow, B.S., M.S., Ed.D.; Hal Riegger, B.S., M.A.; and Ann Van Aken, B.S., M.S. 33 Or If You Know Exactly What You Want Joan Peterson, Mill Valley, Calif. (on scholarship from Morin County Alumnce Club); Patricia Wright, Novata, Calif.; and Debra Sapp, Illinois Iota (on scholarship from Mu Province North) reaping a harvest of colored yarn in their vegetable dyeing class . . . taught by Mary Frances Davidson. AT ARROWMONT "But what a thrill that skill will bring!"-as reflected on the faces of staff and scholars. (Back row) Patricia Spencer, Virginia Alpha scholarship recipient; Connie Cassani, Alspaugh scholarship recipient; Pam Sullivan, Houston Alumnce Club scholarship recipient; and Susan Lechner, Brendell scholarship recipient. (Front row) Caroline Riddle, Arrowmont Administrator; Helen Lewis, Board of Governors member; David Webber, Colorado Springs Alumnae Club scholarship recipient; Marian Heard, Arrowmont Director; Helen Russell, Arrowmont Librarian. </p>
      <pb ref="arr9220027_0005" seq="05" n="34-35  "/>
       <p>iNoKaOi v To Win krrowcraft ys at Convention in Miami and Arrowcraft and Arrowmont in m on a Pi Phi high. While on vel, I'd like to share the Hawaii :oming from nothing to every-years of hard work and belief [ropy. I have a story I read to ,t]. Millions of Cats in which a cat and because there are s, thousands of cats, millions of lot choose and so they take e each is prettier than the next. eel about Pi Phi purses. If you ou can sell Arrowcraft. the basic and true premise that uality, you need not apologize nd that its durability and hand-.e something you can sell with that your belief that Arrow-riot philanthropy and that you igh to support it. Now you're nd sell millions of cats. aft chairperson must believe in ae must be willing to carry a all times, preferably using all senior tote for work, a junior a shoulder bag for sports aini for evening. Use no other use Pi Phi coasters, hot pads, in her home and believe that asion gift is Arrowcraft. g possible to order economically someone is ordering for a gift cess, offer to mail direct from i the customer paying the post-bill comes, charge your price of ostage, and you've made a sale own price list. Type and make e of your own prices with your none number at the top. Raise he traffic will allow. We're here , not to give away Arrowcraft. Lrket and price accordingly. If it stores sell good pot holders Gerry Senner, Honolulu A.C. displays her club's well-earned award for being first in the nation for Arrow-craft gross sales, 1974-75. for $1, charge $1 for Pi Phi potholders. Ours are just as good, if not better. Keep a box of samples in your car, and if anyone asks, "what's in the box ?," show them. Having an item on hand means a quick sale. At least be able to show all four sizes of the purses and some representative colors. When you get checks from customers, write down the ae dress from the check to start a mailing list. Satisfied customers will brag to their friends. When you have a sale, display your items imaginatively. Set your dining table with mats, napkins, napkin rings, coasters, and hot pads. Use your own china and sterling to create a smashing impression. Be agreeable. If someone wants a black bag with purple knots, order it for them. After visiting the Arrowcraft shop and talking to our beautiful Faye and Nella and Ruby, we now understand what "warp" means. As long as the colors are available, if the warp is set up with the basic color, you can plug in any normally stocked color or knot. Satisfy your customers. If they want a long place mat, just ask Arrowcraft to make one. We recently ordered a Daisy mat 100 inches long to go down the center of a long table. The customer doesn't care what it costs, she's getting exactly what she wants. She'll have to wait, but you'll have that satisfied customer. Remember, "they" is you. Four years agowe wondered why they didn't make a coaster. So we asked and last year they sold 17,000 Hawaiian coasters. How about asking they to name something after your club? From now on Arrowcraft is the gift for out-going presidents (junk those silver trays give a revival bag), pledges, new initiates, for Panhellenic auctions, and Christmas bazaars. Create a Pi Phi Purse for a drawing at your meetings. Ours is a wine and blue junior tote. Inside is a roll of drawing tickets and a surprise gift. For 10 each or 3 for 25 you buy tickets and drop the stub in the tote with the money. At the end of the meeting draw the winning ticket. The lucky member gets the surprise gift, the Pi Phi purse to hold 'til the next meeting, and must replace the gift. The money goes to the treasury. If you regularly donate to a Christmas bazaar, make this year's contribution "Mrs. Santa's Purse." Take a red junior tote, fill with some tissue and on top place two green potholders, six red and white coasters, a white hot pad, and a cookbook. It makes an attractive, artistic donation for ally bazaar. Our Panhellenic has a meeting each fall when every alumnae club may bring its fund raising projects to show and tell. Take Arrow-craft. If your Panhellenic doesn't do this type of thing, suggest it, and get to that fantastic group of sorority women who will appreciate Arrowcraft. The most cost saving item of all DO NOT MAIL ANYTHING BACK. You are only paying postage twice and you don't have to sell it all before summer or before changing chair-persons. Keep it and have,an early sale at some-body's September bridge club to generate Christmas orders. If you end up with a real loser, hang in there it will sell eventually, or you can always put it in the Pi Phi Purse for a door prize. Create your own miracles. Aloha. Recipe Is Winner Jill Shiner Hayward of the Philadelphia Main Line Alumni Club picked up an extra $25 last spring when she submitted a winning recipe to the Pantry Planner, publication of a grocery chain. The recipe for Reuben Casserole appears on page 56 of the Arrowmont Cook-book. Jill submitted her recipe to the Consumer Panel and it was selected as a winner. ONE DEBENEDETTI SENNER Honolulu A.G. 34 Watch For Pi Phis In Old Williamsburg by SARA LEWIS, Virginia Gamma Last summer, if you vacationed in historic Colonial Williamsburg or visited the Old Country at Busch Gardens that just opened this year, you may have been greeted by a Virginia Gamma Pi Phi ! Because of the many employment opportunities offered by these two corporations, many of the Pi Phis at William and Mary found that it would be profitable to spend their summer in Williamsburg. In Colonial Williamsburg, Pi Phis Diane Hanretty and Sara Lewis worked as interpreters in 18th century shops along Duke of Gloucester Street in the restored area. In Busch Gardens Pi Phis Sandy Jeter, Melissa Locke, Pam Cutler, Vanessa Popa, Nancy Tienken, Sue Shank, Sue Hanna, and alum Sarah Talis worked at every kind of job from toy store clerk and bank teller to monorail and roller coaster operators. Every-one agrees it was a fun summer, especially those instances when another Pi Phi was discovered. One day at Busch Gardens, a Virginia Gamma met a lady who was a Golden Arrow Pi Phi, as she was boarding the "Eagle One" monorail. In Colonial Williamsburg, a Virginia Gamma noticed a Pi Phi ring that a visitor wore, as she was looking at the display of hand crafted silver. It makes Pi Phi take on more of a national meaning when you meet someone you've never seen before, from across the United States, who shares that same Pi Phi "specialness." Many Virginia Gammas have already decided to stay in Williamsburg again next summer. So if you're traveling our way keep a sharp eye out for the details that tell you who's a Pi Phi. Virginia Gammas will be looking for you too. Diane Hanretty and Sara Lewis enjoy their summer jobs in historic Williamsburg. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



