<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr9040019_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News of Arrowmont the Craft School and Arrocraft the Cottage Industry</title>
                        <author><name>Lehner, Elanor Bushnell</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Summer 1974</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr9040019_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1974</date>, News of Arrowmont the Craft School and Arrocraft the Cottage Industry</title>
                        <author><name>Lehner, Elanor Bushnell</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 19-23</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">41</note>
                        <note type="Folder">10</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 90, Number 4 (Summer 1974), Pages 19-23.</note>
			<note type="document">arr9040019_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Community Workshop Has Enrollment of Forty; Potters Market Thru Arrowcraft; Sandy's Ceramics Earn Many Awards; Luncheon At Arrowmont</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>The Birth of Arrowmont, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1965-1979</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>
                                <item>Community programs</item>
                                <item>Arts</item>
                                <item>Administrators</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr9040019_0001" seq="01" n="18-19  "/>
       <p>"Okie" Earns St te's Highest Honors Frances Rosser Brown, Oklahoma Alpha, is the recipient of the two highest awards obtainable in the state of Oklahoma. Last May she was recognized by the University of Oklahoma when she was selected to receive the Distinguished Service Citation. This is the highest honor awarded by the University which does not give honorary degrees. Mrs. Brown was inducted into the Oklahoma Hall of Fame during Oklahoma Heritage week last November. These honors came in recognition of her "unselfish and unceasing efforts in behalf of her community and state." In speaking of her, one friend said, "She is a modest, original, indomitable woman, semi-invalid for the greater part of her life, widely known both inside and outside of Oklahoma, who for the most part makes headlines for others. "A volunteer publicist, she has helped to establish two hospitals in Muskogee and her stories have sparked all manner of community projects for which she has received recognition from her church, from the Elks, the Kiwanis and Sereptomist service clubs, and from Delta Kappa Gamma and the Da-ce-tah Indian Club, the latter three organizations awarding her honorary membership." A concrete accomplishment has been the fulfillment of her dream that a museum be created which would motivate the gifted Indians of the Choctaw, Chickasaw, Cherokee, Creek,and Seminole Tribes. In the original Indian Agency Building, on Honor Heights overlooking the City of Muskogee, is now housed the heritage and hopes of those people in "The Five Civilized Tribes Museum." On the day of the opening of the Museum, April 16, 1966, the famed wood sculptor, Willard Stone, presented his "Two Seasons" to the Museum in her honor. The Jerome Tiger painting "The Trail of Tears," which hangs in the Museum, bears the inscription "Presented in honor of Frances Rosser Brown in recognition of her dedication to community causes including the restoration and opening of this Museum." Besides the Distinguished Service Award for her role in establishing the Five Civilized Tribes Museum, Mrs. Brown holds a Certificate of Merit for her role in keeping the Thomas Gilcrease Institute of American History and Art in Oklahoma. The Frances Rosser Brown Silver Pitcher Award is presented by Pi Beta Phi to honor the Fraternity's former national historian. One observation has been made that this distinguished Pi Phi colors her exemplary life with wit as well as with dedication and wisdom. This trait was even recognized in her high school days. The year of her graduation from the Muskogee Central High School the following comment appeared under her name in the school annual yearbook: "When Minerva stomps her foot The bravest writhe and wriggle But, Holy Mackerel You ought to hear her giggle !" Just recently an author gave her one of his works. In the book he wrote in part "Frances Rosser Brown, Companion in Mirth." Serves Internship Marty Blakely, former treasurer of Indiana Beta, was chosen from among students at the Indiana University School of Business to serve one semester on an internship in Dallas, Texas. She spent a busy four months as an assistant buyer for Sanger-Harris, a Dallas department store. 18 Edited by ELEANOR BUSHNELL LEHNER Board of Governors the craft school the cottage indL The Great Smoky Mountains Gatlinburg, Tennessee 37738 In the Arrowmont Pottery Workshop, renowned British ceramic artist, Michael Cardew, instructs a class. 19 </p>
      <pb ref="arr9040019_0002" seq="02" n="20-21  "/>
       <p>In the Arrowmont Jewelry Studio, Huntley Hilliard from Baltimore, Md., acquires a new skill. Ed Cook, left, and Wayne Deveney were instructors for the community workshop this spring. Daily Beacon photo.) Community Work shop Has Enrollment of Forty For the first time in some years, but in keeping with the early Settlement School concept of serving the Gatlinburg area, a work-shop for the community was started February 4, to run for 10 consecutive Monday evenings at Arrowmont. Instructors for the course are two young graduate students in the Department of Crafts and Interior Design, College of Home Economics, at the University of Tennessee. Wayne Deveney, from Conover, N.C., received his B.F.A. degree from Western Carolina University and has received first place awards in weaving and textile design at the Annual Crafts and Interior Design Exhibition at the University of Tennessee. Ed Cook, of Racine, Wisc., has B.A. and M.S. degrees. He has received first place in textiles at Mount Mary College in Milwaukee in 1969 and first place in show at St. Francis College in 1967. Both young men expect to continue their study of textiles in Europe after graduation. An enthusiastic group of forty women and one man are learning tie-dye, tie-bleach, batik, quilting, stitchery, applique, wrapping, twining, and looping. Students pay for their own materials and a minimal tuition charge. They work at their own pace; most are beginners, some are experienced craftsmen. Among the students are the Arrowmont Administrator, the ex-Administrator, three Arrowmont office girls, and Faye Cook and Vicki Ownby from the Arrowcraft Shop. SAVE COUPON A program to purchase greatly needed potters' wheels and looms for Arrowmont, through the General Mills coupon plan, is being launched by the Board of Governors. Since the price of a wheel is between $400-450, and a loom costs approximately $200-300, many thousands of coupons will be needed. These coupons are found on packages of General Mills products, and Pi Phis and their friends are urged to cut out and save as many as possible during the summer months. In September, after counting the coupons and noting the number, they should be given to your club's Arrowmont chairman. If there is no club in the area, coupons may be sent directly to Mrs. W. R. Kendall, 4053 O'Grady, Corpus Christi, Tex., 78413, the board member who will co-ordinate this drive. Ask friends and relatives to help in this effortless way to further equip the ceramic and weaving studios at Arrowmont. The September "round-up" of coupons will be followed by another in January. raj b 20 Potters Market hru Arrowcraft Bill and Sue Ashley, natives of the Chattanooga area, have both turned to potting as a way of life and the Arrowcraft Shop in Gatlinburg is one of the marketers of their fine work. Bill, after a tour of duty in the Marine Corps, graduated with a B.A. in Fine Arts from the University of Chattanooga in 1965. Following graduation he spent time working on a shrimp boat in the Florida Keys. Later he became a member of the Merchant Marines, shipping from the West Coast to Vietnam. After returning to Chattanooga, he taught arts and crafts in the Hamilton County schools for five years, during which time he also coached football and wrestling. During the summers he taught at the Chattanooga Art Institute and studied pottery under Charles Counts, at his studio in Rising Fawn, Ga. In June, 1973, Bill left his teaching career behind in order to become a full time potter. Sue graduated from the University of Chattanooga with a B.S. in elementary education in 1968. As a freshman she became a member of Pi Beta Phi and at various times served as music and program chairman in her chapter. Following graduation she taught second grade Bill and Sue Ashley, Chattanooga potters. for five years. During this time she continued study in the field of psychology at the University of Tennessee at Chattanooga, traveled in Europe, and studied pottery under Charles Counts. Both Bill and Sue are now working full time from their home on Missionary Ridge, where they rent an older home and have converted an out-building into a studio. Their work is sold mainly through craft shops in the sur-. rounding area and occasionally from their home studio. They enter a small number of craft shows but are known principally as producing craftsmen right now. Both seem to feel that the satisfaction and independence gained from the potter's way of life make the long hours and hard work worth-while. Their aim is to produce sound, functional pottery that others will enjoy using. ANNOUNCING AN 4rowcra/t ~e~i v~ Award For Handwoven Articles Entry Deadline January 1975 Three Cash Prizes For Information Write atfin ur ann. 37738 ..Arrowcra/t Shop /9. O. /3ox56 7 .21 </p>
      <pb ref="arr9040019_0003" seq="03" n="22-23  "/>
       <p>Sandy's Ceramics Earn Many Awards Every Pi Phi, as well as the other individuals who have attended Arrowmont, knows and ad-mires Sandra L. Blain, Assistant Director of Arrowmont from 1968 to present. Sandra is also Assistant Professor of Crafts and Interior Design in the College of Home Economics of the University of Tennessee. Prior to coming on the staff at Arrowmont, she was a student at Arrowmont for several months. Sandra has received many awards for her pottery. This year at the Fifth Biennial Tennessee Arts and Crafts Association Exhibit in Memphis, Tenn., her ceramics were judged "Best In Show." Her listing of exhibitions is long and impressive, spanning a period from 1964 to present. In the past year she has had several one man shows. "Just Pots" was the title of an exhibition by Sandra at the Drummer Gallery, Knoxville, Tenn, The exhibit included over 100 handbuilt pieces, each with a suggestion of the primitive. Subtle color combinations with glazed and unglazed surfaces and strong textural contrasts emphasized the seemingly ancient origin of the pieces. Pinch, coil, and slab methods of construction were used in creating the sculptural, but utilitarian, forms. In speaking of her work, Sandra explains, "As a potter, I began using the wheel thrown technique of construction for almost all of my pieces, but I soon got tired of the overall sameness and general emphasis on technically proficient saleable items. My desire for simple, straightforward, earthy forms led me to the use of handbuilt construction techniques. I was thus able to manipulate the material in a free and spontaneous manner still realizing my ob-jective of creating sculptural, but utilitarian, functional pots." Another one man show, "Pots for Plants" by Sandra, was exhibited at Ridgeway Gallery, Oak Ridge, Tenn., April 20 to May 25, 1974. Some of her pottery is always on exhibit in the Exhibit Gallery at Arrowmont or in the display cases on the Pi Phi Mall. Sandra has published an environmental multi-media slide series which is a work of art. This series is available on a rental basis from Arrowmont. Her honors have been many, including: chairman of education committee, Southern Highland Handicraft Guild, 1973-74; president, East Tennessee Craft Guild, 1972-75; Tennessee representative to American Crafts-man's Council, 1971-72-73-74; Crafts Advisory Panel, Tennessee Arts Commission 1972-73-74. Pi Phi is indeed fortunate to have such a talented master craftsman as assistant director of Arrowmont. Such perfect teamwork talent between Director Marian G. Heard and Assist-ant Director Sandra L. Blain would be difficult to duplicate. Sandra L. Blain, Assistant Director, Arrowmont Bartlett Jones, San Rafael, Calif., attended Arrowmont on a scholarship awarded by the Marin County Alumnae Club. Here he uses the facilities of the new wood-working studio. Meeting with the Arrowmont Board of Governors recently were prominent Gatlinburg citizens, I. to r., Mayor Bill Mills; W. F. Moehlmann, a member of the Great Smoky Mountain Conservation Association; Bill Postlewaite, owner of The Mountain Press; Helen Deppe Volimar, BOG chairman; Dr. David Ray, president of Rotary Club; Hubert Bebb, prize-winning architect of Arrowmont School. LUNCHEON AT ARROWMONT Other prominent guests were, I. to r., O. J. Matti!, officer of the Southern Highland Guild; O. T. Collett, vice president of Kiwanis; Miss Bernice Stevens, master craftsman with Twelve Designer Craftsman's Shop; Charles Simms, Exalted Ruler of Elks; Wade King, Southern Highland Handicraft Guild; Caroline Mills Riddle, Administrator of Arrowmont and Arrowcraft. 23 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



