<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr9220089_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Lewis, Helen Anderson</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Winter 1975</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr9220089_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1975</date>, Little Pigeon</title>
                        <author><name>Lewis, Helen Anderson</name></author>
                        <extent>Page 88</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">41</note>
                        <note type="Folder">12</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 92, Number 2 (Winter 1975), Page 88.</note>
			<note type="document">arr9220089_0000</note>


	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>The Birth of Arrowmont, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1965-1979</item>
                                <item>People</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft shop</item>
                                <item>Funding</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr9220089_0001" seq="01" n="88-89  "/>
       <p>ay was the climax of our year. Teze Rion charge of it this year and both the actives yed a lovely afternoon. BETH HICICOX DAUWALDER TENNESSEE LITTLE PIGEON ?igeon Alumnw Club started the year on a :h the news that once again we had received i good year book. Also in the good news de-ranked first in the highest commissions per in magazine sales. pported the three Pi Beta Phi philanthropies Ltional memorial contributions to Arrowmont; nt in quite a number of Betty Crocker coupons. atribute to the Sevier County Christmas Fund, my chapter of the AFS, and give an award Tennessee Gamma sophomore who has made provement in grades. in the club showed an increase this year. however, two members have moved away, id to enter the Sevier County Nursing Home. located in Gatlinburg, the site of the Arrow-: do not sell Arrowcraft products. Our one project of the year is our Bridge Marathon sed of two age groups, with the majority being our annual party for the participants was held Library of Arrowmont School of Crafts. our meetings during the year were the visit Province President, Georgia Walker Seagren aid the entertaining of guests at our December lso were privileged to have a program done oman from Gatlinburg who attended Arrowous summer, and a talk by the AFS student ho attended Sevier County High School while amily in Sevierville. ject of the year was arranging for the puborie Ohls Chalmers' book, Better I Stay. This en many years ago and it tells of Marjorie's he nurse at the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School. to have been able to have this book published ,ailable to all Pi Phis through the Arrowcraft we were saddened to learn of the death of Prince, former Director of the Pi Beta Phi col. The Little Pigeon Club set up a Marion 1 Fund within the Arrowmont Memorial Fund, will be used in a suitable way at the school to the contributions made through years of i by a dedicated member of the fraternity. Day was celebrated with a luncheon at Staff i by, a program in the auditorium at Arrow-e privileged to view the new slide program available to clubs and chapters in the coming e fifty-eight alums and actives from Knoxville h our club members that day, making a total 'his present for this occasion. ling to a good year came with the announce-le Pigeon received honorable mention as an was most gratifying to know that even a very as ours, has the opportunity to receive nain. Our members are most appreciative of this HELEN ANDERSON LEWIS MEMPHIS of the Memphis Alumnae Club of Pi Beta we described by the slogan "More in 74."-more and better fellowship and fun; more oney (even during this period of economic ur annual Playday was held in August at the McNaughton Welch with a renewal of Pi after the long, lazy days of summer. The y only served to inspire alums to work ever h information cards going to chapters in all untry. The fervor of our work was relieved ire of a social afternoon of swimming and coffee for new alumnae in the Memphis area ^tember at the home of Pat McAnespie Speltz. rously baked delicious cookies for the rush ssee Delta at M.S.U. came the very successful "Arrow Fair" led Green and held at her home. From the guest the past several years, invitations were mailed omers of Arrowcraft items and new friends of alumnae dressed up in "Mountain Dresses" made by Mae Kellar Weiss, a Golden Arrow ei THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI Pi Phi. Our alumnae club made a profit of over seven hundred dollars from this project. In November the alumnae displayed their culinary skills and prepared their favorite and most delicious dishes in honor of the MSU Pledges. This potluck dinner was held at the home of Beth Gifford Fuller. After introductions were made by pledges and alumnae, a social hour was enjoyed by all. Especially enjoyable was the group's singing of old and new Pi Phi songs which concluded the evening of fun and fellow-ship. The Christmas spirit fell upon Memphis Alumnae in Mid-December, when we celebrated the holiday season with our husbands and dates at our traditional Christmas buffet. This formal affair was held at the beautifully decorated home of Sally Henson Hergenrader. The Memphis Alumnae Club met at the home of Marilyn Skaggs Adams in January for a delicious potluck luncheon meeting. Georgia Walker Seagren, our Alumnae Province President, was our special guest and speaker. Beverly Stewart Fourmy hosted the March evening meeting at which new club officers were elected. Ellen Payne of Vanderbilt was selected by the group to be the recipient of the Sophomore Award in Iota Province. Founders' Day was celebrated by Memphis Pi Phis with a luncheon at Chickasaw Country Club. Four members were honored as Golden Arrow Pi Phi's. Freda Stafford Schuyler, Grand Vice President of Collegians, presented a question and answer program about Pi Beta Phi. The Memphis Alumnae participated in the City's Panhellenic Theatre Party in May. The year's activities concluded with a picnic in May for members and husbands at the home of Emily Manchester Townes. After a social hour, everyone enjoyed delicious box lunches. NASHVILLE The Nashville Alumnae Club experienced a rewarding and productive year under the excellent leadership of our president, Ann Glenn Hayes. We began our year with the annual rush meeting in the fall, followed by an "end of summer" get-together at Mary Powell's lake home. Husbands were invited for a sunny day full of friendship, water sports, and a pot-luck dinner. In October we held our membership coffee. After new alumnae were introduced and welcomed, activities for the coming year were presented and a delicious lunch was served in the garden room. "Christmas Village" was the center of attraction in our November meeting. The chairmen of this year's Christmas Village, encouraged us to give our time, energy, ideas and enthusiasm for making Christmas Village the best ever. Its success allowed us to increase this year's contribution for Arrowmont to $1,300.00. These funds were used for the purchase of permanent jewelry kits that girls from year to year will be able to use. In February to rouse everyone from a long cold winter, we hosted a pre-basketball cocktail buffet for husbands and actives at the chapter house. All of us had a great time meeting the actives and seeing the colorful decorative improvements the chapter had added to the house. April witnessed our Founders' Day picnic at "Hibbitage" (which is a replica of Andrew Jackson's home, "The Hermitage"). The weather being accommodating, everyone enjoyed the evening's entertainment and remembrances by the active chapter. All of us left thinking of our own Founders' Day celebrations and recognizing the challenges awaiting each graduating Tennessee Beta. We were happily surprised when our alumnae club was selected one of ten civic organizations making an outstanding voluntary contribution to the betterment of community life in Nashville. Ann Marie McNamara was chosen our "Beautiful Activist," as she has worked in almost every capacity for our club. This honor for Ann and the entire alumnae club will encourage us to work even harder next year. KATHERINE BETO OLIVER TEXAS AMARILLO The Amarillo alums have been busy again this year with many wine and blue activities for both actives and alumnae. Although we are not as large as some of our neghbors in Pi North Province, Amarillo has some 65 active Pi Phis who quietly but diligently work to spread the love and friendship of the arrow. Through alumnae efforts, Amarillo now has some 18 girls enjoying active Pi Phi membership at six different universities, and we look forward to another Pi Phi rush year. Perhaps the highlight of our alumnae year was the annual party for our actives and pledges in January. This year we had a lovely and scrumptious "South of the Border" THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI luncheon in the home of our club president, Frances Schneider Bauman. All actives, pledges, and their mothers were invited and were honored with wine and blue corsages. After a delightful Pi Phi sing-along, we were treated to the tastiest Mexican food ever found in Texas. Amarilloans really know how to cook southwestern style ! The Amarillo Alumnae Club is especially proud this year of its Arrowmont Award for outstanding achievement in financial support of the Arrowmont School of Crafts. Three years ago we pledged five hundred dollars to Arrowmont and raised the money through various alumnae projects, such as a sherry party, a garage sale, and last year's tasting tea. The tea was called Angels, Arrowmont, and Ambrosia and was done with a little different twist to the typical tasting tea. Twelve different recipes were chosen from the Arrowmont Cookbook, ranging from Wine and Blue Cheese Balls to Brownie Pie to use as tasting dishes, with "extras" sold separately. Then, in addition to selling a complete range of Arrowmont crafts, we also sold many Arrowmont Cookbooks, containing the luscious recipes just sampled. What an easy way to sell a cookbook ! Amarillo's Pi Phi angels look forward to another successful year in "Tall in Texas" country! SALLY MANNING MANNING BRAZOS VALLEY The Brazos Valley Alumnae Club consisting of Bryan-College Station Pi Phis and commuting members from nearby towns began the new year with a coffee and a review of Pi Phi terminology which proved fun as well as educational. In October a member of the Houston Alumnae Club spoke to our group concerning current trends of sororities on college campuses; a subject which we discussed further at the following meeting. January brought much excitement as our annual Panhellenic luncheon was turned into a recycled rush party. Pi Phi participated in the program with an Arrow skit and a rousing chorus of "Ring-Ching." Our biggest turnout of the year occurred when a local artist, Mrs. Eleanor Gates, displayed her macrame designs, and discussed the purposes and pro-grams of the Brazos Valley Art League. Founders' Day was celebrated with our traditional bring-a-salad luncheon and an appropriate dessert of Arrow cake. As of mid-winter, national sororities have arrived in the Texas AM University community. This has added a new dimension to the alumnae clubs in the Brazos Valley and a boost to our City Panhellenic. What an effect this has had on the enthusiasm of our local alumnae ! Already we're in the planning stages for next year, hoping to bring Arrowmont products to the local art festivals, and thereby promoting the name of Pi Beta Phi in the community. We are looking forward to new activities, continued friendships and working together to further the goals of Pi Beta Phi. JEANNIE MITCHIM HANSON CORPUS CHRISTI Corpus Christi Alumna: Club began the 1974-75 season under the leadership of Ann Scott Denton with a luncheon at the Corpus Christi Town Club. It was a thrill for all to see two of our loyal members receive Golden Arrows, and it was exciting to learn from the rush chairman of our new pledges. In October a garage sale involved our complete member-ship, and was most successful. With the proceeds, we gave a Corpus Christi art teacher a scholarship to attend Arrowmont for a summer session, and we also contributed to a local service project. Men's Night was well attended with a covered dish sup-per in November. Province President Charlie Cox Cantrell's interesting words inspired and gicouraged our members at cooky-shine in February. Later in the year Mary Jean Fowler of Houston visited us at our Founders' Day luncheon. She told us the news from Arrowmont and gave a very beautiful slide presentation. Mary Harral Crawford, president for 1975-76 attended the Pi Beta Phi 50th Biennial Convention in Miami. Her report was a helpful boost for the coming year. HOUSTON The Houston Alumnae club of Pi Beta Phi enjoyed a very busy and productive year under the capable leadership of Ann Hill Painter. Twenty-five girls pledged Pi Phi at the University of Texas, T.C.U., S.M.U., L.S.U., Duke, and Vanderbilt Universities. Shirley Doan Shockley was chairman of two Ways and Means projects. The Holiday in Spain was enjoyed by Pi 89 Phis and their friends in November. Elena Brineman was the tour guide and a check for $400.00 was presented to the club for its projects. In March, a Creative Workshop was held at the Con-temporary Arts Museum for two days. Outstanding instructors taught original design Needlepoint, Needle Weaving, Creative Stitchery, and Basketry. Profits were donated locally to the Art After School Program for two classes at the Contemporary Arts Museum. Pam Sullivan was chosen to receive the Arrowmont Scholar-ship. She has volunteered weekly to assist in teaching the blind and senior citizens. Once a month, Pi Phis serve lunch-eon and visit with the senior citizens at Helena House. The Pi Beta Phi Craft Shop moved into its new location in the Woodlake Shopping Mall with the assistance of Charlie Cox Cantrell, our Province President, and her enthusiastic committee. A wine and cheese party was given and a successful sale benefited Arrowmont. Interesting programs were given at each meeting. Carol Vance, our District Attorney, and a Pi Phi husband, was our first speaker. The juniors and seniors combined their meetings to hear a Pi Phi editor of the Houston Post editorial page, review the history of Houston. Don Stewart exhibited and spoke on creative jewelry. Dr. Roy Sessions lectured on the pros and cons of Cosmetic Surgery. A Holiday Brunch honored the new pledges, actives, and their mothers. Something new was tried this year a Mon-mouth Duo with the Kappas on Valentine's Day. Founders' Day was celebrated with a luncheon at the River Oaks Country CIub. Six new Golden Arrow members were honored and presented Carnation pins. Each gave a little speech on what Pi Phi had meant to them. The juniors entertained with a clever skit. Charlie Cox Cantrell, Pi South Province President, gave the highlights of Pi Phi activities at the final meeting of the year. The gavel was turned over to Susan Winton Clevenger and the new officers for 1975-76 were installed. JEANNE RICHEY AMACKER LUBBOCK The Lubbock Alumnae Club has had a rewarding year sharing fun and friendship with the active chapter, the pledge class and the Mothers' Club. Our alum-pledge Big. Sister program continues to be very successful. Besides keeping the alumnae in contact with the pledges, this program helps the pledges realize how Pi Beta Phi can continue to be rewarding after college graduation. In October we learned the name of our special pledge at the little sister arty. At the Christmas party each pledge received a sack of special food to help her through final exams. The Mothers' Club has been very special to both the alumnae and the chapter. The three groups joined together for a spaghetti supper in August and for Founders' Day in April. The alumnae invited the Mothers' Club to a salad luncheon in February. Throughout the year the Mothers' Club has provided food for rush, pledge day, initiation and a Christmas party. As a graduation gift, the Mothers' Club took the seniors to a dinner theater. The active chapter received one hundred dollars from these special mothers. We look forward to next year when we again share our friendship with the chapter and the Mothers' Club. KAREN KLINGER STRIPLING RICHARDSON The 1974-75 season was an especially enjoyable one for the Richardson Alumni Club, under the able direction of BShidlettyerThomascarriedHaynesthout.eOurthem programs, planned by Womt navenes , Pat " W learned more about consumerism, the Arts in Dallas, and fitting and sewing our own slacks. We had a cooky-shine, prepared by Loydell Nash Seward at one meeting, with each of us telling of our own chapters' cooky-shines. This brought back many memories for all of us. Our Province President, Mary Jane Johnson, visited us in February and we met with a representative of the Mid-Cities Club. We also participated in the annual Panhellenic Style Show and Luncheon with our own Nancy Benko Gamble serving as one of the models. Jane Gabe Miller was in charge of our fund raising project which netted $768.82 for the club. It was a Bazaar and Arrowcraft Sale in November, held in the lovely home of Carolyn Kowalik Holland. Each Wednesday for two months prior to the sale, we had workshop sessions in Carolyn's home, where we not only worked on different projects for the sale, but had fun, and really got to know each other well. In January, we had our third annual Actives Party. This is a salad luncheon, this year held at Cindy Free Frey's beautiful home, for all local Richardson actives and their mothers. This is held before the girls go back to school </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



