<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr9120021_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News of Arromont the Craft School and Arrowcraft the Cottage Industry</title>
                        <author><name>Lehner, Elanor Bushnell</name></author>
                        <author><name>Heard, Marian G. </name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Winter 1974</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr9120021_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1974</date>, News of Arromont the Craft School and Arrowcraft the Cottage Industry</title>
                        <author><name>Lehner, Elanor Bushnell</name></author>
                        <author><name>Heard, Marian G. </name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 21-26, 44</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">41</note>
                        <note type="Folder">11</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 91, Number 2 (Winter 1974), Pages 21-26, 44.</note>
			<note type="document">arr9120021_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">The Summer of '74-In Retrospect; Salt Kiln Is Popular; The Arrowmont Dream; </note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>The Birth of Arrowmont, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1965-1979</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>
                                <item>Administrators</item>
                                <item>Facilities</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr9120021_0001" seq="01" n="20-21  "/>
       <p>Lucinda Griffith Burrows, Kansas Alpha, left, and California Eta actives, Laura Schnaidt and Suzanne Scheidt, present a special citation to Mrs. Ruth Plumb Brewster, honoring her 100th birthday, and her 81 years as a Pi Phi. Ruth Brewster Honored On Birthday by LUCINDA GRIFFITH BURROWS Ruth Ellen Plumb Brewster, a resident of Laguna Beach, Calif., since 1957, was 100 years old July 18 of this year. The newly founded California Eta chapter at the University of California at Irvine, and the three Orange County alumn2e clubs honored Mrs. Brewster by presenting her with a specially prepared salute. She was initiated into Kansas Alpha in 1893 as their 130th member, and continued her affiliation with the Fraternity while attending Stanford University. Mrs. Brewster was born in Emporia, Kansas, on July 18, 1874. She is the daughter of the late Senator Preston B. Plumb, one of the founders of Emporia, who was also instrumental in the establishment of Kansas as a state. Her mother was Carrie Southwick of Ashtabula, Ohio. She was married to Schuyler Colfax Brewster in Emporia in 1901 and moved to South Pasadena, Calif., in 1908. Mrs. Brewster moved to Laguna Beach in 1957 to be near her only daughter and son-in-law. Mrs. Brewster's great grand niece, Laura Wheldon Brown, Arizona Beta, received spe-cial chapter recognition last Founders' Day when she received the Diamond Pin Award, chosen by the alumnx as the most outstanding junior. As a sophomore Laura was chosen by the senior class as the girl who most nearly typifies the ideals of Pi Phi. On May 6, 1974, two members of California Eta, Laura Schnaidt and Suzanne Scheidt, accompanied by Lucinda Griffith Bur-rows, a Golden Arrow member of Kansas Alpha, called on Mrs. Brewster at her home to present her with the salutation signed by 112 Pi Phis, recognizing her 81 years as a member of Pi Beta Phi and honoring her 100th birthday. It read: "We, the members of the Orange County Alumnae Clubs and the California Eta Chap-ter of Pi Beta Phi, send to you RUTH PLUMB BREWSTER a member of the Kansas Alpha Chapter, our Pi Phi love on your hundredth birthday." (Continued on page 43) 20 Edited by ELEANOR BUSHNELL LEHNER Board of Governors Attending Arrowmont July 8-14 were, from the left, Susan Ogle, Lakeview, Ore., Oregon Beta; .Elinor Jensen, Ft, Lauderdale, Fla., New York Alpha; Ken Collins, scholarship recipient from Nancy Black Wallace Alumnae Club, Salem, Ore., studying Advanced Fiber Techniques; and Virginia Barker, Ft. Lauderdale, Fla., New York Alpha. News of The Great Smoky Mountains Gatlinburg, Tennessee 37738 21 </p>
      <pb ref="arr9120021_0002" seq="02" n="22-23  "/>
       <p>T H E SUMMER of '74 . ... In Retrospect The number of students attending Arrowmont classes topped 1000 for the very first time. One thousand and forty-three, to be exact. Their ages ranged from seventeen to seventy-five. They came from forty states and two foreign countries. The ten states not represented were Alaska, 'Colorado, Delaware, Hawaii, North Dakota, Rhode Island, Utah, Vermont, and Wyoming. Some of those places are a long way from Gatlinburg. But in all of them there may be Pi Phis or would-be scholarship students who would love to spend a craft-study vacation at Arrowmont. Let's try to find them and have all fifty of our states represented next summer. The largest number of students, 258, came, of course, from Tennessee. But there were 73 from Ohio and 52 each from Georgia and Illinois. Florida sent 96. 53 came from North Carolina, 40 from Maryland, 37 from Virginia, 32 from Indiana, 29 from Michigan, 35 from Texas, 20 from New York, and 23 all the way from Wisconsin. Washington, Oregon, and California sent three, ten, and eight respectively. The District of Columbia was represented by three students. Many of the students were professional craftsmen and teachers themselves, who felt that at Arrowmont they could learn to improve their already considerable skills. But working alongside them in the studios were other students to whom crafts are merely a delightful hobby. Some were attorneys, architects, physicians, or economists. Others were librarians, nurses, or secretaries. One was a postal clerk. Another was a travel agent. A band director, a choir director, a florist, a book store manager, a film-maker, a beautician, a motel manager, a meat clerk, a housing counselor . . . these were among the many professions rep-resented. Seventy-two students classified them-selves as housewives; 115 as teachers; 85 as art teachers; 190 as students; and 13 as graduate students. Arrowmont, it would seem, enjoys universal appeal. Included among the students were 22 Pi Phis and 19 recipients of club or chapter scholarships. The Gatlinburg Rotary Club pro-vided two scholarships, as did the Foothills Craft Guild. According to Sarah Holmes Hunt, Grand Vice President of Philanthropies, a gratifying increase in, alumni contributions enabled the Arrowmont Board of Governors to budget for essentials. These included lights for the parking lot, air conditioning for Staff House, carpeting for cold office floors, and a power paint sprayer for maintenance. Caroline Mills Riddle, the new Arrowmont Administrator, whose responsibilities include making sure that students are comfortably housed and fed, was delightful with the much needed new dishwasher, which "performed al-most without a hitch." She reports that the kitchen staff "melded into a fine group of women, several of whom have asked to come back next summer. The food has been superb." Additional equipment acquired included two looms, a Shimpo electric potters wheel, a spinning wheel, and two re-conditioned type-writers. Pottery students were delighted with two new kilns one built last summer by the kiln-building class plus a salt kiln built in March at one of the workshops. (Director Marian Heard and Assistant Director Sandy Blain contributed the salt kiln, described in a separate column.) Some primitive kilns were built behind the Red Barn by Hal Riegger's class. Marian Heard, Director, and Caroline Riddle, Administrator, steered Arrowmont through its fifth season of summer workshops. 22 Six craftsmen from Nigeria paid a visit to the school. Two of them have decided to en-roll at the University of Tennessee. One will be working toward a master's degree in ceramics. The other will major in textiles. Kirsti Rantanen, a Professor at the School of Industrial Design in Helsinki, Finland, joined the Arrowmont staff from July 29 to August 1 as a textile design instructor, adding a delightful foreign touch to the campus. The book store, operated for the second summer by Paul Rossetter, was, according to Marian Heard, a "great success." Mr. Rossetter invested the necessary funds, worked count-less hours, and then gave the profits to Arrowmont. "How lucky can we be!" exclaimed Director Heard. "He even got one of the senior editors of Van Nostrand-Reinhold and the southeastern service manager to be with us for two days. I believe two or three boks may materialize from our staff as a result of their being here." Miss Heard had praise also for the service staff, all of whom felt themselves to be a part of the total team and gave of their best in whatever capacity they served. She commended the public relations skills of Jan Bailey and Babette Gerhart in the front office, who dealt diplomatically with whatever problems arose. Helen Deppe Vollmar, Chairman of the Arrowmont Board of Governors, has announced the clubs and chapters that contributed the most to Arrowmont and/or purchased the largest vohime of Arrowcraft items. She commented that in reading the letters from chapters for the May Keller Award she found much greater enthusiasm about Arrowmont than was noted in previous years. Montana Alpha and Illinois Eta tied for first place (Grand Council provided two prizes) and Georgia Alpha won honorable mention. Other club and chapter winners were announced in the Information Issue of The ARRow (Fall, 1974). SCHOLARSHIP STUDENTS, JUNE 10721, 1974. Annie Mae Jeu, sent by Houston Alumnae Club; Barbara Blevens, frOm the Monterey Peninsula A.C.; Nancy Rankin, Champaign-Urbana Club; Valerie Miller, Charnpaign-Urbana Club; Virginia Land, Reno A.C.; Gail Gilbert, Buffalo A.C.; Linda Wilson, from the Spokane A.C. Virginia is a Nevada Alpha, Valerie and Nancy are from Illinois Zeta. Marian Heard, Director, and Sandy Blain, Assistant Di-rector, stand beside the new salt kiln which they donated to Arrowmont. Salt Kiln Is Popular Suggestion sheets from 1973 pottery students at Arrowmont repeatedly requested a salt kiln. So arrangements were made for one to be built during the Tennessee Craft Work-shop which the Tennessee Arts Commission held on the Arrowmont campus last March. Lewis D. Snyder, Director of Crafts for the Commission, and William F. Rummel, Crafts Training Coordinator; built it with their students. It proved to be an exceedingly popular addition. The entire student body watched with excitement whenever it was to be opened after a firing. According to Clay and Glazes for the Potter by Daniel Rhodes, salt glazing is "accomplished entirely in the firing process. The ware is put in the kiln raw and taken out glazed. Bisque firing and glaze application are eliminated." The process was discovered by German potters in the 15th century and has been popular in Germany ever since. The German drinking stein is a familiar example. </p>
      <pb ref="arr9120021_0003" seq="03" n="24-25  "/>
       <p>SCHOLARSHIP STUDENTS, June 24-July 5, 1974. Emadene Travers, Mu North Scholarship; Larry A. Beukers, San Mateo A.C. Scholarship; Sonya Anne Benfer, San Francisco A.C.; Katherine W. Watts, Baton Rouge A.C.; Susan DeLong, Tennessee Gamma, Student Assistant. Emadene is an Illinois Epsilon Pi Phi. SCHOLARSHIP RECIPIENTS, July 22-26, 1974. Debbie Rose, Ohio Zeta from Fairfield, Conn., taking Jewelry, sent by her chapter; Sherrie Phillips, from Arlington, Tex., sent by the Mid-Cities A.C., taking Craft Media; Elinor Thornberry, Houston, Tex., sent by the Houston A.C., taking weaving at Arrowmont. Katherine Dallenback of the Champaign-Urbana Alumna:: Club admires the brooms crafted by Elmer and Larry Kear which are popular with Arrowcraft customers. 24 THE ARROWMONT DREAM "The gull sees farthest who flies highest." The day is crystal clear. No fog. No smog. No rain. Every ridge, every valley, every lake, every river is a spot of beauty. Our height blots out those things that might detract from the visual beauty. I am reminded of the day in 1964 when Lura Odland and I were returning from the Pi Beta Phi Convention at Victoria where the Fraternity voted to invest its centennial funds in enlargement of the craft program. What a wise and far-reaching decision that was. So well do I remember that trip aglow with visions of an enlarged program. Today I see again that great mosaic of sights that make up our country our farm-lands, cities, mountains, rivers, deserts. How could anyone not react to this visual feast? Far below me, stretching out as far as the eye can see, is a giant water system big and important only because of the hundreds of small rivers and streams that feed it. Then I think of . . . Arrowmont and its influence which reaches out across our country to the big cities to the small towns to the remote villages. Arrowmont, holding out its arms in welcome not just to the accomplished craftsman but even to the rank be-ginner.. . . Arrowmont, reaching out and seeking to be of service to all ... to the teachers who work with all ages, from the very young to the young in spirit . . . to those involved in re-habilitation, be it mental or physical . . . to those seeking leisure involvement, whether scheduled or enforced . . to those searching for a way of life as a craftsman. . . . Arrowmont, nourishing the tiny streams that feed the mainstream . . . shouldering the bur-den of one week sessions for those who can (ED. NOTE: This article is a condensation of a letter written to the Arrowmont Board of Governors during a flight from Knoxville to San Francisco, where Miss Heard attended the Conference of the Handweaver's Guild of America.) by MARIAN G. HEARD Director of Arrowmont not afford to invest more time or money . . . transmitting the spacious, beautiful magic of its great craft complex to all, regardless of their aesthetic sensitivity. . . . Arrowmont, ever widening its reputation as an excellent, structured craft school which provides superior instruction by well known, established experts who not only know how to teach but also like to teach to share with others their creative spirit, their technical knowledge, their standards, their individual philosophies. . . Arrowmont, offering college accreditation to those who desire it through affiliation with the University of Tennessee College of Home Economics which, through its Department of Crafts and Interior Design, has an excellent reputation in craft education and whose staff and graduates are in leadership positions in many branches of the craft movement. And now . . . our plane is crossing a great desert. In the distance I can see a small village made possible by man's knowledge and efforts, regardless of the harshness of the environment. Then I think of . . . the Pi Phis who came as pioneers to Gatlinburg when it was still a remote settlement in the foothills of the Smoky Mountains and who contributed so much in the areas of education, health, and industry. And I think also of the Pi Phis of today who still retain that pioneer spirit, with all systems targeted toward making significant contributions to the craft movement. If only I could write beautifully! If only I could speak effectively! If only I could convey to you who have such an important part in the growth of Arrowmont the contributions our school is making and can make. And now . . . we are flying past a great dam whose waters, when released, can alter the desert. Then I think of Arrowmont, which will soon be dammed up, closed, after ten great weeks . . to remain dormant for a nine-month period punctuated only by an occasional workshop of visiting craftsmen . . . until another summer arrives to bring it to life again. And so . . my thoughts are many as the earth and the years slip by. So little time re 25 </p>
      <pb ref="arr9120021_0004" seq="04" n="26-27  "/>
       <p>26 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI mains for realizing my dream of being a part of the extension of Arrowmont. I do know that some day it will come to pass. I have already seen many parts of the dream come true. But for one who hopes to see it all the delay is devastating. However, as my plane approaches San Francisco, and the conference I will soon be attending, I do have the satisfaction of know-ing that the famous craftsmen I plan to con-tact and invite to join our staff next year will be well aware of the reputation we have established, both at the University and at Arrowmont. And I can remember with pleasure all of the former instructors (many of whom re-turn to us year after year) who have opened up for hundreds of students a new door, leading to the happiness of a creative life. PI PHIS AT ARROWMONT, July 22-26, 1974. Front: Helen Lewis, Kenhicky Alpha, member of Board of Governors; Jan Scantlebury, Virginia Gamma, from Nashville; Virginia Hardy, New York Delta, from Hanover, N.H.; Nancy Crull, Michigan Alpha, Louisville, Ky.; Marian Heard, Director of Arrowmont; Tena Steinman, Oregon Gamma, Student Assistant. Back: Barbara Hopper, North Carolina Beta, from Naperville, III.; Caroline Riddle, Administrator; Milo Pearmine, Oregon Beta, from Gervais, Ore. Attending Arro,wmont August 5-16, 1974, were Pat Suttles, Atlanta, Ga., Georgia Alpha; Emile Pearce, Fayetteville, Ark., Arkansas Alpha; Margaret Modavis, Plain-field, N.J., a scholarship recipient from the Northern New Jersey A.C.; Patsy Light, San Antonio, Tex., Texas Beta; and Tena Steinman, Oregon Gamma, Astoria, Oregon. Patricia Wright, Novato, Calif., scholarship recipient from the Morin A.C., is not pictured. "Become Involved" Advises Activist (EDITOR'S NOTE: The major portion of this article was written by Lori Lieber, public in formation assistant at Simpson College, Indianola, Iowa. The article appeared in the Simpson Alumnus.) You could call her an international ambassador for the welfare of country women. You could say she was a women's libber before it was fashionable. You might add that she's been an advisor to presidents, prime ministers, and kings. Ruth Buxton Sayre, Iowa Beta, Acworth and Indianola, Ia., has been all of those things at some time in her 78 years. But probably the most fitting description of all for this vivacious and articulate lady with the white hair and infectious smile is that she's "just plain folks," always eager to lend a hand to her neighbor. However, Mrs. Sayre's neighbors haven't been limited to those next door or down the road a piece they live in Europe, Australia, Africa, Asia, Latin America, and Canada. "Most of the people in the world are still engaged in agriculture . . . in most cases a peasant agriculture," Mrs. Sayre said. "Trying to get rural women organized in other countries to help them improve their standard of living" through education was the aim of her international work, Mrs. Sayre explained. She served six years as president of the Associated Country Women of the World and traveled extensively, talking to her fellow country people and meeting with government officials to push for implementation of educational programs that could help primitive and rural societies adjust to today's rapidly changing world. "I guess you'd say I'm an activist," Mrs. Sayre confided. "When something needs doing, I just do it, not just talk about it." Mrs. Sayre's dedication to education began early in life. She attended Simpson at a time when a college education was the exception rather than the rule. Today she remains a concerned and active member of Simpson's Board of Trustees. Mrs. Sayre's pioneering activities extended into the political arena as well. She recalled how "the boys stood on the sidelines and hooted at us" when she and a number of other Simpson coeds took up banners and marched Ruth Buxton Sayre, Iowa Beta around the Indianola square in support of the Constitutional amendment which was to give women the right to vote in 1920. Mrs. Sayre was asked at one time to consider runing for U.S. Senator from Iowa, but turned it down because by that time she felt she had spent most of her energies in her other work. She had served as chairman of the Iowa Farm Bureau's Women's Committee at the county, district, and state levels, and later as midwest regional director, vice president, and president of the Associated Women of the American Farm Bureau Federation. "I'm not a radical," she said of her support of women's rights. But, she said, women need to become involved in the world outside the home. "Home is the center of your life but not the circumference," she declared. Mrs. Sayre eventually found herself involved in a wide range of organizations, including the National Safety Council and the President's Agricultural Advisory Commission, both appointments by President Dwight D. Eisenhower. Mrs. Sayre's Pi Phi interests have never been neglected, but she admits that her activities in Pi Phi "did not begin in earnest until I was free from my international duties." She has been makng up for lost time ever since. In 1965 she became president of the (Continued on page 76) 27 </p>
      <pb ref="arr9120021_0005" seq="05" n="43-44  "/>
       <p>Artist's Plaques Are Cherished iti Tradon An original Pi Phi angel plaque, painted by Lois Thayer Lewis, is one of the gifts received by Illinois Iota, commemorating the chapter's installation. Lois, a talented artist, is a member of the Chicago South Suburban Alumnae Club, and the plaques are a tradition with the club. Lois has been painting them as presidents' gifts for the past seven years and each retiring president treasures her Pi Phi angel. Lois combined her interest in art and Pi Phi when she was awarded a scholarship to Arrowmont where she studied stitchery. She has studied at the Cleveland Institute of Art, the Cleveland Art Museum, Ohio Wesleyan University, and the Chicago Theological Seminary. She has taught creative stitchery for the YWCA, a high school adult education pro-gram, and privately. In addition to stitchery, her work includes oils on wood, and collage oils. She has exhibited in numerous shows and has won many awards. In addition to her exhibitions, Lois frequently presents her pro-gram, "Don't Throw it Out," which has been popular with a wide variety of groups. Lois' training at Chicago Theological Semi-nary has enabled her to become a member of a team ministry, Potential Unlimited, with her husband, Rev. Richard Lewis. Together they Lois Thayer Lewis, at work on some of her Arrowmont projects. Barbara Henricson Peterson, president of the Chicago South Suburban Alumnae Club, holds the plaque presented to Illinois Iota to mark the chapter's installation. conduct youth retreats and celebration work-shops for churches throughout the Chicago area, as well as being youth ministry consultants for the Chicago Metropolitan Association of the United Church of Christ. Girls Swim Team Is Campus Innovation Two members of Illinois Beta-Delta made history in the athletic department program at Knox College. Diane Dillon and Robin Losito competed in swimming and diving, respectively, on the first girls' swim team. Diane, who competed before college, continued to compete in breaststroke. Robin, who was interested in diving but never had the opportunity, learned the dives needed to compete. Thus this was her first year. Due to a change in the athletic program, girls' sports received letters and jackets. Both Diane and Robin were among the first girls to receive letters in women's competition. Robin also made another first at Knox. She became the first woman to compete and letter in a boys' varsity sport. She dove competitively on the team after returning to practice from a shoulder injury. She placed in her first meet, earning points for the team. She continued to compete the rest of the season on both the girls' and boys' swim teams, ending with the conference meet and earning letters in both. Hawaiian Panhel Shows Aloha Spirit by JEANNE NEWMEYER MICHAEL Honolulu A.C. Panhellenic of Hawaii, located in Honolulu, is unique in many ways. It is a City Panhellenic functioning as a state organization; it operates in a state that has no national fraternities, and it handles its funding through dues and various projects rather than through assessments from the 18 group members. Leading this organization is a Pi Phi, Deanna Epps Helber, Oregon Beta, who is not only president of Panhellenic but is also president of the Pi Beta Phi Alumnae Club in Honolulu. The majority of the money earned by Panhellenic is used for scholarships. Through the cooperation of sponsoring businesses, Panhellenic participates in the Community Club Awards program, earning cash for turning in proofs of purchases. A successful Christmas Boutique was held last year to help pay cur-rent expenses. Pi Phis donated a lovely set of Arrowcraft place mats. This year Dee organized the advance sale of admission tickets for Flora Pacifica, a huge annual garden show featuring flora and craft items from the Pacific Basin Area, open to the public for ten days in April and May. Panhellenic of Hawaii maintains a central rush file for all participating NPC fraternities in the Islands, a Memorial Book Shelf of current business books purchased for the University of Hawaii, and an active scholarship program. Two $500 scholarships are provided to girls entering a college or university where there are NPC fraternities. An additional $100 is given each girl to help with sorority expenses if she chooses to pledge. During the summer months, various fraternity alumnae groups give college parties for active fraternity members visiting the Islands. We think Panhellenic of Hawaii reallyshows the Aloha spirit in their cooperative ventures, and all local Pi Phis are very proud that our Dee Helber is president. Sportswomen Garner Three First Places by LYNDA GRASMICK, Florida Delta First place honors were won by Pi Phis in three of nine sports during the 1973-74 sorority intramural season at the University of Florida. Considering that Florida Delta had stiff competition from fifteen other sororities on campus, we were quite proud. Badminton, swimming, and volleyball proved to be the Pi Phi's forte as they captured the first place trophy in all three. Also the Pi Phis proved themselves second best in the highly competitive softball league. Other sports for which Florida Delta sup-ported teams included: basketball, bowling, football, racketball, and tennis. Unfortunately the Pi Phis strong showing only landed them second place among the sororities in the combined intramural sports. Arrowman, Humberto "Humby" Aguilar, contributed greatly to the Pi Phi's athletic success. To encourage enthusiasm in the participating sisters, Humby instituted the unique and novel "Golden Shoe Award." In its first life, the Golden Shoe was one of Humby's very special, but very abused, basket-ball sneakers. It began its second life being renovated, gilded, and mounted. Florida Delta feels that the Golden. Shoe Award was instrumental in generating the great spirit during its first year of existence. It was a big day for Wyoming Alpha when the Elizabeth Summerwill Kozo award arrived. Shown admiring the silver bowl, presented to the chapter which best meets Fraternity standards, are Linda Koontz, Sue Carlson, Bobbi Brown, and Helen Kuiper. 45 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



