<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr9140017_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News of Arrowmont the Craft School and Arrocraft the Cottage Industry</title>
                        <author><name>Lahr, Barbara </name></author>
                        <author><name>Lehner, Eleanor Bushnell</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Summer 1975</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr9140017_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1975</date>, News of Arrowmont the Craft School and Arrocraft the Cottage Industry</title>
                        <author><name>Lahr, Barbara </name></author>
                        <author><name>Lehner, Eleanor Bushnell</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 16-20</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">41</note>
                        <note type="Folder">11</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 91, Number 4 (Summer 1975), Pages 16-20.</note>
			<note type="document">arr9140017_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Special Badge Is Given To Chapter; Arrowcraft Presents The Heritage Hanging; Watson House Is Newest Dormitory; Room for Strenght and Courage in the Smokies</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>The Birth of Arrowmont, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1965-1979</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>
                                <item>Dormitories</item>
                                <item>Facilities</item>
                                <item>Administrators</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr9140017_0001" seq="01" n="16-17  "/>
       <p>Enjoying Virginia Gamma's Golden Anniversary Banquet on March 7 are, l to r, Mary Liz Smith Sadler, AAC chair-man; Nancy Long, chapter president; Leanne Dorman, past chapter president; and Lisa Grable, chapter celebration chairman. Virginia Gamma .. . (Continued from preceding page) nual winners. The name of Pam Cutler, new assistant rush chairman, was the first engraved on the plaque. Lisa Grable explained the Bess Ferguson Ayers Bride's Pin. Mrs. Ayers was the Wisconsin Alpha alum who did so much work with the petitioning group, helped them achieve Pi Beta Phi, and served for many years as AAC chairman. We were proud to have her daughter, Jane Ayers Davis, in attendance. Each Virginia Gamma who is about to be married, or have a 25th or 50th wedding anniversary, may write to the chapter requesting the pin, and wear it somewhere on her wedding costume as some-thing borrowed. The highlight of the evening was the lastnight-of-rush skit performed by the actives. The skit is a candlelight ceremony, telling what Pi Phi means to us, accompanied by songs. A member of AAC, wrote, "Your final presentation of Pi Phi rush week program" to us made me sit a little taller you all have made the Fraternity so relevant, so much a part of "NOW"! How important that is in the "health" of a fraternity at the end of the 20th century!" Saturday morning alumnm, collegians, and friends met again for an open house and coffee at the Pi Phi house. The alums and their husbands took the opportunity to re-inspect the old house, and admire our new shag carpeting. If the "Loved it!!--Delta APP," written on the welcoming banner outside, is any indication, everyone enjoyed this final hospitality in celebration of Virginia Gamma's Golden Anniversary weekend. Special Badge Is Given To Chapter by BARBARA LAHR, Indiana Gamma On March 25 of this year, Indiana Gamma Pi Phis were greatly honored by the presentation to our chapter of the pin worn by the late Marion Webb Prince. Mrs. Prince was an Indiana Gamma and an active alum. In 1953 Marion went to Gatlinburg, Tenn., where she was associated with the Settlement School as Arrowcraft manager. After 18 months of serving the school, she was named its director and held that position for fifteen years. During her time as director she performed a key role in the successful transition from Settlement School to Arrowmont and shared in the great expansion of the Workshop program. Our chapter felt that since Mrs. Prince was so closely connected to Arrowmont and because of the pin's significance we would award the pin to the vice president of moral advancement each year. Presentation of the pin was made by Virginia Brackett Green, a close friend of Marion Prince. They were active Indiana Gammas together, and Mrs. Green was chairman of the Settlement School at the time Marion was manager of the Arrowcraft shop. Mrs. Green spoke to our chap-ter of her experiences at the Settlement School and her hopes for Arrowmont in the future. 16 Edited by ELEANOR BUSHNELL LEHNER Board of Governors Dorothy Mayne Campbell, Central Office Financial Director, shops at the Arrowcraft Shop during a visit to Arrowmont. The Great Smoky Mountains Gatlinburg, Tennessee 37738 17 </p>
      <pb ref="arr9140017_0002" seq="02" n="18-19  "/>
       <p>Arrowcraft Presents THE HERITAGE HANGING This lovely handwoven hanging, designed by Tina McMorran, is approximately 16 X 18 inches. It uses overlaid vegetable dyed yards, and commemorates the 50th anniversary of the establishment of the Arrowcraft Shop in 1926. The hanging depicts the Arrowcraft Shop, the Little Pigeon River which flows nearby, Teachers' Cottage, the flowering countryside, and the splendor of the Great Smoky Mountains. All who have visited Gatlinburg and are familiar with Pi Phi's unique history and involvement there will find this a treasure. The background fabric is rayon and linen in a natural tone. Other colors are mellow, soft earth tones. The hanging is suspended between two strips of carefully finished walnut. The beautiful hanging can be ordered now. Cost is $40.00. About The Designer .. . Tina McMorran, weaver, dyes her own wools with "vegetable" dyes that is, dyes made from plants such as indigo, sassafras, sumach, and poke. Many of her handwoven pieces are used as background for stitchery designs, and in some the design is carried out partly in weaving, partly in stitchery. Vegetable dyed yarns are distinctive because of their soft, muted colors, and these are particularly fitting for Tina's designs, which usually have nature as their theme. Tina's love for the mountains and for trees and birds and flowers is apparent in nearly all her creations. Tina McMorran studied weaving in her native town of Eugene, Oregon. She went to Pi Beta Phi Summer School of Crafts to continue her studies. While she was there she was offere, ? the position as designer for the weavers at Arrowcraft, where she remained from 1947 to 1957. Since then she has devoted most of her time to weaving in her own studio in Gatlinburg. She weaves tapestries for churches, contemporary hangings, as well as traditional; much of her work she is commissioned to do. She is a member of the Southern Highland Handicraft Guild and the 12 Designer Craftsmen; she demonstrates weaving each year at the Guild Fairs and continues to consult with the weaving department at Arrowcraft Shop. 18 Watson House Is Newest Dormitory Watson House, Arrowmont's newest dormitory, has a long and varied history. Situated on the land purchased by Pi Beta Phi for the Settlement School in 1912, it had housed the Andrew Ogle family. Pi Phi converted the building into a much needed health center. Marjorie Chalmers, whose career as Settlement School nurse lasted for more than 30 years, described it thus in her recently published book, Better I Stay: "The Health Center was a white frame cottage with screened porches surrounded by trees and shrubs. Inside there were four rooms. The office was very business-like with big desk, filing cases, typewriter and two phones. One . . . was an inter-school, battery-powered wall phone. "The work room had cupboards and cabinets, sinks and sterilizers and a well stocked surgical dressing table. In the class room was a bed for emergencies, demonstrations and instruction, a folding operating table, dental equipment, and baby scales. "The big room to the east of the office was bare and ugly with an old white hospital bed and a couple of chairs. The second year I was there, this room was converted into nurse's living quarters, and took a new lease on life. With its fireplace of native stone, a rose and blue rug, bright draperies, well filled book shelves, growing plants and easy chairs, it was a pleasant place to relax after a busy day." When the Health Center was moved to the newly constructed building beside the Arrow-craft Shop, in 1948 (now the Administration Arrowmont Board of Governors Chairman, Helen Deppe Vollmar, left, chats with former Settlement School nurse, Marjorie Chalmers, in new dormitory bedroom which once was the Health Center main office. Building), the cottage became a home for the family of Orlie Watson, caretaker for the Pi Phi properties. The Watsons' three sons, Neal, Warren, and Grant, grew up in the house. Mrs. Watson (Josephine McCarter) wove for the Arrowcraft Shop for 25 years and passed away in 1970. After Orlie Watson's death in 1973 the Board of Governors approved remodelling the building for use as a dormitory by Arrowmont graduate assistants. The four large, comfortable rooms can accommodate eight girls at a time. In the fall of 1974 the "new" Watson House was officially dedicated. After a luncheon at-tended by members of the Board of Governors and the Little Pigeon Alumnae Club, Neal Watson cut the wine and blue ribbons across the front door, and the guests were treated to a tour of Arrowmont's newest "addition." Pi Phi visitors mount the steps for an inspection tour of Watson House. The newly remodeled Watson House snuggles down among mountain trees and shrubs. </p>
      <pb ref="arr9140017_0003" seq="03" n="20-21  "/>
       <p>Room for Strength and Courage" in the Smokies In a tiny mountain village, almost hidden from the world, Pi Beta Phi established a Settlement School and staffed it with gallant women whose ruggedness matched the very real challenges they faced. For them the never ending problems and hardships seemed to serve as a stimulus and tonic, perhaps because they knew they were involved in a truly meaningful endeavor. First of all they needed a rare combination of courage and compassion a love of service and a willingness to sacrifice themselves. But even this would have been too little to sustain them had they lacked one further essential an al-most passionate devotion to the physical environment in which they found themselves, an en-chanting world of forests and peaks and rivers and streams known as the Great Smoky Mountains. What this environment meant to these particular women has never been more beautifully expressed than in the words of Marjorie Chalmers as she recalls her experiences in the pages of a book entitled Better I Stay, in which she re-counts samples of the adventures she experienced during her more than thirty years as Settlement School and community nurse. If her years of service brought her any special honors or awards she does not mention them; but no one could read this simple account without recognizing that it was written by an unusually sensitive and capable human being who repeatedly and willingly risked her own life in the service of others. If Miss Chalmers had not decided to become a nurse she could have made a name for her-self as a professional writer. She has the heart of a poet, the eyes and ears of a journalist, and a sense of humor that is irresistible. What her efforts contributed to Pi Beta Phi's image in the Great Smoky Mountains can never be measured. The risks that were part of the fabric of her life cannot be recounted here. The colorful samples of picturesque mountain dialect cannot be repeated. But her poetic descriptions of the setting that sustained her cannot be resisted. "Surely, I thought, one should have the happy gift of patience in these hills. They stand, serene and strong, never-changing, yet ever-changing. One can stand in prosaic fashion, feet firmlyset on earth, while the spirit seems to stand a-tiptoe on the heights. Mental arms fling wide to embrace such beauty. Life permeates every cell, flooding away grief and fear, to make room for strength and courage. How often that feeling brought an uplift of soul that seems like a psalmist's exaltation." "There is so much beauty all around us, no matter where we look. Should the tier on tier of mountain ranges, the sheer drop of a cliff, the towering height of magnificent old trees awe you with over-much grandeur, rest your eyes on the daintiness at your feet. Lacy, delicate lichen like fairy beds of fern, great blue violets, starry in their setting of blue green leaves, fragile tiny slender-leaved pansy-like miniatures the daintiest and the sweetest of the violet family." "It had been a silver gray day. Mt. Harrison and old Sugarlands Ridge had wrapped their shoulders 'round with wooly lengths of cloud. The air was cooly moist against the face not cold and little tendrils of hair curled tightly, as if for warmth, against cheek and neck. Low gray clouds enfolded the valley and the smoke curled downward like tawny plumes, stirring gently with the wind's slow breathing." "The hills are always beautiful, and I never weary of them. They have become the very back-ground of my life strong and calm, untouched by the busyness of every day. They are like old friends, dependable and sure. Changes pass over them, like storm of grief and joy's sunlight. But still they stand, serene." Better I Stay has been printed through the efforts of the Little Pigeon Alumnae Club in Gatlinburg. It is on sale at the Arrowcraft Shop for $2.75 plus Tennessee state tax. Out-of-state would be tax free but subject to a small fee for postage and handling. Direct inquiries to the Arrowcraft Shop. Make ARROWMONT Your Favorite Philanthropy 20 French Society Initiates Author by DORRIS KARCHER WELLING Little Rock A.C. Ruth Moore Malone, Arkansas Alpha, was inducted recently into the Confrerie des Chevaliers du Tastevin in a ceremony at the Chateau du Clos de Vougeot at Corton, France. A robed member of the Grand Council of the Chevaliers du Tastevin tapped Ruth on the shoulder with an ancient, gnarled vine root, thus signifying her acceptance in the Chevaliers. The ceremony, held in France's burgundy country, was followed by an elegant dinner in the chateau's great hall, accompanied by Burgundian wine songs. Relatively few American women are invited to join Tastevin, although there are some 1,900 members throughout the United States in chapters of major cities. They meet periodically to sample great French wines, particularly the burgundies. The ceremony was conducted by officials in red robes and wearing red hats trimmed, like the robes, in gold brocade. Ruth was presented a silver burgundy sampling cup worn on a ribbon around the neck in the same manner of sommeliers, or wine stewards. Closer to home, Ruth is food editor of Holi Ruth Malone is tapped during impressive French ceremony. day Inn Magazine and author of the Holiday Inn International Cookbook, Ozark Cookbook, Dog-patch Cookbook, and Swiss Holiday Wine Cook-book. Ruth's home is in Little Rock with husband Charles. The Malones have two daughters who are also Arkansas Alpha Pi Phis, Bess Malone Lankford of Little Rock and Margaret Malone deMarcy of Hamilton, Bermuda. Ruth is a past president of the Camden, Ark. Alumna Club and was 1962 National Publicity Chairman of Pi Beta Phi Convention which was held in Hot Springs, Arkansas. Members Involved In Student Government Approximately 15% of the University of Minnesota's student senators are members of Minnesota Alpha. Louise Koste and Terri Wray were elected last spring. Besides being a senator, Terri holds a chairing position on the College of Liberal Arts Board. Roxie Goertz, also elected to the senate last spring, is involved with the University Election's Commission, Senate Committee on Resources and Planning, and was recently appointed to be one of six student representatives to the University Board of Regents. As a student senator, Jane Hartley was a hiring chairman for a Title IX University Commit-tee and she is serving on the University Grant Fund Committee. by JACKIE NICHOLS, Minnesota Alpha Other members of the Minnesota Alpha chap-ter hold respected positions on committees of the University of Minnesota. Last fall, Bobbie Kuller was elected to the University Fee's Committee. Debbie Searles serves on the campus committees on student behavior and on printing and publication. Melanie Snider is a member of the University Health Service Committee. Minnesota Alpha's Diane Houpt is the chair-man of the Committee on Convocations and the Arts, a planning committee of cultural programs for the University of Minnesota. Minnesota Alpha Pi Phis are very well rep-resented within the different committees of the University of Minnesota, and within the main governing body itself, the student senate. 21 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



