<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arr9020015_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>News of Arrowmont School of arts and crafts</title>
                        <author><name>Lehner, Elanor Bushnell</name></author>
                        <author><name>Hall, Betty Bailey </name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Winter 1973</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arr9020015_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1973</date>, News of Arrowmont School of arts and crafts</title>
                        <author><name>Lehner, Elanor Bushnell</name></author>
                        <author><name>Hall, Betty Bailey </name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 15-19</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">41</note>
                        <note type="Folder">10</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 90, Number 2 (Winter 1973), Pages 15-19.</note>
			<note type="document">arr9020015_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Caroline Riddle Assumes Duties as Administrator; The Summer of '73-In Retrospect; Three Appointed To BOG Positions</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>The Birth of Arrowmont, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1965-1979</item>
                                <item>Administrators</item>
                                <item>Summer crafts workshop</item>
                                <item>Arts</item>
                                <item>People</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arr9020015_0001" seq="01" n="14-15  "/>
       <p>Heads P.R. For Spokane xposition Jane Sauer Johnson, Idaho Alpha, has been named to supervise communications and publicity activities for Expo '74, the Spokane, Wash., World Exposition, which opens in May, 1974. In her capacity as publicity manager within the Expo public relations department, Jane will be in charge of Expo public information pro-grams, news media contacts, and general community communication activities. Mrs. Johnson will be handling communications aimed at the nearly 5 million visitors expected to cross the gates of the 1974 World's Fair, "Celebrating Tomorrow's Fresh, New Environment." The Fair will bring to Spokane the major nations of the world, leading corporations, and environmentally concerned groups, all with exhibits relating to the environmental theme. "We feel extremely fortunate to obtain the services of a person with Mrs. Johnson's experience and capability," said John V. Geraghty, Jr., vice president for marketing at Expo '74. "As .Expo's opening day draws nearer we will have a continuing and growing responsibility for full communications with the people of the Spokane area, the Pacific Northwest, and the nation." A native of Montana, Mrs. Johnson attended Sandpoint, Idaho, high school, Whitworth College, the University of Idaho, and was gradu Jane Sauer Johnson, Idaho Alpha ated from Arizona State University and U.C.L.A. with a Masters degree. She was named outstanding young woman in the State of Washington in 1970, after being nominated by the Spokane Alumnae Club of Pi Beta Phi. Youngsters Have Field Day With Pi Phis As their philanthropy project for the spring term, Ohio Delta Pi Phis chose to work with young children. After much consideration and rejection of ideas, philanthropies interest group chairman Babette Knull came up with the idea of holding field day races at a local park for a group of elementary school children. The result was a huge success. Pi Phis and Phi Kappa Psi fraternity took over supervision of a neighborhood after-school recreation pro-gram at a Delaware Elementary School for one afternoon. Pi Phis and Phi Psis climbed onto school buses with 70 third, fourth, and fifth graders and traveled across town to Blue Lime-stone Park, where more Pi Phis and Phi Psis were waiting to get the games going. Despite a slight drizzle, all the kids had aby KATHY GEER, Ohio Delta great time going in teams from the timed obstacle course race to the water balloon toss, on to the three-legged races, and clothes-dressing game. Pi Phis and Phi Psis directed the contests, kept track of the winners, and even participated in the races if a child didn't have a needed partner. Some Phi Psis really got soaked in the water balloon toss, while several Pi Phis found themselves with very short partners in the three-legged race. After the games were over, everyone trooped over to the shelterhouse, happy and wet, to munch potato chips and pretzels and drink Kool-aid while the winners' list was tallied. Thoughtful Mom Graham had provided first, second, and third place ribbons for each event. 14 News of Edited by ELEANOR BUSHNELL LEHNER Board of Governors Wood relief sculpture donated to Arrowmont by Joseph Falsetti is on display at the school. Mr. Falsetti taught the first courses in the new wood studio in June, 1973. Two students in the advanced class assisted him in creating this piece. school of arts and crafts The Great Smoky Mountains Gatlinburg, Tennessee 37738 15 </p>
      <pb ref="arr9020015_0002" seq="02" n="16-17  "/>
       <p>Caroline Riddle Assumes Duties As Administrator by BETTY BAILEY HALL Board of Governors A change of administrators, with continuity, took place September 1 at Arrowmont. On that date Helen Anderson Lewis, Kentucky Alpha, retired and Caroline Mills Riddle, Florida Beta, became the Administrator of Arrowmont and Arrowcraft. Caroline has been at Arrowmont since March, learning the duties of the administrator, under Helen's tutelage. Caroline's educational and business experience will be valuable in her new position. Her BA degree was in art education from Rollins College and she has done graduate work in personnel administration, art' education, and guidance. Her position before coming to Arrowmont was as administrator of field services with the Citrus Council of Girl Scouts, where she supervised the field directors as together they provided professional service and guidance to the 50 neighborhood units in six counties of central Florida. Her Scout experience also included advising the personnel committee, coordinating adult learning, working with United Funds, coordinating council day camps, working with both professionals and volunteers to provide quality Girl Scouting in the Council's jurisdiction. (Incidentally, there were three Pi Phis on the professional staff !) Her own creative work has been in the field of stitchery, rug hooking, and ceramics. This summer she took weaving for two weeks and came away with an expanded weaving knowledge and skill, and fabric for a new topper, as well as the feel of how it is to be a student at Arrowmont. Caroline is a widow and has four grown children and four grandchildren. Her son, David, lives in Maitland, Fla., with his wife and two children. Daughter, Barbara Hooker, is the mother of two children and works for Eastern Air Lines, at their Wings of Man exhibit at Disney World. Martha is Mrs. Ray Guenthner and lives in Orlando, Fla. Her twin Linda is the coordinator of a tri-county program for the el Caroline Mills Riddle, Arrowmont-Arrowcraft Administrator. derly with headquarters in Williamsport, Pa. She took a course in batik at Arrowmont last summer and now she and her mother have a plan: Linda will do the batiking for wall hangings, Caroline will do the quilting and complete the article. Several of Caroline's stitcheries are already hanging in the Staff House in Gatlin-burg. Pi Phi is fourtunate to have another of its own members so qualified and eager to carry on this position of responsibility. As Caroline says, "I look forward with excitement to the new work, not only 1974, but in the unfolding years ahead: to working with Marian Heard, students, instructors, Pi Phis, the community all to helping Arrowmont realize its physical and envisioned potential. I look forward to the planning, developing, and dreaming and to the hard work which can make Arrowmont a year-round program." Helen has purchased a home in Gatlinburg and will continue her close association with Arrowmont as a member of the Board of Governors. 16 The Summer of '73 "Part of our vision is to care," said Arrowmont Director Marian G. Heard. "We care for the many people who have only a very short va cation. We make it possible for many to come who could ill afford a longer stay financially." In these words Miss Heard explained why four of Arrowmont's seven summer sessions were one week sessions. Even though the shorter sessions mean extra work for staff members, the advantages to the students make them worth the effort. To be able to spend a single week in the mountains, enjoying the company of stimulating companions, and to carry home an astonishing hoard of self-created treasures jewelry, pottery, stitchery, enamelware, macrame, textiles, woven goods, basketry, woodwork who could ask for a more satisfying vacation! The number of students enrolled for the nine weeks and one day of instruction in 1973 totalled 953 from 42 states and three foreign countries. This was 132 more than the 1972 total. School dormitories can accommodate only 82 at a time. A little quick arithmetic suggests that, during the seven sessions, 379 students must have paid expensive motel rates or camped out. (Alumnm clubs please note! Arrowmont needs beds and rooms to put them in.) One moral is obvious: if you want dormitory space, enroll early. But class space is also a problem. By mid-April some of the classes were already filled. Pity the staff members who had to withstand the demands of those who desperately wanted to study at Arrowmont, only to discover there was no room for them. Student ages ranged from sixteen to over eighty. All ages seemed to be searching and trusting that this experience would fill their individual needs and be even more meaningful than they had anticipated. But their reaction to the experience is always positive. They discover how much can be gained by sharing a learning and living experience with older folks, and they are usually quite vocal in their appreciation of what it has meant to them. Ten of the 26 instructors for 1973 sessions were new to Arrowmont. All are prominent in their respective fields, but only those who "can teach, wish to teach, and do teach" are invited to Arrowmont, according to Director Heard. "I am always touched by the fact that so many are In Retrosi'ect New library shelves at Arrowmont (above), donated by Helen and Bob Russell (below) with Arrowmont Director Marian G. Heard (right). J. Wade King, who constructed the shelves, was a student at Pi Beta Phi High School in Gatlinburg in the thirties and studied woodworking with instructor O. J. Mattel. He is now co-manager of a furniture shop. The shelves were designed by Hubert Bebb, the prize-winning architect who designed Arrowmont. completely dedicated to their students and are in their studios countless hours beyond their scheduled classes," she adds. "They always find devious ways to let me know that they would like to be asked back," she comments. "This is very gratifying, because many are very selective about where they teach." Miss Heard also had high praise for the "ex (Continued next page) 17 </p>
      <pb ref="arr9020015_0003" seq="03" n="18-19  "/>
       <p>Clock created by Doris and Roland Bartels, donated to Curt Benzle, graduate assistant from Rocky River, Ohio, Arrowmont by Mary Frances Davidson. blending clay in new pug mill donated by Wichita, (Kansas) Alumnae Club. Retrospect .. (Continued) cellent assistants." She described them as highly responsible, competent, and willing to do what-ever needed to be done. "They were completely exhausted at the end of their five week work period," she said, "but they still demanded of themselves the best." For still another summer Helen Russell, former Settlement School chairman, returned to manage the library. Not only did she and husband Bob donate a whole wall of new book-shelves, but she also covered every book with a plastic jacket which will add many years to their lives. Among additions to the facilities were a new loom for the weaving studio and a new wheel for the pottery studio, which also welcomed the acquisition of a pug mill and a brick kiln. Donated by the Wichita (Kansas) Alumnae Club, the pug mill is a device for blending dry clay with moist clay in order to attain the desired composition. Bricks for the kiln, which was constructed by students in James Darrow's kiln-building class, were acquired through the efforts of 1972 pottery students, supplemented by Mary Frances Davidson. A popular instructor every summer, Miss Davidson teaches not pottery but vegetable dyeing! Thanks to her continuing generosity, a new clock, created by wood carvers Doris and Roland Bartels, now hangs on the Arrowmont Gallery wall. 18 A gift of fine electroforming equipment, in-stalled by Stanley Lechtzin, the famous metal-smith who was the first to translate this industrial concept to a craft, was presented to Arrowmont by members of the Pittsburg Alumnm Club, whose generosity also provided a new casting machine, a welding outfit, and a polishing machine. (Continued next page) Anne Van Aiken, ceramics instructor from Los Altos, Calif., tests temperature of the brick kiln constructed by James Darrow's kiln-building class. Three Appointed To BOG Positions The appointment by Grand Council of three new members to serve on the Arrowmont Board of Governors has been announced by Helen Vdllmar, chairman. They are Mary Jean Stoddard Fowler, Houston, Tex., an Iowa Gamma and former Arrowmont student; Ceciele Brosfeau Kendall, Manhattan, Kan., Illinois Eta, who has given much assistance through her Travel Dollars for Arrowmont program ; and Helen Anderson Lewis, Kentucky Alpha, who retired in September, 1973, as Administrator for Arrowmont. The three appointees have replaced the retiring members of the committee, Betty Bailey Hall, Henrietta McCutchan Huff, Betty Yelm Kingman, and Olivia Smith Morre. Each of the latter four has devoted much time and excellent guidance to Arrowmont during her term of office. Retrospect . . (Continued) Also new in '73 were courses in basketry and in wood. Joan Austen, whose course was subti tled Sculptural Forms Using Basketry Techniques, is an assistant professor of textile design at California State University in San Diego. Joseph Falsetti, who enriched the gallery with a wood relief sculpture which he created with the assistance of two advanced students, is a professor at the University of Missouri. Some clever remodeling converted two offices into a charming bookstore and craft shop, operated by Paul Rossetter, to the delight of both students and visitors. And another longed-for facility came into being when a seldom used conference room was transformed into a much needed recreation room for students. In addition to her regular duties, Assistant Director Sandra Blain, a skilled photographer, assembled a new series of Arrowmont color slides available to individual clubs and chapters through their province officers. After commending retiring administrator Helen Anderson Lewis for her two years of service to Arrowmont, Director Heard announced that Helen, who has been appointed to the Board of Governors, would probably be the first to enroll as a student in 1974. Pi Phis and scholarship winners who attended the first 1973 Arrowmont session are, back row, Colleen Cox, Montana Alpha, graduate assistant; Kelly Swan, Oregon Beta; Judy Hinz, Idaho Alpha-Boise Alumnce Club; Kay Sexton, Ann Lukeman, both Illinois Zetas sent by the Champaign Alumnce Club; Leanne Elliott, Oregon Gamma. Front row: Susan DeLong, Tennessee Gamma; Barbara Crawford, Oklahoma Beta, graduate assistant; Pat Swan, Oregon Beta, Upsilon Province President; Dorothy Petet, Texas Alpha; Marie Browne, Colorado Springs Alumnce Club. Alumnce Club scholarship holders during the second session were (back row): Kathy Skwiera, Indianapolis A.C.; Judy Hinz, Idaho Alpha, Boise A.C.; Gwen Russell, Sacramento A.C.; Kathy Lower, Georgia Alpha, Virginia Alpha Craft Scholarship. Front row: Catherine Ferguson, Omaha A.C.; Sara Ann Bonde, Illinois Theta, Mu North Province; Carol O'Dell, Columbia, S.C., A.C.; Noreen Christon, Illinois Zeta, Omaha A.C. Pi Phis attending the fifth Arrowmont session were Judith Dralle, Iowa Gamma; Sally Baldwin, Kansas Alpha; Barbara Wehr, Minnesota Alpha. </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



