<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arri160039_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Settlement School</title>
                        <author><name>Thorman, Dorothy Coleman</name></author>
                        <author><name>Mueller, Marion W.</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Fall 1966</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arri160039_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1966</date>, Settlement School</title>
                        <author><name>Thorman, Dorothy Coleman</name></author>
                        <author><name>Mueller, Marion W.</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 39-43</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">41</note>
                        <note type="Folder">3</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 1, Number 6 (Fall 1966), Pages 39-43.</note>
			<note type="document">arri160039_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Chairman of Settlement School Committee; Settlement School Director's Report - June 1965-July 1966</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>The Birth of Arrowmont, Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1965-1979</item>
                                <item>Funding</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>
                                <item>Facilities</item>
                                <item>Staff</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arri160039_0001" seq="01" n="38-39  "/>
       <p>38 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI NOMINATING COMMITTEE The Nominating Committee sent a letter in January to all active chapter and alumnx club presidents informing them that all present officers would continue in office until the 1967 Convention. It also announced with deep regret the resignation of the Grand President, Alice Weber John-son and the Grand Treasurer, Olivia Smith Moore effective June 1967. The Nominating Committee recommended to the active session of the 1966 Convention the endorsement of two officers in training for Grand President and Grand Treasurer to be placed in nomination for election at the 1967 Convention. The recommendation was accepted and the names of Dorothy Weaver Morgan for Grand President and Louise Rosser Kemp for Grand Treasurer were presented and endorsed. The new names received on Nominee Information Sheets have been placed in the committee's file for use at the 1967 Convention and a list given to Grand Council for their use in making appointments to fill vacancies that may occur during the year. National Officers and Convention Delegates were re-quested to submit in writing their suggestions for the endorsees and names of other alumna interested in serving the fraternity to the Nominating Committee, if they as individuals desired to, or if their club or chapter had not already submitted suggestions. The results from the mailing and the written suggestions to the committee when it convened during Convention show suggestions from 36% of the National Officers; 44% of the active chapters; and 7% of the alumnae clubs. These names were given careful consideration in selecting the endorsees. MAXINE WILLIAMS MORSE, Chairman SHIRLEY BRADSHAW SUSAN ROSE SAUNDERS CATHERINE ADDY PATRICIA PHILLIPS PAULA PHILLIPS NATIONAL CONVENTION GUIDE At the Officers' Workshop in St. Louis, June, 1965, a decision was made to change the tentative plans for the 1966 convention from the usual six-day convention, to a three and one-half day "working" convention. Since this meant elimination of the social events, the printing of a convention DAILY, recreation day, and a change in other areas of planning, the convention committee felt the need of another meeting in Gatlinburg in order to start all over again. This was held in October, 1965; actually only one day was needed in Gatlinburg, and the remainder of the three-day visit was spent in Knoxville with the committee members and the transportation chairman. The usual spring meeting of the entire committee was held in late March in Gatlinburg and at that time we were joined by Joy Dirksen Baker, Transportation Chairman and Lucile Jennings who was Seating Chairman as well as Elections Coordinator. At this meeting, we were able to get into more detailed planning with the three hotel managers, the manager of the Gatlinburg Auditorium, and the local Pi Phis who had accepted certain responsibilities. Early in April, we joined the members of the Grand Council at their meeting in Chicago, to get program de-tails worked out, as well as many other matters concerned with convention. During this time, we were able to have brief meetings with Jamie Jo Buntain, the 1967 local chairman, and also Mr. Roy Powell, Vice President and Director of Sales at the Edgewater Beach Hotel. On April 28, it was our pleasure to return to the Chica-go area and speak at the Founders' Day Luncheon sponsored by the Hinsdale Township Alumnx Club. This was a most enjoyable occasion. The Pi Phis in attendance were eager to hear about plans for the Centennial Convention, and showed much interest and enthusiasm, and a willingness to accept job responsibilities. Nancy Burke, Iota Alumna Province President arranged for an overnight stay at her home, and conferences with members of the 1967 committee. The same week, on April 30, we participated in the program of the Founders' Day Luncheon of the Detroit Area Clubs, sponsored this year by the North Woodward Alumnae Club. As in the past, we continue to get communications and brochures from hotels, Chambers of Commerce and Convention Bureaus from various cities in the United States. Many such places could not fill our needs for convention facilities and number of rooms available for housing. Some, while seeming to be good possibilities, are too inaccessible as far as transportation is concerned, and this could present a problem. It has been a pleasure to be a part of the "working team" of Pi Beta Phi; affording an opportunity to strengthen old friendships, and to make new ones. Sincere thanks to all the members of Grand Council, and to all officers and members of Pi Beta Phi for their cooperation and understanding. HELEN ANDERSON LEWIS Settlement Sh00l CHAIRMAN OF SETTLEMENT SCHOOL COMMITTEE The Settlement School Committee wishes to express its appreciation to all clubs and chapters for their support during the year 1965-66. Our standards remain high and we continue to build the strong foundation upon which the Centennial Fund Project will be established. This foundation is now an Art and Craft Center, Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee. It is well established nationally, through its successful Summer Craft Workshop, co-sponsored with the University of Tennessee, and through its Arrowcraft Shop. The value of handcrafted articles was recognized by the first staff members of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School as early as 1915. When staff members saw the beautiful baskets and handwoven articles which were made by the mountain people in their homes, there was immediate interest in encouraging these native abilities. Encouragement was given through purchase of the articles which were sent to friends. Soon a demand arose from these friends who wished to purchase more and more of the handcrafted articles. From this early demand, Arrowcraft Shop evolved and has expanded into the well-known project it is today. The need for instruction in the art of crafts was recognized by Pi Beta Phi very early. The teaching of crafts be-came part of the curriculum of the Pi Beta Phi School in order to preserve interest in the native crafts. In 1943, when Sevier County took over the full responsibility of providing teachers and the administration of the Pi Beta Phi elementary school and high school, the officers of Pi Beta Phi had a survey made to decide how Settlement School could best serve the community. The need for offering opportunities in the study of crafts, to adults, was recognized and the Summer Craft Workshop, co-sponsored with the University of Tennessee was started in 1945. This project has continued and has developed into one of the most outstanding craft schools in the country today. Settlement School interest is now concentrated on craft workshops. Besides the Summer Craft Workshop, others are offered in the spring and fall to local craftsmen and people interested in learning crafts. Settlement School is used by the Southern Highland Handicraft Guild for conferences and workshops. Pi Beta Phi Settlement School was a charter member of this guild. The craftsmen of the Southern Highland Handicraft Guild believe with Mr. Allen Eaton: "He who does creative work, whether he dwell in a palace or a hut, has in his house a window through which he may look out upon some of life's finest scenes." Pi Beta Phi Settlement School provides the facilities which make it possible to offer instruction in handicrafts. In order to provide these facilities, financial support must be continued. Because of past support there has been no gap in the steady progress toward a worthwhile new project. A very important step forward this year was the building of the Ceramic Wing which was completed in time for the opening of the Summer Craft Workshop, 1966. The Ceramic Wing was added to the Loom House Wing, which was built in 1962. Financial support from clubs and chapters, plus other sources of income, make it possible for Settlement School to do the following: Provide and maintain classrooms, 3 dormitories, Staff House, Red Barn Provide necessary equipment and furnishings Provide 6 or more scholarships for Workshop Assistants Provide craft workshops during the fall and spring Pay salaries according to the present standards Subsidize salaries necessary to provide outstanding in structorsIncrease national advertising of Craft Workshop Provide an administrative staff and office Offer the Red Barn to philanthropic groups and Pi Be Phi Chapters for educational retreats in the sprir and fall. Contributions for 1965-66: Total contributions from clubs and chapters $16,041s Active chapter contributions 3,178., Alumnae club contributions 12,863. Settlement School Committee extends its gratitude to 5 chapters and 282 clubs, for their increased support i 1965-66. A small expression of appreciatiin is shown t awarding a Little Pigeon Award, a hand carved walm pin, to clubs and chapters making the highest contribi Lions. Chapters 12 'highest. (The number in parentheses ind cates the number of consecutive years of giving $100 00 i( more.) Texas A (5) $150.00 Illinois Z $77.1 Texas r (11) 150.00 Illinois E 75.1 Missouri B (16) 110.00 Iowa Z 75.1 Alabama B 100.00 Kansas B 75.1 Montana A (4) 100.00 Tennessee B 75.1 Nebraska B 85.00 California r 71.1 Little Pigeon Awards are given to clubs on the basis c membership. The awards were given to the two higher contributors in the following membership classification (The number in parentheses indicates the number of col secutive years of giving $150.00 or more.) 10-24 Everett, Wash. (10) $ 150.( 'Chicago South, 111 50.( 25-49 LaCanada Valley, Calif. (3) 200.( Youngston-Warren, Ohio 107.( 50-74 Contra Costa, Calif. (3) 210.( Franklin, Ind 108.1 75-99 Champaign-Urbana, 111. (6) 200.1 Cleveland West, Ohio (3) 150.( 100 and over Houston, Texas 1200.1 Kansas 'City, Mo. (17) 1000.1 St. Louis, Mo. (17) 1000.1 Pasadena, Calif. (9) 1000.E Honorable mention: North Shore, Ill. (9) $ 600.1 Recognition to clubs making contributions of $150.0 and over: Indianapolis (17) $ 270s Denver (16) 220., Los Angeles (4) 200. South Coast, Calif 200., Milwaukee 158. Westchester County, N.Y 150s A Little Pigeon Award is given to the Province office when every club and chapter in the province makes a co] tribution, thus making it a 100% province. Chapters Clubs Both Beta Alpha Beta Gamma Beta Zeta Eta Iota Kappa Xi Mu Pi South Arroivcraft Shop: It is a pleasure to report that bo Club sales and Shop sales were very successful and high than in previous years. Twenty-eight clubs had sales over $1000.00. The highest club sale was Houston cli with the total for paid purchases at $5300.00. Champaig Urbana was second with a total of $3900.00. Little Pige( Awards were given to the following chapters for the hig est paid-for purchases from Arrowcraft Shop. 39 </p>
      <pb ref="arri160039_0002" seq="02" n="40-41  "/>
       <p>40 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI Ohio E $ 239.49 Kansas B $ 101.85 New York t, 174.89 Washington r 80.77 New York A ... 143.58 Alabama r 78.18 Penn B 120.75 Maryland B 67.57 North Carolina B ... 108.96 Maine A 64.85 Little Pigeon Awards were given to the following clubs for the highest paid for purchases. These awards are given on the basis of membership in the following classifications: 10-24 Manchester, Conn $ 1194.00 Gainesville, Florida 1184.00 25-49 Stillwater, Okla 2012.00 Charleston, W.Va 1383.00 50-74 Arlington Heights, Ill 2184.00 50-74 Akron, Ohio 2033.00 75-99 Champaign-Urbana, Ill 3900.00 San Mateo. Calif 15'12.00 100 and over Houston, Texas and Houston Jr. and Houston Mothers Club 5300.00 Indianapolis and Franklin, Ind 2598.00 To encourage the "friendly competition" tradition which has been recorded for many years, following is a complete list of all clubs which had successful sales and bought and paid for over $10010.00 of Arrowcraft articles and crafts. The reward to these clubs is gratitude for helping to keep Pi Beta Phi well-known and recognized because of its wonderful Arrowcraft Shop project. Lincoln, Neb $ 1800.00 New Haven, Conn. .$ 1214.00 Pasadena, Calif 1754.00 Reno, Nev 1201.00 South Bay, Calif. . . 1397.00 Chicago South, Ill. 1183.00 Bloomfield Hills, Mich. Northern, N.J. . 1177.00 1372.00 Chicago West Sub., North Shore, Ill. .. . 1368.00 Ill 1145.00 Oklahoma City, Okla. Riverside, Calif. . 1144.00 1286.00 Pittsburgh, Pa 1116.00 Harrisburg-Carlisle, Pa. Fayetteville, Ark. . 1053.00 1267.00 South Bend, Ind. . 1049.00 Schenectady, N.Y. .. 1220.00 Many new items have been added to the 1966-67 Price List, both in weaving articles and in crafts. There seems to be increased interest in beautiful handcrafted articles. Pi Beta Phi clubs have a wonderful opportunity of presenting high quality handwoven articles and crafts to their communities through the sale of Arrowcraft. Order early for your 1966-67 sales. Arrowcraft Shop Staff : Manager, Mrs. Maria Hutchins Tate, Florida Beta, has a big job and says she loves it. As manager she keeps inventory high, corresponds with chapters and clubs, supervises orders, works with the weaving designer and supervisor, and manages the Shop. We are grateful to her for her many hours of hard work and for her interest in the success of Arrowcraft Shop. Mrs. Elizabeth Wait Rue, Iowa Gamma, enjoys her work as manager of the Shop in the Mountain View Hotel. Faye Cook is the head of shipping and likes big orders. Nella Hill has been acting Weaving Designer and Supervisor in the absence of a professional. She has done a rewarding piece of work including the designing of two new place mats, a new towel, and a bracelet bag. Other sales staff include: Jean Hembree, assistant shipping clerk, June Parrott, Ruby Watson, and Ruth Kenney. Mrs. Grace Patterson is the bookkeeper. Pi Beta Phi is indebted to this wonderful staff for their loyalty and interest in making Arrowcraft Shop the successful project that it is. Craft Workshops: Summer Craft Workshop co-sponsored with the University of Tennessee. Through this unique association of a university and a fraternity, Pi Beta Phi is making an outstanding contribution to higher education by offering opportunities for creative expression in the inspiring environment of the Great Smokies National Park. Marian Heard, Director, Pi Beta Phi, Professor of Craft Design, Univ. of Tennessee, is an inspiring leader in the field of crafts. Under her direction, and planning, the new Ceramic Wing is the best in the country today. Betty Street, M.S., Assistant Director, University of Illinois, contributesto the success of the program through her ability as a craftsman and as an administrator. The 1966 Summer Workshop faculty is most outstanding, with four new members from different parts of the country. A special seminar in weaving was offered for two days under the direction of Glen Kaufman, Chairman, Weaving and Fabric Design Department, Cranbrook Academy of Art. It was well attended. Other courses offered included: Jewelry, Weaving, Textile Design, Enameling, Pottery, Recreational Crafts, and Stitchery. Assistantship Scholarships were given to seven students for the 1966 session. Two were given to Pi Phis, Gregg Powers Bodie, S.C. Alpha and Barbara Ramsey Wehr, Minn. Alpha. Kay Kauz1arich, Colorado Alpha, was given the Southern California Area Scholarship. Beverly Lewis, Virginia Delta, received the Virginia Alpha Scholarship. Alumna 'Clubs sending scholarship winners were Albuquerque, Buffalo, and Houston. The enrollment for the 1966 sessions exceeded the dormitory space now offered. In order to keep our standards high, it is imperative that plans be made for a new dormitory as soon as possible. Other workshops were held during the year, a valuable contribution to the cultural heritage of the Gatlinburg area. Red Barn: Besides being an attractive dormitory for 32 students during Summer Craft Workshop, it is in demand by religious, educational, and philanthropic groups for weekend retreats in the fall and spring. Pi Beta Phi chapters are urged to take advantage of using it for educational seminars. A nominal rental fee is charged. Gifts and Legacies: A gift honoring Lolita Snell Prouty by her three daughters, Evelyn Prouty Hichman, Jane Prouty Perrella, and Caroline Prouty Shreve, was made to help build the Ceramic Wing. The Ceramic Wing was dedicated on Sunday, June 19th, and is called the Lolita Snell Prouty Ceramic Wing. A memorial gift of $1000.00 was biven by A. E. Minor in memory of his wife. It is to be used for a craft library and is to be called the "Jeannette Mitchell Minor Collection." Denver Alumna Club gave $100 honoring Lolita Prouty to be used to have a plaque made for the Ceramic Wing and remainder to be used for furniture. Contra Costa (California) Club gave $100 to be used as a scholarship for Ralph Ogle, high school student. Dorothy Lexau, Gatlinburg, gave $250.00 which was used to purchase an electric potters wheel. The West Chicago Suburban Club gave three hand carved bears in memory of Robert C. Trow, husband of Julia J. Trow. The Detroit Club gave a slide projector to be used at Craft Workshops, in memory of Sarah Louise Voegtly Fricke, Maryland Alpha. The Berkeley Club sent $75.00 as a memorial to Mrs. Elizabeth Sullivan, which was to be used toward a scholar-ship for the 1966 Craft Workshop. Mrs. Sullivan's daughter Mary Elizabeth was an assistant at the 1965 Work-shop. A Crafts Honoraries Fund was started in June 1966 and has $331.00 which is to be used to buy needed equipment for Craft Workshop. The Memorial Fund was increased by $110'.00, making a total of $506.79. This sum will also be used to purchase needed equipment. Our gratitude is extended to each per-son who has made these gifts possible. Green stamps are always welcomed to help replenish towels and bedding. Director of Settlement School: Mrs. Marion W. Mueller, Indiana Gamma, has served the fraternity in this office for thirteen years. Pi Beta Phi is indebted to her for her many years of loyal and devoted service. She is the one person most responsible for the strength of the foundation for the Centennial Fund Project. Twice she has taken the responsibility of acting as contractor for the building of the craft Center; first the Loom House Wing, and this THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI year for the Ceramic, Wing. The Director's responsibilities include: Craft Workshops' registrations, supervising preparations that are necessary to the operation of Craft Work-shops, organizing fall and spring workshops, public relations, conferences with Dean Odland, of University of Tennessee, and Marian Heard, Director of Craft Work shop, and all administrative duties, plus supervision of maintenance. Marion Mueller gives many hours of service to keeping the Settlement School project the most respected and valuable fraternity philanthropy. Committee Members: Treasurer, Sally Bozman Schneiter, Indiana Alpha, does a very fine job of keeping Settlement School financial business in order and recorded. Pi Beta Phi is indebted to her for her devoted service. Secretary, Eloise Glazner Hensley, Texas Alpha, records all minutes and acknowledges increased contributions. In addition, Eloise is in charge of publicity and sends out pictures to clubs wishing to use them for publicity. Editor of Little Pigeon News, Sally Wild Gordon, Wisconsin Alpha, does a wonderful job of telling the story of what Settlement School is doing today in her articles in The ARROW. As head of Movies and Slides, Edith Hoyer Rankin, Ohio Beta, distributed films and slides to 65 clubs and chapters during the year. The service was well received. There will be a new set of slides available for the year 1966-67 with emphasis on Settlement School as an Art and Craft Center. We are indebted to Edith for her faithful work. Grand Council Contact Member, Evelyn Peters Kyle, Illinois Alpha, Grand Vice-president of Philanthropies, keeps in close contact with Settlement School Committee. Her cooperation and interest are inspiring to the Comm tee. It is a pleasure to work with her. Transition: 1965-66 was a year of transition duri which the last programs of the former Settlement Schc were phased out. The Jennie Nichol Health Center -a closed in August 1965. All serviceable equipment given to the Sevier County Health Department. The bui ing is now the Pi Beta Phi Office. After being on a yc to year basis since 1963-64, the dormitory program for j nior high and high school students was discontinued the fall of 1965. Settlement School Today: The program of Settleme School is now concentrated on its being an Art and .Cry Center providing facilities to be used for Craft Wor shops. The same amount of financial support is necessai because of increased salaries for personnel and increas maintenance costs. The opportunity offered to students learning skills and techniques which can be used to he others to help themselves is a tremendous contribution our American culture and worthy of support. It is not jt the students who attend who benefit, but all persons wl in turn receive help from these students. Please read t: articleS' in The ARROW to understand how people bene from our philanthropy. It continues to be a rewarding and enjoyable experien for me to serve as Chairman of the Pi Beta Phi Settleme School Committee. I am deeply grateful for this opport nity to be of service to the fraternity. It is stimulating as challenging work. Settlement School Committee is lookil forward to a year of close cooperation with the Centenni Fund Project Committees. DOROTHY COLEMAN THORMAN SETTLEMENT SCHOOL DIRECTOR'S REPORT-JUNE 1965-JULY 1966 In retrospect this fiscal year is undoubtedly one of transition at Settlement School. However, the many memories of constant development at Settlement School as it is today are never to be forgotten. They will be treasured memories of a worthwhile project honoring our. Pi Beta Phi Founders. Chapters could be written about our Health Center and its work through the years, however, after forty-five years the Health Service was discontinued in September 1965. The director's office and assistant's office are now in the Jennie Nichol Building, thus giving more much-needed dormitory space in the former office building. After an equal number of years, or more, the dormitory program was discontinued at the beginning of the school year in 1965. Because one of the students ('64-'65) had counted on being in the dormitory and was stranded financially, a scholarship was given to him throughout the year. His playing all season on the first basketball team was re-warding evidence of helping in need. With the end of the school in May 1966 the hiring of an art and craft and music teacher to supplement the County program was discontinued. Also, the last one-room school in the area was closed September 1965. The County hopes to build an addition of fourteen rooms to supplement the two County buildings at Pi Beta Phi. So, with all the transition, progress enters into the picture. The area could not be considered a poverty area with Gatlin-burg's tourist growth, a new County Hospital, and three new industries in the County. Perhaps you are wondering about the craft growth. That, too, has grown both in our workshops and at Arrowcraft. The twenty-second workshop with the University of Tennessee is in session at this writing. Twenty-nine states and Canada are represented among our personnel. An additional class and a seminar were added this year, hence enrollment has increased. However, until additional dormitory replacement is made, few more can live on cam-pus. Living on campus has its psychological effect with thestudents. It adds school spirit to the student body. It amazing how young and old (yes, the age of seventy considered old by some) intermingle with this commi interest in crafts, "Why do they come ?" is a freque question. Many come to improve their skills as professio als, as hobbyists, to increase their school credit rating just to have the satisfaction of creating something whi may have economic, aesthetic, or utilitarian qualities. Living at Settlement School in the Smokies is an expe. ence for Pi Phis. Gregg Powers Brodie, S.C. Alpha, al Barbara Wehr, Minnesota Alpha, are assisting. Virgir Alpha Scholarship's recipient is Beverly Leigh Lewis, V. ginia Delta. Albuquerque Alumnae Club is again pr viding a scholarship, Martha Dawson the recipient. Hot ton Alumna~ Club is providing their first scholarship Dottie Holmes. "Miss University of Colorado," Kay Ka z1arich, Colorado Alpha, received the Southern Califorr Area Council scholarship. The Buffalo Alumni Cll scholarship recipient is Gladys Del Principe. There a four students working on the Rehabilitation Progra grants. It is my wish that each Pi Phi could attend the E hibit of the students' work. It is not only beautiful b displays excellent workmanship throughout. We shoo give a big "thank you" to our summer workshop direct( Marian Heard, Tennessee Gamma, who has demanded t highest standards of workmanship. Testimonial after tes monial reflects this as the highest attribute of our wor shop. The new pottery wing which was dedicated during Co vention to Lolita Snell Prouty is proving an excellent traction to our campus as well as being most efficient f the teaching of pottery. This is one more deep root in o Craft Program. Another wish which I have made ma: times is that each Pi Phi could see Settlement Schoc especially when a workshop is in session. That was a rand ity for all Convention delegates and visitors who arrive on Sunday for the Reception for Grand Council at Sto House and Tour of the Craft Workshop laboratori </p>
      <pb ref="arri160039_0003" seq="03" n="42-43  "/>
       <p>THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI 'ere there were exhibits and students working. There .s much enthusiasm shown for the development of our aft Program. It is at a Convention when I realize the magnitude of r Pi Phi program. Our program could not continue thout the constant efforts of our volunteer personnel, tional officers, and committees. At Convention one sees extent of the interest in our national project. To see a Dvince Officer's pride over her little handcarved pigeon r pigeons) is rewarding. Yes, it is a privilege to be at ttlement School to witness so much interest of Pi Phis this national project. Each donor (club or individual) is thanked for the re-.pt of the many gifts throughout the year, and again a "thank you" is extended to each for loyalty in any Arrowcraft Shop with Manager Maria Tate, Florida ta, has proof of the loyalty of many industrious Pi Phis :ving as Chairmen of the Arrowcraft sales. Each article .d helps some craftsmen. Even though Arrowcraft is on rkway (the main street) where there are many tourists, is our Alum= Clubs who really increase the grand to s of sales. Weaving is still the specialty of the shop th fifty to sixty weavers working in their homes for 11-time or supplementary remuneration. Our Red Barn serves as an excellent spot for retreats religious, philanthropic, or educational groups, and using of workshop groups. Having a capacity of thirty-o beds, and portables for sixteen more, several groups ve been here many times. We have had adult workshops in recent winters, usually ving classes in jewelry, stitchery, weaving, pottery, and sign. These have proved most popular with locals, how-es, they are paving the way for future seminars or workaps with perhaps groups coming from distant places for !ee days, perhaps a week, to study some group interest. this specialized world there are many possibilities for pansion of our program. Yes, there is a constant challenge for Pi Beta Phi to ex-Id its roots. "Tall men like tall trees need deep roots." e must have deep roots if we expect to have fruit from r trees. MARION W. MUELLER AUDITED FINANCIAL STATEMENTS PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL GATLINBURG, TENNESSEE May 31, 1966 Accountants' Report Beta Phi Settlement School Committee, Beta Phi Settlement School, ,tlinburg, Tennessee. We have examined the balance sheet of Pi Beta Phi ttlement School (a division of Pi Beta Phi) as of May , 1966, and the related statements of income and exnses and fund balances for the year then ended. Our amination was made in accordance with generally eepted auditing standards, and accordingly included eh tests of the accounting records and such other au-:ing procedures as we considered necessary in the cirmstances. In our opinion, the accompanying balance sheet and Ltements of income and expenses and fund balances went fairly the financial position of Pi Beta Phi ttlement School at May 31, 1966, and the results of its erations for the year then ended, in accordance with generally accepted accounting principles applied on a basis consistent with that of the preceding year. Little Rock, Arkansas, August 6, 1966. BALANCE SHEETS PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL MAY 31, 1966, AND MAY 31, 1965 ASSETS 1966 1965 Current Assets Cash $ 26,602.84 $ 21,878.76 Marketable securities at cost 4,400.00 Accounts receivable 9,959.01 9,643.34 Inventories at lower of cost (first in, first-out method) or market 109.799 96,212.12 Prepaid expenses 1,715.09 1, 880.65 TOTAL CURRENT ASSETS Other Assets Land Sale Fund: Cash United States Treasury bills at cost (approximately equal to market) Mortgage note receivable $148,076.58 $134,014.87 17,454.32 274 ,928 .84 16,492.28 $308,875.44 86,317.73 84,835.52 3,460.28 3,302.50 3 ,398.04 3 , 247.48 1,005.00 $403,056.49 $ 91,385.50 297,841.53 297,275.53 61,680.98 58,805.23 1,425.00 1,425.00 $360,947.51 $357,505.76 170,980.51 160,883.07 $189,967.00 $196,622.69 1,521.35 1,521.35 $191,488,35 $198,144.04 12,433.35 $203,921.70 $198,144.04 $755,054.77 $423,544.41 LIABILITIES AND FUND BALANCES 1966 1965 Current Liabilities Accounts payable and accrued ex penses $ 2,156.04 $ 4,899.23 Due to Contingent Fund Pi Beta Phi 10,000.00 9,000.00 TOTAL CURRENT LIABILITIES $ 12,156.04 $ 13,899.23 Fund Balances General Fund 330,410.14 321,185.37 Memorial Fund.. . 396.79 321.79 Brendel Scholarship Fund 3 ,460.28 3,302.50 Endowment Fund 86,317.73 84,835.52 Land Sale Fund 321, 308.79 Library Fund 1,005.00 $742,898.73 $409,645.18 $755,054.77 $423,544.41 Settlement School Endowment Fund equity (10%) in Pi Beta Phi Trust Brendel Scholarship Fund savings account Sinking Fund savings account Library Fund cash Property, Plant, and Equipment On the basis of cost: Buildings and improvements Furniture and equipment Automobiles and trucks Less allowances for depreciation. . Land.... Construction in progress-$31,000 estimated to complete from Land Sale Fund THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI 43 STATEMENT OF FUND BALANCES PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL YEAR ENDED MAY 31, 1966 Balances Excess of Balances June 1-65 Income Over May 31-66 Expenses for the Year General Fund $321,185.37 $ 9,224.77 $330,410.14 Memorial Fund 321.79 75.00 396.79 Brendel Scholarship 3,302.50 157.78 3,460.28 Fund.. . Endowment 84,835.52 1,482.21 86,317.73 Fund Land Sale Fund 321,308.79 321,308.79 Library Fund 1,005.00 1,005.00 $409,645.18 $333,253.55 $742,898.73 STATEMENTS OF INCOME AND EXPENSES PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL YEARS ENDED MAY 31, 1966, AND MAY 31, 1965 1966 1965 Income $ 12,869.46 $ 10,285.56 Contributions: Alumnae clubs Chapters 3,178.00 3,224.87 Alumnae Funds Contingent and 15,500.00 of Pi Beta Phi Individual 1,200.45 647.00 Expenses allocable to Settlement School paid by other Pi Beta Phi funds 21,740.70 Arrowcraft sales, less cost of sales 64,411.17 50,449.06 Magazine commissions 10,647.39 11,279.29 Rents.... . 282.00 330.00 Interest and dividends 7,168.87 3,832.25 Room and board 5,911.41 6,276.02 Summer workshop 23,195.69 17,173.35 Gain on sale of assets 321,369.63 Other 485.32 1,029.70 $487,960.09 $104,527.10 Expenses 71,150.13 72,791.87 Salaries Food 6,598.86 8,449.96 Instructional supplies 3,630.96 4,457.82 Utilities , 6,189.04 6,558.48 Pay roll and property taxes 2,928.19 2,618.67 Committee expense ' 1,580.60 770.83 Insurance 7,958.21 . . 5,449.46 Maintenance, housekeeping, and 15,084.18 12,662.32 office expense Legal and accounting 12,091.83 Other 17,397.10 8,880.42 $144,609.10 $122,639.83 EXCESS (DEFICIT) OF INCOME $343,350.99 ($ 18,112.73) OVER EXPENSES BEFORE DEPRECIATION Depreciation 10,097.44 9,119.72 EXCESS (DEFICIT) OF INCOME $333,253.55 ($ 27,232.45) OVER EXPENSES AUDITED FINANCIAL STATEMENTS PI BETA PHI TRUST TEXARKANA, TEXAS June 30, 1966 Accountants' Report Board of Trustee Funds, Pi Beta Phi Trust, Texarkana, Texas. We have examined the financial statements, resulting from cash transactions, of Pi Beta Phi Trust for the year ended June 30, 1966. Our examination was made in accordance with generally accepted auditing standards, and accordingly included such tests of the accounting records and such other auditing procedures as we considered necessary in the circumstances. In our opinion, the accompanying balance sheet and statements of investment income, principal, and undistributed income present fairly the assets and principal and undistributed income of Pi Beta Phi Trust at June 30, 1966, resulting from cash transactions, and the income collected and expenses disbursed during the year then ended, on a basis consistent with that of the preceding year. Little Rock, Arkansas, July 28, 1966. BALANCE SHEETS PI BETA PHI TRUST JUNE 30, 1966, AND JUNE 30, 1965 ASSETS 1966 1965 Cash $ 37,984.92 $ 3,329.45 Investments at cost (aggregate quoted market prices June 30, 1966 $865, 809.61; June 30, 1965 $963,747.59): U. S. Government obligations 14,902.31 45,591.97 Corporate bonds 485,497.47 545,054.09 Corporate stocks 272,699.91 221,761.18 $773,099.69 $812,407.24 $811,084.61 $815,736.69 PRINCIPAL AND UNDISTRIBUTED INCOME $814,226.99 Principal $809,044.03 Undistributed income 2,040.58 1,509.70 $811,084.61 $815,736.69 STATEMENTS OF PRINCIPAL AND UNDISTRIBUTED INCOME PI BETA PHI TRUST YEAR ENDED JUNE 30, 1966 Principal Arrow General Settlement Fellowship Alumnae Total Endowment Endowment School Endowment Life Fund Fund Endowment Fund Membership Fund Fund Balance at beginning of year $506,048.85 $202,821.56 $84,835.52 $20,258.89 $262.17 $814,226.99 Loss on securities transactions (4,208.77) (1,686.90) (705.63) (168.62) (2.04) (6,771.96) Donations 1,589.00 1,589.00 BALANCE AT END OF YEAR $501,840.08 $201,134.66 $85,718.89 $20,090.27 $260.13 $809,044.03 Undistributed Income Arrow Contingent Settlement Alumnus Publishing Fund School Fund Fund Balance at beginning of year $ 932.48 $ 411.52 $ 165.06 $ .64 Net income from investments 21,379.92 9,425.18 3,579.89 10.13 $ 22,312.40 $ 9,836.70 $ 3,744.95 10.77 Less cash distributions ` ' + . + , 21, 046.63 9,278.81 3,528.65 10.15 BALANCE AT END OF YEAR $ 1,265.77 557.89 216.30 $ .62 Total $ 1,509.70 34,395.12 $ 35,904.82 33,864.24 $ 2,040.58 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



