<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arri140047_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Settlement School</title>
                        <author><name>Thorman, Dorothy Coleman</name></author>
                        <author><name>Mueller, Marion W. </name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Fall 1964</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arri140047_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1964</date>, Settlement School</title>
                        <author><name>Thorman, Dorothy Coleman</name></author>
                        <author><name>Mueller, Marion W. </name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 47-52</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">41</note>
                        <note type="Folder">1</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 1, Number 4 (Fall 1964), Pages 47-52.</note>
			<note type="document">arri140047_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Chairman of Settlement School Committee; Settlement School Director's Report-1964</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Changing Mission of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity for Women in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1944-1964</item>
                                <item>Funding</item>
                                <item>Education</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>
                                <item>Staff</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arri140047_0001" seq="01" n="46-47  "/>
       <p>46 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI Chapter 518 " . ' ' " . ' " .' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " . ' " . ' " . ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' 14.07 .22 6.08 ow 523 Oregon A ..~ . . . ~ 7.82 .08 4.45 3.37 525 Oregon r 2.45 .70 `z .04 526 Oregon xm .00 .00 ' 1.6.70 .26 41.97 531 Washington A 532 Washington B ~ 37.10 .47 51.40 533 Washington r *4.60 .50 33'17 1.43 Alurnnce Club Totals *19r.25 $2m.84 Active Chapter Totals 112.74 137.77 MAGAZINE AGENCY COMMISSIONS Px PROVINCE Club Commission Per CaPita Commission Increase 1963-64 1963-64 1962-63 PI NORTH California) Antelope Valley (Lancaster, '.'."."."."."$ 19.12 ^1.74 $ 7.80 $11.32 70{' 4.30 .05 11.10 7016 Contra Costa, California _ 4.70 18.75 7028 Las Vegas, Nevada ~~~~~~~~~~.~. ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 19.21 -_ ~~ .00 9.67 7032 Marin County, California 17.82 1.39 7036 Monterey Peninsula, California 14.25 .41 9.75 4.50 7040 Palo Alto, California 15.40 .22 12.35 3.05 7044 Reno, Nevada '' ' ' ' ' ' ' '' ' '' ' ' ' ' '' ' '' ' '' ' ' ' ' ' '' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' 10.32 .16 15.04 7048 Sacramento, California 28.09 .36 21.48 6.61 7 7060 San Jose, California 056 14.35 .38 22.45 96.20 2.35 143.35 7064 San Mateo, California . . ' ' . . . ' . .' ' " . ' . . ' 62.43 .85 27.10 35. 7068 Solano County, California . . . ' ' ' ' .' ' " . '" ." . ' ' " 9.60 .69 .00 9.60 7076 Valley of the Moon (Santa ~ ~~~~~) 111.08 3.82 110.33 ^n PI SOUTH 7107 'Covina-Pomona, California 5.20 .27 12.70 7123 Long Beach, California ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' . .' ' ' ' ' ' ' 12.15 .45 14.14 7127 Los Angeles, California. . . 95.62 .64 85.88 um 7129 1.00 8.28 .03 7131 Pasadena, California 158.50 100.70 57.80 7135 Phoenix, Arizona 102.55 .95 52.55 50.00 7139 00 1.50 7143 Riverside, California ' 28.76 1.69 35^9 7151 San Diego, California .' ." . .' . ' ' ' ' ' " . " . ' ' " . ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' 16.29 .19 5.67 10.62 715 28.80 .51 103.30 7159 Santa Barbara, California ' ' " . ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " . ' " . ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' 18.59 .29 16.25 2.34 7163 California Santa Monica-Westside, 160.61 2.36 149.70 10.91 7167 South ' ' . .' ' . ' ' . . ' . ' . ' ' ' 43.43 .75 8.20 35.23 7171 South Coast, California ' ' . . ' " . ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " . ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " . ' ' " . " . ' ' ' ' ' 37.33 .72 42.35 7175 Tucson, Arizona 7.12 .11 14.32 7179 Whittier, California ' ' 40.34 1.09 17.84 22.50 Chapter 550 Arizona A 556 'California ~.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 73.34 .91 46.98 62.12 26.36 557 California r 295.15 4.04 260.11 35.04 558 California A 5 59 California E ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 40.69 146.29 ~3 156.27 560 'California x 38.52 .28 142.87 565 Nevada A 138.83 1.31 189.45 Alumnx Club Totals (north) $ 41 $ 417.32 Se ULM t School CHAIRMAN OF SETTLEMENT SCHOOL COMMITTEE It was the decision of the 1964 convention to accept the recommendation of the Centennial Fund Projects Committee to establish an Arts and Crafts Center on the property now known as Pi Beta Phi Settlement School. Thus, the property of Settlement School will continue to be used as a Memorial to our Founders. This new project will have a new name and will include the present Craft Workshop programs; these will be extended to offer courses in creative crafts, the year round. It will also include the Arrowcraft Shop as it now exists. Settlement School Committee rejoices in this decision to continue to offer educational opportunities. In 1912, the opportunities for education were offered to 12 grade school children. The program has progressed with the changing and growing needs of the community, and to-day, opportunities for education are offered to adults to develop human resources which can be used to meet the needs of our changing society. Virginia Brackett Green, Chairman, 1953-58, said, "Future opportunities at Settlement School thrill me beyond imagination." Helen Moffet Russell, Chairman, 1958-63, said, "The Settlement School is a treasured heritage with a potential yet undreamed and unknown for the future." Pi Beta Phi is now challenged to go "beyond the hill" and explore the potential of the future. This new project will not become effective until 1967. Until that time the present Settlement School program will be continued and will continue to need the same sup-port financially from clubs and chapters. Although, Convention took place in the summer of 1964, it is timely to give a brief report of the Settlement School program. The Arrowcraft exhibit was an artistic and attractive display of Arrowcraft weaving and of crafts. Marion Mueller and Maria Tate were responsible for the exhibit. Because of Canadian regulations, no merchandise could be sold. Club and chapter delegates had an opportunity of seeing the many types of articles that could be ordered. The Settlement School report was given by showing a new movie. This movie was taken in the summer of 1963, during the first session of the summer Craft Workshop. It shows the program of Settlement School today, in de-tail, with emphasis on the Craft Workshop. It includes scenes of Gatlinburg, all Settlement School property and buildings, Arrowcraft Shop and all the activities involved in weaving the articles, from scenes in the homes of the weavers to shipping the finished articles to a club or chapter. One section shows Dormitory students and where they live. Health Center scenes show children receiving inoculations. The last half of the film takes you through the classrooms showing the Craft Workshop students at work in each course that is offered. The wonderful film is available for showing by clubs and chapters. It is a 16mm film, 1300 feet long, showing time 35 minutes. It may be used by writing to Mrs. Allen R. Rankin, 2185 Cambridge Blvd. Columbus 21, Ohio. Pi Beta Phi was hostess to two distinguished guests who were the speakers after the Settlement School Dinner. One was Lura M. Odland, Pr.D., Dean of College of Home Economics, University of Tennessee. She explained the role of the University as co-sponsor with Pi Beta Phi in the Summer Craft Workshop program. The other was Miss Marion G. Heard, M.A., Convention Inittate--1958, Director of Craft Workshop, Professor of Craft Design, the University of Tennessee; she explained the needs of our changing society, with emphasis on automation, increased leisure hours and the need for de-veloping human resources to make people independent and useful citizens. The May L. Keller Award was given to Illinois Epsilon for the most informative and unusual Settlement School program. It emphasizes the Craft Workshop program and its potential. Contributions are the most important and necessary part of maintaining Settlement School. Total contributions from clubs and chapters $15,128.00 Total Magazine Commisions, increased by $649.00 .... 9,000.00 Active contribution, increased by $477.00 3,631.00 Alum= Club contributions, decreased by $677.00 .... 11,497.00 In appreciation for this wonderful support, the Settlement School committee extends a warm thank you to all clubs and chapters, and announces the following winners of Little Pigeon Awards: Chapters with the highest contributions, with the consecutive year of giving over $100.00 indicated by the number in brackets. Nevada A (3) $200.00 Nebraska B (3) $100.00 Texas A (3) 150.00 Illinois Z 87.00 Texas T (9) 150.00 Illinois E 75.00 Missouri B (14) 110.00 Kansas B 75.00 Montana A (2) 100.00 Texas B 75.00 Alabama B (5) 100.00 Honorable mention for the highest contribution to Magazine Agency is awarded to Arizona Alpha. This year the committee wished to give more recognition to clubs giving in proportion to membership. A new policy was adopted to give the awards according to the following classification of membership (the numbers in brackets represent the number of consecutive years of giving over $150) . 10-24 Everett (8) ..$150.00 Youngstown-Warren $107.96 25-49 Contra Costa .$215.00 San Jose $113.00 50-74 PhiladelphiaSanta Monica $100.00 Delco $100.00 North Shore jr $ 75.00 75-100 Arlington Bloomfield Hills $100.00 Heights $100.00 Austin $100.00 Cleveland West $ 80.00 Northern New Jersey $100.00 Champaign Urbana $100.00 Portland $100.00 100 and over Kansas City, Missouri $1000.00 North Shore, Illinois 700,00 Recognition must be given to other clubs making contributions of $150.00 and over: Pasadena (7) $500.00 Houston $200.00 St. Louis (15) $400.00 Los Angeles (2) $200.00 Cleveland East (3) $325.00 Westchester (5) $200.00 Indianapolis (15) $260.00 Provinces with 100% contributions receive the Quiet Pigeon Award: Clubs Chapters Both Alpha Alpha Alpha Beta Beta Beta Gamma Gamma Gamma Eta Delta Delta Theta Epsilon Theta Mu Zeta Mu Xi Theta Xi Pi South Iota Kappa Mu Xi Pi 47 </p>
      <pb ref="arri140047_0002" seq="02" n="48-49  "/>
       <p>THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI Dormitory Program continues to be of valuable imrtance because it is a link between the community and Beta Phi, between the present and the past. Over 665 ys and girls have benefited from this program since it Ls started in 1919. This year 17 boys and girls received 1p and guidance when needed, encouragement to finish pool, and the opportunity to participate in character ilding activities after school. Through the interest of Irian Mueller and Ruth Spelman, house mother for Is, guidance and counciling are given to each student. r. Lewelling, Principal of the Elementary school, said his report, "the three eighth grade pupils living in dormitory continue to receive excellent guidance. The provement is noticeable in their interest in school, tter manners and improved attitude in general." "One y definitely would have been a drop-out had he not red in the dormitory." A dormitory high school senior, to was captain of the High School football team said, could find no better place to better myself and further t education." The students who are accepted to live in a dormitories are recommended by the school staff, and me on a voluntary basis. The fee is $7.00 a month, be-use that is all they can afford to pay. This fee is augmted with several hours a week work for Settlement hool. The girls help with preparing and serving the !als, the boys have out-door assignments. The lasting ect of this kind of an experience in the lives of these ys and girls cannot be measured. There is great need r this program and it is worthy of the support of the tternity. Leah Adams, cook for Staff House personnel d the students, will also continue as matron to the boys. Health Center A new nurse, Nancy Shilling, former dent of Pi Beta Phi School and daughter of Dr. Shill-g, entered the service of Health Center in July, 1964. enda Allison, former nurse, resigned to get other exriences in the field of nursing. She left in Feb. after Le year and two months. Again, our wonderful friend, e former nurse Marjorie Chalmers, Illinois B.D. rerned to add 5 more months of service to her previous years. We are deeply indebted to her for her willingss to fill in and to continue to offer services which are important to the community. The summary of the work this fiscal year is as follows: CLASS OF WORK !ld visits 93 Tice calls 3891 vice given 3599 tal Triple Vaccine: Diphtheria, Whooping Cough, Tetanus 322 mpleted series and boosters 187 Ho Prevention Salk 59 Ho Prevention Sabin 141 tanus Toxoid 322 tal Typhoid Inoculations 379 mpleted series and boosters 274 erapeutic Inoculations 153 berculin tests 312 est X Rays 736 ysical examinations 631 diometer tests .. . 177 ;ion tests (Lions Club) 443 Scher-nurse conferences 159 nily Conferences 113 alth talks 8 wspaper articles 4 The community depends on the Health Center being e to provide indigent families with clothes for chil-!n of all ages. Nancy Shilling understands this need i already has had many requests for shoes, in particu-. Children go bare-foot all summer in the mountains, )es are the greatest need. Boys pants are always a welne gift. Nancy has given three layettes for babies and exhausted her supply, particularly that of diapers. )then are put to good use and will be welcomed. Ad-!ss the box to Jennie Nicol Health Center, Pi Beta Phi tlement School, Gatlinburg, Tenn. The well-baby lic is very popular on Friday afternoons. An impor-tant service is the spring round-up for the pre-school child. This May, 54 children and 5 3 mothers attended. Teachers provided by Pi Beta Phi to improve the rating of the school are for music and art and crafts. Last year two excellent teachers provided the children with rich experiences in these subjects. They are going on to new experiences and are to be replaced by Nancy Thomas, who will teach music and Mrs. Joan Oakley who will teach art and crafts. Red Barn, besides providing a dormitory for 32 students during the Summer Craft Workshop, is widely used by groups on week ends, during the rest of the year. The red barn facilities are offered to religious, philanthropic and educational groups for meetings, and to Pi Beta Phi chapters for retreats. There is a nominal rental fee to cover maintenance. Arrowcraft The Settlement School Committee extends its appreciation to all clubs and chapters for their continued support of Arrowcraft by providing a market through sales. The 1963-64 report shows a decrease of $7000.00 in the sales of Arrowcraft weaving. We urge Pi Phis to promote the sale of weaving articles in order that we can continue to give employment to the 60 or 70 weavers who depend on this home industry for economic support. Several new items have been added to the price list. These include: a new bag, and a new towel in bright colors, a one color pot holder, a new mat, called Bow Knot, a change in the colors of stoles and in afghans. The largest sales are still up on the old items: the daisy chain mat 7,199, Whig Rose mats 7,632, hot pads 13,356, and tote bags 4,012. Sales in crafts were up. Sales in the two Arrowcraft shops were up. WE are looking for an increase in club sales this year, because many large orders are already in for fall sales. Our Weaving Designer and Supervisor, Corinne Purdom, left to live in California. Marion Mueller is looking for a replacement. It is important that the applicant know weaving design and the many needs for putting an article into production. Again, our Auditors have pointed out that accounts receivable are much too high. We are asked to make the clubs aware of their responsibility to pay the bills within 60 days. A red sticker will be placed on a notice that will be sent out after the 60 day allowance expires, to remind treasurers of the need for payment. We are extremely proud to report that 31 clubs bought and paid for one thousand dollars and more of Arrow-craft and Crafts during the last fiscal year. Soaring Pigeon Awards were given to the 10 chapters with the highest remittances for purchases from Arrow-craft Shop. New York A $320.00 New York $225.00 Maryland B 296.00 Pennsylvania B 222.00 South Dakota A 276.00 North Carolina B 161.00 Alabama I' 250.00 Virginia r 160.00 Connecticut A 248.00 Vermont A 145.00 In order to give recognition to clubs in proportion to their membership, the policy was adopted to give the Little Pigeon Awards to clubs on the basis of the following classification of Membership: 10-24 50-74 Jefferson City $1,816.00 Akron $2,101.00 Everett 1,194.00 Pittsburgh South Hills 1,938.00 25-49 75-99 Stillwater 1,617.00 Champaign-Urbana .. 3,488.00 Grand Rapids 1,278.00 Bloomfield Hills .... 1,167.00 100 and over Houston $2,765.00 Columbus 1,911.00 To keep up the "friendly competition" tradition which has been recorded for many years, it only seemed fair to give a complete list of all clubs which have faithfully THE ARROW OF P1 BETA PHI 49 bought and paid for at least one thousand dollars worth of Arrowcraft articles, in the past fiscal year. Oklahoma $1,908.00 Ann Arbor $1,166.00 Kansas City, Mo 1,826.00 Milwaukee 1,159.00 Detroit 1,798.00 Seattle 1,142.00 Arlington Heights . 1,545.00 Nancy Black Wallace 1,141.00 North Shore 1,445.00 Manchester 1,095.00 South Bend 1,408.00 New Haven 1,092.00 Cincinnati 1,403.00 Fayetteville 1,080.00 Pittsburgh 1,314.00 Berkeley 1,072.00 Philadelphia Cleveland East 1,029.00 Main Line 1,299.00 Chicago West La Fayette 1,228.00 Suburban 1,022.00 Rochester 1,199.00 Many clubs are following the practice of adding the cost of shipping to the price of the article when sold. Most customers are willing to absorb this cost because the merchandise is of such superior quality and fairly priced. Arrowcraft is very fortunate to have Maria Tate, Florida Beta, as manager. She cheerfully goes about her work keeping up the inventories, corresponding with Chapters and Clubs and managing the shop. Elizabeth Rue, Iowa Gamma, enjoys her work as manager of the Mountain View Hotel shop. Fay Cook is head of shipping and is happy when the orders are large. Nella Cook is assistant to the Weaving Designer and Supervisor; at present, she is taking over the responsibility of Weaving Supervisor. Jean Hemtree assists Fay Cook with shipping and is a sales girl in the shop. June Cook, now Mrs. Parrott, is a sales girl, Shirley Roberts has resigned to have a baby and Ruby Watson has returned to take her place. These employees are very competent workers; we appreciate their loyalty to Arrowcraft Shop. Eunice Cole has retired, as bookkeeper, Mrs. Grace Patterson is taking her place. We are happy to welcome her. It is the continued support of chapters and clubs that makes our Arrowcraft shop the most unique project sponsored by a fraternity. Craft Workshops Please read the report of Marion Mueller, the Director of Settlement School, for a complete picture. Have you seen the article in the April issue of Banta's Greek Exchange? The title is "Pi Beta Phi's Renowned Craft Workshop." Look it up and read it to your club or chapter, you will burst with pride. The co-sponsored Pi Beta Phi and University of Tennessee Craft Workshop is a unique association of a University and a fraternity; it is a compliment to the high level of achievement that is available through this pro-gram. Craft Workshop has been a success for twenty years; it was started in 1945 and has come to have national and inter-national recognition because of the outstanding per-son who is Director, Marion G. Heard. In Marion, Pi Beta Phi and the University of Tennessee have a crafts-man of national and international renown in the related field of arts and crafts. She is United States Representative to the World's Congress of Craftsmen. She is a member of the Board of Trustees of the American Crafts Council. Pi Beta Phi is indebted to her for her fine leadership for 19 successful years. Much credit also goes to her assistant, Betty Street, M.S. Assistant Professor, University of Illinois, and the excellent staff of talented instructors. Courses are offered in Jewelry, Weaving, Tex-tile Design, Enameling, Recreational Crafts, Pottery, and Craft Design. A large inventory, from which materials may be chosen, as well as excellent equipment add to the success of this project. The Virginia Alpha Scholarship winner was Mary Gregg Powers, South Carolina Alpha. Louise Bandy, Georgia Alpha, was a winner of an Assistant Work Scholarship. Southern California Council Area Scholarship winner was Grace Aldrich, Oregon Beta. Other members of Pi Beta Phi who attended Craft Workshop in 1964 were: Helen Russell, Illinois Eta; Carolyn Vaught, North Carolina Alpha; Mrs. Gladys Olds, Oregon Beta; Louise Clark, Mass. Alpha. Gifts and Legacies The DeCastello Estate legacy of $2000.00 was given in honor of Anna Mally DeCasteel, charter member of Iowa Sigma, by her daughter. The Pittsburgh Club gift of $1000.00 honoring Marie B. Davidson (Mrs. Paul B.) was used to build a beautiful bookcase in the Staff House lounge to hold the Grace Coolidge Collection. It also provided funds that were used to redecorate the lounge, upholster some of the furniture, and buy new draperies. The lounge will now be called the Marie B. Davidson Lounge with the Grace Coolidge Collection. This collection consists of books, those given in the name of Grace Coolidge, new books on Crafts and several handcrafted works of art. The West Suburban Club of Chicago is giving a piece of woodcarving, that will be done by Ronnie Moore, a craftsman who went to Pi Beta Phi School. He was given the Alspaugh scholarship to encourage his interest in arts and crafts. This work will be in memory of Mr. Robert C. Trow, husband of Julia J. Trow, Kansas Beta. Mr. Trow was an artist. Several beautiful gifts of silver were given to Staff House: A silver creamer and sugar and tray were given by Ruth Spelman, Illinois Epsilon, in memory of her mother and aunt (Grand Treasurer) who were members of I. C. Sorosis. A silver coffee pot (to match above) was given by the Columbus, Ohio, Panhellenic. It was selected by Edith Hoyer Rankin, in memory of her daugher Mildred Rankin Rader, Ohio Beta. Many boxes of clothes were send from clubs to Health Center, the largest gift came from the San Jose club of California. Books, from many Pi Phis, trading stamps, Christmas gifts and money, Magazine subscriptions, toilet articles for Health Center are a part of the many gifts so gratefully received by Settlement School. The Memorial Fund gifts totaled $276.49. All gifts are put to very good use and will always be welcome. General Information Everything was done to keep the standard of maintenance high. The three maintenance men, Neal Watson, Richard Watson and Zanley Watson take great pride in their responsibilities to Settlement School. The farm business has been discontinued and now the property has the look of a well groomed park. The members of the staff have cooperated with the Southern Highland Guild in many ways: as hostesses to their fall meeting; as workers in setting up the Crafts-man's Fair in the fall; as hostessess at the Festival of Crafts in Knoxville, in the spring. The Fraternity is indebted to Marion Mueller, Indiana Gamma, for her loyal and devoted service as Director of Settlement School. Her interest in the Dormitory program and the school activities, makes her a valuable person to the community. A great deal of the success of Summer Craft Workshop is due to her work as registrar, to supervising the preparations that are necessary to its operation, and especially her faith in its future. The winter workshops are completely organized and administered by Marion. She gives many long hours to keeping the Settlement School project the most respected and valuable fraternity philanthropy. Committee Lois Summers, Secretary, has completed her five years of service to the Settlement School Committee; we are sorry to lose her. The new member appointed in her place is Edith Hoyer Rankin, Ohio Beta. We welcome Edith and are pleased that she has accepted the responsibility for distributing Slides and Movies. Eloise Hensely will now be the Secretary, after a busy year of circulating slides to 80 chapters and clubs. Publicity Editor of "Little Pigeon News," Sally Wild Gordon, will continue to send news from Settlement School. The treasurer, Sally Bosman Schneiter, and her husband are Pi Phi Angels. They do a terrific job of keeping our financial business in order and recorded. We are grateful </p>
      <pb ref="arri140047_0003" seq="03" n="50-51  "/>
       <p>50 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI to them for their work for Settlement School. Grand Treasurer, Olivia Smith Moore, has been a loyal member of the committee; she is always ready to give advice and guidance when needed. Thank you, Miss Olivia. The new organization plan adopted at convention places the Settlement Committee under the direction of the Grand Vice President of Philanthropies, Evelyn Peters Kyle. We welcome her to the committee. The Settlement School has been instrumental in mak-ing Gatlinburg a major Craft Center and a leading area for hand weaving in this country. Pi Beta Phi contributes to the Culture of America, through the promotion of Arts and Crafts. It has been a rewarding and enjoyable experience for me to serve as Chairman of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School Committee. I am deeply grateful for this opportunity to be of service to the Fraternity. DOROTHY COLEMAN THORMAN, Chairman SETTLEMENT SCHOOL DIRECTOR'S REPORT-1964 Our Settlement School is nestled in the foothills of the Smokies in the heart of Gatlinburg. The city limits have been extended to include a population which now totals 2,303. Along with other manifestations of growth motel and restaurant accommodations for the thousands of tourists and entertainment for all ages our school has its roots deeper in the craft field. It is amazing to see students come from afar twentyseven states and five foreign countries were represented in the 1964 Pi Beta Phi-University of Tennessee Craft Workshop and to see them become so engrossed in their respective crafts. The exhibit on the last night is evidence of much effort during a brief time. 1964 was my twelfth summer to witness and participate in this event, and truth-fully, each year is increasingly more thrilling hence more rewarding to me. Fourteen Pi Phis were here, either as students or on the staff . Several have vowed to return and to spread the word so others can take advantage of this opportunity to study crafts, to increase one's skill, and to live at Settlement School in the Srnokies. In late winter a letter with the brochure for the current summer workshop is sent to each active chapter and alumni club as listed in Central Office. If, for any reason, yours was not received kindly notify my office. Hours, days, and years are spent in planning our program, so we wish all Pi Phis to be informed. Marian Heard who has served most capably as director for eighteen summers is constantly planning for a "bigger and better" workshop. Nothing could vie with the superlative natural beauty of the area; however, the crafts are a close second. Pi Beta Phi participates in the Southern Highland Handicraft Guild Fair in October (with paid admissions over 14,000 in five days). Last winter there were adult classes in de-sign, pottery, silk screen, block print, and jewelry. The interest is growing, yes, it's contagious! Pi Phis should be proud of the foresight of our members who recognized the potentialities of our program. Arrowcraft with its specialty of weaving (providing an outlet for over sixty weavers throughout the year) and a sales outlet for other craftsmen is outstanding in the craft field. At first crafts were made only by the mountaineers. Now there is a happy intermingling of the college-trained and the mountaineer. It is no secret that our Pi Beta Phi Alumnae Clubs are the biggest outlet for Arrow-craft. This is a Pi Phi project. Every Pi Phi should burst with pride over this national memorial to our Founders. The Settlement School Staff is most appreciative of each bit of thoughtfulness and efforts of our members. We salute you! The gift list is evidence of the loyalty of many members. As each gift is made a thank-you note is sent immediately. However, again I wish to thank all donors and to emphasize that this is your project; yes, the project of Pi Beta Phi. For staff members it is a privilege to participate and to work with so many loyal members. Our Health Center has the usual routine with preventive inoculations and first-aid. Our nurse heading the Center is Nancy Shilling, a recent graduate and daughter of a local physician. Having been reared in the Burg it isa compliment to the school that she would choose home territory. Pi Phi again had the music and craft instruction for grades 1-8. Nancy Thompson, a graduate of Maryville College, will teach music in 1964-65. Joan Oakley will teach crafts. Our most intangible activity at Settlement School is the dormitory program; yet, seeing the development of the boys and girls is believing. Improvements in standards in daily life and school are difficult to measure. Our housemother, Ruth Spelman (Illinois Epsilon) and others who work closely with the children can testify to much benevolence. In the school year of 1963-64 we had eleven boys and seven girls with a few subsequent dropouts. The dormitory program has proved to be a most rewarding challenge to me. Lela Adams again served as cook and housemother to the boys. Neal Watson heads the maintenance. Zanley Watson can serve equally well in plumbing, electricity, or something mechanical. Richard Watson's specialty is gardening, however, he is on call for extra lifting or moving, or as an extra hand on a paint or carpenter job. Orlie Watson's recent years have been on semi-retirement. Living on the place, he is on call for emergencies which have a way of coming at night. Elizabeth Rue, Iowa Gamma, continues as manager of the Mountain View Arrowcraft Shop with limited retirement hours. Maria Tate, Florida Beta, will soon conclude her second year as Arrowcraft manager. She will correspond with the many Alumna Club chairmen in charge of Arrowcraft sales. Grace Patterson came recently to replace Eunice Cole, now retiring. Eunice has served as book-keeper most capably for many years at Arrowcraft. Nadine Grooms Whitted serves as secretary to the di-rector. As projects at Settlement School develop the di-rector's office work increases accordingly. Actually that day for "just loafing" never arrives. In conclusion my personal comment must be made regarding the Convention Centennial decision at Victoria. To say I am pleased is an understatement. However, since our program at Settlement School becomes more and more entrenched in crafts, the decision seemed to be most logical. How fortunate Pi Phi is to have the roots so deep in the craft field so there can be participation in the American Craft program in this expanding spectrum. The May/ June 1964 issue of The American Craftsmen sums up authentically their position as follows: "The rise of the American craftsman, in the most highly industrialized nation in the history of man, is the paradoxical expression of an abundant society's needs for more than functional necessities, of its drive to humanize and individualize against the homogenizing pressures of mass production, and of its rich artistic growth, accelerated and matured through the internationalizing forces of communication. The American craftsman has created an entirely unprecedented situation a prolific and vigorous handcraft culture within the structure of industrial power." Respectfully submitted, MARION W. MUELLER, Director Pi Beta Phi Settlement School THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI 5 Accountants' Report Pi Beta Phi Settlement School Committee, Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, Gatlinburg, Tennessee. We have examined the balance sheet of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School as of May 31, 1964, and the related statements of income and expenses and fund balances for the year then ended. Our examination was made in accordance with generally accepted auditing standards and, except that we did not observe the procedures employed in ascertaining inventory quantities at May 31, 1963, or make tests of the valuation thereof, it included such tests of the accounting records and such other auditing procedures as we considered necessary in the circumstances. In our opinion, the accompanying balance sheet presents fairly the financial position of Pi Beta Phi Settlement School at May 31, 1964, in accordance with generally accepted accounting principles applied on a basis consistent with that of the preceding year. As the scope of our examination did not include observance of the inventory-taking at May 31, 1963, or tests of the valuation thereof, and as we were unable to satisfy ourselves by other means as to the amount at which the inventory was stated at May 31, 1963, we are not in a position to express an opinion upon the accompanying statements of income and expenses and fund balances. ERNST and ERNST Little Rock, Arkansas, September 15, 1964. BALANCE SHEETS PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL MAY 31, 1964, AND MAY 31, 1963 AssETs Current Assets 1964 1963 Cash $ 30,423.50 $ 30,201.E Marketable securities at cost (market value $7,150.00 at May 31, 1964, and $7,177.50 at May 31, 1963) 4,400.00 4,400.0 Accounts receivable 11,399 .46 9,612.S Inventories at lower of cost (first-in, first-out basis) or market 100,314.85 98,107.1 Prepaid expenses 1,975.09 2,574..'. TOTAL CURRENT ASSETS $148,512.90 $144,896.4 Other Assets 83,336.25 81 ,628.( Settlement School Endowment Fund equity (10%) in Pi Beta Phi Trust Brendel Scholarship Fund savings 3,270.37 3,260.( account Sinking Fund savings account 3,121.37 3 ,000.( $ 89,727.99 $ 87,888.1 Property, Plant, and Equipment 297,107.37 296,720. On the basis of cost: Buildings and improvements Furniture and equipment 57,730.66 56,217.1 Automobiles and trucks 1,425.00 1,425.( $356,263.03 $354,363.( Less allowances for depreciation 151, 763.35 142,620.1 $204,499.68 $211,742. Land 1,521.35 1,521.; $206,021.03 $2137264-: $444,261.92 $446,049.: LIABILITIES AND FUND BALANCES 1964 1963 Current Liabilities Accounts payable and accrued expenses $ 2,384.29 $ 2,617. Due to Contingent Fund Pi Beta Phi 5,000.00 5 ,000., $ 7,384.29 $ 7,617. Fund Balances General Fund 349 ,994 .22 353,411. Memorial Fund 276.79 131. Brendel Scholarship Fund 3,270.37 3,260. Endowment Fund 83,336.25 81,628. $436,877.63 $438,431. $444,261.92 $446,049. (Continued on the next page) </p>
      <pb ref="arri140047_0004" seq="04" n="52-53  "/>
       <p>52 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI STATEMENTS OF INCOME AND EXPENSES AND FUND BALANCES PI BETA PHI SETTLEMENT SCHOOL YEARS ENDED MAY 31, 1964, AND MAY 31, 1963 Income and Expenses 1964 1963 income $ 12,175.24 Contributions: Alumnae $ 11,497.33 Chapters 3,662.50 3,136.55 Individual 2,432.90 3,508.25 Alumnae Fund 11,000.00 155.00 Health Center Arrowcraft sales, less cost of sales 60,294.25 64,050.94 Magazine commissions 13,986.81 8,351.70 Rents 780.83 527.00 Interest and dividends 3,740.05 4,219.42 Room and board 7,047.60 6,304.45 Farm produce sales 1,313.60 Summer workshop 12,209.90 17,463.25 Other 360.44 1,123.12 $127,012.61 $122,328.52 Fxpenses 66,904.26 Salaries 74,043.41 Food and farm expense 8,849.55 9,690.95 Instructional supplies 2,479.12 4,255.39 Utilities 6,823.11. 7,226.53 Pay roll taxes 2,522.98 2,169.04 Committee expense 1,615.27 1,472.55 Insurance 5,977.82 4,839.32 Maintenance, housekeeping, and office expense 9,341.22 9,836.80 Other 7,770.90 11,239.49 $119,423.38 $117,634.33 EXCESS OF INCOME OVER EXPENSES BEFORE DEPRECIATION $ 7,589.23 $ 4,694.19 Depreciation 9,143.24 9,088.96 EXCESS OF EXPENSES OVER INCOME ($ 1,554.01) ($ 4,394.77) Fund Balances Balances Excess (Deficit) Transfers Balances June 1-63 of Income Over May 31-64 Expenses for the Year General Fund $353,411.47 ($3 ,517.25) $ 100.00 $349,994.22 Memorial Fund 131.49 145.30 276.79 Brendel Scholarship Fund 3,260.03 110.34 (100.00) 3,270.37 Endowment Fund 81,628.65 1,707.60 83,336.25 $438,431.64 ($1,554.01) -0 $436,877.63 Standing Committeei HOLT HOUSE Holt House and all who use it are bursting with pride at its new "old" look, and are eagerly anticipating many visitors. Since May 1963 the music room, Pine room, parlor and hall have been refurbished. The music room and Pine room were the first to get new paper, paint and curtains. This spring the parlor welcomed the same treatment and the stairway and downstairs hall received a new carpet. The committee met "informally" in the fall, and architect, Robert Mann, submitted a recommendation for a long term plan for the repairs on the house and grounds. This was presented to Grand Council in November, and won their approval. Several landscape firms in the Galesburg area are making plans and estimates for landscaping the grounds. Our goal is to have the house and grounds in tip top shape by the Centennial in 1967. Much work re-mains to be done in the next two and one half years. Jo Boydstun, our treasurer, reports a spring lag in contributions, but May is always the big month so we hope we will at least equal and perhaps exceed last year by having 100% support from all the chapters and clubs. Those who have been fortunate enough to have visited Holt House are most enthusiastic. I'm sure if each Pi Phi had that opportunity, her heart would swell with pride knowing that the preservation of this lovely old home ex-presses to Pi Phis as well as the general public the wonderful heritage of our founding. Holt House continues in its service to the community. From May 1, 1963, through April 1964 there were 111 functions, and only 19 of these were for Pi Phis. In October 1963 the committee voted to raise the fees, effective Jan. 1, 1964. This is the first time they have been raised in many years, but we felt the small increase was not out of line with the many improvements that have been made. The specific changes are as follows: Special fees to Pi Phi individuals: Wedding, changed from $10.00 to $12.50 Reception $10.00 to $12.50 Wedding and reception $15.00 to $20.00 Regular schedule of fees: Meeting with tea or light refreshment $5.00 to $7.50 Meeting with meal (food prepared elsewhere) $7.00 to $10.00 Meeting with meal (food prepared at H.H.) $12.00 to $15.00 COMMITTEE Meeting with meal prepared at H.H. and over 50 people $20.00 (no change) Wedding $15.00 to $20.00 Reception or tea $20.00 to $25.00 Wedding and reception 425.00 to $35.00 If used both afternoon and night $40.00 . (no change) The Westchester Alumni Club of Scarsdale, New York sent a beautiful sterling silver sandwich plate in memory of Marjorie Lee Fritz, great granddaughter of Jennie Home Turnbull. The Cleveland East and Cleveland West Alumnae Clubs sent $20.00 in honor of Miss Jacquelyn Mayer who was Miss America. Mrs. Margaret T. Schoonover, Iowa Alpha and Mrs. Lavanda Carr Zoeckler, Iowa Zeta, sent a silver plated fruit dish with handle and the initials I. C. engraved in the center of the bowl. It had been a gift to Mrs. Schoonover's mother, Hattie Gassner Torrence, Iowa Alpha, in 1882. The Senior Alumni Club of Milwaukee sent a pewter bowl in memory of Florence Bird Jackson of Iowa Zeta. The Des Moines Alumna club gave $100.00 for the chandelier fund. Pi Province sent eight green stamp books, and Mrs. Jessie Hamilton French gave $35.00 for the chandelier fund. Mrs. Jerome L. Anderson of Hunter, Oklahoma has offered a small collection of old spoons that are 150 years old. The committee wishes to express its deep appreciation and sincere thanks to all the above for their thoughtful gifts and memorials. Has your chapter or club seen the slides recently? They make a most interesting and informative program. Why not schedule them for 1964-65? We expect to have new slides of the rooms that have been redecorated. This last year has been an interesting and rewarding one for all of the committee. I wish to thank each one for their understanding and support. Cleone Rawson, our Monmouth member, has done an outstanding job in supervising the redecorating and taking care of the myriad-small items that always abound in such a project. Dorothy Morgan, as our liaison officer with Grand Council, has been a wonderful inspiration to us all. It has been a great privilege and a pleasure to serve on the Holt House committee. Respectfully submitted, SHIRLEY JONES MANN, Chairman Holt House Committee ANNUAL REPORT HOLT HOUSE TREASURER 1963 1964 Balance on hand June 1, 1963 $3,461.31 Receipts Contributions from chapters and clubs 4,235.10 Half revenue and sale of etchings 362.75 Houston Mothers' Club 5.00 $8,064.16 Disbursements Hostess' salary $ 936.32 Illinois Power Co 515.92 Insurance 147.50 House tax 397.92 Central Office for hostess' SS and WH taxes Committee expense (meeting, chairman's petty cash, stamps for treasurer) 93.28 Bank service charges 4.61 Authorized work on house: Painting porch, cement work 162.79 Patching, papering, and painting in music room 546.31 Carpentery in music room 171.99 Van Tine Decorators 158.91 Morton Interiors 2,307.89 Repairing windows, piano bench, doors, fixing lights 46.26 Laying carpet 52.48 Shortening drapes, new traverse rods 21.93 $3,468.56 53 </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



