<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arri110029_0000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
			<title>Settlement School Report</title>
                        <author><name>Russell, Hellen Moffett</name></author>
                        <author><name>Mueller, Marion W.</name></author>
                        <respStmt>
                             <resp>Responsible for TEI creation from MODS, image and OCR'd text files</resp>
                             <name>DeRidder, Jody</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
		    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Pi Beta Phi Fraternity</publisher>
                        <series>The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi</series>
		        <date>Fall 1961</date>
		        <idno type="SPCID">arri110029_0000</idno>
		        <availability>
	        	 <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.
</p>
		        </availability>
	            </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
	              <bibl>
                        <title><date value="">1961</date>, Settlement School Report</title>
                        <author><name>Russell, Hellen Moffett</name></author>
                        <author><name>Mueller, Marion W.</name></author>
                        <extent>Pages 29-33</extent>
                        <note type="collection">Pi Beta Phi Fraternity Archives, St. Louis, Missouri</note>
                        <note type="Box">40</note>
                        <note type="Folder">14</note>
                        <note type="Citation">The Arrow of Pi Beta Phi, Volume 1, Number 1 (Fall 1961), Pages 29-33.</note>
			<note type="document">arri110029_0000</note>
                        <note type="Table Of Contents">Settlement School Committee, Settlement School Director's Report</note>

	              </bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
                   <projectDesc>
                       <p>Created for the Great Smoky Mountains Arrowmont project.</p>
                   </projectDesc>
                   <editorialDecl n="1">
                       <p>TEI body is composed of OCR'd text files with no editorial tags.</p>
                       <p>Non-ascii characters have been removed.</p>
                       <p>No presentation tags have been added, apart from a paragraph for each page.</p>
                   </editorialDecl>
                   <classDecl>
                        <taxonomy>
                             <bibl> 
                               Subjects assigned are chosen from a list designed for the Arrowmont project.  This controlled vocabulary list may be viewed at http://idserver.utk.edu?id=200700000000593.
                             </bibl>
                        </taxonomy> 
                      </classDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                    <profileDesc>
                       <textClass>
                           <keywords>
                              <list>
                                <item>Changing Mission of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity for Women in Gatlinburg, Tennessee, 1944-1964</item>
                                <item>Funding</item>
                                <item>Arrowcraft</item>
                                <item>Staff</item>

                              </list>
                           </keywords>
                       </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
             </teiHeader>
	     <text>
             <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
      <pb ref="arri110029_0001" seq="01" n="28-29  "/>
       <p>28 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI Club No. PI PROVINCE Commissions Commissions Earned Per Earned Capita Last Year 1960-61 1959-60 Commissions Earned Name of Club or Chapter 1960-61 1604 Berkeley, Calif $ 13.85 $ .14 $ 7.18 1605 Stockton, Calif 3.85 21 6.15 1606 Centinela. Valley, Calif 5.25 .23 14.45 1608 Contra Costa, Calif 6.00 .38 7.22 1610 Fresno, Calif 1.10 .04 3.79 1622 Long Beach, Calif 40.91 .74 54.42 1624 Los Angeles, Calif 158.29 .84 154.75 1626 Marin County 18.75 .33 27.76 1628 Palo Alto, California 24.00 .27 25.65 1630 Pasadena, California 145.55 .67 151.94 1632 Phoenix, Arizona 30.13 .50 34.09 1634 Reno, Nev 19.78 .25 13.47 1636 Sacramento, Calif 31.36 .43 38.41 1640 San Diego, Calif. ... . 41.52 .42 2.39 1642 San Fernando, Calif 77.49 1.31 108.84 1643 Whittier Area 22.10 .58 15.22 1644 San Francisco, Calif 36.37 .52 38.67 1646 San Jose, Calif 185.99 7.75 184.45 1648 San Mateo, Calif 21.25 .53 28.49 1650 Santa Barbara, Calif 27.26 .78 35.03 1652 Santa Monica, Calif 158.84 2.84 177.60 1654 Solona County .75 1655 South Bay, Calif 31.07 .74 46.20 1656 South Coast 22.24 .49 40.63 1658 Tucson, Ariz_ 35.52 .44 37.60 1660 Valley of the Moon 157.95 6.08 181.44 1663 Covina-Pomona, Calif 15.36 .50 10.45 1664 Antelope Valley 24.82 1.91 40.93 1665 Riverside, Calif 32.01 1.19 20.60 1668 Monterey Peninsula, Calif 13.35 .61 _ California B 95.05 1.67 136.56 California r 173.11 2.84 131.10 California A 78.36 2.31 81.57 California E 119.30 5.19 149.89 California Z 93.97 1.81 76.26 Nevada A 52.46 1.59 34.77 Arizona A 93.92 1.65 138.19 TOTAL FOR PI PROVINCE FOR YEAR 1960-61 $2,108.13 Pi Province Alumnie Club Commissions $1,401.96 Pi Province Active Chapter Commissions 706.17 $2,108.13 ttfement School leeport SETTLEMENT SCHOOL COMMITTEE The Pi Beta Phi Settlement School was 49 years old this past year and that means the 50th birthday is just over the horizon ! The fraternity will officially commemorate the Golden Anniversary of the Settlement School at the 1962 Convention in Washington, D.C., the place where the idea for it was originally conceived. Actually, the date of February 20, 1912 marks the day when Pi Beta Phi started its first class for 14 curious students of as-sorted ages in the tiny, isolated, mountain community called Gatlinburg. From that small beginning, the growth of the school and related settlement endeavors moved for-ward steadily until now it is truly an impressive place, serving in both old and new ways as a living Memorial to the Founders of Pi Beta Phi should serve. It is a bit difficult to concentrate on a year that has gone past when such an important celebration year is immediately ahead. Yet, those who do take the time to read to the end this and the Director's report may find some interesting facets of our national philanthropy to evaluate. 50 years of living gives anyone pause, and it is a good time to evaluate the heritage of those years for one's posterity. It is a good time to weigh the present status that has been attained, and to consider possibilities and probable strengths for further effective work and service. When the Settlement School began in 1912, it was a single classroom for elementary age children only. Today, its influences are far, far broader than that, even though the original name has been retained intact. It is tragic that not all Pi Phis know the areas of work at the Settlement School today, and it is hoped that an annual re-port enlightens in regard to both problems and accomplishments. The Educational Program at the Pi Beta Phi Elementary and High Schools is in the beginning stage of several possible future changes. As a result of a Sevier County School Survey made last year by the State Department of Education, there is considerable county-wide, citizen interest in the many recommendations made by the survey team. Some of these are short-range, including such improvements as the installation of panic doors and safety glass, chalk and tack boards, and more adequate storage 'space. Other recommendations are long-range, involving consolidations, improved teacher accreditation, better teacher salaries, more advanced course offerings for the able students, and the like. Of interest to the fraternity is the recommendation to consolidate Pi Beta Phi High School with Pitman Center High School at a new site between the present two schools, and, if this is done, the expansion of the elementary school into the vacated high school building to relieve crowding in the lower grades. It is anticipated that several years of citizen effort will be required for any consolidation procedure to be effected; there are many preliminary decisions to be made before any specific planning can start. It should be understood that the fraternity is not directly involved in any decisions at the present time, for since 1943 the Sevier County Board of Education has been operating the Pi Beta Phi School (grades 1-12) under a lease agreement for the fraternity's grounds and buildings. Since that date also, the fraternity has been augmenting the minimum county program by providing several teachers' and classes which otherwise would be omitted from the curriculum. There were 622 students enrolled at Pi Beta Phi under the direction of 26 teachers this past year. Approximately 60% of the students were transported to and from school by bus, and of these about three-fourths live more than a mile and a half away. The Pi Beta Phi School serves a widearea far beyond the confines of Gatlinburg. Subject matter requirements were met in all grades, and the Pi Beta Phi offerings helped to maintain an A rating. Mrs. Enloe will continue the music classes in the elementary grades and the glee club classes in the high school. There were choruses for grades 5-6 and 7-8, and all music students participated in several school and public programs throughout the year. Mr. Carl Huskey will continue his classes in woodworking for junior and senior boys. He should be complimented for having so many accident-free years in his classes. It is a pleasure to welcome a Pi Phi to the teaching staff provided by the fraternity, and to wish Margaret Struble, Iowa Gamma, a most happy and successful year. She will be teaching the Art and Crafts classes in grades 1-12. The Craft Workshop, sponsored each summer by the University of Tennessee and the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School, had a record enrollment of 133 students for courses offered at the 1961 session. Students came from 26 states, District of Columbia, Canada, Pakistan and Indonesia a pattern of near-and-far appeal that has prevailed for the past several years. Ages ranged from 17 to over 80 and this, too, has been a recent trend of considerable interest. Since the Craft Workshop began 17 years ago, its reputation has grown to such a degree that it is now known as one of the two best craft workshops in the United States today! This is an especially fine tribute to the leadership of Marian Heard, Professor of Related Arts and Crafts at the University of Tennessee, and Tennessee r, who has been Workshop Director for 15 years. It is a tribute to Marion Mueller, Indiana r, who has been tireless in improving local facilities since she became Director of the Settlement School in 1953. It is a tribute to the excellent standards regarding faculty and courses which University of Tennessee sponsorship has consistently brought to the Workshop an aspect Pi Beta Phi could not have accomplished alone. It is also a tribute to Pi Beta Phi for its foresight in promoting art and craft education on an adult level. Lastly, it is a tribute to the maintenance men on the local scene who have lifted tons and tons of necessary equipment to set up the Workshop each summer, and then store it again to make way for the regular classes ! That back-breaking work on the part of loyal employees can no longer be overlooked; neither can the fact that dismantling and stacking of bulky equipment for weaving and pottery is hastening deterioration. Consequently it was decided this summer that a weaving studio and a pottery room are musts for the very near future. While architect's plans will be drawn for both needs at one time, it is most likely that due to limited funds only a weaving studio can be erected this year. The number of foreign students who have attended a Craft Workshop totals 25, and they have come from 12 countries. The Philippine Islands and Canada have sent 5 each; Pakistan and Thailand have sent 3 each. Indonesia has sent 2 students, and 1 each has come from Hawaii, Lebanon, Finland, Iran, Puerto Rico, Greece and Sarawak. This is an impressive influence abroad because most of the foreign students return to their own countries to teach their own people. The Craft Workshop is filling a tremendous need today for adults in our own country. It serves teachers at all levels who come for further training and for graduate credit. It fills a need for numerous leaders of youth groups who go back to their own communities and also teach. Those working with handicapped children in hospitals or special schools come for new ideas and inspiration. Those 29 </p>
      <pb ref="arri110029_0002" seq="02" n="30-31  "/>
       <p>30 at rehabilitation centers have found that the workshop has much to give for helping adults with physical or mental problems. The undergraduate strident comes to develop artistic talents, earning credits toward graduation at the: same time. Often the already skilled craftsmen attends for a refresher course in his own field. An increasing number of senior citizens come each year to learn a craft or pursue a hobby that will give personal satisfactions during the retirement years. The Workshop's outreach is already extensive. With increased automation, an expanding population, an earlier retirement age and greater life expectancy, there will be more and more leisure hours to fill in some productive way. Every prognosis of future American society indicates a continuing and even greater need for guidance and training in personal creativity. This is exactly what the Craft Workshop is already doing so well. There is the direct influence which is always found in the teacher-pupil relationship, but when the pupils become teachers back in their own communities, in fact or by example, the outreach goes on and on. This is one of the most thrilling as well as most responsible aspects of the Craft Workshop in the eyes of Pi Phis the influence that gets back to the local community wherever it may be. The Dormitory Program for certain youth of the area is one of Pi Phi's endeavors that unfortunately can never be seen by a summer visitor and can only be realized by a winter visitor after several days of on-spot observation. The inability to show the program in operation, however, in no way lessens its worth. It involves the annual selection of 8-10 junior or senior high girls and boys attending Pi Beta Phi High School for on-grounds living, Before acceptance, the student and at least one parent are inter-viewed by the Director regarding willingness to (I) pursue daily studies at school, (2) stay for two-week intervals in the dormitory, (3) pay a very nominal fee per week for room and board to be $7 this fall, (4) supplement this token fee with daily chores involving meals, buildings, grounds or farm, and (5) conform to the regulations and standards of conduct set by the fraternity and supervised by the Director. In return, the dormitory students receive (1) supervision and help with their school work, (2 ) continuous high-standard guidance for the school year, (3) definite encouragement to continue their basic education, (4) opportunity to participate in after-school sports because early bus schedules to rural areas make this impossible otherwise, (5) relief, in some cases, from unhappy home complications, (6) good daily nutrition that is foreign to many, and (7) for the able, the possibility for further education after high school with scholarship assistance from Pi Beta Phi. Ruth Spelman, Ill. E, completed 3 years of genial yet firm supervision at Stuart Cottage for girls, while Marion Mueller, and Lela Adams shared equally fine results with supervision of boys at Helmick (Teachers) Cottage. The principal and local board member have only praise for the dormitory program and wish more boys and girls could have the personal benefits of the kind of supervision and influence given by all of the resident staff. Our dormitory program has never been measurable in terms of statistics. For some students better nutrition has provided the most visible result. For others, it might be found in a changed purpose, a more integrated personality, increased poise, a better understanding of family problems, an acceptance of one's own worth, a bit higher standard, or a greater willingness to do any work well! These things are not for parade; no guidance program ever is. Since the inception of the dormitory idea in the early 1920's, Pi Phi clubs and chapters have made a special and personalized investment in at least 600 youth of our nation. The fraternity cannot do. for all, but it can continue to do for some where we have the place and the facilities already established. The Health Center was the scene of another busy year. It was an especially memorable year as well, for last December Marjorie Chalmers, R.N., completed 25 years of THE ARROW OF P1 BETA PHI service there am!. in the t m Th.iuit5'. C fc al fraternitq rcCestraition w.ts withheld until the summer meetings when many Pi Phis from all over the otintry could be present to Share th.tt I,. p pv ca,.', asiora With her (see story in 1961 fall a'"l n w) . There can be no doubt that f'arjorle's continuous consent for the .good health of the babies born in the area has had a direct effect of better community health t Marjorie started weekly \\'ell.li.abv Clinics shortly oda ~ a , . , , , after her arrival, has continued tlt:rss ever since, and flow has several third generation records in her tiles ! Much of her work to day is Pre entive.... in onto.ast to her earlier years of more Curative care, and all inoculative clinics for the surrounding area are held at the Health Center, :Marjorie: has been .a sr otlats corntortirsyi person to have at hand for the resident staff, the summer 'Workshop students, and tin: young .students at Pi Leta Phi Elementary and I li,TI : liools t She also continues to serve the chip dren of the rural . .lades School, All of ber school chit dri n have ;snssual physie;`al vx,ussinations---a service that very few affluent schools in the I.'nite,l States can claim. Children in the ;'.atlinlnirg area are said to have far better polio pre.; teetwe so them .grad in the statew-x.,,.a source of satisfaction to .arjorie . We think it k also a fine tribute to her w atehttal t, . re.#' Pt Beta Phi is indeed grateful to Marjorie ('h.dr:acrs for her faithful and devoted years of service, and we wish her rmm.ara , many more! The two clinic rooms were. painted this year and Mar jt r~ie herself painted the iota soy yil iraet ;, She can always use more ''hippies (diapers t) and toothbrushes, toothpaste, soaps, e}tt',. with wlai h to :ear her young charges! An occa i sion.al box of t s or sat;rtcd .arair}r.als is nose welcome too. During the summer meetings, cash gifts from province officers, and Xi and Omicron representatives were sufi ciett to purchase 1,! little folding chairs. No longer will the legs of the "least liras' d.sn_!e trneosnfortahls from grown-up chairs while waiting turns to see Miz Charmer! The Health Center continues to be a welcome place for county medical meetings, and the designated Command Post for the G.atlinburg evacuation area in case of disaster. Pi Phis can be assured that the Health Center serve.: in the sixties to meet present-day challenges. It would be a sad commentary on past aceomplishnwnts if this were not true! 'The Aaron-craft Sb q ' has acquired a new look during the year and this his already proven effective in drawing more tourist lover's into the shop. A handsome new sign tells passersby that the .attr.i .tine building set back from the sidewalk is truly a quality' sheap and not just a residence. Lighting was inert..1s a! both inside and out. A sidewalk from the parking lot to the front door was installed. New landscaping and slim window boxes with colorful geraniums were added. The unused inner court was converted into an unusual display area for baskets, brooms and pottery.. As a result of .a most generous and timely stock gift from our Gr.uad Treasurer, it was possible to replace the aged furnace with a t:omhin.ttb. n neat-eool enit for year around shopping; comfort and eleenliness. Late in the summer, :=.n addition to the shipping room will he built to permit better space, organization and efficiency in shipping operations which are so vital to Arrow. craft's continuing success. A lovely new Arrower.aft symbol was designed last spring which hits already been used on the new sign and on the new color brochure des. riling Arrosvcraft's purpose and s hat the shots has to tatter. As soon as the present stock of tags and other printed matter is depleted, the new symbol will become more familiar. So, be looking for a weaver at her loom in silhouette, Arrowcraft Shop and II B 4) letters flowing around the oval, and an upward pointing Arrow for background! Many new and attractive designs have been created by Winogene Redding;, our Weaving Designer. These plus the familiar favorites will be seen in the fall price list which has a new look too. Nevada Christian, our energetic Arrowcraft Manager, has prepared and sent sales kits to provide club chairmen with information and order ma THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI 31 terials all in one folio ! Chairmen are reminded that Helen Dix, Publicity Member of Committee, has materials to lend clubs for display at Arrowcraft sales; early correspondence to reserve a date for these materials is essential. For the wary or the club that has not held an Arrow-craft sale in several years, a sample kit is available from the shop for a short period of time. Orders can be taken for goods shown as a small and assuredly successful beginning. Arrowcraft sales support our work at the Settlement School in two ways. First and foremost, club and chapter sales are providing a market for the products of our weavers. During the winter months when many of their friends and neighbors are living on unemployment compensation since some work is only available during the tourist season, our weavers are self-supporting because Arrowcraft purchases their work every month. Second, when the profits from the sales are returned to the Settlement School in the form of contributions, this helps support all areas of our work there. Minimum wage requirements must be met in paying the weavers, and at the same time, the cost of the woven article must be kept within an acceptable price range. While this does not allow a very large margin for operational costs, or profit, the satisfaction of providing year-around employment to talented and proud craftsmen should indeed be rewarding. During the year, work was provided for 65-75 weavers by Arrowcraft. A look at their year might be of interest. Three weavers had babies, two of whom died. Miss Red-ding is always very strict that weavers do not work at least 2 months before and after a baby is due; work at the loom was not a factor. One weaver's house burned down, and she and her 3 children barely escaped before the roof fell in; they all cut their feet badly running over frozen ground. One weaver's mother and another weaver's husband died. Two weavers had serious operations. One married and moved away, and another wove on weekends to earn her expenses to continue in college. The human factor can never be foreseen. Many more weavers asked for work than Arrowcraft was able to provide and this is another reason to endeavor to increase sales. Every $1000 increase provides 6 months' weaving for one person. There were 24 clubs that paid $1000 or more for Arrowcraft products during the last fiscal year. While this is a decrease of 5 from the high number reached the previous year, the loss is not too worrisome. Many clubs move in and out of this honorable mention group which may indicate that special effort is made in alternate years. Numerous other clubs held successful sales only slightly less in remittances than the ones listed. All deserve praise for the hard work and careful planning necessary for success. There were approximately 60 clubs that were not heard from at all last year, and these are the ones whose support is most earnestly desired too. Outstanding club remittances for the year were: Pittsburgh, Pa $3,686.55 Stillwater, Okla $1,4.14.53 Champaign-Urbana, Cleveland East, Ohio 1,240.74 Ill 3,197.78 Wichita, Kans 1,232.84 Oklahoma City, Southern New Jer Okla 2,809.58 sey 1,204.01 Arlington Hgts., Ill. 2,469.90 Tulsa, Okla 1,203.11 Grand Rapids, Mich. 2,244.30 Galesburg, Ill. . 1,165.15 Akron, Ohio 2,083.61 Milton Township, Northern New JerIll 1,143.99 sey 1,819.29 Kansas City, Mo 1,083.30 Ann Arbor, Mich. 1,675.91 Miami, Fla 1,075.36 Philadelphia, Pa 1,655.33 Milwaukee, Wis. 1,025.42 Schenectady, N.Y. 1,516.51 San Antonio, Tex 1,022.34 Lincoln, Neb 1,461.86 St. Louis, ,Mo. . 1,009.14 South Bend, Incl 1,434.09 A word of commendation should be expressed for the better payment of Arrowcraft accounts. The accounts receivable at the end of the fiscal year were at the lowest level in 13 years, and this is greatly appreciated. The Arrowcraft Shop in the Mountain View Hotel had a very successful year under the leadership of Elizabeth Rue, Iowa Beta, who keeps busy in leisure moments by showing visitors over the Settlement School grounds and surrounding area. Club and Chapters Contributions. One of the outstand ing features of 49 years of Settlement School support an( growth has been the continuous policy of voluntary con tributions. No club or chapter has ever been assessed. Thi excellent, unit-determination policy often causes ups an, downs in income for operational expenses, even while an: donation, large or small, is always most gratefully re ceived. For the concluding year, the following were 1005 provinces in contributions: Clubs Chapters Alpha Alpha rota Eta Gamma Kappa Iota Delta Lambda Kappa Epsilon Mu Xi Zeta Xi Pi South Eta Pi Alumnx Club contributions, received by the Settlemer School Treasurer, reached a new high of $11,271.59, a increase of $273.04 over the year before. In these cor tinuing days of dollar devaluation, the increases from 6 clubs were most gratifying. 162 clubs contributed the sarr. as the prior year and this was a considerable help too. decreased contributions of 45 clubs was disheartening, an especially sad is the fact that apparently 41 clubs forg( the Settlement School entirely. Little Pigeon Awards fc the highest % increase (1100%) went to DeLand, Florid and for the highest dollar increase ($210), to Narthex New Jersey. Of 18 clubs contributing $150 or nor those starred (*) have been so mentioned for at least years: *Kansas City, Mo. ..$950.00 Champaign-Urbana, *St. Louis, Mo 800.00 Ill $200.( North Shore, Ill. . 500.00 North Shore, Ill. Jr. 200.( Pasadena, Calif 388.00 *Milwaukee, Wis 200.( Northern New jersey 310.00 Oklahoma City, Okla. 200.( *Indianapolis, Ind. 270.00 *Denver, Colo 165.( Arlington Heights, Palo Alto, Calif. 156.! Ill 250.00 *Everett, Wash. 150.( Miami, Fla 221.56 Sacramento, Calif. .. 150.1 Philadelphia, Pa. .. 210.00 Westchester Co., N.Y 150.1 Chapter contributions totaled $2,689.09, a decrease $181.51. Welcome increases came from 22 chapters; helped by maintaining their prior donations; 11 decreas( their gifts, and 6 chapters made no contribution. Litt Pigeon Awards were given to Ohio A for the highest increase (200%), and to Vermont B for the bight dollar increase ($34.14). Of 4 chapters contributing $I( or more, those starred (*) have been similarly named f at least 5 years: *Texas Gamma $150.00 Alabama Beta $100. So. Dakota Alpha .. 120.70 *Missouri Beta 100. About 10 different individuals, clubs, chapters Mothers Clubs sent additional gifts direct to the Sett. ment School. These included the always-needed ba things, teen-age clothing, monetary gifts for general designated purposes, various other articles, and the helpful TV or SH trading stamps. All were Brea. appreciated. Many replacements and 'free purchases' w( made possible through the trading stamps. Please contin to send these to the Director. Memorial Fund contributions are usually sent by in, viduals or clubs in memory of someone dear who was as! ciated with the fraternity. A beautifully engraved and i propriate acknowledgement card is always sent to the fam of the deceased. This special fund received $133 in su gifts this past year. Several different chapters of Sigma Phi Gamma sent total of $175 for the Corrective Fund to be administer by our Jennie Nicol Health Center. This is a practice long standing, as well as a compliment to the fraternit work there. The Magazine Agency augmented the above contril tions with a commission check of $11,258.62 for anoti banner year. This is an increase of $457.34. Many that and great praise are due the hard-working and efficil </p>
      <pb ref="arri110029_0003" seq="03" n="32-33  "/>
       <p>32 THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI Magazine Chairmen who have attained new highs for 3 straight years. If every Pi Phi active and alumna will re-member our own Magazine Agency for every subscription within her own sphere of influence, the opportunities for expanding this means of contributing to the Settlement School are almost limitless and very thought provoking. The May L. Keller Award for 1960-61 was presented to Alice Barron, Florida Beta. A new Settlement School program booklet containing this and several other fine pro-grams is being compiled this fall and will be ready for distinction to chairmen in the second semester mailing. Many interesting eye-witness programs should be given this fall as a result of the summer meetings held in Gatlin-burg, and it was believed the new compilation would be more immediately useful later in the year. Many chapters and clubs use the annually revised Slides Program at regular intervals, while others do not seem to know that it is available. If a group has not seen this free program for several years, please write the Committee Member in charge, Lois Summers, as soon as possible to arrange a date on her schedule. 73 clubs and chapters used this program last year, another record high, and there was considerable appreciation for its brevity and comprehensive, up-to-date coverage of the total Settlement School enterprise. The Red Barn is always the scene of much activity during the Craft Workshop sessions. This activity was repeated in late October when the Gatlinburg Craftsmen's Fair and the American Craftsmen's Council meetings were held. Tennessee Alpha was the only chapter to make a visit last year; that chapter is not too far away and distance is a factor. It is quite exciting to learn that a chapter near the Great Lakes is planning a visit this coming year! During the spring months, three separate and successful work-shops were held at the Barn and several other groups held meetings there. In connection with the coming October Fair a very beautiful and interesting time to visit the area, Marion Mueller will have a busy and responsible extra job as Local Chairman. The Red Barn will again be put to good use at that time. Scholarships, in relation to the Settlement School, were as follows for the year. Bonnie Hutchinson, Cal. r, won the Workshop Scholarship given annually by the Southern California Area Council to a Pi Province active. Jean Carroll, S. Car. A, was winner of the newly established Virginia Alpha Scholarship for the Workshop also. Graduate Assistant winners (perhaps a form of scholarship) were Jan Rhoda of Neb. B, and Peggy Schumacher of Wis. B. Interest from the Alspaugh Scholarship Fund provided local scholarships, in the amount of $100 each, which were awarded to Patsy Moore, Myrtle Ownby, and Douglas Price, graduating seniors at Pi Beta Phi High School. A North Shore Alumni Club Scholarship was received too late to award last spring and will be awarded to a qualified recipient as soon as possible. The Grace Coolidge Library received four treasured books that had belonged to Mrs. Coolidge, Vermont 13, from her son, John Coolidge. The Settlement School is deeply indebted to Sarah Rugg, former Arrow Editor, for her personal efforts in regard to this gift. Several new books were purchased for the Grace Coolidge Collection last year, and more will be purchased in the coming year. The death of Miss Evelyn Bishop last spring brought sadness to the hearts of all Gatlinburg residents and to Pi Phis who remember her as Head Resident of the Settlement School during many of its early formative years. After retirement, Miss Evelyn had continued to live in Gatlinburg and was dearly loved by all. She was a member of New York Alpha. She was a very fine musician, and her piano has been given to the school. It was placed in Teachers Cottage where she had lived and worked for so many years. The summer meetings for Province Officers, Chapter Presidents, Pledge Supervisors, and Advisory Chairmen provided a wonderful opportunity to see the Settlement School as it is today. It was quite a challenge to attempt to relay some of the enthusiasm for the Settlement School which those who work closely with it always acquire. It is hoped that everyone who came and saw was impressed with the total program of the Settlement School today, and returned to her own chapter or club realizing that practically every major form of community service and welfare program is aided through the present Settlement School program: education direct and indirect for children, youth college students and adults; scholarships to and from the Settlement School; Health young and old, individual and community; economic welfare; child welfare; foreign students; rehabilitation of the handicapped and underprivileged; gerontology; plus an established base of considerable asset for further endeavor, perhaps in American arts and crafts, a field of increasing importance. Any Settlement School year is one with problems to solve and decisions to make. The competence and devotion of the entire resident staff could not be excelled. One finds equal abilities and service from committee members each year. It was sad to lose Lois Finger of Pasadena who had served so ably, and a pleasure to welcome Eloise Hensley, former Nu Province President, who brings her own talents to the committee. Other members will continue past assignments so we are assured of both continuity and competence: Zoe James as Treasurer, Lois Summers in charge of Slides, Helen Dix who writes Little Pigeon News, and Olivia Moore as Grand Council adviser. An able committee and resident staff, together with the loyalty and support of every club and chapter, should lead to a memorable 50th anniversary year for the Pi Beta Phi Settlement School. HELEN MOFFETT RUSSELL, Chairman Gatlinburg SETTLEMENT SCHOOL DIRECTOR'S REPORT Arrowcraft Shop Pi Beta Phi Settlement School is in the heart of Gatlin-burg, a part of the community, yet an entity in itself. The village grows, business enterprises increase each year the largest in the making is a ski lodge and lift. With thousands of tourists visiting each season the two thousand residents are lost in the picture. Approximately one hundred motels, four small hotels and forty restaurants are the nucleus of the tourist business however, these tourists come for a purpose, primarily to see the beauty of the area much of which is in the adjoining Great Smoky Mountain National Park. The many beautiful handcrafts, many of them native crafts, are also an attraction. Driving through the village on Parkway one notes our Arrowcraft Shop which sells the crafts of the Southern Highlands. We trust every Pi Phi visitor in Gatlinburg comes to Arrowcraft for a preview of the many items our Clubs will display at their sales throughout the year. Nevada Christian (Nevada Beta) serves capably as manager. Winogene Redding directs the weaving. Nella Hill, Faye Cook, Jean Hembree, Shirley Roberts, Ruby Watson, and June Cook are the local girls who serve as salesgirls and are kept constantly on the alert filling Club orders. Elizabeth Rue, Iowa Gamma, operates the Arrowcraft Shop at the Mountain View Hotel. Eunice Cole has served as bookkeeper several years. The staff at Settlement' School perhaps realizes the ex-tent of the loyalty of the Alum= Clubs more than any. Huge sales do not "happen." We know the many excellent THE ARROW OF PI BETA PHI 33 sales records of our Clubs are due to hours and years of volunteer work by our members. It is largely due to them that sixty or seventy weavers and many other crafts-men have outlets for their beautiful work. To help in appearance as well as efficiency, Arrowcraft has been renovated including a new furnace and air-conditioner. At present the shipping room is being enlarged. Clubs should benefit with the resultant efficiency. Health Center Near the Arrowcraft Shop on Parkway one notes the Health Center. Marjorie Chalmers has completed her twenty-fifth year as nurse for Pi Beta Phi. Her report of these years gives evidence of the change to preventive health work. Pi Beta Phi-U. of T. Workshop "A bigger and better workshop" might well have been the slogan for the 1961 workshop with the University of Tennessee its seventeenth summer. It is an amazing and challenging experience to work with the many craftsmen young and old who come from many walks of life to learn more skills, usually for undergraduate or graduate credit. Our personnel came from twenty-six states and three foreign countries. Jan Rhoda and Peggy Schumacher were Pi Phi assistants; Bonnie Hutchinson and Jean Carroll received two Pi Phi scholarships. Yes, Marian Heard, this was a most successful workshop! High School and Elementary A survey made by the state recommended consolidation of the high school with Pitman Center approximately fifteen miles distant. In order to offer better opportunities to students and because of crowded conditions all agree the high school should move, yet where it will be located is a question. The American Legion has a new field which will be used for school athletics. Pi Phi supplements the county program with music, arts and crafts, and two classes in woodcraft. Margaret Struble, Iowa Gamma, is scheduled to teach Arts and Crafts this year. With an enrollment of one hundred-eighty there were forty-three graduates. Even though small, the school is rated Class "A." Dormitories Sixteen to twenty boys and girls were privileged to live in our dormitories last year. The five dollar payment per month was difficult for some to make. As a whole the attitude was excellent as shown in their willingness to pre-form assigned duties in lieu of their board and room. This attitude seemed to carry over to the school where many honors were received during the year. In fact, there were so many that I doubt if such a record will be obtained for some time. Ruth Spelman, Illinois Epsilon and wearer of the Golden Carnation, has served very capably as housemother for three years. Nadine Grooms, a local Pi Phi graduate, served as my secretary since there was no Pi Phi available. Mrs. Adams, our cook, also serves as chaperon for the boys. Farm and Grounds Richard Watson continues as farm manager and care-taker of our chickens. Arlie Watson is now completing his thirty-fourth year as head maintenance at S. S. Whether it's a roof leak, plumbing or electrical need night or day we can relay upon Arlie to "fix it." Neal Watson, Arlie's son, is every-ready for heavy work, especially at Arrow-craft and Workshop. Neal's cousin, Zanley Watson, is now learning the trade to replace Arlie when he retires. With twelve buildings and seventy-eight acres of land there is constant need of repair somewhere. Staff House Ruth Barrett Smith Staff House is the scene of many large functions, as well as serving as living quarters for Staff and dining quarters the year round. During Workshop approximately eighty were served three meals a day. The cooking was done by Home Economics majors under the supervision of a dietician, Little Pigeon Alumna' Club Ruth Spelman was reelected president of our local alumnae club. Our second annual style show was a huge success. The Club project is the making of our Log Cabin into a museum for Pi Phi. Arlie's wife, Josie, became quite interested, so it has an authentic mountain touch with its Civil War vintage. Red Barn Our Red Barn/Dormitory has grown in popularity during its two years since remodelling. With its multi-purpose design and furnishings many different group! find it most inviting. Thirty-one beds are set up, eight portable cots are available, and four sofas may be converted to sleep two. Chanticleer's entrance lounge accommodates small groups for meetings or workshops, or serves as dining room with the meal prepared in the adjoining kitchenette. The Owl's Nest on the second floor has been the scen( of workshops, social functions, summer workshop movie! and parties, and dormitory parties. Well over a hundrec can gather here. On the landing leading to the Little Pigeon Loft is ow newest acquisition, a pigeon mobile, designed andmade b3 our workshop enameling instructor. The mobile is corm posed of large pigeon designs of crushed glass on plastic, giving a stained glass effect. The loft will sleep twelve as is, or several more with portable cots. Gifts Our annual list of gifts is an impressive one. Large gifts and small ones are all deeply appreciated. At Settlemeni School Pi Phis have a memorial to their Founders foi which they can be and should be proud. Our work is divided largely into six categories school and education. dormitory, health, Arrowcraft Shop, Workshop with the University of Tennessee, and Barn/Dorm for educational or philanthropic purposes. What do we do? "Come see." Respectfully, MARION W. MUELLER </p>
       </div1>

    </body>

  </text>

</TEI.2>



