<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03040006000">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[Letter]  Feb. 8, 1920, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
                    <name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
                    <name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
                </address>
                <date>2006</date>
                <idno type="SPCID">arm03040006000</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. 
                        For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee 
                        Libraries, Knoxville, TN</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from which the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
                <bibl>
                    <title>[Letter]  Feb. 8, 1920, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                    <date value="1920-02-08">Feb. 8, 1920</date>
                    <author>
                        <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                    </author>
                    <extent>4p</extent>
                    <note type="summary">Harrison and family ill with flu - Condition of their home - </note>
                    <note type="box">3</note>
                    <note type="folder">4</note>
                    <note type="document">arm03040006000</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Local Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <list>
                        <item>Living conditions</item>
                        <item>People</item>
                        <item>Social life</item>
                        <item>Influenza</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="abstract">
                <pb ref="arm03040006001" seq="01"/>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <item>Harrison and family ill with flu - </item>
                        <item>Condition of their home - </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="letter">
                <pb ref="arm03040006002" seq="02"/>
                <head>
                    <date value="1919-02-08">Feb. 8, 1920</date>
                    </head>
                <p><del>
                    Dearest family - Sunday night and all in bed but myself - I hope to get my usual Monday letter tomorrow full of good news  - Suppose you are busy with Mabel at present - 
                    and can imagine - how she is flitting around preparing for her migration to Montana especially busy will she be if she puts in half time at the library.  What kind of clothes
                    has she made now? for am sure she has made over something ere this! I wrote her yesterday and also the Pi Phis &amp; mailed a little box to you - a valentine - all of 
                    which no doubt will reach their destinations by the end of the week.</del>
                </p>
                <p>
                    This has been a short and yet <pb ref="arm03040006003" seq="03"></pb> a long week too with nothing much to write about in its passing. Harrison his wife and two of the youngsters
                    are in bed with the flu or something similar - all in the same room &amp; <hi1 rend="underscore">in</hi1> <hi1 rend="underscore">their</hi1> <hi1 rend="underscore">clothes.</hi1>
                    Evelyn has been going up several times a day since <add place="supralinear"><abbr expan="Thursday">Thurs</abbr></add> <add place="supralinear">when</add> they 
                    <del>were</del><add place="supralinear">came</add> down with it. She says the place is <hi1 rend="underscore">awful</hi1> - beds have not been changed
                    all winter I guess. They are much better today however and beginning to have an appetite - The mother in-law is there looking after them and if she stays - poor Evelyn will be
                    relieved of that responsibility. As she had to go over this morning I took her Sunday School class - not a particularly pleasant <pb ref="arm03040006004" seq="04"></pb> task but we
                    got through it - Everyone was so slow this <abbr expan="morning">a.m.</abbr> - we were down at the church-house over two hours - After dinner Abbie &amp; I called on
                    Mrs. Husky - one of Aunt Lydia&apos;s daughters and also visited Mrs. Whaley - who lives next Lucrettie&apos;s Has five little boys - all but one in school.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <abbr expan="Baptist Young Person&apos;s Union">B.Y.</abbr> was as usual tonight - we were glad to come home and have our supper in the living room - Toasted
                    biscuits &amp; had chocolate jetty - potato salad - cookies - Evelyn played &amp; sang afterwards - very nice time.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Yesterday was the darkest &amp; rainiest day we&apos;ve had so stayed in the house all day - usual tasks kept us busy - Dr. Massy was here for supper &amp; stayed
                    all night - His visits are always pleasant breaks in the quiet - My lamp is beginning to wane so must hurry up these last few words - 
                </p>
                <p>
                    There is little news as you see and seven more weeks of school <hi1 rend="underscore">only</hi1>! Think I shall be glad to see the finish too.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Hoping this finds all well with you both and with loads of love as ever
                </p>
                <p>
                    Ruth.
                </p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>