<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03030016000">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[Letter]  Nov. 12, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
                    <name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
                    <name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
                </address>
                <date>2006</date>
                <idno type="SPCID">arm03030016000</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from which the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
                <bibl>
                    <title>[Letter]  Nov. 12, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                    <date value="1919-11-12">Nov. 12, 1919</date>
                    <author>
                        <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                    </author>
                    <extent>10p</extent>
                    <note type="summary">Autumn coloring everywhere - School subjects - Plans for Thanksgiving program</note>
                    <note type="box">3</note>
                    <note type="folder">3</note>
                    <note type="document">arm03030016000</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
            </projectDesc>
        <editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Local Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <list>
                        <item>Living Conditions</item>
                        <item>Holidays</item>
                        <item>People</item>
                        <item>Social life</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="abstract">
                <pb ref="arm03030016001" seq="01"/>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <item>Autumn coloring everywhere</item>
                        <item>School subjects</item>
                        <item>Plans for Thanksgiving program</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="letter">
                <pb ref="arm03030016002" seq="02"/>
                <head>
                   <date value="1919-11-12">Nov. 12, 1919</date>
                   </head>
                <p><del>
                  Dearest Jane - Your nice letter came this Wednesday just as you predicted after I had expected it Monday &amp; then was sure it would come
                    Tuesday - However Monday brought a great long one from Mabel <add place="supralinear">Abbot</add> Cousin Viva &amp; <abbr expan="Tuesday">Tues.</abbr>
                    one from Brennie ditto in length so you see I fared well anyway although your fair handwriting is more welcome &amp; pleasing to the eye
                    than any other! It&apos;s 9:30 this <abbr expan="evening">eve.</abbr> &amp; everyone has been in bed for over an hour but myself - I do not 
                    want to get the <hi1 rend="underscore">sleep</hi1> <hi1 rend="underscore">habit</hi1> though it&apos;s sort of a temptation when all the others
                    leave so ear<add place="supralinear">l</add>y - but the newspapers - Literary Digest &amp; such have much news in them &amp; try to look them over
                    even if only hastily.</del>
                </p>
                <p><del>
                    The youngsters must be too cute &amp; dear for words &amp; would give anything to see them. Can picture you &amp; Miss <hi1 rend="underscore">Pancos</hi1>
                    in front of the heater peacefully passing away the evenings - am glad she is quick for you have been in a storm center for so long! Mabel&apos;s letter
                    was very very nice and interesting &amp; am glad she feels that my letters are for her too </del><pb ref="arm03030016003" seq="03"></pb><del> and is so nice as 
                    to write me. I try &amp; write pa about twice a week too so you see between the two of you there isn&apos;t much left for others - Sunday I 
                    dashed off letters to Mr. Snell - Miss Hobroyd - Uncle Art &amp; Charlotte am pleased to say - </del>
                </p>
                <p><del>
                    As <gap reason="illegible" resp="bds"></gap> going into business with Mr. St. <gap reason="illegible" resp="bds"></gap> what sort does he mean?
                    Am not <unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">keen</unclear> for <unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">Reedley</unclear> or any part of the 
                    <unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">intenar</unclear> for it&apos;s <unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">insufficiently</unclear> 
                    <gap reason="illegible" resp="bds"></gap> am sure - part of the year - <gap reason="illegible" resp="bds"></gap> are no doubt all right but
                    <gap reason="illegible" resp="bds"></gap> know <gap reason="illegible" resp="bds"></gap> first before <gap reason="illegible" resp="bds"></gap>
                    anything <gap reason="illegible" resp="bds"></gap> Californians <gap reason="illegible" resp="bds"></gap> It <unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">will</unclear>
                    <gap reason="illegible" resp="bds"></gap> friends <gap reason="illegible" resp="bds"></gap> Don&apos;t <gap reason="illegible" resp="bds"></gap> thing
                    <gap reason="illegible" resp="bds"></gap> hand <gap reason="illegible" resp="bds"></gap> work in <gap reason="illegible" resp="bds"></gap> for that
                    <unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">mostly</unclear> <gap reason="illegible" resp="bds"></gap> you </del><pb ref="arm03030016004" seq="04"></pb> <del>make up your
                    mind to that. Why can&apos;t he find something else to do in Tacoma. I should think Arthur might be of assistance in that respect. You are quite right
                    when you speak of an upheaval in the midst of the family! But things will eventually work out as we&apos;ll know which way to turn.</del>
                </p>     
                <p>
                    Let me move on now for a minute about the wonderful coloring. Monday was very windy (a regular <abbr expan="mountain">mt.</abbr> wind people call it)
                    <del>&amp;</del> <add place="supralinear">which</add> seemed to turn the trees druing the day so that at noon it was really starting to 
                    see the change. All had been touched except the evergreens which seem to grow in long fingerlike clusters down the ridges in quite regular stripes like - 
                    their dark green contrasts wonderfully with the solid golden color of all the other trees occasionally brightened by a maple - gum tree - sumach or
                    sourwood - a solid mass of f<del>a</del>lame color from top to bottom &amp; then the copper colored oaks tone that down. Well it&apos;s
                    just about the most wonderful thing I&apos;ve seen here - these golden - green - &amp; red hills in every direction!
                </p>
                <p>
                    Emily Aunt Lizzie &amp; I sat out on the porch steps after lunch today admiring it while waiting for Mr. Creswell to bring up the mail - Evelyn &amp;
                    Miss Langmaid went to Sevierville Sunday afternoon &amp; will be back tomorrow - at least Evelyn phoned tonight to that effect.
                    <abbr expan="Baptist Young Person&apos; Union">B.Y.</abbr> is rather lonesome without her playing &amp; singing as Emily isn&apos;t much at the 
                    piano - but better than I am anyway. Mr. <abbr expan="Cresswell">C.</abbr> got back from his <sic corr="weekend">week-end</sic> in time to take
                    charge though Abbie didn&apos;t make it until last the next morning. We got through about 7:30 &amp; then Tom McCarter &amp; Mr. <abbr expan="Cresswell">C.</abbr>
                    brought the <pb ref="arm03030016005" seq="05" n="2"></pb> lamps over &amp; chatted awhile - Tom is the most amusing &amp; original youngster you can imagine
                    but thoroughly good &amp; dependable. He has been out nearly all month plowing getting in corn etc. &amp; has been learning his part 
                    <del>in</del> as Miles Standish while doing the <hi1 rend="underscore">former</hi1>! 
                </p>
                <p>
                    There was a boy shot up in the Sugarlands Sunday noon - by a Mr. Bracken - an elderly man of about sixty - trouble over a still &amp; about which
                    there are conflicting stories - Anyway <hi1 rend="underscore">our</hi1> Harrison went up after Mr. <abbr expan="Bracken">B.</abbr> Sunday night - 
                    started right after <abbr expan="Baptist Young Person&apos;s Union">B.Y.</abbr> on old Dan. It was an awfully windy night way up in the 
                    <abbr expan="mountains">mts.</abbr> &amp; Harrison looked so excited while telling Mr. <abbr expan="Cresswell">C.</abbr> about fixing the furnace at 
                    school etc. for Monday morning. We <pb ref="arm03030016006" seq="06"></pb> can just imagine how <hi1 rend="underscore">Sherlock</hi1> <hi1 rend="underscore">Holmesy</hi1>
                    &amp; funny he was. Anyway he got his man &amp; there was a trial by Squire Maples at his house at the foot of our lane to which men for miles around 
                    came Monday noon - He was let out on bail until <hi1 rend="underscore">court</hi1> (circuit every 3 <abbr expan="months">mon.</abbr>) in February or 
                    about then. We were right at the house where <add place="supralinear">was</add> the scene of the shooting on our <abbr expan="Smoky Mountains">Smoky</abbr> trip - 
                    stopped to get a horseshoe for Dan.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Well I must on with my tales of my doings such as they are. Monday Abbie stayed with us as the Carr girls did not come to the cottage - Rose being sick &amp;
                    Litha not willing to stay without her I suppose - they get mad about things every so often as do the others. Aunt Lizzie isn&apos;t much of a cook you know
                    &amp; wondered what we could have for supper - so I made some <pb ref="arm03030016007" seq="07"></pb> muffins &amp; Jane they were about the best I ever baked - 
                    so light - these with our old standby chocolate &amp; some war cake were quite filling - Then great excitement a man come up in a wagon with our dishes
                    a big barrel<del>l</del> so after the repast was over down we went with hatchet &amp; lamp &amp; the three of us managed to get the top
                    off &amp; the dishes out of the excelsior - Such a relief as it is to have cups - saucers - bowls etc sufficient for the food &amp; partakers thereof!
                    They are a very pretty pattern neat &amp; cha<del>t</del>ste! Something like Bavarian dishes - pink roses with a tiny blue flower and 
                    a little gold band.
                </p>
                <p>
                    We have sugar bowl - cream pitcher - three sizes of plates - sauce dishes - oatmeal &amp; soup dishes - vegetable dishes &amp; platters besides the cups &amp;
                    saucers - Some of the dinner plates were broken - also vegetable dishes &amp; two platters but we are content with the rest. We washed up enough for breakfast
                    &amp; I arranged the table even to the bread &amp; butter plates. Abbie had brought some little pink chrysanthemums from home so our table looked very pretty.
                    Did I tell you that Evelyn had a large window box in the dining room? <del>in front of the <sic corr="window">wind</sic></del> It is about
                    a foot wide &amp; three long - wandering Jew - colis - begonia &amp; geraniums make it very pretty.
                </p>
                <p>
                    I stayed till late at school reading about Daniel Boone for my geography class (we have been studying <abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn.</abbr>) &amp; looking up
                    information about the Constitution for my <abbr expan="United States">U.S.</abbr> class Incidentally I&apos;m learning quite a little myself. We finished the
                    history having be-<pb ref="arm03030016008" seq="08" n="3"></pb>gun with the close of the Civil War - The Spanish-American War had been almost entirely erased from 
                    my mind &amp; so feel that I&apos;m quite a little more intelligent in regard to my country than before.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Yesterday we didn't close school but had our assembly from 2 till about 2:20 &amp; then dismissed - Liberty Day - you know - It&apos;s my week to have assembly
                    but don't mind it any more - We had the flag salute - Star Spangled etc Columbia the gem etc America the beautiful - Mr. <abbr expan="Cresswell">C.</abbr> told
                    about the doings in Liverpool where he was at the time &amp; so ended that part. Then I drilled on my play for a long time &amp; had much fun with them. They are
                    <pb ref="arm03030016009" seq="09"></pb> awfully nice about it &amp; quite interested for them! You know I have Priscilla&apos;s part divided between Rose Carr &amp;
                    Cora McCarter thus taking in the four in the 9th grade. Cora has the two spinning scenes as she can spin &amp; we are using our &quot;stage properties&quot;
                    now  which makes it more interesting. Have planned to work in the whole class into the last scene
                    closing with a Thanksgiving song. Maybe I&apos;ve told you all this before - for as you are situated in regard to me &amp; pa so am I towards you both. (No your
                    items in today&apos;s letter had not been written me before &amp; was much interested to know of your manifold activities in the bazaar as member of <pb ref="arm03030016010" seq="10"></pb>
                    Aurora P.E.U. &amp; <abbr expan="Daughters of the American Revolution">D.A.R.</abbr> - also was glad to look over year books of first &amp; latter.) After this rehearsing I did
                    a little studying &amp; then went with Emily for a stroll up the river into all the gorgeousness. After supper for which we had some of Aunt Lizzie&apos;s good 
                    tomato soup we sat around the fireplace &amp; read &amp; talked. Mr. <abbr expan="Cresswell">C.</abbr> came over and joined us - He is alone at the 
                    bungalow with Mrs. <sic corr="Proffitt">Proffit</sic> &amp; imagine he gets rather lonesome.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Oh yes - he &amp; Tom - Rose &amp; I have been slated for a quartette for the <abbr expan="Baptist Young Person&apos;s Union">B.Y.</abbr> Sunday
                    <abbr expan="evening">eve</abbr>! So that&apos;s my next feat - unless the boys don&apos;t get over their colds before then. What we shall sing is as 
                    yet unknown. A hymn no doubt. Rose &amp; I will sing soprano - the other two can sing whatever they wish! Today was a repetition largely of 
                    yesterday - more rehearsing after school - Then Emily &amp; I went to the store - Charlie&apos;s - for candy - (Is there a sugar famine home as here - ?)
                    He produced a box of chocolates perfectly grand fresh ones - &amp; as <del>he</del> we have not bought any candy since being here we
                    purchased it between us &amp; have had a gay time eating them.
                </p>
                <p><del>
                    Well it&apos;s getting so late I hate to look at the clock - and must wend my way to bed - Weather is rather warm &amp; damp again so wear my gingham
                    with green slip on &amp; white shoes! Oh yes - this is Brennie&apos;s news &amp; a <hi1 rend="underscore">secret</hi1> - she is engaged! Someone I never
                    heard of &amp; know nothing about - widower named Fred Marsh &amp; Herbert&apos;s Sunday School teacher - <hi1 rend="underscore">perfect</hi1> &amp; she is
                    <hi1 rend="underscore">so</hi1> <hi1 rend="underscore">happy</hi1>! Isn&apos;t that nice? She is such a dear -</del>
                </p>
                <p><del>
                    Goodnight dearest Jane with so much love - Ruth</del>
                </p>    
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
