<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03020016000">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[Letter]  Oct. 05, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
                    <name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
                    <name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
                </address>
                <date>2006</date>
                <idno type="SPCID">arm03020016000</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. 
                        For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee 
                        Libraries, Knoxville, TN</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from whi1ch the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
                <bibl>
                    <title>[Letter]  Oct. 05, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                    <date value="1919-10-05">Oct. 05, 1919</date>
                    <author>
                        <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                    </author>
                    <extent>15p</extent>
                    <note type="summary">We visit the Sevierville Fair &amp; see <hi1 rend="underscore">our</hi1> exhibits and others. Visit the McCarter family to see the making of molasses.</note>
                    <note type="box">3</note>
                    <note type="folder">2</note>
                    <note type="document">arm03020016000</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Local Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <list>
                        <item>Living Conditions</item>
                        <item>People</item>
                        <item>Fairs</item>
                        <item>Social events</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="abstract">
                <pb ref="arm03020016001" seq="01"/>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <item>We visit the Sevierville Fair &amp; see <hi1 rend="underscore">our</hi1> exhibits and others</item>
                        <item>Visit the McCarter family to see the making of molasses.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="letter">
                <pb ref="arm03020016002" seq="02"/>
                <head>
                    <date value="1919-10-05">Oct. 5, 1919</date>
                </head>
                <!-- Page 1 missing -->
                <p>
                    I was there.
                </p>

                <p><del>
                        Have not heard a word from St. Paul since my arrival here though wrote twice and 
                        told them about things &amp; sent kodaks. I think it&apos;s perfectly funny the way things have moved since 
                        I left and hope that next <gap></gap> land on the market. Think our original plan of building on the <gap></gap> 
                        lots quite feasible &amp; <gap></gap> discuss it with him? Did you ever think of his finding you 
                    something to do? Don&apos;t for goodness sake buy another store - ever.</del>
                    </p>
                <p><del>
                        <gap></gap> since I wrote and seems ages since then somehow - the days </del><pb ref="arm03020016003" seq="03"/> <del>
                        have been so full - I do not like to let a week roll around without getting off a letter - I had to write the Tacoma Pi 
                        Phis &amp; that&apos;s where my letter writing time went this week - I send them a letter the beginning of each 
                        month you know.</del>
                    </p>
                <p>
                    Talking  about the Puyallup Fair - you should have seen the one I saw at Sevierville - We went down in the Huff 
                    Ford - Mr. Cresswell Abbie &amp; I - besides three youngsters &amp; Estel who drove - In another car were about 
                    ten of the school youngsters. This was 7 a.m. Tuesday - and no school - We arrived in an hour or so and went 
                    to the big square red brick courthouse where the fair was in progress. Around the building is quite a yard with 
                    a number of large old trees. Here were many cars &amp; people congregated early as it was &amp; inside the 
                    rooms where were the ex-<pb ref="arm03020016004" seq="04" n="03"/>hibits - it was very jammed. Last year was 
                    the first time Sevierville had a fair &amp; it lasted one day only. This year it was for two days and there were exhibits 
                    from twelve places around. Ours was one and we ranked eighth place which wasn&apos;t so bad considering. 
                    Then the school exhibits were separate - There were only four of them but we were at the head &amp; 
                    <hi1 rend="underscore">way</hi1> <hi1 rend="underscore">ahead</hi1> too! There were many things that we never 
                    have - I saw sugar cane - cotton on the plants - peanuts ditto - peppers ditto - tobaco plants - a pumpkin 
                    weighing 133<num type="fraction" value="one forth">1/4</num> <abbr expan="pounds">lbs.</abbr> - an ear 
                    of corn 14 <abbr expan="inches">in.</abbr> long - apples and apples - besides the usual assortment. In 
                    one small room was exhibited part of the morning a whole collection of stills - over twenty of them. You 
                    re-<pb ref="arm03020016005" seq="05"/>member I saw all but the still itself <hi1 rend="underscore">once</hi1>! A still 
                    is a big copper vessel in which the stuff is boiled together &amp; from which a pipe carries off the steam to formed. 
                    The steam distilled makes the moonshine. I took some pictures of the collection &amp; hope they prove good as 
                    they will be interesting to say the least. Then in one big room the colored people had all their exhibits to themselves 
                    &amp; very nice they looked too. Lots of canned stuff &amp; fancy work especially quilts. Well we stayed around a 
                    long time. Then Evelyn &amp; I went off &quot;down town&quot; which was across the street - bought some ice-cream 
                    cones &amp; deposited my check (first month&apos;s pay of &#36;60) in the bank &amp; got a little check book - 
                    We had our lunch at the dormitory of Murphy College &amp; going back to the grounds partook of cake &amp; 
                    lemonade sold by the Epworth League - Strange that they were the only ones who sold <pb ref="arm03020016006" seq="06" n="04"/>
                    stuff to eat and as for kewpies &amp; chances on articles nary a one was there - exhibits &amp; nothing else. 
                    Outside were the livestock - hogs - chickens - cows - oxen - horses &amp; mules. The excitement after lunch was 
                    to see the riding. One street was roped off for this. The people lined the sides &amp; the judges stood at one end 
                    &amp; gave out <del>the</del> ribbons - first the mules were exhibited about twenty or more 
                    and such a dust as they kicked up! Next three fine horses - ridden by three women cantered &amp; walked up 
                    &amp; down many times before us - followed by twenty horses ridden by men. They were of all sorts &amp; 
                    conditions as were the riders - farmers - methodist minister with a little straw hat &amp; square jaw - spruce 
                    lieutenant spick &amp; span in uniform - a <pb ref="arm03020016007" seq="07"/> fat old doctor and an elderly squire - 
                    We didn&apos;t stay for it all - it was too hot and dusty to stand so long - Going back to the grounds - we fooled 
                    around &amp; in the course of time began packing up our exhibits which was quite a job. There was a good 
                    <sic corr="deal">dealed</sic> of canned stuff in it that all had to be wrapped. We were tired &amp; dirty when we 
                    got home just before dark &amp; glad to go to bed early.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The next day passed off without any excitement out of the ordinary but the next <hi1 rend="underscore">oh</hi1> 
                    <hi1 rend="underscore">my</hi1>! The McCarters - a very nice family of which I have four in school - sent word that they 
                    wanted us to go out there and see them make molasses - and that was the afternoon. Boiling sorghum is the 
                    great thing that keeps the youngsters out of school at present and the <pb ref="arm03020016008" seq="08" n="05"/>
                    McCarters had all been out for a week or more. Well we all piled into our old rickety hack Mr. Cresswell at the 
                    reins &amp; started off after school - to their thouse about three miles off - A mile isn&apos;t much on a paved 
                    street or one of our good roads - but over these it&apos;s some distance especially in a vehicle that has to be 
                    driven as carefully as our hack. When we took the trip up Smokey you remember a shaft broke which was fixed 
                    with a piece of barbed wire - Well Harrison had doctored it some more &amp; consequently they were at an angle 
                    so that when Dan stayed in the middle of the road &amp; went straight ahead as he should the hack didn&apos;t - 
                    but followed in a zigzag course rather dangerous at times when you are in a narrow road <pb ref="arm03020016009" seq="09"/>
                    way up the side of a mountain! We arrived however &amp; there in a field by the house were all the family working away. 
                    A huge oven had been built of stone with chimney at one end - and on top were three vats in which the sap was 
                    boiling &amp; at one side <del>was</del> <add place="supralinear">were</add> the rollers through 
                    which the sorghum is put. The juice is a light green &amp; boiling turns it brown - They had boiled about twenty eight 
                    gallons that day &amp; since noon of the day before. We took pieces of the cane &amp; dipped them into the big tins 
                    full of the molasses &amp; <hi1 rend="underscore">licked</hi1> them off - Did not care much for 
                    <hi1 rend="underscore">them</hi1>. People here always think of molasses as <hi1 rend="underscore">they</hi1> never 
                    <hi1 rend="underscore">it</hi1>. Chewed a piece of the cane too - sweet &amp; insipid tasting. 
                    Then we stirred <pb ref="arm03020016010" seq="10" n="06"/> the molasses cooking away - which is hard work - hot and 
                    steamy. The ladles are heavy too. But it was loads of fun &amp; incidentally messy - my clean white dress 
                    &amp; shoes of the morning were no longer! The mountains are lovely from their farm - and we hated to start 
                    back but finally did. It was dark when we got to <abbr expan="Gatlinburg">the burg</abbr> and just by our lane 
                    we stopped to let a car pass - It stopped too and a voice called out &quot;Anyone want to go to Pigeon Forge?&quot; 
                    Pigeon Forge is seven miles down the river you know &amp; quite a place not as big as Sevierville I guess 
                    which has about 1500 but is nearly half as big anyway. All the week there has been what is called 
                    &quot;Association&quot; going <pb ref="arm03020016011" seq="11"/>on there - a sort of conference of all the 
                    Baptist churches round about. People went and stayed all day &amp; took their youngsters out of school for it - 
                    several of ours stayed out for that purpose &amp; the school at Pigeon Forge had to close. Well I thought it was 
                    Mr. Huff in the car &amp; so asked Abbie if she didn&apos;t want to go - we two then jumped out &amp; got into 
                    the car &amp; found it to be two of the boys up here - we went anyway - supperless
                    and dirty. It was a lovely balmy night &amp; the boys had some pears which stayed the pangs of hunger a little. We
                    were too messy to go into the meeting which was well attended the church being full &amp; loads of boys &amp; men outside. 
                    We waited in the car till it was over - <pb ref="arm03020016012" seq="12" n="07"/>and then about 9:30 when it broke up started back 
                    - eight of us all together in that little Ford. They dropped off one by one so that we were back to our original number when we got about two
                    miles toward home. Here we stopped - left our Ford &amp; got into a big truck &amp; lumbered up the remaining five miles
                    in it. You see the boy in whose car we were - Lillard Maples - had some hauling to do in the <abbr expan="morning">a.m.</abbr>
                    with said truck &amp; thought he&apos;d save a trip by taking it up then. We sat on the front seat but it was awfully bumpy &amp; noisy
                    as you can imagine. But quite an adventure to get home at 11 p.m. in this qui<del>t</del>et burg via a truck!
                    Friday was quite a peaceful day except for an <pb ref="arm03020016013" seq="13"/> awful rainstorm at noon - just torrents 
                    came down - yet by the time school was dismissed in the <abbr expan="afternoon">p.m.</abbr> the sun came out &amp; we 
                    girls took a stroll - Spent the evening quietly in the light of the lamp reading.</p>
                <p>Saturday was a day of toil until about four when I was cleaned up and through sweeping sewing dusting etc. - I
                    went over to see the Huffs and eventually stayed for dinner. About seven went to the school-house where was an old-fashioned
                    sing scheduled to come off - You remember there was one the early part of <del>the</del> my arrival
                    at the house - Only one man showed up however but he was very nice and went <pb ref="arm03020016014" seq="14" n="8"/>
                    about  and sang some of those ancient &amp; quaint ballads with the help of his young daughter for an hour or so - Evelyn
                    played &amp; sang some - and then we all sang &amp; by 9:30 all were home and bedtime arrived. It gets dark so early &amp; 
                    we have an early supper so that the evenings are delightfully long - 8 seems like 10 - and nine o&apos;clock is midnight!
                </p>  
                <p>
                    The new preacher arrived yesterday &amp; held services - you know its once a month we have &quot;preaching&quot;
                    <hi1 rend="underscore">only</hi1>. None of us went Saturday so all took in the Sunday School - &amp; church - I didn&apos;t 
                    stay for the latter however. Will wind up with <abbr expan="Baptist Young Person&apos;s Union">B.Y.P.U.</abbr> <pb ref="arm03020016015" seq="15"/> tonight to make up for it though - I didn&apos;t go to 
                    <abbr expan="Baptist Young Person&apos;s Union">B. Y.</abbr> last Sunday night &amp; was studying &amp; looking over papers 
                    all alone downstairs - as the others had gone - &amp; Aunt Lizzie supposedly in bed - when in she came saying that she knew 
                    there were cows in the corn. Taking the lamp in one hand I went forth with her &amp; chased cows up &amp; down between the 
                    rows of corn. Can you picture it?
                </p>
                <p>
                    Must cease this long scribble - Do write me soon &amp; tell me all about everything. Write Jane <hi1 rend="underscore">often</hi1>
                    so she wont get lonesome &amp; be sure to get her some little thing she will appreciate - so much -  
                </p>
                <p>
                    Loads of love dear pa - 
                </p>
                <p>
                    Ruth
                </p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
