<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03020008000">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[Letter]  Sept. 6, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] Pi Phi Alumnae Club, Tacoma, WA</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
                    <name>Young, Phillip</name>
                    <name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
                    <name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
                </address>
                <date>2006</date>
                <idno type="SPCID">arm03020008000</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. 
                        For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee 
                        Libraries, Knoxville, TN</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from which the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
                <bibl>
                    <title>[Letter]  Sept. 6, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] Pi Phi Alumnae Club, Tacoma, WA</title>
                    <date value="1919-09-06">Sept. 6, 1919</date>
                    <author>
                        <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                    </author>
                    <extent>10p</extent>
                    <note type="summary">More about the school - Boys&apos; dormitory - Plans for first fair at the school - Trip after a still.</note>
                    <note type="box">3</note>
                    <note type="folder">2</note>
                    <note type="document">arm03020008000</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Local Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <list>
                        <item>Social life</item>
                        <item>School activities</item>
                        <item>Enrollment</item>
                        <item>Moonshine</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="abstract">
                <pb ref="arm03020008001" seq="01"/>
                <list>
                    <item>More about the school - </item>
                    <item>Boys&apos; dormitory - </item>
                    <item>Plans for first fair at the school - </item>
                    <item>Trip after a still.</item>
                </list>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="letter">
                <pb ref="arm03020008002" seq="02"/>
                <head>
                    <date value="1919-09-06"> Sept. 6, 1919</date>
                </head>
                <p>
                    Dear Pi Phi Sisters - 
                </p>
                <p>
                    One week from today will be &quot;the second Saturday&quot; and will no doubt see you gathered together for a meeting. Lida told me in her note
                    that no August meeting was held as so many were away - I hope the summer has been a happy and restful one for you all and that the coming year will 
                    strengthen the bond of Pi Phi and see much accomplished. The fraternity means so much to the community here and has done so much good that it makes 
                    one feel that the <pb ref="arm03020008003" seq="03"></pb> school is a great trust for which we can all work whether near or far away. These mountain people 
                    are very reserved and conservative and as one of there revival songs expresses it - &quot;What was good enough for my father is good enough for me!&quot; 
                    So that the coming generations whom we reach through the school are the ones who will really better conditions. But do not think that we teachers give without 
                    <hi1 rend="underscore">getting</hi1> - for sometimes one wonders if there is not more of <hi1 rend="underscore">getting</hi1> on our part after all. 
                    They are so hospitable and kind hearted - so pleased with simple things - so like big children in many ways - that you realize that there are some things
                    they have that the busy outside <pb ref="arm03020008004" seq="04" n="2"></pb> world has unfortunately grown away from. I&apos;m getting quite philosphopical am
                    I not and will now proceed to statements of what all we&apos;ve been doing for the past month.
                </p>
                <p>
                    First as to the school itself - we have enrolled exactly ninety-two of which the girls have a little higher enrollment that the boys. They are not up to
                    <add place="supralinear">the standard of</add> our schools in the West by any means - nor do they know how to settle down and study. On the other hand
                    when you remember that many of them come from homes <pb ref="arm03020008005" seq="05"></pb> where the parents are <del>uneducated</del><add 
                        place="supralinear">illiterate</add>, that they see no books or magazines except at school - that they do not come in contact with the outside world - not 
                    even as <del>far</del><add place="supralinear">near</add> as Sevierville fourteen miles away - that they have to stay out of school part
                    of the time to help with the washing and ironing and field work - you wonder that they do as well as they <hi1 rend="underscore">do</hi1> <hi1 rend="underscore">do</hi1>!!
                    (If my sentences get involved &amp; full of repetition please overlook for I cannot take the time to send you a polished and elegantly written epistle.) I attended
                    County Institute at Sevierville last Saturday - held in the assembly room of Murphy College. About thirty-five teachers were there - a small percent
                    <pb ref="arm03020008006" seq="06" n="3"></pb> I&apos;m told of all the number in the county. When I gazed upon their youthful childlike faces (for most of them were in
                    their teens or very early twenties) I did not wonder that wild stories circulated about the poor teaching and discipline and that the schools were in bad
                    condition. The salaries are very very low also and it seems that politics play<del>s</del> a large part in school management. Our school
                    is the best equipped in the county - so far.
                </p>
                <p>
                    We have at last a manual training <pb ref="arm03020008007" seq="07"></pb> teacher - Mr. Cresswell from Jefferson County. He is very young but seems to be just the
                    right man for the place. Since his arrival the boys&apos; dormitory has been started and for the past two weeks he with three boys from Pigeon Forge and 
                    Mrs. <sic corr="Proffitt">Profit</sic> cook and housekeeper - have  lived in the Maple house at the foot of our road. Wouldn&apos;t you like an outline of a 
                    day at school. Harrison the man about the place unlocks the building <add place="supralinear">&amp; starts the fires about 6 - </add> and at 7:45 either 
                    Emily or I ring the first bell - we take turns - a week at a time - The boys play ball - the girls play a little but seem to prefer to sit around and talk - until
                    eight o&apos;clock when the last bell rings for <hi1 rend="underscore">&quot;books&quot;</hi1> as they say. The whole <pb ref="arm03020008008" seq="08" n="4"></pb>
                    school gathers in my room - which is the largest and has the piano - for assembly or opening exercises presided over by one teacher for a week. Evelyn Bishop 
                    is usually present to play the piano &amp; help with the singing. We have the flag salute at least once a week - several songs - Scripture reading - and the
                    Lord&apos;s prayer. Miss Burton&apos;s primary class has acted a little play a couple of times - a quartet of boys sang once - another of girls - short talks
                    by a visitor or something of that sort adds variety occasionally.<pb ref="arm03020008009" seq="09"></pb>
                </p>
                <p>
                    Then the little ones march to their room followed by Miss Runyan&apos;s fourth fifth and sixth graders and Mr. Cresswell takes his four mathematics classes
                    and I my English &amp; grammar. These latter are held in the sewing room which serves the purpose nicely with its tables benches and blackboard. By this time
                    it is ten and a fifteen minute recess follows. One of the youngsters always takes our mail down to the postoffice at Charley Ogle&apos;s store during this interim.
                    Next is spelling conducted by Mr. Cresswell and I have fifteen minutes breathing spell until 10:30 when my beginning Latin class consisting of four arrives - Mr. 
                    <abbr expan="Cresswell">C.</abbr> meanwhile conducting a <pb ref="arm03020008010" seq="10" n="5"></pb> class in agriculture. After these he is through until 11:25 when 
                    he takes a geography class in Abbie Runyan&apos;s room so she can go home and help her two girls get dinner ready. I finish up the morning with geography and
                    writing. From 1 to 2 I have U.S. History and ancient history - recess from 2:00 to 2:15. Then Mr. Cresswell and Abbie each have their manual training and domestic
                    science every day (except Friday) until 3 <del>dismal</del> dismissal <pb ref="arm03020008011" seq="11"></pb> time and I have the leftovers in my 
                    room to study. Usually I take the last fifteen minutes for games or reading of some kind.
                </p>
                <p>
                    A girls&apos; club is organized now - consisting of girls from ten years up - and has a membership of about twenty-five - object good times and deeds of service. We
                    have had a picnic - a darning party - a party for the boys here at the house - and this next week there is to be a marshmallow roast. The darning party was here
                    after school last Monday and of course the very ones who couldn&apos;t darn failed to arrive. They are not keen about such things but all turned out for the party 
                    for the boys which was here last Friday evening. <pb ref="arm03020008012" seq="12" n="6"></pb>
                </p>
                <p>
                    It seems to take so much push to get things started here - and to rouse enthusiasm. We try to make the girls feel that <sic corr="its">it&apos;s</sic> their club 
                    and that they are the ones to plan and work with our help of course but that we are not the club.  
                </p>
                <p>
                    Mr. Cresswell is planning to organize a debating club among the boys which will be a fine thing for them. So much for the school - If you have any questions please
                    ask them there are so many new things that I can only touch briefly on them and no doubt leave out some that you&apos;d like to know. <pb ref="arm03020008013" seq="13"></pb>
                </p>
                <p>
                    We all enjoyed a visit of several days from Mrs. Helmick this past month. The mountain people think the world of her you know and she is in turn devoted
                    to them and loves all Gatlinburg and the school. She always inspires people to higher and better things. At present a Miss Turner is visiting
                    <add place="supralinear">who is</add> also a Pi Phi from Washington D.C. and Evelyn and I think she at one time has been a grand president for the other 
                    evening she mentioned something as having happened &quot;during my administration&quot; - It seems that she was the real originator of a school here in the
                    mountains but as she has never been here is greatly interested and charmed with everything.
                </p>
                <p>
                    In two weeks Gatlinburg and our school is to have a fair (the first one) on the school <pb ref="arm03020008014" seq="14" n="7"></pb> grounds - They are being
                    held all over the county this month and will be a fine way to bring the people together and give them some new ideas. The school itself will have 
                    exhibits (at least we hope to) of school work from manual training &amp; domestic science departments as well as maps writing papers etc. - also livestock
                    farm products &amp; fancy work. My next months letter will tell you about it all. We hope to work in various little things that at present are up in the air.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Now to lighter things! My dears you will <pb ref="arm03020008015" seq="15"></pb> never guess my latest wild escapade for in my wildest flights of fancy
                    about the mountains I never pictured myself going after a <hi1 rend="underscore">still</hi1>! But that is just precisely what we four teachers did one 
                    night in company with the deputy sheriff - our Harrison! It was last week and just before supper of a lovely evening - Busy as bees had we been since 
                    school - cleaning our rooms and the rest of the house - so Evelyn suggested that we have a little ride with Harrison in the &quot;back&quot; (two 
                    seated buggy) while she and Aunt Lizzie got supper ready - Off we started bareheaded - in light dresses &amp; thin shoes - little dreaming of what was 
                    to come! Before we had any more than gotten on the road the conversation had turned to <hi1 rend="underscore">stills</hi1> and their capture. Harrison
                    <pb ref="arm03020008016" seq="16" n="8"></pb> mysteriously confided to us that he was going after one the next night - Of course we girls wanted to go - but
                    that was the night of the club party so we said - why not then and there and the three of us soon had the poor man completely at our mercy and saying
                    we&apos;d stop and get &quot;Prof. Cresswell&quot; he meekly yielded. Of course there was no time for us to stop and dress for the part and anyway
                    we didn&apos;t quite realize the wild scramble that was awaiting us. To cut a long story short Mr. <abbr expan="Cresswell">C.</abbr> was charmed &amp;
                    bought a big watermelon while Harrison bought a flashlight &amp; <pb ref="arm03020008017" seq="17"></pb> some gay candy &amp; made several mysterious 
                    disappearances. He was perfect in his part the whole evening - so cautious - always whispered - stopped &amp; peered hither and &quot;yonder&quot;! At 
                    last we were off down the road towards Sevierville which we followed for about two miles. Then we left the hack Dan &amp; the watermelon and scrambled 
                    down to the river. Emily &amp; I in French heels &amp; white pumps had an awful time leaping gracefully from rock to rock as we had to cross the river
                    thusly. I landed at one spot with both feet in the water. That was a small item however &amp; arriving at the other side we plunged through the 
                    unbroken wilderness where <abbr expan="Harrison">H.</abbr> did the Sherlock Holmes act to perfection as stated above. Eventually we struck a faint
                    trail which lead right up a little &quot;branch&quot; in the wildest &quot;holler&quot;. For nearly a <pb ref="arm03020008018" seq="18" n="9"></pb> mile we
                    jumped scrambled &amp; almost crawled occasionally <abbr expan="Harrison">H.</abbr> went ahead &amp; then would come back &amp; we&apos;d whisper &amp; 
                    proceed silently as before. At last we had whiffs of moonshine - &quot;plumb&quot; strong ones too - &amp; then we came to the spot where was the furnace
                    and several barrels - the <del>furn</del> still itself was gone - <abbr expan="Harrison">H.</abbr> thought it probably concealed
                    in the laurels nearby while &quot;they&quot; were at work &quot;pulling fodder&quot;. Everyone is stripping their corn at present &amp; as soon as 
                    that is done the still will be active no doubt &amp; <abbr expan="Harrison">H.</abbr> will visit them again. It was almost dark when we started back
                    along our wild &amp; <pb ref="arm03020008019" seq="19"></pb> romantic trail. Going across the river was even more disastrous than before &amp; we were all 
                    wet to the knees except Abbie. After hitching up Dan we stood around in the dusty dark road in our dripping sodden shoes &amp; garments eating that
                    toothsome melon and how we giggled over the whole thing! Well it was about 9 or 9:30 when we finally got home after binding ourselves to secrecy as to 
                    our adventure. Evelyn thought it a wonderful &amp; unusual experience but rather risky as shooting <del>in</del> is no uncommon
                    thing at a raid - and also not <add place="supralinear">a</add> very wise thing for us as teachers to do. She is right of course and we won&apos;t go
                    again but we would not have missed it either - not any of it! <pb ref="arm03020008020" seq="20" n="10"></pb>
                </p>
                <p>
                    I have called at a number of homes and stayed all night Wednesday at a typical cabin - and thoroughly enjoyed it. Have also had some more long tramps
                    and tasted my first (and last) moonshine!
                </p>
                <p>
                    As it is almost time for the mail to go out I must say goodbye and hasten to the store with this letter which I&apos;d love to make twice as long. I have 
                    asked my mother to give you the kodak pictures for your meeting and if <pb ref="arm03020008021" seq="21"></pb> the Seattle Pi Phis will forgive me I&apos;m going
                    to ask them to share my letters with you as so far there has not been time for me to write them separately. Perhaps later there will be more opportunities
                    for writing.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Hoping that all is well with each one of you and that the inspiration to write me may come to some of you I am
                </p>
                <p>
                    Lovingly yours in Pi Phi
                </p>
                <p>
                    Ruth E. Sturley.
                </p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>