<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03030005000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[Letter]  Oct. 20, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
				<author>
					<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
				</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
					<name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
					<name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
				<address>
					<addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
				</address>
				<date>2006</date>
				<idno type="SPCID">arm03030005000</idno>
				<availability>
					<p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from whi1ch the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
				<bibl>
					<title>[Letter]  Oct. 20, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
					<date value="1919-10-20">Oct. 20, 1919</date>
					<author>
						<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
					</author>
					<extent>5p</extent>
					<note type="summary">Aunt Lydia Whaley. Her cabin.</note>
					<note type="box">3</note>
					<note type="folder">3</note>
					<note type="document">arm03030005000</note>
				</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
			</projectDesc>
		<editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<bibl>
						<title>Local Subject Headings</title>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<list>
						<item>Living Conditions</item>
						<item>People</item>
						<item>Social life</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div1 type="abstract">
				<pb ref="arm03030005001" seq="01"/>
				<p>
					<list>
						<item>Aunt Lydia Whaley</item>
						<item>Her cabin</item>
					</list>
				</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="letter">
				<pb ref="arm03030005002" seq="02"/>
				<head>
				<date value="1919-10-20">Oct. 20, 1919</date>
				</head>
				<p><del>
                        Dear papa - you surely have received the three letters sent you to Reedley by this time containing my doings - was very glad to get yours
                        and hope you do not leave too soon for home - and pa be sure to go down to Los Angeles - For you do not really know California until
                        you see the southern part - Hope that in your next you will tell me you are going. How was Berkeley? You did not tell me a thing about
                        what you did at Katherine&apos;s.</del>
                    </p>
				<p><del>
                        Jane seems to be getting along without you - but am glad Miss <unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">Pancoat</unclear> will be with
                        her until your return.</del>
                    </p>
				<p>
                    There is no particular news I guess since last I scribbled to you. It has been pretty rainy this week &amp; such slippery mud as results - you
                    can&apos;t imagine! Mr. Huff has put up <pb ref="arm03030005003" seq="03"/> his car for the winter &amp; will now depend on horse and buggy
                    to get through. Our mail doesn&apos;t get in till noon while ordinarily it comes up about 10:30.
                </p>
				<p>
                    Old Aunt Lydia Whaley a regular character around here and who has been away ever since my arrival visiting either children grandchildren 
                    <unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">or</unclear> great grandchildren. She lives about a mile up the river in a one room cabin so low that 
                    I just get in without stooping &amp; the ceiling just an inch above my head - It was simply cluttered full except around the fireplace with boxes - 
                    beds - tables bundles - firewood baskets of corn sacks of potatoes - while from the walls &amp; ceiling hang paper bags &amp; news papers of 
                    various herbs - seeds - etc. She does all her cooking  in the fireplace even to baking her cornbread. She is eighty years old or thereabouts.
                </p>
				<p>
                    I stayed all night at a house on Little Dudley Creek about <pb ref="arm03030005004" seq="04"/> a mile and a half from here. Evelyn went with me. Had a very 
                    nice time. It&apos;s rather strenuous staying over night however and doubt <unclear reason="illegible" resp="tl">plan</unclear> to do it very often.
                </p>
				<p>
                    Am sending some chestnuts to the family - if you were there you&apos;d get some too - but you won&apos;t now you see. They are good but pretty wormy.
                </p>
				<p>
                    Last night there was a &quot;spelling&quot; at the schoolhouse - We spelled round &amp; round - our side won fortunately.
                </p>
				<p>
                    Began this yesterday after Sunday School but did not finish it - am now sitting out on the front steps after school as it has been a lovely day - 
                    still wearing white &amp; enjoying butterflies &amp; bees! We had company yesterday - the Halls - and went for a little walk with Evelyn &amp; 
					them &amp; <pb ref="arm03030005005" seq="05"/>instead of going to <abbr expan="Baptist Young Person&apos;s Union">B.Y.</abbr> - went to bed &amp; slept like a log - Had a 
                    meeting with the girls after school tonight which kept me in late - we are planning a <sic corr="Halloween">Hallow - een</sic> party for next week -
                </p>
				<p><del>
                        Had a long letter from Jane this <abbr expan="morning">a.m.</abbr> - who seems busy and bustling as ever - you 
                        and I will keep her more busy with letter writing too.</del>
                    </p>
				<p><del>
                        Does California come up to your expectations? Now do write soon &amp; tell me how you pass your days.</del>
                    </p>
				<p>
                    Have decided to spend the weekend at Knoxville - if the weather is so we can get out. It will soon be impossible even to get to 
                    <del>a movie</del> Sevierville and a glimpse of street cars - paved streets &amp; bustling people will do me good.
                </p>
				<p>
                    Loads of love
                </p>
				<p>
                    Ruth.
                </p>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
