<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03030009000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[Letter]  Oct. 29, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
				<author>
					<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
				</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
					<name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
					<name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
				<address>
					<addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
				</address>
				<date>2006</date>
				<idno type="SPCID">arm03030009000</idno>
				<availability>
					<p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from whi1ch the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
				<bibl>
					<title>[Letter]  Oct. 29, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
					<date value="1919-10-29">Oct. 29, 1919</date>
					<author>
						<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
					</author>
					<extent>4p</extent>
					<note type="summary">In Knoxville. Trip to Wear's Valley for baskets. Home again at the burg.</note>
					<note type="box">3</note>
					<note type="folder">3</note>
					<note type="document">arm03030009000</note>
				</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
			</projectDesc>
		<editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<bibl>
						<title>Local Subject Headings</title>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<list>
						<item>People</item>
						<item>Landscape</item>
						<item>Baskets</item>
						<item>Living conditions</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div1 type="abstract">
				<pb ref="arm03030009001" seq="01"/>
				<p>
					<list>
						<item>In Knoxville</item>
						<item>Trip to Wear's Valley for baskets</item>
						<item>Home again at the burg</item>
					</list>
				</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="letter">
				<pb ref="arm03030009002" seq="02"/>
				<head>
					<date value="1919-10-29">Oct. 29, 1919</date>
					</head>
				<!-- Page one missing -->
				<p>
					<del>it&apos;s</del>
					<add place="supralinear">Knoxville</add> is a big town rather than a city - population 80 or 90,000 - 
                    people all awfully ordinary looking - no culture or refinement - It&apos;s a university town too. We went down one street where all the 
                    mountain people who drive in with produce line up their wagons while all the <del>Kn</del> city - people buy - 
                    regular public market - chickens - fruit - vegetables - nuts molasses &amp; flowers for sale. We felt quite at home among them - so 
                    many familiar types!
                </p>
				<p>
                    Well we had to be at the depot by 7 - but as it was the Sunday we turned back our watches - it wasn&apos;t so bad. The car company 
                    started their cars that morning using strike breakers - and <del>even</del> later in the day there was trouble &amp; 
                    has been all week - state troops are there now as a general strike is set for Saturday - <abbr expan="November">Nov.</abbr> 1st -
                </p>
				<pb ref="arm03030009003" seq="03"/>
				<p>
                    The ride between  <abbr expan="Knoxville">K.</abbr> &amp; <abbr expan="Sevierville">S.</abbr> was lovely for it&apos;s in the mountains 
                    where the foliage is becoming gorgeous - its farther along than up here - where there is much greenness yet - our field of rye is fresh &amp; green 
                    just right for the cows now. When we reached <abbr expan="Sevierville">S.</abbr> again &amp; had gotten into a jitney ready for the ride up the hill to the 
                    Bishop&apos;s Evelyn came climbing up with the information that if we so desired we would all leave for <unclear reason="illegible" resp="tal">Wears</unclear> 
                    Valley where she wanted to find a basket woman. Of course we were all enthusiasm - so hastening home we had a hasty lunch &amp; then set forth in 
                    the worst looking old Ford - we three girls &amp; Mrs. B. - but the top was down - the day was lovely - too warm for wraps so we were all gay 
                    as larks - Wears Valley is in the mountains back of Pigeon Forge - It&apos;s a wild country - the people real mountaineers and the cabin where we 
                    went was typical - 4 double beds <pb ref="arm03030009004" seq="04"/>in one little room with small built in kitchen - walls covered with news paper - baskets &amp; 
                    dried stuff hanging around - rocker table &amp; straight chairs - Two half grown &amp; very pretty girls were home - It seemed miles aways from 
                    civilization &amp; so it is in more than one sense.
                </p>
				<p>
                    The people are so attractive &amp; well featured in spite of the dirt &amp; untidiness.
                </p>
				<p>
                    Well we got to Pigeon Forge about two where our same rigs met us and by 4:30 we were home again - Aunt Lizzie &amp; Mrs. Profit waiting on 
                    the front porch for us &amp; so pleased to see us as we had <hi1 rend="underscore">all</hi1> been gone over the week end.
                </p>
				<p>
                    It took the rest of the day to clean up - put away cot &amp; go to <abbr expan="Baptist Young Person&apos;s Union">B.Y.P.</abbr> where three of 
                    us teachers had to talk impromptu.
                </p>
				<p>
                    Monday I spent getting papers &amp; report cards ready - Tuesday (yesterday) was spent in getting a letter <add place="supralinear">ready</add> 
                    for the Arrow about the school - Stopped a little while to go down to a corn husking in the Maples
                    barn at the foot of our lane - weather uncertain so not a large crowd -
                </p>
				<p>
                    Tonight was the debate - only two of us on a side &amp; the other side won - However it was fun after all &amp; no doubt I won&apos;t mind 
                    next time <add place="supralinear">at all</add> really didn&apos;t mind it much tonight.
                </p>
				<p>
					<del>Well it&apos;s bedtime and must bid you a fond goodnight <unclear reason="illegible" resp="tal">?</unclear> just lots of love and kisses -</del>
				</p>
				<p>
                    Ruth.
                </p>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
