<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03030014000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[Letter]  Nov. 9, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
				<author>
					<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
				</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
					<name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
					<name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
				<address>
					<addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
				</address>
				<date>2006</date>
				<idno type="SPCID">arm03030014000</idno>
				<availability>
					<p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from which the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
				<bibl>
					<title>[Letter]  Nov. 9, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
					<date value="1919-11-09">Nov. 9, 1919</date>
					<author>
						<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
					</author>
					<extent>7p</extent>
					<note type="summary">Red Cross Meeting - Details of interruptions that break into our schedule</note>
					<note type="box">3</note>
					<note type="folder">3</note>
					<note type="document">arm03030014000</note>
				</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
			</projectDesc>
		<editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<bibl>
						<title>Local Subject Headings</title>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<list>
						<item>Living conditions</item>
						<item>People</item>
						<item>Social life</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div1 type="abstract">
				<pb ref="arm03030014001" seq="01"/>
				<p>
					<list>
						<item>Red Cross Meeting</item>
						<item>Details of interruptions that break into our schedule</item>
					</list>
				</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="letter">
				<pb ref="arm03030014002" seq="02"/>
				<head>
					<date value="1919-11-09">Nov. 9, 1919</date>
				</head>
				<p>
                   Dearest Jane - Sunday afternoon and a beautiful day though cold enough in the house to make a furnace fire desirable - Our little
                    frosty spell is over and yesterday <abbr expan="afternoon">p.m.</abbr> it tried to get warm and rainy again. Wonder what you are all
                    doing today. Picture you enjoying a ride somewhere. Do you suppose I&apos;ll remember how to drive? At last the baskets are
                    ready to send - so you may expect them about the time this letter arrives. The big one is not strong enough to go through the mail
                    like the others so put it in the box with a small one as the sack was not large enough for the three small ones together as I first
                    expected to send them. Among the newspapers in the box you will find a few sweet peppers they look like ours only are not
                    peppery. We cut some &amp; ate with <pb ref="arm03030014003" seq="03"/> rice and gravy for dinner today. I have seen them as yellow
                    as can be but could not get them to send you - nor have I been able to get the October beans &amp; the persimmons they say are
                    too soft to send. Have you even eaten them? Funny little things! The big basket is yours &amp; the other Nellie&apos;s while in the 
                    sack is one for Jo &amp; Mabel. Hope they suit. I like them very much especially yours Jane - Am sending <add place="supralinear">the</add>
                    small kind to Aunt <unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">Lottie</unclear> - Aunt Carrie &amp; Charlotte &amp; want a couple
                    more for Maudie &amp; Fannie. These are about all I can do for Christmas presents except the immediate family.
                </p>
				<p>
                    I wonder if you would just as soon call up Miss <unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">Lathrop</unclear> or <pb ref="arm03030014004" seq="04"/>
                    have Nellie K. <!-- Unknow name bds --> do it &amp; find out where she got the paint for our wooden toys two years ago. It was a 
                    powder which we mixed with water &amp; glue &amp; which we have not been able to get in Knoxville. Ask her what Chicago firm
                    or some other place near us would have it? Whether a school supply house or regular paint store.
                </p>
				<p>
                    Since writing you <abbr expan="Wednesday">Wed</abbr>
					<abbr expan="evening">eve.</abbr> have not done anything of note. Darned - 
                    looked over my papers &amp; prepared lessons - visited with Miss Langmaid &amp; fussed around generally. Dr. Massey blew in
                    Friday &amp; brought along a grand beef roast. Evelyn always cuts off a few slices to fry for supper when he brings one - The Red 
                    Cross meeting was at 6:30 so we went over with our lamps as usual - Some of the young people came &amp; only a few - very few
                    of the older - I had taken down the big map and put up the Red Cross posters that Charlotte sent - they came just at the right time and
                    look very pretty. My <unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">photogravers</unclear> look very nice too - on the piano have one of the 
                    baskets filled with hemlock branches while on a flower stand below my little silk flag is another with pine branches &amp; cones. Across
                     the panels at the back are pages of thin writing and printing. We had expected a speaker from Sevierville but they phoned up that the
                    roads were too bad &amp; though told it was possible for a car to get through now - no one arrived. Evelyn &amp; Miss Langmaid
                    talked some - also an ex-soldier Charlie Clabo - then we sang &amp; sang &amp; that finished it. <pb ref="arm03030014005" seq="05"/>
				</p>
				<p>
                   Yesterday was a busy day - We (Emily &amp; I) did our sweeping right after breakfast - I packed up the baskets too - fixed my room - 
                    got some films ready to send off - another mean little job - made the war cake &amp; cleaned up myself. Aunt Lizzie didn&apos;t feel
                    good &amp; went to bed before supper - Mrs. Proffitt was over as Mr. <abbr expan="Cresswell">C.</abbr> &amp; Abbie both went
                    home this weekend. Mrs. Huff &amp; Stella came over with some friends of their from Knoxville a Mrs. <unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">
                        Borlin</unclear> &amp; her daughter. Emily &amp; I are going to try to go over to Huff&apos;s some night this week &amp; stay.
                    She has been wanting us to do it for a long time &amp; we had <pb ref="arm03030014006" seq="06"/> planned to go last night if these 
                    friends hadn&apos;t arrived. So many interruptions all day long here - a Mrs McCarter came before breakfast to have Evelyn call up
                    Knoxville General Hospital to find out about her son <unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">Arlie</unclear> (had him in school a
                    little while) whose hand had been hurt. Far a wonder she was able to get a message through &amp; then had to write a letter for her - 
                    (she can&apos;t read nor write). Then a Mr. Jerry Whaley came to have a message sent - Richard Ogle came to <del>have</del>
                    make some hearth brooms - Otha Reagan &amp; his father were hauling up our wood - <unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">
						<hi1 rend="underscore">Isorie</hi1>
					</unclear>
                    came to get rags soap etc. to scrub up the school - etc. etc. There is a great coming &amp; going here. The only place not to be 
                    interrupted is off in the woods or shut up in your room <pb ref="arm03030014007" seq="07"/> as I am now.
                </p>
				<p>
                    This morning was Sunday School as usual after which Emily &amp; I walked a mile or more up  <abbr expan="Baskins Creek">Baskin&apos;s</abbr>
                    with the Ogle girls &amp; after much difficulty managed to get away without having to stay to dinner. Wore my new bouquet - which
                    everyone admired muchly - It is surely awfully cute!  We saw so many butterflies on our walk - think of that!
                </p>
				<p>
                    This is rather a stupid letter I fear but am really rather sleepy for some reason or other &amp; not a bit <unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">newsy</unclear> - 
                </p>
				<p>
                   Miss Langmaid is very very nice - extremely calm &amp; placid in her way but inexorable too - one would never dream of running in 
                    opposition to her wishes unless absolutely necessary! She used to have one of Aunt Lizzie&apos;s nieces in school - <hi1 rend="underscore">Exy</hi1>
                    for short - from <hi1 rend="underscore">Ex&apos;</hi1>
					<hi1 rend="underscore">a</hi1>
					<hi1 rend="underscore">mine</hi1>! Think of 
                    that for a name. The machinery <add place="supralinear">for chair factory</add> &amp; dishes are at Sevierville but not  here yet - the
                    site for the factory isn&apos;t settled as yet so the machinery doesn&apos;t matter but we do long for our dishes! Evelyn tries to 
                    find someone <del>to</del> who is coming this way to bring up our stuff rather than make a special trip after it.
                </p>
				<p>
                    Will write again in a day or so - with loads of love to you all as ever - 
                </p>
				<p>
                    Ruth
                </p>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
