<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03030008000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[Letter]  Oct. 28, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
				<author>
					<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
				</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
					<name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
					<name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
				<address>
					<addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
				</address>
				<date>2006</date>
				<idno type="SPCID">arm03030008000</idno>
				<availability>
					<p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from whi1ch the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
				<bibl>
					<title>[Letter]  Oct. 28, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
					<date value="1919-10-28">Oct. 28, 1919</date>
					<author>
						<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
					</author>
					<extent>7p</extent>
					<note type="summary">Trip to Knoxville. Trip to Wear's Valley. Debating Club</note>
					<note type="box">3</note>
					<note type="folder">3</note>
					<note type="document">arm03030008000</note>
				</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
			</projectDesc>
		<editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<bibl>
						<title>Local Subject Headings</title>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<list>
						<item>Living Conditions</item>
						<item>Knoxville, Tennessee</item>
						<item>School programs</item>
						<item>People</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div1 type="abstract">
				<pb ref="arm03030008001" seq="01"/>
				<p>
					<list>
						<item>Trip to Knoxville</item>
						<item>Trip to Wear's Valley</item>
						<item>Debating Club</item>
					</list>
				</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="letter">
				<pb ref="arm03030008002" seq="02"/>
				<head>
					<date value="1919-10-28">Oct. 28, 1919</date>
				</head>
				<!-- Page 1 is MISSING -->
				<p>
                    my last epistle was written on Wed. As usual it rained Thursday &amp; Evelyn still was in Sevierville. In the evening we organized
                    a debating club - Steve Whaley - one of our prominent citizens is president &amp; Mr. Cresswell secretary - name - Gatlinburg
                    Literary Society. We hope it is going to work into a club just for the boys and men - For they leave everything to us girls to do as
                    long as we&apos;re around. We debate tomorrow night - Mr. <abbr expan="Cresswell">C.</abbr> made out the list &amp; put
                    himself in and me just to get things started - So picture me on the negative side with one of the girls Emma Maples and Lawson
                    Reagan (our chorister) 
                </p>
				<p>
                    The affirmative - Mr. <abbr expan="Cresswell">C.</abbr> Tom McCarter and Rose Carr one of the school girls also - Our subject
                    Resolved - that a <del>public</del>
					<add place="supralinear">state</add> highway <pb ref="arm03030008003" seq="03"/>
                    will be of greater benefit to <abbr expan="Gatlinburg">G.</abbr> than railroad. Well such is life!
                </p>
				<p>
                    Had to talk at <abbr expan="Baptist Young Person&apos;s Union">B.Y.</abbr> Sunday night too - poor Tom <abbr expan="McCarter">McC.</abbr> was all
                    distressed over topic given him so helped him out. Evelyn &amp; Mr. <abbr expan="Cresswell">C.</abbr> also talked impromptu like
                    myself - Emily is on for next Sunday!
                </p>
				<p>
                    Well to return to my adventures. Emily &amp; I gave up all thought of Knoxville for Friday <abbr expan="morning">a.m.</abbr> was a steady
                    downpour but lo at noon the brilliant sunshine so cheered us that we gaily packed our bag &amp; got Mr. <abbr expan="Cresswell">C.</abbr>
                    to hustle around about transportation down to Sevierville - He &amp; Abbie both decided to go in too so about three we started off in two
                    buggies - Emily &amp; I in one with <unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">Otha</unclear> Reagan one of the boys and the other two in
                    the second. It proved to be a perfectly beautiful afternoon balmy and too warm really for <pb ref="arm03030008004" seq="04"/> our jackets - I 
                    wore my lovely hat &amp; felt quite dressy! It took us 2 hours to drive the <hi1 rend="underscore">seven</hi1> miles to <del>
						<abbr expan="Sevierville">S.</abbr>
					</del>
					<add place="supralinear">Pigeon Forge</add> - such roads you never saw - impossible for a car even a Ford to get through - horse walked most of the
                    way. At <abbr expan="Pigeon Forge">P.F.</abbr> we were reunited in a Ford however for here the pike takes us to <abbr expan="Sevierville">S.</abbr>
                    &amp; we were soon at the Bishops&apos; Emily &amp; I - where they expected us. <del>and</del> After dinner we sallied
                    forth to Murphy College to an amateur minstrel show - not half bad either. Then bed &amp; off on the train by 8:30. It cleared again and was 
                    lovely all the rest of the weekend - Miss Whittle went down on the train with us. The street car strike made walking necessary &amp; we
                    gaily trod the pavement from the station about half a mile or so up town. There is one main business street - Gay Street where everything is
                    located. The new Farragut Hotel - very nice proved to be full and we finally wound up at the St. James - nice enough but not as nice as we would have liked.
                    Well we put in a busy day shopping - eating - walking - the movie etc. It was lots of fun and did us both good - For when we left Sunday 
                    <abbr expan="morning">a.m.</abbr> at 9:30 we were perfectly satisfied with our trip and at the same time pleased at the thought of returning
                    to our green mountains again. Evelyn met us at the depot with the information  that we were to hustle up to the house and then on a trip up Wears Valley - 
                    Charmed at the prospect we hustled in our <unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">jitney</unclear> up the hill bag &amp; baggage - Didn&apos;t buy much
                    but seemed to take lots of space - comb &amp; brush for Aunt Lizzie&apos;s birthday - some bulbs - hairpins - &quot;Young Visitors&quot; for Mrs.
                    Bishop - (Emily got her flowers) candles <pb ref="arm03030008005" seq="05" n="03"/> for our jack-o-lanterns - cookie cutters for Abbie. Later the Ford
                    came after us and we three girls &amp; Mrs. <abbr expan="Bishop">B.</abbr> set forth. We went nearly up the pike to Pigeon Forge but turned off
                    there right up into the ruts. Where we climbed in the trusty Ford to the top of one thereby having the finest view I&apos;ve had yet - and then down and 
                    part way up another. There were a number of the usual cabins &amp; people en route - our destination was Jim Watson&apos;s house. We found it up 
                    a holler off the road and across a creek - not very far. Mrs. Watson is going to make baskets - hence our pursuit of her. She <del>is</del>
                    wasn&apos;t home but two half grown girls showed what she had done - such pretty girls. But such a place - four double beds in that one room and a 
                    little kitchen! Smells and dirt galore.
                </p>
				<p>
                    We had a delightful trip &amp; <pb ref="arm03030008006" seq="06"/> about two got to the Forge where eventually the same boy &amp; buggies brought  us 
                    home - arriving about 4:30. It took the rest of the day to clean up - put away - have supper and <abbr expan="Baptist Young Person&apos;s Union">B.Y.P.</abbr>
                    - start the wheels going again. Spent about &#36;10 on the expedition - all told including expense there and back - but am glad I went for don&apos;t expect
                    to go out again until <abbr expan="Christmas">Xmas.</abbr> We figured up our New Orleans trip will cost nearly &#36;125 apiece - unless we can
                    stay at the Pi Phi House or <abbr expan="Young Women&apos;s Christian Association">Y.W.</abbr> as we hope to be able to do.
                </p>
				<p>
                    Monday after school was a meeting  with the girls about the party - then corrected papers &amp; worked my report cards till bed time - and planned Halloween
                    <unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">stunts</unclear> with Evelyn.
                </p>
				<p>
                    Today as I said before was struggling with my Arrow letter <pb ref="arm03030008007" seq="07"/> getting home late from school - Sat out on the porch
                    in white minus wrap &amp; wrote &amp; watched a storm blow up &amp; pass away again. Such huge black clouds but not a drop of rain
                    after all.
                </p>
				<p>
                    Stopped about half an hour or so tonight to go down with Emily to a corn husking held in the Maples barn at the foot of our lane - where our boy&apos;s
                    dormitory was you remember. The Maples expect to move back there this week. It was such an uncertain night that only a dozen or so were
                    there - Sit on the ground and husk - tossing ears up into big bin - might be fun with a big crowd - but we soon wended our way upward again. Finished 
                    my letter - while the rest of them sat on the porch - even Aunt Lizzie - &amp; then we all went to bed - but <hi1 rend="underscore">me</hi1>!
                </p>
				<p>
                    Must cease for now - will measure my head in the <abbr expan="morning">a.m.</abbr> as the tape is downstairs just now.
                </p>
				<p>
                    Goodnight dearest Jane - with ever so much love
                </p>
				<p>
                    Ruth
                </p>
				<p>
                    P.S. On reading this over it sounds very airy like and also <hi1 rend="underscore">jerky</hi1> and erratic - but have written so fast and am also
                    sleepy that you will excuse and know that there is much love with it too - won&apos;t you?
                </p>
				<p>
                    Head <unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">23</unclear>
					<abbr expan="inch">in.</abbr> low down where cap would come - Which kind are 
                    you going to make - shall enjoy either?
                </p>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
