<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03030012000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[Letter]  Nov. 4, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
				<author>
					<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
				</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
					<name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
					<name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
				<address>
					<addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
				</address>
				<date>2006</date>
				<idno type="SPCID">arm03030012000</idno>
				<availability>
					<p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from which the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
				<bibl>
					<title>[Letter]  Nov. 4, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
					<date value="1919-11-04">Nov. 4, 1919</date>
					<author>
						<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
					</author>
					<extent>7p</extent>
					<note type="summary">Community Halloween Party in the school - Visit over night at the Reagan&apos;s - Trip to Round Top</note>
					<note type="box">3</note>
					<note type="folder">3</note>
					<note type="document">arm03030012000</note>
				</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
			</projectDesc>
		<editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<bibl>
						<title>Local Subject Headings</title>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<list>
						<item>Living Conditions</item>
						<item>Holiday</item>
						<item>People</item>
						<item>Hiking</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div1 type="abstract">
				<pb ref="arm03030012001" seq="01"/>
				<p>
					<list>
						<item>Community Halloween Party in the school</item>
						<item>Visit over night at the Reagan&apos;s</item>
						<item>Trip to Round Top</item>
					</list>
				</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="letter">
				<pb ref="arm03030012002" seq="02"/>
				<head>
					<date value="1919-11-04">Nov. 4, 1919</date>
				</head>
				<p><del>
                    Dearest pa - It will be a week tomorrow <abbr expan="Wednesday">(Wed)</abbr> since last I wrote you and have not heard from you during
                     that time unless you sent the Tacoma newspapers which came today - Thank you muchly for them - but I do think our paper a disgrace with it&apos;s
                    glaring red headlines &amp; nothing but sensational news. A letter came from Jane also in which she spoke of your settling in California - 
                    that she would hate to leave the children but otherwise did not care somehow! But if you do contemplate making the change be sure to stay 
                    on the coast for inland it&apos;s insufferably hot &amp; remember too that there is <hi1 rend="underscore">no</hi1>
						<hi1 rend="underscore">booster</hi1>
                    like the Californian. To him his state is Paradise &amp; nothing else.</del>
                </p>
				<p>
                    Since my last epistle have done a number of things which I&apos;ll <pb ref="arm03030012003" seq="03"/> proceed to relate. A Miss Freeman an Iowa
                    Pi Phi from the same chapter as Miss Brenholtz whom she knew in college has been with us since <abbr expan="Thursday">Thurs.</abbr> and
                    leaves in the morning for her home. Both Thursday and Friday were devoted to preparations for the Halloween Party for <abbr expan="Friday">Fri.</abbr>
                    eve. It (the affair) began at 6:30 and everybody came so that the school was crowded with old &amp; young - The rooms (Abbie&apos;s &amp; mine)
                    were made into one &amp; looked very pretty decorated with autumn leaves. The girls dressed in sheets &amp; pillowcases gave a witch song
                    in the dark carrying jack-o-lanterns &amp; marching around the rooms. Then we divided the youngsters in two sets &amp; had a trackmeet on the 
                    order of the one Jane&apos;s club once gave. Then they bobbed for apples etc. and lastly three girls told fortunes in the two cloak rooms. By nine the 
                    doughnuts (our refreshments made <pb ref="arm03030012004" seq="04"/> by the girls&apos; cooking classes) were passed &amp; eaten &amp; all 
                    started for home. We had made a lot of witches cats - bats moons &amp; jack-o-lanterns of paper &amp; colored them &amp; decorated 
                    blackboards &amp; windows with them. All enjoyed it &amp; behaved pretty well - Strung up a couple of big jack-o-lanterns &amp; boughs of 
                    autumn leaves on the flagpole - but that wasn&apos;t much for Halloween was it?
                </p>
				<p>
                    Saturday was a <hi1 rend="underscore">big</hi1>
					<hi1 rend="underscore">day</hi1> for we took a most strenuous trip - Miss Freeman - Mr. Cresswell - 
                    Emily &amp; myself - We climbed Round Top - a perfect cone of a little mountain about seven miles away. On the way (we started at 8:15 from the 
                    <abbr expan="Gatlinburg">burg</abbr>) we made a call about 5 miles up - at a house where a Reagan family lives and here we were joined by 
                    three more - Charlie Clabo &amp; two of the Reagan youngsters - It was fortunate they went too for we would never have found the way without their
                    guidance. At the foot of the mountain we stopped for lunch - building a campfire right by the creek - Roaring Fork - It was quite an elaborate meal too.
                    The boys had found apples in a deserted orchard &amp; wild grapes - we fried the former - also sweet potatoes &amp; eggs &amp; made coffee - 
                    All of this with bread - biscuits - jelly - and doughnuts proved most filling though originally planned for four &amp; we had nearly doubled! Just as 
                    we had finished our last cookery - the rain which had threatened finally came in <pb ref="arm03030012005" seq="05"/> earnest &amp; we seized our
					<unclear>viands</unclear> &amp; hastened a short distance to a huge rock big as a house which was hollowed out neatly along one side &amp; formed a perfect shelter
                    for us all. We then started for the top striking right up the side - pulling ourselves along by catching at the laurel little pine trees &amp; other shrubs &amp;
                    getting a wonderful view as we went higher &amp; higher - It took a good hour to get to the top &amp; how I panted en route. It is by far the hardest 
                    climb I have ever attempted - the Smoky trip had nothing like it. By the time we reached the summit the storm &amp; gray mist had come upon us
                    so that we could not get a view - and when we returned  the rain again came down <pb ref="arm03030012006" seq="06"/> this time in torrents. I was
                    soaked to the skin literally - wore my tramping costume but on account of the warmness of the atmosphere was minus hat &amp; coat. However
                    the continuous exercise of walking kept me comfortably warm in spite of my dampness. We all enjoyed the experience &amp; had a good time
                    laughing at each other&apos;s apperance. However we were pleased to reach the <abbr expan="Gatlinburg">burg</abbr> in the darkness at 
                    6:30 &amp; not have to pass the bunch of porch gazers usually congregated in front of the stores as long as daylight lasts!
                </p>
				<p>
                    Sunday was Church Sunday which proved to be the usual three hour session! including <pb ref="arm03030012007" seq="07"/> including Sunday School.
                    I didn&apos;t go last month but went this time. After that was dinner &amp; some of the the Saturday work to be done - cleaning my room etc.
                    Next the weather having turned clear &amp; cold Abbie Miss Freeman &amp; I made a call at one of the houses up the river getting back just at
                    dusk - and just as Harrison drove up with the long expected Miss Langmaid - She is the head of the school committee &amp; will be with us about
                    two months - is very nice &amp; pleasant - quite short &amp; stout - wealthy too I imagine.
                </p>
				<p>
                    Well Monday (last night) I was asked again to stay all night <del>with</del> at Lucrettie Reagan&apos;s about half a mile up 
                    Little Pigeon &amp; where we made the call <unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">Sunday</unclear>
					<unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">Fith</unclear>
                    I had to go so Emily &amp; I both went. That mountain woman old Mrs.<abbr expan="Aunt Sophie Campbell">Camel</abbr> stayed there too - 
                    Imagine me sitting in the family circle around the fireplace with Mrs. <abbr expan="Aunt Sophie Campbell">C.</abbr> beside me puffing away at
                    her long stemmed pipe while Mr. Reagan puffed away opposite! Then sleeping on a mattress of corn shucks under a feather tick! Emily &amp;
                    I slept together - Mrs. <abbr expan="Aunt Sophie Campbell">C.</abbr> Lucrettie &amp; her little sister all slept in the other bed in the same room - 
                    <hi1 rend="underscore">in</hi1>
					<hi1 rend="underscore">their</hi1>
					<hi1 rend="underscore">clothes</hi1>! 
                </p>
				<p>
                    Well it&apos;s late &amp; must get to bed - spent all day at school doing odds &amp; ends &amp; tonight we sat around the fireplace - I looked 
                    over my newspapers. Miss <abbr expan="Freeman">F.</abbr> leaves in the morning - Hoping to hear from you tomorrow &amp; that you are
                    soon to start for the <hi1 rend="underscore">best</hi1> part of <abbr expan="California">Calif.</abbr> &amp; with loads of love <hi1 rend="underscore">as</hi1>
					<hi1 rend="underscore">ever</hi1>
				</p>
				<p>
                    (no <unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">voting</unclear> for us!) Ruth 
                </p>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
