<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03040013000">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[Letter] March 3, 1920, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
                    <name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
                    <name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
                </address>
                <date>2006</date>
                <idno type="SPCID">arm03040013000</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. 
                        For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee 
                        Libraries, Knoxville, TN</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from which the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
                <bibl>
                    <title>[Letter] March 3, 1920, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                    <date value="1920-03-03">March 3, 1920</date>
                    <author>
                        <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                    </author>
                    <extent>4p</extent>
                    <note type="summary">Time for report cards - </note>
                    <note type="box">3</note>
                    <note type="folder">4</note>
                    <note type="document">arm03040013000</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Local Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <list>
                        <item>Living Conditions</item>
                        <item>Students</item>
                        <item>Snow</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="abstract">
                <pb ref="arm03040013001" seq="01"/>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <item>Time for report cards - </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="letter">
                <pb ref="arm03040013002" seq="02"/>
                <head>
                    <date value="1920-03-03">March 3, 1920</date>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <del>Dearest family your letters came Monday and Tuesday respectively with a long one from Mabel - Nellie K. - Gail - and Mrs. Davis - 
                        also cards from Lida telling me that the baskets had arrived. That reminds me - in my reply to her I did not tell her that the package she had sent has 
                        <hi1 rend="underscore">not</hi1> come - she wanted to know about it - Will you please tell her?</del>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <del>I am glad you are all well and that things are going along as usual. I am very anxious to see you - and also wonder what you think 
                        about my staying here a</del><pb ref="arm03040013003" seq="03"></pb><del>nother year. Where is the money coming from for my going home &amp; return if I do teach here next 
                            year? Katherine has been writing me again very enthusiastically about Oakland but I do not feel drawn toward it in spite of the large salary. It seems 
                            hard to find out &amp; decide what is the best thing to do but I surely will know before long. Nellie Jane must be the cutest thing - am crazy to see all three 
                            of the youngsters - suppose the two scoots Weir &amp; h. j. will have to get acquainted all over again with me. It doesn&apos;t seem as though it were 
                        time to garden yet</del> - Our snowstorm was so like winter but the last three <pb ref="arm03040013004" seq="04"></pb>days have been sunny &amp; today was 
                    warm like spring exactly - a tree toad was singing away somewhere when I was dressing for supper tonight. <del>Am glad our Dodge 
                        is in trim again. Nellie K. says her is just fine &amp; looks very gay in the new green license plates! Am sorry that John has been sick - Did the U. shut 
                        down because of the flu?</del> We surely have been fortunate in the burg - so far there has been little sickness except bad colds. Things have gone 
                    on as usual this week - drill &amp; play take up lots of time - Went for a walk with Abbie up the road one evening - Tonight took a nap after school - &amp; 
                    consequently have sat &amp; written letters all evening.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Report cards should have been out today but I just couldn&apos;t get at them before &amp; didn&apos;t feel like it tonight &amp; <hi1 rend="underscore">may</hi1> 
                    tomorrow. Isn&apos;t that a thrilling state of affairs? Imagine going back to the iron clad rules of the regular school system after the fine &amp; easy 
                    way of management here! I really enjoy looking at those cards here on the table &amp; my register &amp; then turning my back on them so careless like!
                </p>
                <p>
                    <del>Arthur is probably too busy &amp; taken up with his own affairs to say very much of anything. As for my talking - after teaching all day 
                        my head is like an empty cistern! Am glad you liked the N. A. pictures. Thank <!-- Pages missing TAL --></del>
                </p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>