<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03020009000">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[Letter]  Sept. 7, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
                    <name>Young, Phillip</name>
                    <name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
                    <name>Bridger Dyson-Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
                </address>
                <date>2006</date>
                <idno type="SPCID">arm03020009000</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. 
                        For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee 
                        Libraries, Knoxville, TN</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from which the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
                <bibl>
                    <title>[Letter]  Sept. 7, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                    <date value="1919-09-07">Sept. 7, 1919</date>
                    <author>
                        <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                    </author>
                    <extent>15p</extent>
                    <note type="summary">Description of my room in the Teachers&apos; Cottage with diagram - Trouble over Mary &amp; Marshall Ogle - 
                    Miss Turner at the hotel - How Sunday is spent - </note>
                    <note type="box">3</note>
                    <note type="folder">2</note>
                    <note type="document">arm03020009000</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Local Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <list>
                        <item>Social life</item>
                        <item>Feuds</item>
                        <item>Church</item>
                        <item>People</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="abstract">
                <pb ref="arm03020009001" seq="01"/>
                <list>
                    <item>Description of my room in the Teachers&apos; Cottage with diagram - </item>
                    <item>Trouble over Mary &amp; Marshall Ogle -</item>
                    <item>Miss Turner at the hotel -</item>
                    <item>How Sunday is spent - </item>
                </list>
             </div1>
            <div1 type="letter">
                <pb ref="arm03020009002" seq="02"/>
                <head>
                    <date value="1919-09-07"> Sept. 7, 1919</date>
                </head>
                    <p>
                        <del>
                       Dearest family - It&apos;s four o&apos;clock this warm Sunday afternoon and I wonder what all you many be doing and whether fair Mabel
                       is still in you midst - Have decided that the best name for her is Mabel - the maiden of mystery!
                            </del>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <del>
                        My writing looks worse than usual doesn&apos;t it - but have been writing a lot these last two days and guess that&apos;s the reason - 
                        Finally got my Pi Phi letter off to Lida yesterday - Emily went to Sevierville and mailed it there - wrote Charlotte a long one &amp;
                        am in the middle of one to Jo - a note to Bessie - Ruth D. - a letter to the Cavanagh&apos;s - note to Emily&apos;s cousin who selected
                        the khakhi middy for me - and another to the company in Knoxville who have done my developing &amp; <pb ref="arm03020009003" seq="03"></pb>
                        printing with which will have to go a money order - then am sending some more films to another company with order for film packs - It
                        seems to me some of my pictures are printed too dark when I ask them to be duplicated. So thought I&apos;d try a new place.
                        </del>
                    </p>
                <p>
                    It&apos;s getting dark &amp; sultry - every indication of a storm - downstairs the Junior <abbr expan="Baptist Young Person&apos;s Union">B.Y.P.</abbr>
                    is gathering with Emily - Evelyn is reading in her room - Aunt Lizzie &amp; Mrs. <sic corr="Proffitt">Profit</sic> are hobnobbing
                    together somewhere - Mrs. <sic corr="Proffitt">Profit</sic> spends the <sic corr="weekends">week ends</sic> here as her boys &amp;
                    Mr. <abbr expan="Cresswell">C.</abbr> go Friday night - Abbie is usually with us as her girls also depart but she departed herself
                    for Sevierville after school Friday.<pb ref="arm03020009004" seq="04" n="2"></pb>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <del>Have not had a letter since the beginning of the week a longer lapse of time than usual but know that you all
                        have been busy - even pa was roped into the party no doubt. Saw the notice of it in the paper!</del> Truly I <sic corr="won&apos;t">wont</sic>
                    know how to act in the city after while! Before I forget in my rambling along - let me tell you that the <hi1 rend="underscore">paper</hi1>
                    <hi1 rend="underscore">bag</hi1> is a great boon and has already made over night trips with me - Emily &amp; I took it for the trip to Maud
                    Clabo&apos;s house and then I took it Friday night when I went over &amp; stayed with Mary Ogle. It&apos;s so convenient to carry and holds so
                    much. We will enjoy it for picnics I&apos;m sure - for can fold it up after we <pb ref="arm03020009005" seq="05"></pb>get through eating. The bundle
                    of papers came &amp; was pleased to find my quarterly and the booklets. Aunt Lizzie enjoyed them so much the afternoon they came - that the same
                    evening when Emily &amp; I were at Maud&apos;s she got them out to show them to Dr. Massey &amp; Evelyn. Thank you very much for your sweet
                    thoughtfulness. <figure><figDesc>Line drawing of Ruth Sturley&apos;s room in the Teachers&apos; Cottage.</figDesc></figure> How do you like my
                    room? On the table is a green blotting pad - books - writing paper etc. and here I spend most of my time when in this place (except when I sleep).
                    The dressing table is just a plain table like the study table but with my bureau scarf silver things - pa&apos;s &amp; Jane&apos;s pictures
                    <pb ref="arm03020009006" seq="06" n="3"></pb> and a mirror above its not so bad as it might be. On the left of the mirror is <unclear 
                        reason="illegible" resp="bds">Weirs</unclear> smiling face &amp; on the other side Arthur &amp; Nell - with the little California picture
                    Victoria gave me. On the <del>be</del> Chiffonier is the picture of the two youngsters and Charlotte&apos;s - 
                    <hi1 rend="underscore">my</hi1> <hi1 rend="underscore">lamb</hi1> work basket etc. On the window seat is a growing collection of papers
                    etc. The walls are plain wood like the floor - pine I believe - no rugs as yet. Am clad in my pongee old white shoes - my hair is somewhat fuzzy
                    having been washed yesterday &amp; I&apos;m brown also <hi1 rend="underscore">fatter</hi1> than when we parted! Truly I eat something
                    fierce! This morning had two cups of coffee - <hi1 rend="underscore">4</hi1> hot baking powder biscuits &amp; much apple jelly. For
                    dinner we had fried chicken - boiled rice which took <pb ref="arm03020009007" seq="07"></pb>the place of <hi1 rend="underscore">potatoes</hi1>
                    (<abbr expan="singular">sing.</abbr> potato!) and is exceedingly good with the chicken gravy - baked apples - more hot biscuits - 
                    cake and orange &amp; banan<del>n</del>a sliced together. Aunt Lizzie has been making apple jelly &amp; apple butter
                    all week and yesterday they got a bushel and a half of pears - which she is going to can - They are not particularly good - rather small 
                    and green.
                </p>
                <p>
                    As usual it&apos;s been a busy time since I wrote you Thursday night. Stayed at school till about 4:30 putting up some pictures in my room - 
                    cleaning out my desk - getting down some cobwebs - supervising the cleaning of the three little girls. We also cleaned out the fireplace. All
                    the garbage &amp; waste paper is burned there so <pb ref="arm03020009008" seq="08" n="8"></pb>that it was full to overflowing. They ought to have some
                    garbage cans it seems to me. A Mr. Lawson Reagan came over to fix the clock in my room which had been out of commission most of the week - my little
                    alarm clock sat on the piano over there all day Friday - Mabel will be pleased to hear this she was so fond of that singing instrument! Mr. Reagan
                    is the father of Flora in my 8th B Class and a typical mountaineer - am hoping to get his picture some time! He is one of the pillars in the church
                    (though a very short one) and leads the singing - Stands by the organ &amp; beats time while we all sit in the choir seats facing him &amp; 
                    <hi1 rend="underscore">sing</hi1> <hi1 rend="underscore">sing</hi1> <hi1 rend="underscore">sing</hi1> - Rescue the <unclear reason="illegible"
                        resp="bds">penshing</unclear> etc. Some of the hymns aren&apos;t bad though. - There are not books enough for every-<pb ref="arm03020009009" seq="09"></pb>
                    one - so the audience never sings - just &quot;we uns!&quot;
                </p>
                <p>
                    Well to return to after school Friday - I also had Mr. Reagan fix the front door which has a spring for holding one side open which also had
                    been out of commission most of the week - Just as I was ready to leave Miss Turner (our Pi Phi) and a Mrs. Hall arrived from the hotel. Miss
                    Turner wished to get a book and by that time Mr. <abbr expan="Reagan">R.</abbr> was through and decided to take two - He wanted Pilgrim&apos;s
                    Progress which he said he&apos;d read a long time ago and took &quot;The Blue Bird&quot; along with it. Miss <abbr expan="Turner">T.</abbr>
                    selected one of Mrs. Burnett&apos;s books - She is very nice but a typical old maid in many ways - is enraptured with everything here however.
                    They went off and I got home &amp; comfortably settled on the porch with <pb ref="arm03020009010" seq="10" n="5"></pb> something to read &amp; an apple - 
                    Emily &amp; Evelyn were both gone to Sevierville &amp; Pigeon Forge - when Mrs. Huff appeared with her sister-in-law and stayed the rest of the 
                    afternoon winding up with a visit at the school - Her sister lives in a small town near Knoxville and hadn&apos;t been in our school before. Soon
                    the girls came home and during supper - Mary Ogle blew in begging one of us to go and stay all night with her. You know her husband is getting a
                    divorce from her - through the evil influence of a Mrs. Brown in the <abbr expan="mountains">mts.</abbr> nearby <del>who</del>
                    It&apos;s a long &amp; involved story and I do not know all the details fortunately but know enough about it to feel rather wrathy when the Pi Phis
                    and school are blackened! You see Evelyn discharged Marshall <del>her</del> Mary&apos;s husband &amp; his <pb ref="arm03020009011" seq="11"></pb>
                    people and he are trying to revenge themselves on the school by attacking reputations of some of the Pi Phis who taught here several years ago - 
                    and Evelyn&apos;s - I&apos;ve discussed it with her and she thinks now about it as I do that the thing to do is give them a good scare &amp; settle
                    this gossip for good and all by going to a lawyer. The Ogle family live just below Mary&apos;s and when Marshall is in town &amp; then she is afraid.
                    There really is nothing to be afraid of - and I was there Friday night - we found out later that the minister was at the Ogles&apos; that night and
                    that they told these things to him - He comes up once a month for services Saturday <abbr expan="afternoon">p.m.</abbr> &amp; Sunday - So yesterday
                    (<abbr expan="Saturday">Sat.</abbr>) about 2:30 was church. It was rumored around that several people were going to be turned out of church too.
                    I had had a busy morning (my first <abbr expan="Saturday">Sat.</abbr> here <pb ref="arm03020009012" seq="12" n="6"></pb> all day too - ) writing but
                    bustled around with my both hairwashing manicuring etc. &amp; was clothed in my gray garb &amp; best hat by the time the last church bell rang &amp;
                    on my way to church with Evelyn - It was a very peaceful meetin&apos; as far as any dismissals were concerned - though the minister talked very
                    plainly about &quot;the capers the devil had been cuttin up&quot; &amp; &quot;haw people had been rarin&apos; around&quot; saying things behind the
                    back &amp; not &quot;square to the teeth&quot; etc. His expressions were so funny but he was very much in earnest. 
                </p>
                <p>
                    Evelyn went right to him after church &amp; had it out with him - He was very much - and as two or three pillars <hi1 rend="underscore">were</hi1> 
                    there it was quite a clearing of the atmosphere. You see like all small places there seems to be one family who <pb ref="arm03020009013" seq="13"></pb> try
                    to stir up trouble &amp; this particular Ogle family is <hi1 rend="underscore">the</hi1> <hi1 rend="underscore">one</hi1> here. Evelyn goes to a 
                    lawyer in Sevierville this week - Judge Paine a personal friend of hers - and as it happens Marshall&apos;s lawyer - isn&apos;t that rich?
                </p>
                <p>
                    Well to continue after church I came home &amp; planned to go up Pi Phi lane &amp; make another attempt to read having been failed the previous
                    afternoon - But failed again was the word for Miss Turner appeared and so we went for a walk up Pi Phi lane on to Baskin&apos;s Creek returning
                    about six. Then while supper was being prepared we called on Mary Ogle as Miss <abbr expan="Turner">T.</abbr> wanted to see the house - She stayed
                    the rest of the evening &amp; we took her back to the hotel about nine. It was a perfect night <pb ref="arm03020009014" seq="14" n="7"></pb> balmy and the 
                    moon nearly full - I know the moon is much brighter than ours at home - the last Geographic has an interesting article on stars which I read after we
                    finally tore ourselves away from the porch - Emily went to bed and Evelyn sat down &amp; played &amp; sang at the piano - She has a lovely contralto
                    voice. Was up at six this lovely morning &amp; donned my walking costume as Miss Turner wanted to go up Tom <sic corr="Campbell">Camel</sic>&apos;s
                    trail and we planned to start about <del>se</del>eight getting out of sight before the gathering for Sunday School. I had a feeling
                    she wouldn&apos;t go somehow &amp; was not surprised when a small boy arrived about 8:30 with a note saying she couldn&apos;t &amp; would
                    <pb ref="arm03020009015" seq="15"></pb> explain later - She was on the verge of a nervous breakdown when she came so do not think hard walks are her line 
                    exactly. I was in the midst of various activities &amp; decided to keep right on and not go to any church function till tonight. Emily &amp; Evelyn went
                    and were gone <hi1 rend="underscore">three</hi1> <hi1 rend="underscore">long</hi1> <hi1 rend="underscore">hours</hi1>!! I cleaned my shoes changed my
                    bed - straightened out my top drawer - scoured the stationary wash stands with Dutch cleanser - changed my dress - wrote letters - fixed my tan dress that
                    Bessie made and of course did some washing!! So now you know just about all that has been doing up to the present moment! Will close for now &amp; will
                    try to get off another letter the middle of the week - Hoping to hear from some of you tomorrow &amp; with much of love as always - Ruth.
                </p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>