<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03020014000">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[Letter]  Oct. 01, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] Tacoma, Washington Pi Beta Phi Alumnae Club</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
                    <name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
                    <name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
                </address>
                <date>2006</date>
                <idno type="SPCID">arm03020014000</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. 
                        For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee 
                        Libraries, Knoxville, TN</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from whi1ch the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
                <bibl>
                    <title>[Letter]  Oct. 01, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                    <date value="1919-10-01">Oct. 01, 1919</date>
                    <author>
                        <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                    </author>
                    <extent>21p</extent>
                    <note type="summary">Letter to Pi Phi Alumnae Club in Tacoma, Aunt Lizzie, Other schools in neighborhood, <del>Shir</del>Shivaree First fair at the burg, Fair in Sevierville</note>
                    <note type="box">3</note>
                    <note type="folder">2</note>
                    <note type="document">arm03020014000</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Local Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <list>
                        <item>Living conditions</item>
                        <item>People</item>
                        <item>Schools</item>
                        <item>Fairs</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="abstract">
                <pb ref="arm03020014001" seq="01"/>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <item>Letter to Pi Phi Alumnae Club in Tacoma</item>
                        <item>Aunt Lizzie</item>
                        <item>Other schools in neighborhood</item>
                        <item><del>Shir</del>Shivaree First fair at the burg</item>
                        <item>Fair in Sevierville</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="letter">
                <pb ref="arm03020014002" seq="02"/>
                <head>
                    <date value="1919-10-01"> Oct. 1, 1919</date>
                </head>
                <p>
                    Dear Pi Phi sisters - In the light of two Rochester lamps on the big table in the living room Emily and I are working. 
                    She is ruling paper in inch squares for her primary class and I&apos;m writing you all which perhaps should not 
                    be considered work and in fact really is more pleasure than anything else but yet there is an element of labor in pushing 
                    a fountain pen on and on &amp; forming rhythmical sentences suitable for your ears - the bad grammar I constantly 
                    bear may prove too much for me and if &quot;hits&quot; &quot;caint&quot; &quot;I reckon&quot; &quot;you-un&apos;s&quot; 
                    &quot;plumb slack&quot; and other &quot;plumbs&quot; don&apos;t twine themselves into my vocabulary it will be a wonder 
                    <pb ref="arm03020014003" seq="03"/>and a &quot;heap surprising&quot; &quot;sure enough!&quot; Abbie Runyan has just been 
                    over to mix up &quot;light bread&quot; for her household and Aunt Lizzie did ditto for hers - The latter is very proud of her 
                    bread &amp; until last winter had never made any with yeast and white flour - Tonight she was instructing 
                    <del>Evely</del> Abbie as to just how to make it and last week she knew exactly what was the matter 
                    with some made by Evelyn. She is such an old dear! I told you didn&apos;t I that she was quite progressive for a mountain 
                    woman? Made herself a khaki skirt (rather narrow) not long ago and wears white cotton stockings (without feet) over her 
                    heavy ones so that the effect is modern anyway. She is also affectionate and likes to kiss us all &amp; be kissed - which 
                    is very unusual among these people - there are so very very undemonstrative. I get so impatient at times with their supreme 
                    contentment in their ignorance and dirt to wonder how they can live as 
                    they do and yet there is something so fine &amp; likeable after all that externals vanish completely. I do love the youngsters 
                    at school - but the little they know is appalling &amp; the poorly prepared lessons <del>is</del> 
                    <add place="supralinear">are</add> more than appalling. I scolded my whole room the last five <pb ref="arm03020014004" seq="04" n="02"/>
                    minutes before noon one day about everything from conduct to dirtiness in the schoolroom &amp; in themselves. Then I 
                    went home and by the time I&apos;d read my mail and eaten lunch was quite calm. Returning to school at 12:45 I found my 
                    room swept &amp; lovely wild flowers everywhere in baskets. So you can see how it is - quite like school anywhere else in 
                    many respects. Since I wrote you last month I&apos;ve gazed upon four school buildings on various creeks - just three 
                    miles or so from here and such pathetic places as they are. It makes me wonder why our school so wonderfully equipped in 
                    comparison is not full to overflowing - that our enrollment is not two hundred rather than half that number. These schools were 
                    one-room log buildings all of them - a rusty stove at one end (at the front with one exception) benches and no desks - a little 
                    blackboard back of the teacher&apos;s <pb ref="arm03020014005" seq="05"/>desk - which is more apt to be a split log on end with 
                    a small board across it than a table. No textbooks except readers and an occasional arithmetic or history - the youngsters have 
                    to buy their own books - a great handicap among these people - Writing is not often taught just reading - This is a fine 
                    description without exaggeration &amp; no omissions except big chinks in the walls of one and glassless windows in another!! 
                    There is so much absence and tardiness every day and nothing to be done about it either. You girls that teach know what a sin 
                    tardiness is and <add place="supralinear">how</add> almost criminal is truancy! Twice have we had boys stay out part of a 
                    morning to fish in Little Pigeon &amp; afterwards present us with the fish they caught! It&apos;s funny isn&apos;t it and 
                    yet provoking. &quot;Pulling fodder&quot; was the chief occupation last month and since then it&apos;s been picking 
                    beans and making molasses from sorghum. By the way molasses is considered plural number here - &quot;molasses 
                    are&quot; - never &quot;molasses is&quot; - We teachers are going in the hack after school tomorrow night about 
                    three miles to the McCarter&quot;s and see the <del>sug</del> boilin&apos; - by 
                    <pb ref="arm03020014006" seq="06" n="03"/>special invitation and girls we are going possum hunting some night soon 
                    if the fates smile upon us - doesn&apos;t that thrill you? It does me.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Miss Turner was in our midst at the time of my last epistle and has now gone back to Washington and from the 
                    letter sent us had a very interesting and profitable visit here. She is anxious and expectant too that in the course 
                    of time the fraternity turn the school over to the county - a thing we would never wish done for we girls feel that it 
                    would rapidly degenerate. She came over one night from the hotel - such a wonderful baling moonlight night as 
                    it was - and found Abbie Evelyn &amp; I starting forth on a <hi1 rend="underscore">shivaree</hi1> (don&apos;t 
                    believe that&apos;s spelled correctly) you know what that is - don&apos; you - a noisy celebration in honor of a 
                    newly married couple - We had a cow bell - sheep bell &amp; two tin cavers to be clapped together 
                    <pb ref="arm03020014007" seq="07"/> a la cymbals and were bubbling over with giggles &amp; excitement I fear we we 
                    shocked Miss Turner a wee bit. Three of the school girls also went and a dozen or more of the older boys - some 
                    in school but most of them not and also our manual training teacher Mr. Cresswell - We girls went in a Ford about 
                    three miles up the river &amp; the boys walked until the Ford went back after them - Then reunited we left the car &amp; 
                    proceeded up a steep &amp; exceedingly rocky trail on a mountain side which we followed for about two miles 
                    &amp; what do you suppose was the name of this place? Wild Cat Holler and the cabin in a clearing was at Dry Pond! 
                    Here in the light of the moon we held a whispered consultation and then broke the peaceful stillness of the night 
                    by <add place="supralinear">an</add> awful din going round &amp; round the house until lights appeared &amp; 
                    various people - Finally the bridegroom came forth &amp; was at once seized &amp; ridden up &amp; down on 
                    a fence rail - some dynamite was set off and guns fired - Then the bride appeared &amp; was given a ride. She is 
                    a girl about seventeen - perhaps younger - and has gone to our school - Mrs. Helwick when here this fall offered to 
                    pay her <del>way</del> <add place="supralinear">expenses</add> if she would go away to school - 
                    but instead she married this young fellow &amp; I suppose will live like the rest of them. Her honeymoon was certainly 
                    pitiful - They were at her <pb ref="arm03020014008" seq="08" n="04"/>husband&apos;s brother&apos;s and as I had 
                    the priviledge of going through the house can describe it briefly with the statement that it was beds and old clothes 
                    principally - absolutely no order or cleanliness anywhere visible to the naked eye. Well in spite of the pathetic side 
                    to it all we did enjoy the experience immensely &amp; got home about 11:30.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The same weekend we went to Sevierville to a <hi1 rend="underscore">party</hi1> given by the Bishops for the Murphy 
                    College faculty. Emily &amp; I stayed all night at their home. They are such lovely people - and we thoroughly enjoyed
                    visiting in a real home among our own kind. As Gatlinburg played Murphy College that same weekend we stayed until 
                    after the game - the only Gatlingburger&apos;s there in the small but enthusiastic crowd of baseball fans. We were 
                    terribly beaten too - 16 to 3 - It was a funny game - long waits while <pb ref="arm03020014009" seq="09"/>the ball was 
                    being hunted in neighboring fields &amp; for ten minutes or more complete stoppage as a small boy was hit -
                </p>
                <p>
                    Next happening during the month was Evelyn&apos;s stay of a week with a friend in Alabama - She felt guilty about 
                    going but we insisted that it would be perfectly all right so away she went &amp; we proceeded to celebrate as we 
                    had told her we&apos;d do - Had a picnic one night just we four teachers on top of Pi Phi hill &amp; planned our trip 
                    across the Smoky <abbr expan="Mountains">Mts.</abbr> to North Carolina - a thing we had so often talked of 
                    doing. Then we got up a party for the youngsters one night - had two animal games &amp; what fun they all had! The 
                    next day which was Friday we started on our expedition as we had planned. Our chaperone was Mrs. Reagan the 
                    mother of one of our girls - our equipage consisted of Dan &amp; the hack - our equipment - blankets - provisions - 
                    lantern - hatchet - <del>rifle</del> shotgun and kodak.
                </p>
                <p>
                    We had many minor mishaps but none serious or dampening to our enthusiasm - we took the wrong road once 
                    - broke a shaft - Dan proved most obstreperous Abbie lost her hat - we flavored our coffee one night with liquid from 
                    canned sausage - in the dark the tin was exactly like our can of condensed milk &amp; until morn-<pb ref="arm03020014010" seq="10" n="05"/>ing 
                    we didn&apos;t know what was the matter with our coffee - At the boundary line between <abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn.</abbr> 
                    &amp; <abbr expan="North Carolina">N. C.</abbr> <add place="supralinear">on the top of the Smokies</add> <del>just</del> 
                    as we were gazing in admiration at the many ranges one above the other (five in all) stretching out in the blue hazy 
                    distance the outlines became dim &amp; blotted out in gray mist which soon enveloped us &amp; turned into a heavy 
                    downpour of real &amp; wet rain. We hastily ran down the mountain side into North Carolina &amp; found shelter in 
                    a thick grove but did not escape a thorough wetting. It soon passed over however &amp; we walked gaily back to the 
                    cabin about four miles from the summit where we passed the night. Never before had I spent two days fully clad even 
                    to shoes - nor rolled up in a blanket &amp; slept on Mother Earth in the light of the moon &amp; stars. All of this did 
                    we do &amp; with what joy did we welcome hot water &amp; clean clothes on our return - yet we enjoyed every 
                    minute of the trip &amp; the cooking over a fire &amp; the packing &amp; unpacking. We drove 
                    <pb ref="arm03020014011" seq="11"/>about six miles only but such miles &amp; such roads - Then we abandoned the 
                    hack and made Dan into a pack horse - even to the lantern and hats!
                </p>
                <p>
                    The next excitement was our fair which happened last Thursday and took all the week in preparation. A community 
                    meeting was held the Monday before at the schoolhouse for which we girls had made posters which were sent 
                    up the various creeks. On top of all our <sic corr="business">busy-ness</sic> two wandering musicians arrived 
                    &amp; asked to give an entertainment the next night at the school - Permission was given &amp; of course we all 
                    went &amp; sat in front seats. Can&apos;t you imagine what it was like? - wailing songs accompanied by guitar 
                    music &amp; one original song about the tragic death of John Henry - copies of which were sold afterwards and 
                    as it was such a gem I got one &amp; sent it home - It is typical of the songs we have at our 
                    &quot;<hi1 rend="underscore">sings</hi1>&quot;. This was followed by an animated conversation between Dennis 
                    and Sambo as our entertainer was also a ventriloquist.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Thursday - the day dawned &quot;brite &amp; fair&quot; &amp; by ten o&apos;clock practically everything was labelled 
                    and on exhibition - Although not very much was brought in after all - <pb ref="arm03020014012" seq="12" n="06"/>the building 
                    looked gay &amp; festive. This is the first year Gatlinburg ever attempted a fair and next year more will bring things 
                    and come themselves. The panels were up between the three recitation rooms for a program was to be given at 
                    11 a.m. As you went in the hall baskets met your gaze on the right &amp; the manual training exhibits on the left - 
                    Ferns in baskets which the girls had dug up &amp; helped plant were (<del>in baskets</del>) 
                    everywhere and on the <del>mantal</del> <add place="supralinear">mantel</add> - boughs of 
                    gorgeous red sumac were in the fireplace &amp; great bunches of golden rod &amp; little wild asters - whilte &amp; 
                    lavender were in the windows back of the radiators - Great bunches of the same were on the desks in our rooms - 
                    boughs of autumn leaves. Our maps and writing papers filled three corners in my room and some drawings of 
                    Japanese lanterns in colored crayons filled another corner <pb ref="arm03020014013" seq="13"/>corner and formed 
                    a border across the blackboard where was written the program consisting of flag salute - patriotuc song - several 
                    drills - article on farm life - <unclear reason="illegible">matin</unclear> songs &amp; dramatizations 
                    by primary class with more singing by the whole school - Then one of our prominent citizens talked &amp; the two 
                    judges who came up from Sevierville - Miss Whittle who had charge of the fairs in the country was very much pleased 
                    with everything we did &amp; had. In the sewing room was shown a table of cooked things by the little girls in 
                    Abbie&apos;s class - some bags made by my girls - three cases of canned fruits &amp; vegetables - two tables of 
                    apples - two coverl<del>&apos;eds</del><add place="supralinear">ets</add> and fancy work - In the 
                    shop were the vegetables - peppers - stalks of corn - sage - pumpkin - potatoes etc. The livestock exhibit consisted 
                    of six white chickens &amp; a tiny puppy!
                </p>
                <p>
                    &quot;Dinner on tho&apos; grounds&quot; renewed our energies. Aunt Lizzie - Evelyn &amp; her mother who came 
                    up for the celebration had made four pies - two cakes &amp; fried chicken &amp; others had contributed generously 
                    so that two long tables back of the schoolhouse were loaded &amp; all had enough to eat. I forgot to say that 
                    besides the children I don&apos;t <pb ref="arm03020014014" seq="14" n="07"/>believe more than sixty people were 
                    present in the morning - But after lunch more came as there was to be a baseball game with Murphy College at 2:30 - 
                    Three carloads of players &amp; girls including the teachers soon arrived - and we had a great game full of pep - which 
                    extended to the grandstand too. The Murphy College girls are great rooters &amp; ours were soon inspired to follow 
                    suit &amp; all were so worked up before long that personal remarks began flying. That was soon stopped &amp; as we 
                    beat 6 to 4 we didn&apos;t mind what was said - by the other side. The Sevierville bunch came to the house afterwards 
                    and found food &amp; rest before going back. We were glad to wave adieu to the last of them all &amp; go quietly to bed 
                    after hunting up scraps of food for ourselves - found a <del>racl</del> <add place="supralinear">pan</add> 
                    of bis-<pb ref="arm03020014015" seq="15"/>cuits in the warming oven that fortunately escaped a trip with the other edibles to 
                    school - also Abbie&apos;s cookery on display helped to fill out the menu.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The next day was one of cleaning up &amp; putting away along with recitations. Emily &amp; I were pleased to leave 
                    the burg all of Saturday on a tramp up Baskin Creek and down Roaring Fork - making a few calls - Roaring Fork is 
                    beautiful - great boulders &amp; rocky cliffs a <unclear reason="illegible" resp="tl">braniling</unclear> brook (as 
                    the poets say) always by the roadside and over the road many times too. Some day auto parties are going to infest 
                    Roaring Fork - am pleased to be able to see it before its pristine beauty is spoiled.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Tuesday (yesterday) was our day for the Sevierville fair. Abbie and Evelyn went down before to get our display in 
                    order &amp; then we chaperoned about a dozen youngsters there. However the chaperonage rested rather lightly 
                    on our shoulders - The most of them went down in a car ahead of us teachers who went with the Huff youngsters. 
                    It was a long day <pb ref="arm03020014016" seq="16" n="08"/>we started at seven and left about five -
                </p>
                <p>
                    The fair was so interesting though and the exhibits quite different from ours. Sevierville is an awfully unattractive 
                    town so ungainly and sprawly - a big square red brick courthouse topped with tower and clock is the main building 
                    &amp; in it were the exhibits and in the yard were autos - chickens - cows - oxen - horses - mules etc. There was 
                    one large room where the colored people had their things on display by themselves and a good showing they made. 
                    And what else do you suppose was unusual? A small room was opened up part of the morning &amp; in it were 
                    over twenty <hi1 rend="underscore">stills</hi1> that had been captured in the mountains. You remember I 
                    <pb ref="arm03020014017" seq="17"/>had seen all of the equipment but the still itself. I took two pictures of them and 
                    surely hope one at least proves good. There were exhibits from twelve communities in which ours ranked eighth - 
                    but among the four school exhibits <del>exhib</del> ours stood way above the others am glad to 
                    say. One pumpkin weighed 133<num type="fraction" value="one fourth">1/4</num> <abbr expan="pounds">lbs.</abbr> 
                    - there were ears of corn 14 <abbr expan="inches">in.</abbr> long - cotton plants - peanuts attached to plant - 
                    peppers ditto - broom corn - sugar cane - apples etc. Then the handwork was of all sorts. The fair was not anywhere 
                    near as large as that in Puyallup - but Sevierville is only fifteen 
                    hundred strong and began only last year having an annual fair. The people turned out in full force and seemed to 
                    thoroughly enjoy it - warm as the day was - the correct garb was a fall suit and hat. They felt comfortable when we 
                    started in the early morning but our afternoons <pb ref="arm03020014018" seq="18" n="09"/>are still so very very hot - 
                    Evelyn and I had our lunch at the dormitory of Murphy College from whence we departed to the &quot;horse show&quot; 
                    - One street was roped off &amp; here all the mules were first displayed &amp; ribbons awarded - Next three 
                    beautiful horses were ridden by three women up &amp; down a dozen times or so &amp; then they were adorned. 
                    Fifteen or twenty men on horseback were next on the program &amp; they went up and down many times and oft - 
                    all sorts of horses &amp; men too from a dignified <pb ref="arm03020014019" seq="19"/>and correct lieutenant in 
                    uniform to the fat old squire. The funniest was a typical country square jawed minister who conversed with his horse 
                    most of the time - when he passed us at least - &quot;Easy now - easy now&quot; then when he warmed up to the 
                    situation he urged his steed on valiantly clinging to his strawhat. I was rather sorry he didn&apos;t get a white 
                    ribbon for his earnest endeavors.
                </p>
                <p>
                    I have written on and on this whole evening &amp; must cease and get to bed. I must tell you how funny Aunt 
                    Lizzie &amp; I were Sunday night - Everyone had gone to <abbr expan="Baptist Young Person&apos;s Union">B.Y.P.U.</abbr> 
                    (Baptist Young Person&apos;s Union) Naughty Ruth Sturley felt that the two hours in Sunday School that morning 
                    was sufficient &amp; was studying &amp; looking over papers - Aunt Lizzie was supposedly in bed - But lo she 
                    <pb ref="arm03020014020" seq="20" n="10"/>came padding downstairs in her wrapper with the announcement that she 
                    could hear cows in the corn. Well I seized the lamp &amp; we sallied forth and sure enough way up in the 
                    distance were dim forms - so picture me running up &amp; down the rows of corn clutching the lamp in one 
                    hand trying to chase cows. Aunt Lizzie nearly convulsed me when she got after them she simply growled at them.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Such is life in Gatlinburg! You never know what may happen next - at least I don&apos;t - and that&apos;s 
                    <pb ref="arm03020014021" seq="21"/>one of its many charms -
                </p>
                <p>
                    Chestnuts are beginning to ripen and the foliage is turning - while trees of red can be seen occasionally among 
                    the green - As yet we have had no frost but as soon as that comes then they&apos;ll turn fast enough I imagine.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Before I close I must say that your program sounds very interesting and am glad to have it. Now I can picture what 
                    you do at your meetings each month.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Let me remind you all again that letters are much appreciated.
                </p>
                <p>
                    With love to you all -
                </p>
                <p>
                    Ruth Sturley
                </p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
