<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03030015000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[Letter]  Nov. 10, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
				<author>
					<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
				</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
					<name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
					<name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
				<address>
					<addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
				</address>
				<date>2006</date>
				<idno type="SPCID">arm03030015000</idno>
				<availability>
					<p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from which the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
				<bibl>
					<title>[Letter]  Nov. 10, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
					<date value="1919-11-10">Nov. 10, 1919</date>
					<author>
						<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
					</author>
					<extent>7p</extent>
					<note type="summary">Shooting in the Sugarlands - Squire Maples makes an examination</note>
					<note type="box">3</note>
					<note type="folder">3</note>
					<note type="document">arm03030015000</note>
				</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
			</projectDesc>
		<editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<bibl>
						<title>Local Subject Headings</title>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<list>
						<item>Living conditions</item>
						<item>Crime</item>
						<item>People</item>
						<item>Social life</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div1 type="abstract">
				<pb ref="arm03030015001" seq="01"/>
				<p>
					<list>
						<item>Shooting in the Sugarlands</item>
						<item>Squire Maples makes an examination</item>
					</list>
				</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="letter">
				<pb ref="arm03030015002" seq="02"/>
				<head>
					<date value="1919-11-10">Nov. 10, 1919</date>
				</head>
				<p>
                    Dearest pa - It&apos;s Sunday night about 9:30 and more than bedtime. Emily &amp; I have done our duty &amp; gone to 
                    <abbr expan="Baptist Young Person&apos;s Union">B.Y.</abbr> and then visited with Mr. Cresswell &amp; Tom McCarter - one of the 
                    boys in school and very nice too - he is quite discouraged as he has to stay out so much to help with the farming at home &amp; in 
                    fact they all peg away for dear life &amp; no more than make a living I guess. You see the land here in the <abbr expan="mountains">mts.</abbr> 
                    is productive enough but the soil is very thin and washes away in the hard rains too.
                </p>
				<pb ref="arm03030015003" seq="03"/>
				<p>
					<del>Your letter came the next day just as I had hoped - I mean the day after yours came
						<add place="supralinear">I wrote you.</add> Didn&apos;t finish last night after all - same interruption came along. A long letter came from 
                        Mabel this morning &amp; also from Cousin Viva Glasier. She was quite surprised to learn of all the happenings in our family I guess. </del>
				</p>
				<p>
                    You aught to hear the wind tonight it is tearing up everything for miles around. And the trees have turned so much today - the coloring is simply 
                    wonderful now - great masses of yellow with long lines of green from the evergreens <pb ref="arm03030015004" seq="04"/>which seem to grow in 
                    clumps together rather than scattered. Then every so often is a tree one mass of fiery red from top to bottom or copper color - you can&apos;t imagine 
                    how beautiful it is. Even the youngsters are stirred by it!
                </p>
				<p>
                    There has been great excitement here now today for yesterday noon a shooting occurred up in the Sugar lands. An old man Mr. Bracken shot down 
                    a young boy. It seems that <del>the</del> Mr. <abbr expan="Bracken">B.</abbr> reported this boy to be implicated in running 
                    a still the boy came down to his house to talk to him about it and was shot - killed instantly no witnesses &amp; conflicting stories - so today 
                    Squire Maples had a trial or examination down here at his house at the foot of our lane - The upshot is that he is out on bail &amp; the trial to be 
                    next month I believe. They say men are drunk up in the Sugar lands every Saturday night &amp; I imagine it&apos;s not very safe - the very heart 
                    of the &quot;still country.&quot; Some of the youngsters played truant from school to go <add place="supralinear">to trial</add> and guess I&apos;ll just 
                    have to keep them in tomorrow to make up their lessons - you can&apos;t blame them for being interested though - we wanted to go ourselves. 
                    I went down to the store about four p.m. to mail the baskets I&apos;m sending home - just before the trial was over - There were a number of 
                    saddle horses <pb ref="arm03030015005" seq="05" n="02"/>and the big picturesque wagons outside. The mountain men are all so much alike - tall 
                    lean &amp; shrewd looking - think I&apos;ll always be able to pick one out hereafter.
                </p>
				<p>
                    All the past week I&apos;ve been pretty busy working at school till late over one thing and another. My room does look pretty though - and try to keep it 
                    orderly which is not easy for the boys &amp; girls are not like those at home about helping &amp; act as though they were doing a great favor thereby. 
                    However they are improving in that respect.
                </p>
				<p>
                    The red Cross meeting Friday night was poorly attended being made up of the school youngsters &amp; the <abbr expan="Baptist Young Person&apos;s Union">B.Y.</abbr> 
                    crowd. <pb ref="arm03030015006" seq="06"/>Don&apos;t know whether we got in our quota or not - nor how much it was. Evelyn talked <del>as</del> 
                    also Miss Langmaid as the expected speaker from Sevierville failed to arrive.
                </p>
				<p>
                    Sunday after the usual session of Sunday School Emily &amp; I walked up Baskin&apos;s Creek with the Ogle girls to their home - about a mile 
                    or so - crossing the creek exactly twelve times on the way - via footlogs. We didn&apos;t stay for dinner though urgently pressed to do so - There was 
                    a possibility of our going in the Ford up to the forks of the river &amp; besides that we didn&apos;t feel like corn bread pork &amp; potatoes. At home 
                    was a ground beef roast &amp; fruit. <pb ref="arm03030015007" seq="07"/>Mrs. Ogle however brought forth a dish of baked sweet potatoes just out of 
                    the oven &amp; insisted on our taking some - So we walked home peeling our &quot;tater&quot; &amp; thoroughly enjoying it. But how funny to go away 
                    from the house where you call heaving a hot potato in your hand - yet it seemed quite natural &amp; not a bit surprising. See how accustomed to things 
                    I&apos;m becoming.
                </p>
				<p>
                    I must tell you about the names of two youngsters arrived here - at least they were when Miss Langmaid taught here about four years ago. One little 
                    girl &amp; the niece of our Aunt Lizzie was Exy. short for <hi1 rend="underscore">Ex&apos;</hi1>
					<hi1 rend="underscore">a</hi1>
					<hi1 rend="underscore">mine</hi1> 
                    and another Lar ce ny - Do you get that? examine &amp; larceny!
                </p>
				<p>
					<del>The folio you sent from Berkeley has not arrived and hope all your other letters have - Am so glad you are going south 
                    &amp; having such a good time everywhere. While in Los Angeles you better hunt up the girl I taught with in <unclear reason="illegible">Ilwaco</unclear> 
                    - Mrs. J. R. Hawkins 1250 West 48th St. I visited her a couple of weeks when there - they were very nice to me. Call her up anyway over the phone - 
                    Was glad to get the kodaks &amp; think them pretty good - Have just sent in another set to be developed &amp; will send you some if good - Goodnight 
                    dear papa - &amp; with much love</del>
				</p>
				<p>
                    Ruth.
                </p>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
