<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03030023000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[Letter]  Nov. 30, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
				<author>
					<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
				</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
					<name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
					<name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
				<address>
					<addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
				</address>
				<date>2006</date>
				<idno type="SPCID">arm03030023000</idno>
				<availability>
					<p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from which the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
				<bibl>
					<title>[Letter]  Nov. 30, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
					<date value="1919-11-30">Nov. 30, 1919</date>
					<author>
						<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
					</author>
					<extent>4p</extent>
					<note type="summary">All night at the Huffs - Plans for Christmas and usual routines</note>
					<note type="box">3</note>
					<note type="folder">3</note>
					<note type="document">arm03030023000</note>
				</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
			</projectDesc>
		<editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<bibl>
						<title>Local Subject Headings</title>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<list>
						<item>Home visits</item>
						<item>Living conditions</item>
						<item>People</item>
						<item>Holidays</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div1 type="abstract">
				<pb ref="arm03030023001" seq="01"/>
				<p>
					<list>
						<item>All night at the Huffs</item>
						<item>Plans for Christmas and usual routine</item>
					</list>
				</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="letter">
				<pb ref="arm03030023002" seq="02"/>
				<head>
					<date value="1919-11-30">Nov. 30, 1919</date>
				</head>
				<p><del>
                    Dearest family - I picture you as a <sic corr="reunited">re-united</sic> group tonight having tea at some fireside together listening to pa&apos;s tales of the sunny south!</del>
                </p>
				<p>
                    As usual have been full of busy-ness since my last dashing scribble of Thanksgiving Day! We went to Huff&apos;s that night about dark in the light of Emily&apos;s big
                    flash arriving just before their dinner was served &amp; <hi1 rend="underscore">we</hi1> had to sit down &amp; eat more chicken - potato - hot biscuits - jelly - coffee - etc.
                    Three of the men who work at their sawmill down the river were there - too. Mrs. Huff - Stella &amp; Betty waited on the table. Estel &amp; Jim had gone possum hunting 
                    having captured one the night before. We girls sat at the table while the feminine members ate &amp; then went into the other room by the fireplace where I did some darning
                    in the light of the three lamps on the &quot;fire board&quot; - (can you guess what the <hi1 rend="underscore">fire</hi1>
					<hi1 rend="underscore">board</hi1> is or have I told you 
                    in another letter?) <pb ref="arm03030023003" seq="03"/> Next morning we were awakened about six by Mrs. Huff&apos;s coming in to light a fire in the little heater so that we rose 
                    &amp; dressed luxuriously <del>in its heat</del>. After breakfast Mr. Huff asked us if we wanted to go to Emmert&apos;s Cove and of course we did &amp;
                    away we went in the Ford in short order - Blanche &amp; Mattie with us. It&apos;s a drive of about an hour though I don&apos;t imagine it&apos;s more than six or 
                    <del>seven</del> miles at the most. A cove corresponds to a <hi1 rend="underscore">large</hi1>
					<hi1 rend="underscore">holler</hi1> as far as I can see - &amp;
                    this one is more like a winding valley shut in by high mountains - There seemed to be no town just a house here &amp; there until finally we came to a sawmill where we stopped 
                    for a half hour or more &amp; while Mr. Huff talked business we girls watched some big oak log cut up into lumber. The largest was about 3 1/2 <abbr expan="feet">ft</abbr>
                    in diameter &amp; <pb ref="arm03030023004" seq="04"/> such hard solid oak too! We got home about 10:30 &amp; then I was busy the rest of the day - washing - shampooing my hair - 
                    catching up in my reading &amp; eating my <hi1 rend="underscore">lovely</hi1>
					<hi1 rend="underscore">candy</hi1>. You don&apos;t know how good it tasted! so much better than
                    all chocolates! I mended &amp; darned all evening as nearly everything seemed to need a helping hand somewhere. Yesterday (Saturday) there was a very high wind so that 
                    we gave up our hike though Cora Ogle came over before we were up to see if we would go - We spent most of the day working at school - Fixing up our rooms &amp; planning
                    work - also our Christmas programs - Cora went over with us &amp; he<del>p</del>lped put up pictures writing papers, etc. You see every time the panels
                    go up everything has to come down that has been put on them. My writing papers had been up since Halloween so put up new ones in a different way.
                </p>
				<p>
                    Today was Sunday School - &amp; <abbr expan="Baptist Young Person&apos;s Union">B.Y.P.</abbr> as usual - I spent the <abbr expan="afternoon">p.m.</abbr>
                    reading &amp; tonight Mr. <abbr expan="Cresswell">C.</abbr> was over &amp; Emily &amp; I went over our <abbr expan="Christmas">Xmas</abbr> plans with
                    him as he usually has to make something for such things! You&apos;d never guess what I did after <abbr expan="Sunday">S.</abbr> School this <abbr expan="morning">a.m.</abbr>
                    Do you remember the little cards &amp; bookmarks I used to make &quot;when I was young&quot; adorned with sprigs of holly? Well I got out my paints &amp; made
                    three vanities to get the girls started making some tomorrow at their club meeting.
                </p>
				<p><del>
                     Have been wondering what to give the girls here - Emily Evelyn &amp; Abbie - What do you think of handkerchiefs? Guess you&apos;ll have to get them &amp;
                     send them to me. Evelyn likes Ned&apos;s song &quot;Three Words&quot; so well I wonder if I could get it for her? Three weeks from today we expect to reach
                     New Orleans (Emily &amp; I) You all can send me some writing paper for a present as mine is about gone - like the thin foreign paper. It&apos;s so late must
                     cease &amp; <hi1 rend="underscore">withdraw</hi1> Had a grand long letter from Eliza Jane yesterday.</del>
                 </p>
				<p><del>
                     With loads of love to you all as ever</del>
                 </p>
				<p><del>
                     Ruth</del>
                 </p>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
