<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03020007000">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[Letter]  Sep. 04, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
                    <name>Young, Philip</name>
                    <name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
                    <name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
                </address>
                <date>2006</date>
                <idno type="SPCID">arm03020007000</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. 
                        For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee 
                        Libraries, Knoxville, TN</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from whi1ch the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
                <bibl>
                    <title>[Letter]  Sep. 04, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                    <date value="1919-09-04">Sep. 04, 1919</date>
                    <author>
                        <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                    </author>
                    <extent>21p</extent>
                    <note type="summary">The general store belonging to Charlie Ogle, County Institute in Sevierville, Visit at the Clabos, Miss Turner arrives for 10 day visit - she who suggested the school to honor our
                        Founders.</note>
                    <note type="box">3</note>
                    <note type="folder">2</note>
                    <note type="document">arm03020007000</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Local Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <list>
                        <item>Living Conditions</item>
                        <item>Community</item>
                        <item>Landscape</item>
                        <item>People</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="abstract">
                <pb ref="arm03020007001" seq="01"/>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <item>The general store belonging to Charlie Ogle.</item>
                        <item>County Institute in Sevierville.</item>
                        <item>Visit at the Clabos.</item>
                            <item>Miss Turner arrives for 10 day visit - she who suggested the school to honor our
                                Founders.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="letter">
                <pb ref="arm03020007002" seq="02"/>
                <head>
                    <date value="1919-09-04">  Sep. 4, 1919</date>
                </head>
                <p>
                Dear Family - Its just a week ago tomorrow night since I wrote you and I&apos;m truly sorry and ashamed not to have 
                gotten off a letter sooner - Your letters of Sunday &amp; Wednesday came Tuesday - a letter from Aunt Carrie <abbr expan="Saturday">Sat.</abbr> 
                and from Uncle Art today - <unclear reason="illegible">Bonnie</unclear> yesterday (Wednesday.)
                </p>
                <p>
                    The papers also came with the two booklets and am glad especially to have the latter. Then Monday my <hi1 rend="underscore">lovely</hi1> hat came 
                    and a khaki colored niddy from New York ($2.75) ordered by Emily&apos;s cousin just the thing for down here. All the bundles usually have holes torn in the corners 
                    - curiosity on somebody&apos;s part but it makes me rather cross and I&apos;m not the only one who has the same experience. Would you send a letter of 
                    complaint to Washington D.C? Don&apos;t bother Mr. F. about my itinerary any more for I sent in my expense account a week or more ago but as yet have not heard 
                    from it - came to $113. &amp; if I remember rightly - Have this exact amount itemized under my <unclear reason="illegible">blotting</unclear> pad or my table at the house - 
                    Since at the present writing am up Pi Phi
                                <pb ref="arm03020007003" seq="03"></pb>
                lane under the trees can&apos;t give you the exact figures - Pa - your letter does not sound like a <hi1 rend="underscore">vacation</hi1> and do hope that by the time 
                you run out of such jobs you will take a trip! Shall be anxious to know about <unclear reason="illegible">Sceine</unclear>! What did we do last Labor Day? Can&apos;t remember! No 
                Labor Day holiday in Gatlinburg - they never do have one you know. Before I forget will you please rummage in the right end of my desk or in the pigeon holes &amp; see 
                if the <hi1 rend="underscore">quarterly</hi1>  C.S. beginning with October isn&apos;t there?
                </p>
                <p>
                    If you sell the house it sure will mean something doing &amp; what? Where will you go? Perhaps my next letter from you will say where &amp; that you have gone and 
                    done it!
                </p>
                <p>
                    Jane is really horrid about the kitty especially when she was the main attraction for the poor kitty. Now in answer to some
                questions - Yes the pupils buy their own text books - Aunt Lizzie is a mountain
                woman you know &amp; not a <hi1 rend="underscore">real good</hi1> housekeeper -
                Evelyn is very southern in many ways too &amp; has lots of outside things to do
                - so Emily &amp; I have rummaged around &amp; cleaned out <pb ref="arm03020007004"
                    seq="04" n="02"/>several choice spots - Emily &amp; I both like to clean up
                however - There is not girl working for her board after all. Have neither heard nor
                seen anything about or of my salary. Evelyn said today that she had been expecting
                to hear from some of the "high ones" all week as they have now finished up the
                Council meeting - She is wondering what her salary is to be - I still have a $20
                traveler&apos;s check &amp; about $10 from another so shall get along nicely for a
                while - Most of my money has gone for films &amp; printing pictures since I got
                here - it seems - Mary Ogle has my dress &amp; presume it will be done some time
                this week - just love to wear that dress too - Wear those silk skirts at our parties
                &amp; Sundays - sometimes. Think I shall dispose of a number of my old shoes &amp; garments here - 
                    hope so - my white pumps are most pathetic after that <hi1 rend="underscore">still</hi1> hunt! 
                    Have decided to finish up that green jersey instead of buying a sweater. Do you think that a wise idea or not? 
                    My pheasant hat is simply a <hi1 rend="underscore">darling</hi1> and I&apos;m
                <pb ref="arm03020007005" seq="05"/>
                    crazy about it &apos; so are the girls - it sits up quite high on my head in the back &apos; low on my brow in front so my hair &apos; head are not all 
                    covered up as most of my hats have done - Then the long tail feathers have the most bewitching bend in them and rear up high in the back 
                    giving the height Jane that you are always talking about! They have put the dark green <add place="supralinear">&amp; white</add> breast feathers in 
                    the middle of the front on the top <del>is</del> <add place="supralinear">are</add> some of lovely taupe shade &amp; in back tans 
                    and browns - the taupe velvet <del>is</del> edges the turban with a twist of it across where the tail feathers &quot;<hi1 rend="underscore">rare</hi1> up&quot; 
                    as Abbie says. Wrote to the milliner &amp; told her how pleased I was - My long letter to Aunt Carrie passed the one she wrote me - so I know about her visitors 
                    &amp; she knows a little oh my doings - Sent a long letter to the Cavanagh&apos;s also with kodak pictures which I&apos;ve asked to be sent to Aunt Carrie &amp; asked 
                    her to send them on to the St. Paul folks - Uncle Art&apos;s letter today said the downstairs of their house was finished but not the big upper hall nor
                <pb ref="arm03020007006" seq="06" n="03"/>
               the two bathrooms - One of the bedrooms is being remodeled into a bathroom. They have hopes of selling their house so may then get a car &amp; while motoring over 
                    Uncle Art&apos;s territory may get down to see me. Would enjoy having them &amp; would especially enjoy Aunt <unclear reason="illegible">Lottie</unclear> in a mountain cabin! I told them in my letter that to come 
                    down here &amp; see the <hi1 rend="underscore">real</hi1> <hi1 rend="underscore">thing</hi1> meant tramping around in the hills - in big boots &amp; divided skirt - 
                    &amp; that I didn&apos;t know whether they&apos;d enjoy it or not but that I thought it great! Also told them the hotel was good - so mayhap they will be here - 
                    who knows? He also said that Aunt <unclear reason="illegible">Lottie</unclear> fell down the cellar stairs <abbr expan="August">Aug.</abbr> 6th &amp; burst a bloodvessel on her instep 
                    &amp; twisted a knee - in bed two days. As he said nothing more on that subject suppose she is all right by now.
                </p>
                <p>
                    You asked about Charlie Ogle&apos;s
                stores. My dears it&apos;s overflowing with everything - shoes - cabbages - hats
                &amp; blueing - shoe polish - ink - fruit - flour in short<pb ref="arm03020007007"
                    seq="07"/>it&apos;s a general store - copiously stocked - crowded - jammed - The
                post-office occupies one small corner - Then Saturday p.m.s the men gather around
                outside &amp; are <hi1 rend="underscore">barbered</hi1> - I think Charley does
                that too! Our board is not so <hi1 rend="underscore">awfully</hi1> varied - but it&apos;s
                very good &amp; I eat &amp; eat &amp; have a horrid fear that I&apos;m
                gaining! The staple products are corn bread - corn - tomatoes - string beans - <hi1
                    rend="underscore">hot biscuits</hi1> - ! These latter we always have at least <hi1
                        rend="underscore">once</hi1> a day &amp; usually for breakfast and such
                delicious ones as Aunt Lizzie makes. The wild blackberries here were as large as our
                tame ones &amp; we have been eating the most delicious jam - There are so many
                wild flowers - can&apos;t stop to tell about them now - pretty-by-night is one - jewel
                weed - beggar weed - touch-me-not - cardinal flowers - swamp day wood - golden rod -
                wild purple asters - yellow evening primrose - smooth false fox glove - jo pie weed
                - yellow daisies - passion flower - They call zinnias <hi1 rend="underscore">old
                    maids</hi1>! Petunias are very common here - also sunflowers. We have seen some
                wonderful butterflies - great yellow<pb ref="arm03020007008" seq="08" n="04"/>and brown
                ones - another large variety is a black &amp; blue &amp; green called spice
                wood - as the caterpillar lives on spice wood tree. The maples are beginning to turn
                a brilliant red. Emily says October is a wonderful month - &amp; there will be
                loads of chestnuts - would you like some? Be sure and tell me. Frosts killed most of
                the fruit so apples have been scarce &amp; hard to get. Aunt Lizzie has been
                canning a lot of little green ones this week awfully good sauce they make too. One
                of the girls brought me eight big red ones - Tennessee reds - she said they are
                called. We four girls sat out on the porch a little bit this p.m. &amp; enjoyed
                them for they are "plumb good"! <hi1 rend="underscore">Plumb</hi1> is one of the
                expressions here. Dr. Bishop has sent water melons &amp; <hi1 rend="underscore"
                    >cantaloupes</hi1> Oh my such cantaloupe I never imagined - huge &amp; yellow
                &amp; rich &amp; sweet &amp; tender! Others have sent up melons so we
                have had quite - a number. As to my spelling potato &amp; tomato - that is one
                of my weak points - perhaps will remember better now after your gentle hint Jane! Am
                glad Betty &amp; Mary are going to have a vacation together. Will try &amp;
                write - Betty but<pb ref="arm03020007009" seq="09"/>
                fear I won&apos;t for awhile. Will you please get all my kodak pictures to the Pi Phi meeting next week - if they have one &amp; be sure to get them to the Seattle &amp; home again 
                    am keeping a duplicate set of my own to take to New Orleans at Christmas time to show the Pi Phis down there. (Am glad I have a pretty hat to wear any way!) Your hat 
                    sounded very pretty Jane - send me a kodak of you in it - why not another of you all and the car? Would love to see Virginia May - and <unclear reason="illegible">weir</unclear> and Nellie Jane 
                    besides the rest of the family - but am so glad not to be starting in school again in Tacoma - even high school - that I&apos;d rather be here without you all - That is I feel that 
                    way now - I surely hope things won&apos;t pall before my eight months are up.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Was sorry to hear of Bessie&apos;s loss - Was her mother&apos;s death unexpected? Will write her a few times - have wanted to get around to doing it before. Have 
                    not as yet written Jo &amp; Charlotte isn&apos;t that awful of me? Have planned to do that this week with the Pi Phi chapter letter.
                <pb ref="arm03020007010" seq="10" n="05"/>
                    Who is putting up the house by <unclear reason="illegible">Edinundres</unclear>?
                </p>
                <p>No am not going to drink any more moonshine but just had to taste it to say I&apos;d
                    had it you know - What will you think of my <hi1 rend="underscore">still</hi1>
                    episode I wonder!</p>
                <p>Will now turn back the leaves of time to last Friday the night of the party -
                    which as I said was a great success. The next morning Emily &amp; I arose a
                    little after five to prepare ourselves for the trip to Sevierville - County
                    Institute you remember. We dressed up in our suits - the first time I&apos;d worn
                    mine &amp; quite an appropriate garb as it had showered in the night
                    &amp; was dark &amp; cloudy - I took my ex-school bag &amp; white
                    silk gloves (which however I did not put on once) so you may know it was an
                    occasion - Stuck the long letter I&apos;d written you in my bag along with gloves
                    pencil &amp; diary &amp; purse. About 6:30 after a delicious breakfast
                    of hot biscuits - jam - oat-meal &amp; coffee for Aunt Lizzie like an old
                    dear got up early - Mr. Huff drove up for us - In we got &amp; later picked
                    up Mr. Cresswell &amp; Mr. Prickett formerly of <pb ref="arm03020007011" seq="11"
                    />our school you know - He is now way up in the Sugar Lands in some school - We
                    are all going up there some Saturday for a visit! The road was awful beyond
                    words &amp; moreover gets worse as fall &amp; winter approach - Half of
                    the fourteen miles are on this narrow mountain road &amp; the other seven on
                    the pike which are buzzed over in about twenty minutes. The trip takes at least
                    an hour. When we arrived at Sevierville it was raining and about 7:45 - no
                    institute till nine. Mr. C. kindly took us to his brother&apos;s home - (state
                    senator) where we visited til about nine - His niece of about 13 &amp;
                    brother (not the senator) entertained us - later the lady of the house &amp;
                    her infant daughter arrived - you see we got there before breakfast. This
                    brother is younger even than Mr. C. I imagine &amp; teaches in Murphy
                    College - his first year. From here we went over towards the college but seeing
                    no signs of life about crossed the street to Dr. Massey&apos;s. Their house is quite
                    large &amp; pretty outside - huge veranda across the front &amp; side -
                    <pb ref="arm03020007012" seq="12" n="06"/>But when you go in - it&apos;s so bare
                    &amp; run down - just as most of these places seem to be. The youngest
                    daughter Juanita (her name just suits her - she is fuzzy as to hair worn with
                    bobs over the ears - tall &amp; thin &amp; about twenty I imagine) lead
                    us right in to the living room where sat Blanche &amp; the baby &amp; in
                    the big bed was Dr. Massey. This greeting people in bed is just the queerest
                    thing to me &amp; the most matter-of-course performance down here - it&apos;s
                    funny. We all sat &amp; visited - Mrs. Massey came in presently too. They
                    said Institute probably began about ten. So at that hour we set forth again -
                    and fell in with Dr. Bishop &amp; a maiden who proved to be a new music
                    teacher with a lovely Southern accent from Alabama. We sat &amp; visited in
                    the office a long time &amp; after while maidens &amp; youths (most of
                    whom seemed to be in their early teens) began to amble in - two or three at a
                    time. About a quarter of eleven we went to the assembly room &amp; found
                    about 30 of these before seen children sitting around - Some of them chewing gum
                    &amp;<pb ref="arm03020007013" seq="13"/>&amp; most of the girls clad in
                    <unclear reason="illegible">airiest</unclear>of georgette waists - Well after while another
                    youth <abbr expan="president">pres.</abbr> of the association took to the
                    platform &amp; we sang &amp; had a few opening exercises - One of their
                    speakers did not arrive so Dr. Bishop gave a very nice address &amp; then
                    one of the teachers was called on - after which the county superintendent talked
                    &amp; that was all! They have it the last Saturday in each month but not
                    being compulsory it is not usually much better attended than we saw. However we
                    had done our duty &amp; joyfully departed. It was not yet noon so we started
                    down town &amp; meeting Mrs. Bishop talked with her a while discovering that
                    she &amp; the doctor were going to have dinner with Miss Whittle too. Thus
                    we strolled down the main street in the rain to the red brick courthouse -
                    sprawly &amp; dirty - like the <unclear reason="illegible">town</unclear> - cobblestones in the
                    middle of the street in lieu of a crossing. The one side of the street on which
                    are the stores has an asphalt walk - We found Miss Whittle and in the course of
                    time walked with her over to the home of the Trotter&apos;s where we had a very good
                    dinner with the usual hot biscuits - corn <pb ref="arm03020007014" seq="14" n="07"
                    />bread &amp; rolls besides jelly applesauce - tomatoes - corn and string
                    beans - I don&apos;t know what all. After this we <hi1 rend="underscore">shopped</hi1>
                    - going in six or seven stores - bought an umbrella - ink - elastic - picture
                    for Aunt Lizzie - peanut butter for our mountain trip &amp; chocolate bars.
                    We found one spot where we enjoyed maple nut ice cream - the second time only
                    that I&apos;ve tasted such a delicacy since leaving Chicago. After this wild splurge
                    we went back to Miss Whittle&apos;s office at the courthouse &amp; as she was
                    busy with a committee meeting in a nearby room we perched our-selves comfortably
                    on a table (the chairs were occupied by the committee) and proceeded to write in
                    our diaries. About 3:30 we decided to start for the depot where we would find
                    Mr. Huff &amp; the Ford to take us home. This is way at the end of town
                    and during the jaunt Mr. C., his brother &amp; niece passed us in their
                    Ford - stopped &amp; asked us to go with them in the care the rest of
                    the way - which we did - Later got a picture <pb ref="arm03020007015" seq="15"/>of the
                    depot - Murphy College &amp; the <hi1 rend="underscore">train</hi1>! Going
                    back was as bumpy as coming down &amp; how glad we were to get here! Abbie
                    &amp; Evelyn walked down the road to meet us &amp; told us what they had
                    been doing while we were gone - for it had seemed like two days at least. We eat
                    and go to bed early - Sunday was a busy day as usual - Got up early - finished
                    fixing my room - (not quite - done since the still <hi1 rend="underscore"
                        >hunt!</hi1>) worked &amp; went to Sunday School about nine - Here I wound up
                    by teaching a class of youngsters - lesson Daniel - was busy the rest of the day
                    - marking papers - working out grades &amp; report cards - getting films
                    ready for Knoxville and so on - Evelyn &amp; Abbie went to the hotel
                    &amp; out walking - Emily read and wrote letters - well the girls got home
                    just as Aunt Lizzie Emily &amp; I were enjoying toast (baked in oven)
                    &amp; chocolate - Next was B.Y.P. at which Mr. C. presided - but Emily
                    Abbie &amp; I each had been given a topic on which we had to talk for a few
                    minutes - <pb ref="arm03020007016" seq="16" n="08"/>Evelyn&apos;s was Social Service -
                    Abbie&apos;s was Faith without Works &amp; mine - Duty to one&apos;s neighbor. About
                    sixty or seventy were there mostly young people - We sat in the choir seats
                    &amp; sang as usual! Monday after school - their girls&apos; club came over to
                    the house - about eleven only - &amp; as they didn&apos;t bring stockings to darn
                    Emily &amp; I got out ours &amp; passed them around. The very ones who
                    did not know how to darn &amp; whom we had wanted especially to be there
                    didn&apos;t come! Well after they left I darned on &amp; on myself &amp;
                    after dinner took my white dress to Mary&apos;s &amp; stayed for a little visit.
                    Tues. a.m. Evelyn goes to Sevierville &amp; after school Emily &amp; I
                    walk nearly two miles up Roarin&apos; Fork with six or seven youngsters to call on
                    the Partons three of whom form part of our escort. We sat on the porch - ate
                    apples - &amp; visited with Mrs. Parton while she shelled beans - they are
                    right in the wilderness - have a little patch of corn &amp; chickens as
                    usual - Very nice people. Then on the way back along <pb ref="arm03020007017" seq="17"
                    />the road we stopped at another home - a frame two story house this time - and
                    the home of Mrs. Parton&apos;s mother. The Roarin&apos; Fork road is lovely winds along
                    the creek which is very gurgling all the way &amp; also picturesque
                    &amp; rocky - The sun is so hot in the p.m. but the early mornings and
                    evenings are cool enough for wraps now. We got home about six &amp; found
                    Evelyn had come back with Dr. Massey in his car. He is still not feeling well
                    &amp; stayed over until this morning - After dinner we sat around the
                    fireplace enjoying a little fire very much - He wants to get a pheasant hat like
                    mine for Juanita!</p>
                <p>Then yesterday (Wednesday) Emily &amp; I went home with one of my little
                    girls Maud Clabo - She stands the last one in the school picture on the right -
                    Her father and mother are not living so she stays with an aunt Ruth Clabo -
                    Younger than I am I imagine - She has a little girl about a year old - her
                    husband is <pb ref="arm03020007018" seq="18" n="09"/>still in France - She has taught
                    four <hi1 rend="underscore">schools</hi1> around here (People never says the <abbr expan="number">no.</abbr> 
                    of years one teaches but always the <abbr expan="number">no.</abbr> of schools)
                    &amp; went to Murphy College for two years - worked her way. Her home is a
                    real cabin though immaculately clean - one room and kitchen built on - Between
                    kitchen &amp; <unclear reason="illegible">this</unclear> room are three steps! In the room are
                    two double beds - two rockers - sewing machine bureau - cupboard - enlarged
                    portraits on the walls &amp; pictures from magazines. The walls are all
                    covered with past newspapers - the stone fireplace occupies one end and I think
                    there is one window only but very clean with a curtain. There were some of the
                    little <unclear reason="illegible">splint</unclear> bottomed chairs like the one in the picture I
                    sent you - also a table. In the kitchen was a stove &amp; kitchen cabinet -
                    Well we had promised to stay all night &amp; it was very pleasant - We ate
                    in the kitchen at a table covered with a <pb ref="arm03020007019" seq="19"/>white cloth
                    centerpiece &amp; asters in a vase - Had mashed potato rolls - beans -
                    tomatoes - milk - canned blackberries and cake. We went with Maud up the hills
                    after the cows and took a couple of pictures - A cousin of Ruth&apos;s was there
                    visiting &amp; for dinner but he went to the grandfather&apos;s after supper - so
                    all was peaceful as we sat around the fire in the evening - By 8:30 we were all
                    in bed too. It is dark about seven so that the evenings already seem long - This
                    morning after a filling breakfast of coffee hot biscuits and sausage - we left
                    about seven for school - It&apos;s a walk of about two miles - hence the early start
                    -</p>
                <p>A new Pi Phi arrived in our midst day before yesterday from Washington D.C. -
                    Miss Turner - elderly thin small and active but on verge of nervous breakdown
                    from too much war work. Has been in the Treasury Department at <abbr
                        expan="Washington">Wash.</abbr>
                    <pb ref="arm03020007020" seq="20" n="10"/>for years and belongs to same chapter as Miss
                    Abbott. She is going to be here about ten days &amp; is at the hotel for the
                    present. We have given up our mountain trip that we had planned for the week end
                    - because of her arrival - Mrs. Helmick wrote Evelyn to be especially nice to
                    her. None of us knew anything about her beforehand but think we made a discovery
                    tonight - (You see since beginning this dinner time came &amp; went
                    &amp; after dinner Miss T arrived &amp; no letter writing) During the
                    conversation something was said about a group of girls at Cornell who petitioned
                    at one time for a chapter. Miss Turner said - "That was during <hi1
                        rend="underscore">my administration</hi1> and I ought to remember about
                    that!" Evelyn &amp; I have concluded that she is an ex-Grand president
                    &amp; we&apos;re going to look her up <pb ref="arm03020007021" seq="21"/>in the
                    fraternity listing!</p>
                <p>Well it&apos;s getting late for we took Miss T. home &amp; had to sit on the hotel
                    porch &amp; visit a little while longer before returning. Must stop and hie
                    me to bed! We have no plans made for Saturday yet - waiting to see how much Miss
                    T. is game for! We like her too.</p>
                <p>Ask all the questions you wish. There is so much that is new down here it&apos;s hard
                    to think of everything. Shall not stop to read this
                    <unclear reason="illegible">lengthiness</unclear> over again for correction so if there are lots of
                    mistakes just overlook them.</p>
                <p>Hoping to hear from some of you soon - Tell Mabel these letters are for her too
                    as so far I just can&apos;t write separately. Loads of love &amp; fond kisses to
                    all - Ruth. </p>
                <p>Thursday eve - Sept. 4th.</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>