<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03020001000">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[Letter]  Aug. 3, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
                    <name>Carter, Genny</name>
                    <name>Young, Philip</name>
                    <name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
                    <name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
                </address>
                <date>2006</date>
                <idno type="SPCID">arm03020001000</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. 
                        For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee 
                        Libraries, Knoxville, TN</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from which the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
                <bibl>
                    <title>[Letter]  Aug. 3, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                    <date value="1919-08-03">Aug. 3, 1919</date>
                    <author>
                        <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                    </author>
                    <extent>25p</extent>
                    <note type="summary">Arrival at Knoxville- train to Sevierville &amp; eventually to Gatlinburg.  First experience calling on a mountain family</note>
                    <note type="box">3</note>
                    <note type="folder">2</note>
                    <note type="document">arm03020001000</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Local Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <list>
                        <item>Living Conditions</item>
                        <item>Social life</item>
                        <item>People</item>
                        <item>Home visits</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="abstract">
                <pb ref="arm03020001001" seq="01"/>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <item>Arrival at Knoxville- train to Sevierville &amp; eventually to Gatlinburg.</item>
                        <item> First experience calling on a mountain family</item>
                        </list>
                </p>
             </div1>
            <div1 type="letter">
                <pb ref="arm03020001002" seq="02"/>
                <head>
                    <date value="1919-08-03">Aug. 3, 1919</date>
                </head>
                <p>
                    Dearest family - Well I&apos;m arrived - unpacked and settled at the Settlement School
                    and will proceed to unfold my life history from the time of mailing the last
                    letter at Indianapolis - or rather giving it to a girl who got off there and
                    offered to mail it in town for me - which no doubt she did. After passing for
                    hours through almost continuous and constant cornfields we arrived at Cincinnati
                    about 6:30 p.m. A red cap carried my luggage for me to the checking station and
                    then I went to the dining room and got some food as I was exceedingly hungry. It
                    was pretty good and better than I had anticipated. After that I strolled up town
                    following the most respectable looking whites - all around the depot seems to be
                    the colored section and lots of it too. The nice stores are quite a little
                    distance from the depot &amp; though I saw only a small part - was satisfied
                    <pb ref="arm03020001003" seq="03 "/>to get back to the depot about 8 p.m. The
                    streets are quite narrow and were full of people - movies going full blast - I
                    went as far as a large public square adorned with a huge fountain. The depot is
                    a large old fashioned stone building overflowing with people also so my
                    impression of Cincinnati was that is quite a large busy city - not as big as
                    Seattle but larger than Tacoma. The Louisville &amp; Nashville was due to
                    leave at 8:30 but since it was made up at Cincinnati I could get on at 8 which I
                    did having previously fortified myself with the August Atlantic Monthly. It was
                    an awfully long train and only two Pullmans - mine being the last car no diner
                    or observation accompanying us along the route. There were about a dozen
                    youngsters along - varying in age from two to twelve years. The porter said we
                    were due <pb ref="arm03020001004" seq="04" n="02"/>in Knoxville at 6:04 a.m. and knew
                    nothing about the Knoxville - Sevierville (accent 2nd syllable) &amp;
                    Eastern line that I was supposed to take. Well - I and a good many others were
                    up at 5:30 and ready to alight at schedule hour - the porter put our baggage up
                    in front brushed us off and said we&apos;d be there in ten minutes and lo we stopped
                    and remained that way a half hour or so - Finally I roamed out to the end of our
                    car where it was all open. A brakeman put in his appearance - the porter and
                    conductor - and I learned that there was a freight wreck ahead - 8 cars of coal
                    having turned over and that we had to back up to Coal Creek 32 miles distant
                    where we would switch to the Southern Railway&apos;s tracks &amp; pursue our way
                    to Knoxville thusly. The porter got me a chair and it was lovely &amp; <pb ref="arm03020001005" seq="05"/>cool backing along - we went through two tunnels for
                    we were right in the mountains - at least that&apos;s what they are called here - and
                    they are just like the pictures - many pointed - perfect cones - and others
                    rounding &amp; larger all densely wooded - and the air! It&apos;s an absolutely
                    different woodsy smell from our forests - more medicinal - aromatic or something
                    - I think it&apos;s the cedar which is quite different from our cedar - I like it and
                    wish I could bottle up some &amp; send to you to sample - I asked the porter
                    if there was anything on the train to eat - He laughed and said sandwiches -
                    asked me if I wanted some and as I was quite panting for food said yes - He came
                    back with a towel in which were two buns split &amp; ham between - They
                    didn&apos;t look particularly good - but hunger <pb ref="arm03020001006" seq="06" n="03"/>is
                    quite insistent you know - so asked him how much they were - He said &quot;nothing&quot;
                    &amp; thought they were part of his lunch probably but as there seemed no
                    way of getting out of it took them &amp; ate them. He ate two similar ones
                    also. Finally we got to Coal Creek &amp; then everybody began piling off and
                    going up the tracks to some little stores and getting food- pop - etc. Here we
                    had to wait for another engineer as the signals differed from those on the L.
                    &amp; N. road - so it was ten before we finally started up Southern&apos;s
                    tracks. We ambled along for an hour perhaps going up grade &amp; finally
                    stopped in the wilds - a long time - This was because the length of the train
                    was too much for the engine &amp; <pb ref="arm03020001007" seq=" 07"/>half the
                    train was pulled up the grade &amp; then our half - It was about noon when
                    we got to the railroad yards where we again lingered. Meanwhile it had been
                    getting cloudy - more cloudy - sultry and more sultry - The porter did not make
                    up the berths and you can imagine how uncomfortable it was but all those
                    youngsters behaved pretty well at that. While we lingered as I said above the
                    storm broke - thunder &amp; lightning and torrents of rain a regular
                    cloudburst - so much so that one could not see across the street. We gradually
                    moved on again and about 12:30 arrived at the L. &amp; N. depot for which I
                    was pleased as my trunk had to be checked again &amp; they <pb ref="arm03020001008" seq="08" n="04"/>told me the Southern depot was on the other side of town. I
                    found out that the Sevierville train depot was four or five blocks from the L.
                    &amp; N. so had my trunk taken right over for the 2:30 train and got some
                    lunch. Had coffee two poached eggs on toast and ice cream &amp; cake - funny
                    combination wasn&apos;t it - but so good - as the two sandwiches &amp; two <sic corr="bananas">banannas</sic> were all I had eaten since the night before.
                    When I asked what kind of cake they had - the woman in charge said - chocolate
                    cake - white cake and camel cake - I said &quot;Camel cake - what kind is that?&quot; <pb ref="arm03020001009" seq="09"/>Then when she said it was brown I grasped her
                    meaning and laughed and said - &quot;Oh caramel cake!&quot; She said &quot;Why yes <hi1 rend="underscore">cahmel</hi1> cake!&quot; I ordered it &amp; it was &quot;right
                    good.&quot; After this refreshment I hunted up the same red cap &amp; he carried
                    my baggage over to the other depot. It was a funny little spot and there were
                    two waiting rooms - one was labelled &quot;Colored waiting room&quot; - so I felt I was
                    really in the South. The train reminded me of that one going to
                    <unclear reason="illegible">Ilunco</unclear>- only the coaches are not quite so narrow &amp;
                    there are only two - I rode just back of the engine - which squeaked &amp;
                    heaved and grunted all the way - The other passengers were typical country
                    people. <pb ref="arm03020001010" seq="10" n="05"/>The scenery was very pretty but the
                    same funny little hills that I had seen all day with an occasional patch of corn
                    and farmhouses - very crude - and some of logs with stone chimney at one end -
                    just like the pictures in the Arrow - the women wearing sunbonnets &amp;
                    dark colorless dresses - they themselves ditto. Finally I put my coats on my bag
                    at the end of the seat &amp; curling up went to sleep. About 4:30 we got to
                    Sevierville which is quite a town - big red brick building - school house and
                    many houses spread out in a little valley shut in on every side by the <abbr expan="mountains">mts.</abbr> The train goes down the main street and way
                    off at one end is the depot. <pb ref="arm03020001011" seq="11"/>Here was quite a crowd
                    of people and half a dozen cars or more. A little dark eyed - thin faced - eye
                    glassed woman came right up and I knew it was Miss Bishop. She is quite southern
                    but very very nice &amp; I imagine about 35 - She lead me over to a car
                    where were two other ladies - about her age and married - They do not live in S.
                    now but were visiting their father &amp; mother Dr. &amp; Mrs. Massey -
                    Mrs. Wood had her baby with her - a boy about five or six months old - awfully
                    cute fat youngster too. The other drove the car &amp; we - Miss B. &amp;
                    I sat in the back seat - We all went up to the Bishop&apos;s house - Dr. &amp;
                    Mrs. B. were <pb ref="arm03020001012" seq="12" n="06"/>not there but came later. I
                    cleaned up &amp; by that time Miss B. had supper ready &amp; the two
                    Massey girls &amp; baby also had supper with us. Their house is on a hill
                    overlooking the town - rather a rambling old fashioned structure. We had just
                    begun the meal when Miss B.&apos;s father and mother arrived. He is tall &amp;
                    thin &amp; she is dark &amp; rather plump - looks like the daughter.
                    Murphy College of which Dr. B. is president is right in Sevierville - They are
                    both very nice and hospitable and I enjoyed meeting them. The two girls had to
                    leave almost as soon as we finished eating - then we did up the dishes &amp;
                    Miss B. &amp; I sat on the porch <pb ref="arm03020001013" seq="13"/>and talked
                    school. Right by their house is a hill that has been set out in corn - and I&apos;ve
                    seen others similar - imagine a cone shaped hill covered with great stalks of
                    corn - 6 or 7 <abbr expan="feet">ft.</abbr> high - or half a hill - way up to
                    the summit. While we talked there was a perfect chorus of crickets and all kinds
                    of insects that made the croaking of our frogs quite insignificant - also I saw
                    oodles of fire flies - my first - and am quite crazy about them. I slept like a
                    log &amp; got up about 8 - as they had been up for some time ate breakfast
                    alone - But first I forgot to tell you that the night before Miss B. showed me
                    some &quot;kivvers&quot; &amp; baskets - the latter are made of willow <pb ref="arm03020001014" seq="14" n="07"/>mostly - and I&apos;m sure Mr. Van Decar will like
                    them. The only trouble is Miss B. has lots of orders that have not been filled
                    so don&apos;t know when mine will get done - Then the &quot;kivers&quot; are wonderful - The
                    pattern is quite small - &amp; of strands about half an inch wide blue and
                    white - red and green brown &amp; yellow - the latter combination is very
                    rare - imagine the blue &amp; white is the kind made oftenest. They are $25-
                    and hard to get! I shall try to get one! About ten o&apos;clock Mr. Huff came to the
                    foot of the hill in his Ford to take us to Gatlinburg so we hustled off - bag
                    &amp; baggage - For seven miles we had a very nice gravel <pb ref="arm03020001015" seq="15"/>road similar to ours - only called a pike - and then we turned off
                    into a <abbr expan="mountain">mt.</abbr> road - Such a road I&apos;ve never ridden
                    over - rocks - ruts &amp; holes - then as it had rained quite hard the
                    afternoon before it was also skiddy - much of the soil is red - red as can be
                    like that around Colorado Springs - We went up &amp; down over this said
                    road for nine more miles following Little Pigeon River - which was a very muddy
                    stream from the bad rainstorm - Then we came to a little valley and the road
                    took us past a hotel and farther on and back on a knoll from the road - are the
                    school - the big cottage - the little cottage which may be a girl&apos;s dormitory
                    and another cottage where the Ogles live who look after <pb ref="arm03020001016" seq="16" n="08"/>the farm in connection with the school - the horse and the
                    cow - also some nice white chickens - We got out of the Ford &amp; said good
                    bye to Mr. Huff - who is a tall thin spare man - shrewd face and quite advanced
                    for a mountaineer I believe - in the ways of the rest of civilization - Arriving
                    at the big cottage I met Aunt Lizzie Reagan - who is also thin and spare - gray
                    hair - brown eyes - and almost as brown and wrinkled as our old squaws at home -
                    So many of these women are that way - the sun &amp; hard work are
                    responsible I presume. I won&apos;t stop to describe the house in this letter
                    &amp; will in the next and will also send a picture as soon as <pb ref="arm03020001017" seq="17"/>possible - several of them - We three had lunch or
                    dinner together - cold fried chicken rice &amp; chicken gravy - tomatoes -
                    hot biscuits - jelly - and honey - very good too. Then one of the other teachers
                    who had been to the revival meeting came - Emily Burton - She is from New York -
                    is not a Pi Phi - but has been here two years and has primary grade - She is a
                    little mite of a thing - like Mrs. Ward &amp; is very bright and interested
                    in everything &amp; I like her very much - She arrived just the day before -
                    Our trunks came next &amp; we proceeded to unpack - I had things nicely
                    messed up - when Emily came in &amp; wanted to know if I&apos;d go up to call on
                    <pb ref="arm03020001018" seq="18" n="09"/>the Bradley&apos;s - real mountaineers - I
                    forgot to tell you about Miss Abbott - She - her father and mother drove in a
                    Ford from Chicago to Gatlinburg &amp; have been visiting here two weeks -
                    She is much older than I am and teaches English in one of the Chicago high
                    schools - is very nice &amp; a Pi Phi - Well she took us about two miles up
                    a road similar to that we came over in the <abbr expan="morning">a.m.</abbr> into the <abbr expan="mountains">mts.</abbr> - then we three left the car &amp; proceeded a long half
                    mile on foot - it was a very steep climb &amp; exceedingly rocky - we
                    stopped at a spring house on the way up - my first spring house! and got a nice
                    drink - Then we arrived at a little clearing on the side of the hill &amp;
                    there was a perfect <abbr expan="mountain">mt.</abbr> cabin - <pb ref="arm03020001019" seq="19"/>and inside ditto! Papered with newspapers - most of which had been
                    torn off or scratched - a big cobblestone fireplace at one end - and a double
                    bed on one side of fire place at other a cupboard with garments piled on it -
                    &amp; at other end opposite fireplace were 3 more double beds! Mrs. Bradley
                    was a colorless woman sitting in a rocker by the littered up fireplace &amp;
                    excused herself for not getting up as she had been &quot;right puny for two or three
                    weeks&quot; - Emily knew her &amp; introduced Miss A. &amp; myself to her -
                    There was another woman also sitting there but we were not introduced to her -
                    it was not etiquette I guess - Emily didn&apos;t <pb ref="arm03020001020" seq="20" n="10"/>know her &amp; Mrs. B. didn&apos;t make any effort. Then there was a younger
                    woman - Mrs. B.&apos;s daughter or daughter-in-law - I imagine but she was not
                    introduced either - She had a year old little girl lying asleep on one of the
                    beds - Occasionally one or the other of the two older women spit into the
                    fireplace - very neatly never missing so that it evidently was a customary act!
                    They talked about various relatives that Emily knew and many were the h&apos;s added
                    to various words - always &quot;haint&quot; and &quot;hit&quot; for &quot;it&quot;! Well I was just so
                    interested I couldn&apos;t keep from staring a little but not half as much as I
                    wanted to. We got back about 6:30 and as Miss B. &amp; Aunt Lizzie <pb ref="arm03020001021" seq="21"/>were through we scared up our lunch and ate at the
                    table on the back porch - Then I rustled around &amp; cleaned up for revival
                    meeting at 8 p.m. Oh my! the church was full - two hundred or more - the
                    youngsters seem to be the ones who go to the mourner&apos;s bench - There were four
                    little girls and three boys - they cry and cry - it&apos;s awfully pathetic. This
                    morning Emily &amp; Miss B. went to the Sunday School while I finished
                    unpacking - then by ten Aunt Lizzie &amp; I started for church which lasted
                    until noon - It was worse than the night before - as they all got wound up
                    towards the last &amp; wept &amp; shook hands all around! There is
                    service again going on now - it began at 3:30 - and another one tonight - We
                    have to go again to- <pb ref="arm03020001022" seq="22" n="11"/>night - The services
                    have been all week - a man from Knoxville conducting them - The church is just
                    beyond the school on the road - and is a white building with the usual noisy
                    bell - plain ceiled walls &amp; ceiling inside - Miss B. played the organ
                    this a.m.</p>
                <p>Well I was glad to go to bed last night and am going to take a nap now - it&apos;s
                    bright and sunny again but is lovely &amp; cool nights &amp; mornings -
                    altitude about 2000 I believe - Hills or rather <abbr expan="mountains">mts.</abbr> all around us - and a great field of corn just back of the house -</p>
                <p>School begins at 8 in the morning and closes for the morning revival service
                    continuing in the <abbr expan="afternoon">p.m.</abbr> I believe we are ex - <pb ref="arm03020001023" seq="23"/> pected
                    to take the youngsters down in the  <abbr expan="morning">a.m.</abbr> Shall have the upper grade - the third
                    teacher is from Sevierville and will have domestic science - Miss B. has not yet
                    found a man teacher and doesn&apos;t know how big the school will be - or what we are
                    to do as yet - So shall tell you about that later.</p>
                <p>It is now nearly eleven - had a long nap - then dressed - had supper - Abbie
                    Runyan - the other teacher came from Sevierville tonight - She lives there and
                    has been to a college at Maryville something like a Normal School - She seems
                    very sweet &amp; is quite young - was here the last 2 mo. of school
                    &amp; will stay until they find someone else to take the domestic science
                    permanently - We went to revival again which lasted a good two hours - must
                    finish this up &amp; get to bed - will you please see if you can get a book
                    for me - <pb ref="arm03020001024" seq="24"/>and if you can&apos;t get it ask Pirrel&apos;s - (?)
                    bookstore to send for it and have it forwarded to me or else get me the name of
                    the publishing house &amp; price and I&apos;ll send direct - It&apos;s that book Miss
                    Holroyd lent me - games - and is called &quot;Ice Breakers&quot; by Edna Geisler. Then
                    Emily and I are talking about getting up a play &amp; I wondered if my fair
                    cousin could &quot;root&quot; around &amp; find one or send me the name of a
                    publishing house - We&apos;d like one for girls - from 10 yrs. old up to 15 or 16 -
                    with or without music - She might see if she could find one that would do for
                    both boys &amp; girls-</p>
                <p>Did you ever ask about my bank balance Jane - it ought to be about $4. I forsee a
                    busy year ahead but think in fact <gap reason="illegible" resp="gc"></gap> it&apos;s going
                    to be very enjoyable - but lacking <pb ref="arm03020001025" seq="25"/>many of the
                    comforts of home - Expect to wash out my little union suits myself - also my
                    gingham as Miss B. says it&apos;s safer as they are apt to fade things. 50 cents for
                    the wash. I&apos;m anxious to get another letter as the last arrived a week ago
                    tomorrow (Monday) The revival has taken a lot of time - a long session last
                    night &amp; two today but after that is over it will be less rushed and I
                    hope to write again in a day or so &amp; describe the house - the school
                    &amp; my room -</p>
                <p>Have not stopped to peruse this hasty scribble so know not how it sounds - was
                    very sleepy &amp; hot while writing it so there may be many mistakes - Wore
                    my white voile &amp; yarn trimmed hat today &amp; my new gray tonight
                    &amp; last night - With just lots &amp; lots of love to all and kisses
                    too - Ruth. 
                </p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
