<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03040003000">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[Letter]  Feb. 1, 1920, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
                    <name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
                    <name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
                </address>
                <date>2006</date>
                <idno type="SPCID">arm03040003000</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. 
                        For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee 
                        Libraries, Knoxville, TN</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from which the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
                <bibl>
                    <title>[Letter]  Feb. 1, 1920, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                    <date value="1920-02-01">Feb. 1, 1920</date>
                    <author>
                        <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                    </author>
                    <extent>6p</extent>
                    <note type="summary">Aunt Lydia Whaley &amp; her willows for baskets - Men from Delco Light System visit us to make estimate</note>
                    <note type="box">3</note>
                    <note type="folder">4</note>
                    <note type="document">arm03040003000</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Local Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <list>
                        <item>Living Conditions</item>
                        <item>Electricity</item>
                        <item>Social events</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="abstract">
                <pb ref="arm03040003001" seq="01"/>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <item>Aunt Lydia Whaley &amp; her willows for baskets</item>
                        <item>Men from Delco Light System visit us to make estimate</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="letter">
                <pb ref="arm03040003002" seq="02"/>
                <head>
                    <date value="1920-02-01">Feb. 1, 1920</date>
                </head> <!-- Page missing -->
                <p><del>
                    has been on the job a long time. Thank you for the papers.</del>
                </p>
                <p><del>
                    It seems so funny to think of Jane working &amp; pa home - it&apos;s surely a change for you both!</del>
                </p>
                <p>
                    My last was written Wednesday - started it in the <abbr expan="morning">a.m.</abbr> &amp; then finished it that night - Well - after school Thursday - we girls - 
                    Abbey Emily &amp; I went to Aunt Lydia&apos;s after some baskets. It was a perfectly beautiful day warm &amp; bright (have been wearing my lovely sweater
                    &amp; cap on walks lately as it&apos;s been so nice) and we had a very nice call &amp; came <pb ref="arm03040003003" seq="03"></pb> home loaded with baskets.
                </p>
                <p>
                     I sent Lida &#36;18&apos;s worth Friday - and told her to bring to you what she couldn&apos;t sell among the girls - Jane - The money goes to Mrs. 
                    Richardson whose name is on the bill. Aunt Lydia has a number of willows growing on the bank of the &quot;branch&quot; just outside her cabin door that
                    she trims for making the baskets - &quot;golden willow&quot; she calls it &amp; just the color of gold too.
                </p>
                <p>
                     Friday was the debate on suffrage - the whole community is against I guess - Several of those who were to take the part wouldn&apos;t the last minute - but
                    managed to fill in their <pb ref="arm03040003004" seq="04"></pb> as we had discussed it quite thoroughly in school that afternoon. The negative side was given the 
                    decision of course - 
                </p>
                <p>
                     We were glad when the drill by my girls was over &amp; could come home - <del>S.</del> Two men representing the Delco - Light System 
                    were <del>there</del> here whom Miss Langmaid had asked to come up way before <abbr expan="Christmas">Xmas</abbr>. They went over
                    things that night - showed their illustrations etc. &amp; the next morning went over the place &amp; will send in an estimate soon - it will be nearly &#36;2000
                    including everything but the fixtures - all the buildings &amp; the grounds lighted. However it&apos;s not definitely decided yet.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Saturday morning was busy as usual &amp; in the <abbr expan="afternoon">p.m.</abbr> went up to the Forks of the River with Cora Ogle - Lucrettie Reagan &amp;
                    her mother. The girls were going to stay for a sing that evening - but Martha Reagan &amp; I just called at Ollie Carr&apos;s (one of my girls) &amp; then came 
                    back &amp; stopped &amp; made another call on <hi1 rend="underscore">Hattie</hi1> - Charlie Ogle&apos;s wife - who is a Maples - the oldest daughter of Squire
                    Maples where we stayed for dinner last Sunday.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Dr. Massy was here for dinner &amp; stayed all night making a pleasant break in things. He is dabbling in lumber and has made a good deal of 
                    <del>lumber</del> money this <del>spring</del><add place="supralinear">fall</add> &amp; winter I guess - 
                </p>
                <p>
                    As this was church Sunday we put in the three <add place="supralinear">hour</add> usual <pb ref="arm03040003005" seq="05"></pb> session - Poor Evelyn
                    <del>went</del> <del>over</del><add place="supralinear">stayed</add> three hours yesterday afternoon. (Guess I&apos;m getting
                    sleepy - have made so many mistakes!) After dinner I dashed off some letters and did some reading - Then three of the little girls - who dropped in - Evelyn &amp;
                    I went <del>up</del><add place="supralinear">down</add> the road to meet the girls as they drove back - Next was supper followed by 
                    <abbr expan="Baptist Young Person&apos;s Union">B.Y.</abbr> &amp; then we sat around the fire a little while before coming upstairs. The light  went out at
                    church tonight &amp; finally the two lamps - so that we <pb ref="arm03040003006" seq="06"></pb> had to send for our two faithful Rochesters to finish things. So endeth this 
                    day!
                </p>
                <p>
                     With much love to you all as always - Ruth.
                </p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>