<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03020004000">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[Letter]  Aug. 20, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
                    <name>Young, Philip</name>
                    <name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
                    <name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
                </address>
                <date>2006</date>
                <idno type="SPCID">arm03020004000</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. 
                        For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee 
                        Libraries, Knoxville, TN</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from whi1ch the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
                <bibl>
                    <title>[Letter]  Aug. 20, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                    <date value="1919-08-20">Aug. 20, 1919</date>
                    <author>
                        <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                    </author>
                    <extent>13p</extent>
                    <note type="summary">Mrs. Helmick&apos;s visit. <abbr expan="Manual">Man</abbr> teacher Mr. Cresswell arrives -
                        Picnic for schoolgirls -</note>
                    <note type="box">3</note>
                    <note type="folder">2</note>
                    <note type="document">arm03020004000</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Local Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <list>
                        <item>Living Conditions</item>
                        <item>Singing</item>
                        <item>Education</item>
                        <item>People</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="abstract">
                <pb ref="arm03020004001" seq="01"/>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <item>Mrs. Helmick&apos;s visit.</item>
                        <item><abbr expan="Manual">Man</abbr> teacher Mr. Cresswell arrives -</item>
                        <item>Picnic for schoolgirls -</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="letter">
                <pb ref="arm03020004002" seq="02"/>
                <head>
                    <date value="1919-08-20">  Aug. 20, 1919</date>
                </head>
                <p>Dearest family - Nine p.m. Wednesday and am ready for bed but will scribble off a
                    few hasty lines to &quot;you all&quot; first. Wonder what the news in your midst is by
                    this time. Sent off two more film packs to Knoxville today for developing
                    &amp; am so anxious to see them - for have had some fine subjects! As soon
                    as they come will send them to you.</p>
                <p>My last letter left off with the <hi1 rend="underscore">sing</hi1> I think did it
                    not? Usually three musicians come who play violin guitar and banjo - one of them
                    does most of the singing &amp; everyone sits around quietly and listens in
                    the most serious way. They are all very mournful or gruesome tales but on the
                    other hand perfectly ludicrous - One of recent origin is on the death of <abbr expan="William">Wm.</abbr> McKinley - who &quot;while 
                    <pb ref="arm03020004003" seq="03"/>shaking hands one said &quot;I&apos;m shot&quot; in a quiet way &quot; They go on
                    interminably - &quot;Charming Betsy&quot; is another - &quot;Cynthy&quot; - &quot;Sourwood Mt.&quot; &quot;Boston
                    Girl&quot; - (a most bloody tale) The music sounds very much the same - &amp; has
                    a decided rhythm to which they tap time with their feet while playing - It was
                    held in Mrs. Helmick&apos;s honor you know - She is really a remarkable woman - her
                    husband is Gen. H. as I probably told you! As Emily &amp; I were off all day
                    Saturday. Sunday a.m. we scuttled around &amp; cleaned downstairs going to
                    Sunday School at 9 - There is no minister here for all the time but 
                    <abbr expan="Sunday School">S.S.</abbr> is held each week. Dr. Bishop was up for
                    the week-end so he helped things along &amp; Mrs. Helmick also - We sang
                    &amp; sang - then went to <pb ref="arm03020004004" seq="04" n="02"/> our classes.
                    As there were revival meetings up to the <hi1 rend="underscore">&quot;Forks&quot;</hi1>
                    (about 3 miles over I think) only 35 or so were present - There was a class of
                    boys - little girls &amp; then the rest of us were taken care of by Dr. B. -
                    He is a <abbr expan="Methodist Episcopal">M.E.</abbr> minister - but very
                    broadminded - the lesson was on missions - After this session - flew home
                    &amp; got out of my gray dress into dirty one &amp; continued work -
                    cleaning my room &amp; doing a little washing - &amp; by noon was
                    cleaned up once more &amp; on my way to the hotel with the rest of the crowd
                    to have dinner with Mrs. Helmick - The hotel people sit at two long tables on
                    the enclosed porch - &amp; our party occupied all of one end - After dinner
                    which con- <pb ref="arm03020004005" seq="05"/> sisted of fried chicken - potatoes corn
                    - beans - tomatoes - jelly - hot rolls - baked apples - lemon pie &amp;
                    watermelon we sat on the porch - I went over my work with Dr. B. which was a
                    great help - then the rest of them went back to the house &amp; I stayed
                    &amp; visited with Mrs. Helmick &amp; Mrs. Huff. Finally Mrs. Helmick
                    &amp; I strolled over to the little old school on the hill opposite us where
                    there is such a wonderful view of the <abbr expan="mountains">mts.</abbr>
                    &amp; talked Pi Phi. She told me a lot about the early beginnings of the
                    school - all of which she knows as she was here &amp; superintended much of
                    the building - even helped out with the teaching &amp; for five or six 
                    <abbr expan="years">yrs.</abbr> was the chief one in the committee - Now she is
                    not connected with it in any way - but takes <pb ref="arm03020004006" seq="06" n="03"/>a 
                    very keen interest in it &amp; everyone around. We stayed there until
                    the church bell rang about 9:30 for young peoples meeting - B.Y.P. it&apos;s called -
                    so went down for that. More singing with a business meeting - electing officers
                    etc. Evelyn had charge - &amp; was like pulling teeth to get anyone started.
                    Finally the new manual training teacher Mr. Cresswell (who had arrived from
                    Sevierville during the p.m.) was put in for president. It was way after nine
                    when we finally started home - Mrs. H. &amp; the new man went up to the
                    house - we had lunch &amp; talked about the school &amp; then bed time!
                    Mr. C. is a very nice young fellow - grew up around here somewhere - has a farm
                    - was in the army <pb ref="arm03020004007" seq="07"/> &amp; seems willing to do
                    &amp; start anything - He &amp; two boys are now living in the house at
                    the end of the road - a picture of which you have - They are at present having
                    their meals here as the stove for that house has not yet arrived. He (Mr. C.)
                    visited at school Monday &amp; got the shop ready - Tuesday he took over my
                    four mathematics classes &amp; spelling - so now have four English classes -
                    writing - U.S. History - geography - Latin &amp; ancient history - We begin
                    at 8 a.m. &amp; have a 15 <abbr expan="minutes">min.</abbr> assembly of
                    whole school - which we teachers take charge of a week at a time - 15 
                    <abbr expan="minutes">min.</abbr> recess at 10 a.m. - 15 recess at 2 p.m.
                    dismissing at 3 - with an <abbr expan="hour">hr.</abbr> at noon <pb ref="arm03020004008" 
                        seq="08" n="04"/>of course- Mondays &amp; Wednesdays - my
                    boys &amp; girls (24 in <abbr expan="number">no.</abbr> at present) are all
                    gone to sewing &amp; <abbr expan="manual">m.</abbr> training from 2 to 3 -
                    but I have all of Abbie&apos;s youngsters to keep in order - Today they studied hard
                    for about 25 <abbr expan="minutes">min.</abbr> &amp; then I showed them some
                    games until dismissal - Both Monday &amp; yesterday p.m. I put in writing
                    &amp; took a few pictures also - Last evening as I was going down to feed
                    the pig - yes I had a big bucket of <hi1 rend="underscore">slops</hi1> - Emma
                    Maples one of my girls arrived with her brother &amp; two youngsters in
                    their Ford - having brought us some gasoline - Emma walked down with me to the
                    pig&apos;s dwelling which is down the walk past the cornfield &amp; <pb ref="arm03020004009" 
                        seq="09"/>school house - way over at the end of our land - On
                    our way back she said they were going up to the Forks (along Fightin&apos; Creek) to
                    the other Maples family where her mother was visiting &amp; bring her back -
                    She wondered if I&apos;d like to go - Of course I said yes &amp; getting Emily
                    piled in &amp; off - We just flew up &amp; down &amp; over bumps -
                    along a winding hilly road by Fightin&apos; Creek - It gets dark so early now -
                    &amp; by the time we reached the house it was real dark - but lovely
                    &amp; starlight no wrap necessary either - The two boys in this family -
                    Rellie &amp; Ephraim are in my room - &amp; very nice - Their house is a
                    large frame farmhouse - with a big porch all around - and here <pb ref="arm03020004010" 
                        seq="10" n="05"/>were Mr. &amp; Mrs. Maples in bed - We sat down
                    &amp; visited cheerfully as though they had been up &amp; dressed in
                    chairs - Finally Mrs. Maples got up - the other (Emma&apos;s mother) was also in bed
                    &amp; arose - The boys were up &amp; Emma&apos;s married sister - We wound up
                    with a big watermelon - (am getting very fond of it - you don&apos;t know what a <hi1 
                        rend="underscore">real melon</hi1> is back there) &amp; a pressing
                    invitation to stay all night - In the front room was a bed - several big chairs
                    &amp; a table - While there must have been about a dozen enlarged family
                    portraits on the walls - They are very nice people &amp; we are going up
                    again &amp; stay. Today the excitement was a picnic of girls in Abbie&apos;s room
                    &amp; mine - Twenty seven of us in - <pb ref="arm03020004011" seq="11"/>cluding
                    Evelyn - Abbie - &amp; myself climbed up the hill beyond the school and
                    above the place in the road where I took a snap of Miss Abbott &amp; her car
                    - Here on top of the hill was a great broad shady expanse of level ground - wild
                    purple asters in blossom near by &amp; pennyroyal all over the steep sides
                    of the hill! We played &quot;ship-comes-in&quot; while cooling off - a game they didn&apos;t
                    know - also 3 deep another one new to them and then started our lunch - For our
                    share we took &quot;light bread&quot; as white raised bread is called &amp; butter -
                    also juice of blackberries &amp; lemons which made a fine cooling drink when
                    we added water - They brought tomatoes (this is certainly tomato land- they eat
                    them like apples) crackers - jelly - sausage <pb ref="arm03020004012" seq="12" n="06"/>two 
                    pies - apples - cookies. This sounds like more than it was - for we came
                    home &amp; ate as much supper as usual about 7 - an hour later! Then we ran
                    races - girls ran according to their sizes - with some left over apple quarters
                    for prizes - I ran &amp; lost my heel - also got quite dirty before getting
                    home as we climbed several fences en route. Wore that one piece heavy white
                    dress I got at McCormack&apos;s - It&apos;s so comfortable - am quite crazy about it I
                    would like to wear it all the time. We are going to organize these girls into
                    club tomorrow night something on the order of Girl Reserve&apos;ss perhaps - Anyway -
                    they meet in my room &amp; elect officers <pb ref="arm03020004013" seq="13"/>choose
                    names etc. Next week am going to have them work up a party for the boys - After
                    supper - Emily - Cora Ogle one of my girls &amp; I took a jaunt up the road
                    along Little Pigeon - &amp; since then have been scribbling away to you fast
                    as my pencil will go - must now cease my prating &amp; hie me to bed - Am
                    glad the little Dodge is not going over these awful roads - Hope all is well
                    &amp; that I hear again soon - Oh yes - we have put off our Smoky <abbr 
                        expan="Mountain">Mt.</abbr> trip another week for various reasons - Well
                    once more dear one farewell &amp; adieu with very much love - Ruth</p>
                <p>
                    <date value="1919-08-20">Aug. 20 - </date>
                </p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
