<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03020015000">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[Letter]  Oct. 05, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
                    <name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
                    <name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
                </address>
                <date>2006</date>
                <idno type="SPCID">arm03020015000</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. 
                        For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee 
                        Libraries, Knoxville, TN</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from whi1ch the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
                <bibl>
                    <title>[Letter]  Oct. 05, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                    <date value="1919-10-05">Oct. 05, 1919</date>
                    <author>
                        <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                    </author>
                    <extent>17p</extent>
                    <note type="summary">Fair at Sevierville, At the McCarters&apos; to see <hi1 rend="underscore">molasses</hi1> made - </note>
                    <note type="box">3</note>
                    <note type="folder">2</note>
                    <note type="document">arm03020015000</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Local Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <list>
                        <item>Social life</item>
                        <item>People</item>
                        <item>Schools</item>
                        <item>Fairs</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="abstract">
                <pb ref="arm03020015001" seq="01"/>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <item>Fair at Sevierville</item>
                        <item>At the McCarters&apos; to see <hi1 rend="underscore">molasses</hi1> made - </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="letter">
                <pb ref="arm03020015002" seq="02"/>
                <head>
                    <date value="1919-10-05">Oct. 5, 1919</date>
                </head>
                <!-- Page 1 missing -->
                <p><gap></gap>I did not go to <abbr expan="Baptist Young Person&apos;s Union">B.Y.P.U.</abbr> that evening but settled down to papers and history while 
                    Emily upheld the lemons at lunch - First interruption was two of the girls after lamps as the lights at church were on the blink 
                    They informed me that Litha <pb ref="arm03020015003" seq="03"/>Carr one of 
                    Abbie&apos;s girls was over at the house alone &amp; in bed sick. Well of course I went over and as Abbie had phoned up 
                    from Sevierville that she could not get back here as no one seemed to be coming this way - I brought Litha 
                    over here for the night - Her illness was just a headache as she had slipped &amp; bumped her head that <abbr expan="afternoon">p.m.</abbr> 
                    Second interruption was Aunt Lizzie&apos;s appearance (she was sound asleep upstairs supposedly) and her announcement 
                    that there were cows in the corn. That meant we had to go &amp; chase them forth. So picture me lamp in hand going along in the dark 
                    hunting cows &amp; chasing them between the rows of dried stalks over to the schoolhouse where we let down the bars &amp; 
                    so got them safely shut up - They were Huffs&apos; cows who had strolled up our land from the road &amp; belonged down at 
                    the hotel     
                </p>
                <pb ref="arm03020015004" seq="04" n="03"/>
                <p>
                    We are still having many absences at school as making molasses from sorghum is the present occupation. No one can 
                    hire help so the youngsters are kept out regardless of everything else. We make arrangements to get about ten youngsters 
                    down to the Sevierville Fair the next day - Abbie gets back about ten with the mail - The evening is spent making out report cards 
                    - next morning the two Fords arrive about seven to take nine or ten youngsters down - Mr. Cresswell puts them all in one car - 
                    Lilland Maple&apos;s (you&apos;ll hear of him later on) &amp; sends them off. Estell Huff has the other Ford &amp; takes 
                    Abbie Mr. C. - and myself back <add place="supralinear">to his</add> home &amp; after waiting around we start forth with Jim &amp; 
                    Stella Huff &amp; Betty Rose who lives with them &amp; helps with the work - a cute girl of about sixteen. We have a lovely though 
                    bumpy ride to town &amp; go right to the courthouse. Although it&apos;s only 8:30 there are loads of people gathered together in 
                    the yard and in the <pb ref="arm03020015005" seq="05"/>rooms where were the exhibits. We had passed all sorts of conveyances 
                    on the way in too - You see the Fair was only Monday &amp; Tuesday and this is the second year one has been held - so people 
                    are beginning to wake up to it. Twelve little places had sent exhibits. Gatlinburg&apos;s ranked eight in the list - but our school 
                    exhibit which was apart from the other stood first among the four that had been sent in - We are the only ones that have manual 
                    training &amp; domestic science among the schools in the county I believe. The communities send in displays very much alike - 
                    cornstalks &amp; sugar cane - vegetables apples principally for the first &amp; quantities of canned stuff - all kinds of seeds too. 
                    Saw a pumpkin weighing 133<num type="fraction" value="one fourth">1/4</num> <!-- I have no idea if this is the correct way to insert fractions -->
                    <abbr expan="pounds">lbs.</abbr> - <add place="supralinear">ears of</add> corn 14 <abbr expan="inches">in.</abbr> long - peanuts 
                    attached to their plant - cotton ditto also peppers - (tiny red ones) ditto - and what <pb ref="arm03020015006" seq="06" n="04"/>else do you 
                    suppose? a room <hi1 rend="underscore">full</hi1> of stills taken in the mountains - over twenty of them. You know the still itself was 
                    the one thing lacking on our <hi1 rend="underscore">hunt</hi1> It is a huge copper vessel in which the ingredients are boiled &amp; 
                    from which pipes carry off the steam which condensed is the moonshine. At least that&apos;s the way I understand it to be. I took 
                    two pictu<add place="supralinear">r</add>es of them and hope they are successful. The fancy work was in a room by itself with a few 
                    art attempts - Don't believe painting is as frequently tried here as at home. Miss Sharp the domestic science teacher at Murphy College 
                    had exhibited a big cloth of solid talling (quite fine) except for six small pieces of linen 
                    set is - Think these pieces were for the plates. She <del>was</del><add place="supralinear">is</add> going to send it to 
                    Boston where someone lives who has bought it for &#36;500! I did not like it - not at all artistic in my eyes! One large room was 
                    set aside for the colored people who had their things quite by themselves - very 
                    <pb ref="arm03020015007" seq="07"/> nice they were too. After beholding everything even to the livestock outside in the yard - chickens - 
                    hogs - mules - cows - oxen - horses - Evelyn and I went &quot;down town&quot; (across the street) where I deposited my &#36;60 
                    check - just arrived - for my first month&apos;s teaching in the Sevierville bank &amp; got a little check book - Then we roamed around 
                    in some of the stores - bought ice cream cones - and went up to Murphy College dormitory &amp; had lunch. This sounds as though 
                    the chaperonage rested lightly on our shoulders - as it did. Evelyn seeming to think it perfectly <sic corr="alright">allright</sic> to let 
                    the youngsters look after themselves. Abbie found her sister &amp; her friends - Mr. C. his mother brothers &amp; friends so all 
                    were happy - After lunch we went over to the Massey&apos;s where I lay in the porch swing &amp; read while Evelyn hustled Mrs. 
                    Massey around for the &quot;riding&quot; was to be at one - About one thirty or more we got to the <pb ref="arm03020015008" seq="08" n="05"/>
                    street roped off for that purpose &amp; joined the throngs lined up either side - Finding Abbie seated on the doorsteps of the <add place="supralinear">home of the</add> 
                    Sevierville weekly paper - &quot;The Vindicator.&quot; It was awfully hot but I was correctly garbed in my gray  winter hat &amp; suit. 
                    We waited &amp; waited. Finally many mules - about twenty were lead forth kicking &amp; prancing in mulish fashion &amp; after a 
                    vain attempt was made to line them up ribbons were awarded. Then three beautiful horses ridden by three women cantered and walked 
                    up &amp; down many times - ribbons were awarded. These were followed by men on horseback twenty or more. They rode &amp; rode 
                    &amp; rode - all sorts &amp; kinds were they - fat old doctor - farmer boys - squire - Methodist minister &amp; most comical <del>liet</del> 
                    lieutenant in uniform. The minister was especially funny took him some time to get warmed up but he <pb ref="arm03020015009" seq="09"/>did 
                    eventually clinging to his straw hat &amp; surging on his valiant steed which at first he had restrained with a firm hand muttering 
                    &quot;Easy now! easy now!&quot; We finally left and went back to the courthouse where the crowd seemed thick as ever. There was 
                    no selling of anything not even chances on a kewpie. The Epworth league had a booth outside of pie cake lemonade etc. but that was 
                    absolutely all. Finally we started packing up our stuff and by five were headed for home a weary crowd - was so glad to get to bed that 
                    night. Emily &amp; Aunt Lizzie had had a quiet peaceful day here by themselves - presented them each with a big stick of peppermint 
                    candy - stupid! Next day after school write letters and spend all evening to <hi1 rend="underscore">midnight</hi1> scribbling to my Pi Phi     
                    sisters in Tacoma as Saturday is their meeting again. Don't know whether they want a letter <hi1 rend="underscore">every</hi1> time or 
                    not but <pb ref="arm03020015010" seq="10" n="06"/>as I said I&apos;d send them one each month will try to do so. Certainly have no lack 
                    of material for writing - too much rather! Thursday morning Evelyn gets back &amp; after school that night we all pile into the hack &amp; 
                    set forth for McCarter&apos;s - Mr. C. at the reins. They were making molasses and had sent special word for us all to come that day 
                    after school. We like them so much - Tom and Cora are in the high school class - Polly is in the 8A (she uses snuff!) Birthana 
                    (awful name) is in the 8B. They had been out all week helping boil sorghum. The three miles to their house made a pleasant ride 
                    &amp; as it was a lovely evening we enjoyed it - in spite of the prospect of the hack&apos;s falling to pieces at every bump - The family 
                    were all in a field by the house working away - a big oven had been built of stones - chinks filled in with clay and chimney at one end. 
                    On it were three vats in which <pb ref="arm03020015011" seq="11"/> the molasses <hi1 rend="underscore">were</hi1> <hi1 rend="underscore">boiling</hi1>. 
                    Molasses is always <hi1 rend="underscore">they</hi1> never it for people here think of it in the plural only - You must ask them not &quot;How much did you make?&quot; 
                    but &quot;How many!&quot; All around on the <unclear reason="illegible" resp="tl">grain</unclear> lay the squeezed cornstalks while 
                    nearby were the rollers &amp; big kettle for the squeezing - with long pole to turn and to which horse was fastened.  In the distance 
                    were stalk stacks of <del>corn</del> <add place="supralinear">cane</add> cut &amp; ready for the next day&apos;s boiling. 
                    We took pieces of the cane &amp; sticking them into the big tins of fresh molasses licked them off. I did not care much for &quot;them&quot; 
                    nor for the cane - a little piece of which I chewed - it&apos;s insipid &amp; sweet. We stirred some which is hard work as ladles are heavy 
                    &amp; one has to dip to keep it from boiling over. Great fun though &amp; we stayed as long as we could getting back just at <del>dark</del> 
                    dark. Right <pb ref="arm03020015012" seq="12" n="07"/> at our lane we met a car which we waited to let pass but it also stopped and a voice 
                    called out. &quot;Anyone want to go to Pigeon Forge?&quot; I thought it Mr. Huff and asked Abbie if she didn&apos;t want to go - We 
                    were both messes and also very hungry but piled into the other vehicle &amp; disappeared in five minutes. Wasn&apos;t that crazy? - 
                    and it wasn&apos;t Mr. Huff but Lillard Maples &amp; Loy Reagan two of the boys around here who should be in school or away 
                    at school. It was a lovely night though and Lillard is a great driver so we just zipped along - The reason for going to Pigeon Forge - 
                    seven miles down the river you know and half way to Sevierville - was because of <hi1 rend="underscore">Association</hi1>. This is
                    like a conference - all the Baptists &amp; their ministers meet annually &amp; preach &amp; have business meetings for 
                    several days - all day. <pb ref="arm03020015013" seq="13"/>So important is it that the school at <abbr expan="Pigeon Forge">P. F.</abbr> 
                    was closed and some of our youngsters stayed out most of the week for it. When we arrived we <add place="supralinear">girls</add> 
                    decided not to go in to the church as we were such sights &amp; the seats seemed all full anyway. The two boys roamed off and 
                    some of Abbie&apos;s friends came up - We stayed in the car until it was over about 9:30 and then started home about eight altogether. 
                    They dropped off until we were down to our original number two miles toward home. Then we stopped and all got into a big Ford truck 
                    after getting a man out of bed &amp; fussing to get the engine started. The reason 
                    for this change was that as Lillard had to do hauling in the <abbr expan="morning">a.m.</abbr> he thought he might as well take 
                    the truck up then as make a special trip for it. It was really awfully jolty. <pb ref="arm03020015014" seq="14" n="08"/> We girls were on the 
                    front seat too but even there comfort was quite lacking. Quite an evening wasn&apos;t it with only a pear for nourishment. It was 
                    eleven when we finally arrived after a slow noisy &amp; laborious journey of five miles. Heaven knows what I&apos;ll do next! Found 
                    cold scalloped tuna fish rolls - blackberry jam &amp; beans for the appeasing of my appetite. Tuna was fixed by my fair hand a la 
                    Jane! Friday about noon the worst rainstorm descended &amp; we got soppng wet going home even under an umbrella - Abbie 
                    &amp; Mr. C. both went home that <abbr expan="afternoon">p. m.</abbr> &amp; we girls here took a little walk after school - had 
                    supper &amp; sat around in the living room in the light of the Rochester. Evelyn gave Emily a music lesson 
                    - knitted - I read in the <pb ref="arm03020015015" seq="15"/>monitor and went to 
                    bed rather early - about 8:30. Have not read all the back numbers of my papers etc. yet. The evenings are going to seem delightfully 
                    long when winter sets in and hope to get lots done - Saturday we all worked so hard all morning - I made some of our cooked 
                    dressing - washed - sorted out my winter garments from my trunk &amp; hung them up in the closet to get out the wrinkles - did 
                    some ironing - washed some of the mirrors round about - cleaned out the washstands - changed <add place="supralinear">my bed &amp; turned</add> my mattress - so you know I had on one of my <hi1 rend="underscore">thorough</hi1> cleaning spells. By four o&apos;clock 
                    I was in a clean dress and ready to make a call on the Huff&apos;s. Eventually stayed for dinner and as there was a &quot;sing&quot; 
                    at the schoolhouse that evening we went over there. <pb ref="arm03020015016" seq="16" n="09"/>Only one of the musicians 
                    arrived however - but he and his daughter Jillian - one of my 7th grade girls sang &amp; sang those tragic old ballads! 
                    Evelyn also sang &amp; played &amp; then everyone sang - winding up with Star Spangled Banner after which the 
                    party broke up and we were all soon in bed. This is the minister&apos;s weekend but <add place="supralinear">as</add> 
                    none of us went to church yesterday we all went to Sunday School - I didn&apos;t stay for church as I knew 
                    <abbr expan="Baptist Young Person&apos;s Union">B.Y.P.U.</abbr> awaited in the evening &amp; chose the lesser 
                    of two evils. Shortly after dinner about 12:30 (fried chicken again) Abbie arrived coming in a friend&apos;s car. He is 
                    a man who has lived three years in New Orleans so Emily &amp; I were quite interested to meet him. He thinks it 
                    a great city and a trip <pb ref="arm03020015017" seq="17"/>well worth taking. After he left I wrote to pa then 
                    <abbr expan="Baptist Young Person&apos;s Union">B.Y.P.</abbr> next. The lights would not work at the church so we 
                    came up to the school house - Evelyn &amp; I getting the lamps &amp; keys - Then we spent most of the evening 
                    singing as some new song books had arrived. The room was full of young people mostly. Now it&apos;s bedtime 
                    and I must cease &amp; take to the covers. <gap reason="author edit" hand="rs" extent="8 lines" resp="tl"></gap>
                </p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
