<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03030011000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[Letter]  Nov. 2, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
				<author>
					<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
				</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
					<name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
					<name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
				<address>
					<addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
				</address>
				<date>2006</date>
				<idno type="SPCID">arm03030011000</idno>
				<availability>
					<p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from which the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
				<bibl>
					<title>[Letter]  Nov. 2, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
					<date value="1919-11-02">Nov. 2, 1919</date>
					<author>
						<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
					</author>
					<extent>10p</extent>
					<note type="summary">Halloween affair at school for community - Visit to Round Top - Miss Langmaid (Chairman of the Settlement
                    School Committee) arrives for visit</note>
					<note type="box">3</note>
					<note type="folder">3</note>
					<note type="document">arm03030011000</note>
				</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
			</projectDesc>
		<editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<bibl>
						<title>Local Subject Headings</title>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<list>
						<item>Living Conditions</item>
						<item>Community programs</item>
						<item>Extracurricular activities</item>
						<item>Holidays</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div1 type="abstract">
				<pb ref="arm03030011001" seq="01"/>
				<p>
					<list>
						<item>Halloween affair at school for community</item>
						<item>Visit to Round Top</item>
						<item>Miss Langmaid (Chairman of the Settlement School Committee) arrives for visit</item>
					</list>
				</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="letter">
				<pb ref="arm03030011002" seq="02"/>
				<head>
					<date value="1919-11-02">Nov. 2, 1919</date>
									</head>
				<p>
                    Dearest Jane - Sunday night again &amp; 8:30 by our time but the correct time is 45 <abbr expan="minutes">min.</abbr> slower for we go 
                    by the sun up here. In fact not much attention is paid to the calendar Evelyn says - Thanksgiving &amp; Christmas receive no recognition 
                    except through the school.
                </p>
				<p>
					<del>You have been awfully good about writing so often and I much appreciate the letters and the pictures with 
                        Halloween tokens. Thank you kindly!</del>
				</p>
				<p>
					<del>The house must look very nice with all the fresh paint without &amp; within.</del>
				</p>
				<p>
                    My last was written <del>We</del> Tuesday night wasn&apos;t it? After school Wednesday Emily &amp; I went up to the 
                    Connor&apos;s on Baskin Creek where I took the kodaks some time ago of the molasses making. They were finishing the last of them and were 
                    more than pleased with the pictures. <pb ref="arm03030011003" seq="03"/>Will get more printed &amp; send you some. I seem pretty slow about 
                    getting things send - guess I&apos;m getting like the rest of the natives!
                </p>
				<p>
                    Right after supper (we have dinner at noon) had to see about the debate - Mr. Reagan on my side &amp; Tom McC. on the other didn&apos;t 
                    come so it was between Mr. Cresswell &amp; Rose - Emma &amp; myself. They won for which I was glad - though we put up a good fight. 
                    The general sentiment is in favor of the highway rather than a railroad anyway. When I got back here wrote pa -
                </p>
				<p>
                    Thursday noon Miss Eva Freeman arrived from Alabama where she has been helping a friend who teaches in a school somewhere down there. 
                    She is from Iowa &amp; from the same chapter as Brennie whom she knows - also knew Mr. Grimbling &amp; has met Mrs. G. is <pb ref="arm03030011004" seq="04"/>
                    acquainted with Sadie. She is very pleasant and nice &amp; seems to have travelled all over the <abbr expan="United States">U.S.</abbr> &amp; in 
                    Europe - but you&apos;d never guess it judging by appearances. Celebrated the evening by planning more details in regard to the Halloween party 
                    &amp; writing a letter to the Tacoma Pi Phis. Am enclosing a letter sent me by Mrs. Helmick - really copy of a letter written by a girl who as you see was a 
                    real pioneer in Gatlinburg for the school. Will you give it to them for the meeting Saturday or else next month - and ask them to return it to you.
                </p>
				<p>
                    Most of Friday was spent in preparation for the Halloween function. The cooking classes made doughnuts that <abbr expan="afternoon">p.m.</abbr> 
                    &amp; the previous day - The youngsters got quantities of autumn leaves of gorgeous coloring. We filled the baskets &amp; waste baskets - put them 
                    in the fireplace &amp; behind the radiators - pasted our paper jack-o-lanterns in a border at top of blackboards - with witches cats moons etc. on the 
                    windows - &amp; opened the two rooms Abbie&apos;s &amp; mine into one.
                </p>
				<p>
                    The schoolhouse was full of company before we had finished our supper so that by 6:30 we were all over with lamps &amp; calming the 
                    youngsters by our mere presence. Outside were many boys &amp; young fellows from places miles away - Inside the seats were full &amp; 
                    overflowing (in the big room) with the older people - The girls hustled into their sheets &amp; pillowcases in the sewing room &amp; 
                    after much confusion as each wanted to be pinned <pb ref="arm03030011005" seq="05" n="02"/>immediately &amp; there were only 4 of us 
                    to do about twenty. Then the jack-o-lanterns were lighted &amp; brooms found for some of us there were not quite enough pumpkins to go around. 
                    Arlena also in sheet &amp; pillowcase played the piano for the witch song &amp; they all filed in one by one - marching round &amp; round singing. 
                    It was quite effective as the other<del>s</del> lights were darkened. Then Rose Carr &amp; Estel Huff were leaders for the next 
                    event the track meet - Had 15 youngsters on a side &amp; the leaders chose the ones they wanted to do the various stunts. All the others looked 
                    on - First was the suitcase race - cracker eating &amp; potato races - etc. I found most of them in &quot;Ice - Breakers&quot;. They all seemed 
                    to enjoy it. Next was apple bobbing and stringing apples &amp; doughnuts! Lastly the fortune <pb ref="arm03030011006" seq="06"/>telling. Emma 
                    &amp; Rose told them in the boys cloak room - dressed in sheets &amp; pillowcases - two big jack-o-lanterns for light. In the other Josie Trentham 
                    from the hotel did the same. She was just like a witch - Had on a good mask - pillow case - kimono apron &amp; lots of jewelry. The crowd really 
                    behaved pretty well - couple of jack-o-lanters &amp; boughs were strung up the flagpole &amp; that&apos;s all. Well along toward 8:30 the doughnuts were 
                    passed to the children &amp; what were left to the older ones. By nine we looked up the school - house &amp; came home with our lamps - 
                    tired &amp; pleased to have it over.
                </p>
				<p>
                    The next morning by 8:15 Mrs Freeman Mr. <abbr expan="Cresswell">C.</abbr> Emily &amp; I were started for Round Top - the mountain we
                    have so long <pb ref="arm03030011007" seq="07"/> wanted to climb. My two big paper sacks &amp; kodak constituted our luggage - We had the 
                    frying pan pail for coffee - eggs - bread - biscuits doughnuts &amp; oh yes - cold sweet potatoes <add place="supralinear">&amp; glass of jelly</add>.
                    The weather was uncertain like - Aunt Lizzie &amp; Mrs. <sic corr="Proffitt">Proffit</sic> both predicting rain &amp; that we&apos;d never make 
                    the trip in a day. We went up the Roaring Fork road about five miles where we stopped at the Reagan&apos;s cabin. Here was Charlie
                    <unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">Clabo</unclear> the soldier lad we met some time ago who wanted us to be sure to stop &amp; have him
                    go along when we took the climb. Well they all predicted rain &amp; Charlie didn&apos;t enthuse about going. Just as we started off however
                    he decided to join us - also two of the Reagan children came to the same conclusion - Alfred about 14 &amp; Julia 16 - she is coming to school
                    later &amp; stay at <hi1 rend="underscore">Abbie&apos;s</hi1> (our dormitory)
                </p>
				<p>
                    The boys got a lot of apples in a deserted orchard &amp; found some wild grapes. At the foot of the <abbr expan="mountain">mt.</abbr> we 
                    stopped &amp; started lunch - frying apples - eggs - &amp; the potatoes &amp; making coffee - Then at this <del>crt</del>
                    critical point it begain raining - We seized everything &amp; climbed up a little ways to where <add place="supralinear">was</add> a huge rock
                    nicely hollowed out in a long crevice making a perfect shelter for our party of seven. Here we sat &amp; ate &amp; ate in absolute comfort &amp;
                    dryness. Seems strange that a lunch planned for 4 should so completely satisfy nearly twice that number. But it did. The rain had practically 
                    ceased by one when we started for the climb which Charlie said would take an hour. Such a climb I&apos;ve never made! Smoky
                    <abbr expan="Mountains">Mts.</abbr>
					<pb ref="arm03030011008" seq="08" n="3"/>were nothing to it. We did not follow the trail as that was too
                    long but went right up the - pulling ourselves along by the little bushes &amp; pines. The mountain has been burned over by forest fire several times
                    &amp; logged so at present the trees are not very large &amp; there is much undergrowth - mountain laurel - (ivy they call it) especially. The view
                    going up was lovely - At one point we could see the <abbr expan="Gatlinburg">bu<add place="supralinear">r</add>g</abbr> way off - seven miles away - 
                    Seven miles doesn&apos;t sound like much does it - but the rough stony road we had followed made walking slow &amp; hard - Before we got to the 
                    top it began sprinkling so we were dampish on our arrival. It was a very satisfactory peak <pb ref="arm03030011009" seq="09"/> to climb - For one 
                    really felt <del>they were</del>
					<add place="supralinear">he was</add> on a peak - the land dropped away so steeply in every direction
                    &amp; the extent of the peak being rather small - not as large as our dining room. We stopped about 15 <abbr expan="minutes">min.</abbr> &amp;
                    then began the descent. The storm which we had seen way off down the valley &amp; on distant hills now enveloped us &amp; we simply dripped
                    moisture - Had on my tramping outfit - no hat or coat - nor did I need them - For it was a warm day &amp; the walking kept one comfortable even 
                    though soaked to the skin. None of us minded  it - Miss Freeman is a good sport &amp; liked everything! Well it was dark when we got home - 
                    and though am a little stiff in my knees &amp; hips am very glad I went &amp; thoroughly enjoyed it. <pb ref="arm03030011010" seq="10"/>
				</p>
				<p>
                    This morning we didn&apos;t get to breakfast until quite late for us - 8 o&apos;clock - By 9:30 we were all at Sunday School &amp; 
                    <unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">as</unclear> it was church Sunday - we were there for <hi1 rend="underscore">three</hi1> hours.
                </p>
				<p>
                    When I got home had to get busy doing my Saturday work which was interrupted by dinner - But in the course of time got my shoes cleaned - 
                    washing sorted - room swept &amp; dusted - summer hats put away - bathroom &amp; upper hall cleaned - bulbs planted.
                </p>
				<p>
                    Next Abbie - Miss Freeman &amp; I went to make call on Aunt Lydia who unfortunately was also calling - We asked about her at several places - 
                    but she had just left each &amp; none knew where she might be - so we examined her mill gazed at the little cabin &amp; then called at
                    Mrs. Reagan&apos;s (Lucrettie&apos;s mother &amp; the chaperone on our Smoky trip) We had a nice call - sitting in front of the fireplace
                    &amp; eating chestnuts. (The weather had cleared &amp; turned cold this <abbr expan="morning">a.m.</abbr> so wore my old challie &amp; 
got out my big coat for church but green coat warm enough for <del>a</del><abbr expan="evening">p.m.)</abbr> We got home
                    at dusk just as Harrison arrived in a buggy with Miss Langmaid from Pigeon Forge. She is rather pretty - short &amp; stout - very sweet - We
                    had supper &amp; wound up with <abbr expan="Baptist Young Person&apos;s Union">B.Y.</abbr> - &amp; so ends this day - As it&apos;s
                    now getting late will bid you a loving good night with much of love for the whole family as ever. Hoping to find another letter tomorrow from you - 
                </p>
				<p>
                    Ruth
                </p>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
