<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03030018000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[Letter]  Nov. 18, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
				<author>
					<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
				</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
					<name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
					<name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
				<address>
					<addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
				</address>
				<date>2006</date>
				<idno type="SPCID">arm03030018000</idno>
				<availability>
					<p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from which the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
				<bibl>
					<title>[Letter]  Nov. 18, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
					<date value="1919-11-18">Nov. 18, 1919</date>
					<author>
						<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
					</author>
					<extent>4p</extent>
					<note type="summary">Armistice Day - Call on the Prickets, former teachers at our school - Debates - Plans for factory set up by the school
                    made by Miss Langmaid</note>
					<note type="box">3</note>
					<note type="folder">3</note>
					<note type="document">arm03030018000</note>
				</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
			</projectDesc>
		<editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<bibl>
						<title>Local Subject Headings</title>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<list>
						<item>Living conditions</item>
						<item>War</item>
						<item>People</item>
						<item>Social life</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div1 type="abstract">
				<pb ref="arm03030018001" seq="01"/>
				<p>
					<list>
						<item>Armistice Day</item>
						<item>Call on the Prickets, former teachers at our school</item>
						<item>Debates</item>
						<item>Plans for factory set up by the school made by Miss Langmaid</item>
					</list>
				</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="letter">
				<pb ref="arm03030018002" seq="02"/>
				<head>
					<date value="1919-11-18">Nov. 18, 1919</date>
					</head>
				<p>
					<del>Dearest Pa - Your letter came this noon (Tuesday) and suppose by the time this reaches you - 
                            Los Angeles will be entertaining you - As to your plans for going into business I do not know what to think - don&apos;t 
                            believe I&apos;d hurry about it too much for you have not had a real vacation for such a long time! It&apos;s nice you can 
                            fix their yard and that so many auto rides are coming your way -</del>
				</p>
				<p>
                    We celebrated Armistice Day with just a little program of patriotic songs and dismissal of half an hour earlier than usual.
                </p>
				<p>
                    Since last writing you have done practically nothing but school work it seems like. The weather is beautiful &amp; bright but cold 
                    &amp; frosty - so much so that our <pb ref="arm03030018003" seq="03"/>milk for breakfast is usually frozen. Have shed my thin dresses 
                    except for house wear as our furnace keeps us exceedingly warm.
                </p>
				<p>
                    Friday night was the debate and very interesting it was - the youngsters got quite warmed up over it &amp; one of the boys kept us 
                    convulsed all the time he had the floor - Another one comes off this Friday about capital punishment.
                </p>
				<p>
                    Saturday I worked around the house all day &amp; then Emily &amp; I went over to Huff&apos;s for dinner &amp; the night. We had 
                    a very nice time. They live in a <hi1 rend="underscore">real</hi1> house - two stories - the front room (where we slept) has piano - bed 
                    bureau etc. - all the rooms have beds in these houses -
                </p>
				<p>
                    Well Sunday after the morning <pb ref="arm03030018004" seq="04"/>session was over we got Lillard Maples to take us in his Ford into 
                    the Sugar Lands - about six miles away - where we called on the Prickett&apos;s who used to teach here last year &amp; before. 
                    They live in a two room cabin and as they have two small youngsters seem rather crowded - We had a nice dinner consisting of the 
                    usual fried chicken hot biscuits &amp; sweet potatoes.
                </p>
				<p>
                    Then the next excitement was <abbr expan="Baptist Young Person&apos;s Union">B.Y.</abbr> for which we got home just in time. 
                    Yesterday was club meeting with my girls who took most of the time learning a song for Thanksgiving - Spent the evening helping two 
                    of the youngsters with Latin &amp; today the play has taken all the extra time. There are a number of things to get ready - have been 
                    fixing some Puritan caps for the girls - suppose eventually everything will be done. We stay here for Thanksgiving &amp; if it&apos;s 
                    nice will probably plan a hike somewhere.
                </p>
				<p>
                    Two men were up from Sevierville to discuss the proposed dam &amp; site for factory which  the school wants to put in. The dam alone 
                    would cost 5000 - Miss Langmaid doesn&apos;t know how soon the money can be raised - it&apos;s more than was first planned.
                </p>
				<p>
                    This is a stupid letter but must stop &amp; send it anyway for it&apos;s bedtime &amp; I&apos;ve been up late the past week.
                </p>
				<p>
                    Give my love to the <unclear reason="illegible" resp="tal">Witten&apos;</unclear> &amp; with much for yourself -
                </p>
				<p>
                    Ruth.
                </p>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
