<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03040008000">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[Letter]  Feb. 22, 1920, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
                    <name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
                    <name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
                </address>
                <date>2006</date>
                <idno type="SPCID">arm03040008000</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. 
                        For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee 
                        Libraries, Knoxville, TN</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from which the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
                <bibl>
                    <title>[Letter]  Feb. 22, 1920, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                    <date value="1920-02-22">Feb. 22, 1920</date>
                    <author>
                        <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                    </author>
                    <extent>7p</extent>
                    <note type="summary">Sending a telegram from Gatlinburg</note>
                    <note type="box">3</note>
                    <note type="folder">4</note>
                    <note type="document">arm03040008000</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Local Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <list>
                        <item>Living Conditions</item>
                        <item>Efficiency</item>
                        <item>People</item>
                        <item>Social life</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="abstract">
                <pb ref="arm03040008001" seq="01"/>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <item>Sending a telegram from Gatlinburg</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="letter">
                <pb ref="arm03040008002" seq="02"/>
                <head>
                    <date value="1920-02-22">Feb. 22, 1920</date>
                </head>    
                <p>
                    <del>
                    Dearest family: It does seem as though your letter Sunday is put off till the last thing &amp; then rushed through and I&apos;m so ashamed of it - 
                    too far you know you all are the dearest &amp; best! Wonder what you have been doing  today and what I&apos;ll hear from you tomorrow. Five more weeks
                    <gap reason="illegible" resp="bds"></gap> than decide <gap reason="illegible" resp="bds"></gap> discovery <gap reason="illegible" resp="bds"></gap> not
                    But all the time underneath has been the felling that <gap reason="illegible" resp="bds"></gap> <unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">another</unclear>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="bds"></gap> for <gap reason="illegible" resp="bds"></gap> things this year and next year</del> <pb ref="arm03040008003" seq="03"></pb> can try to finish them. What do you think? 
                </p>
                <p>
                    Since starting this about 9:30 <abbr expan="afternoon">p.m.</abbr> Dr. Massy <del>cam</del> has come in from a trip up 
                    <abbr expan="Baskin&apos;s Creek">Baskin&apos;s</abbr> - tired &amp; muddy. Evelyn &amp; the others had gone upstairs so I got the soup on the coals
                    in the fireplace until <abbr expan="Evelyn">E.</abbr> came down &amp; she fixed him some of Aunt Lizzie&apos;s <hi1 rend="underscore">toddy</hi1>!
                </p>
                <p>
                    When we got back from <abbr expan="Baptist Young Person&apos;s Union">B.Y.</abbr> tonight Evelyn had returned driving up with the doctor. The roads are
                    perfect awful as I&apos;ve written so many times before but in places it is so deep it&apos;s nearly to the bed of a wagon - You know part of the time it
                    freezes - then it thaws out &amp; rains &amp; lumbering is very profitable so that hauling heavy loads of lumber has been continued fast &amp; furiously
                    <pb ref="arm03040008004" seq="04"></pb> all winter. Well in some places the mud is so thick &amp; deep that the doctor had to get out before the horse could get
                    through pulling only Evelyn in the light buggy.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Yesterday was rainy as usual &amp; I gave my room and things in it an unusually <del>hea</del> thorough cleaning and glad I am it&apos;s
                    done for who do you suppose may be here this next for a little visit? Blanche <unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">Bollinger</unclear> of all people. A letter
                    came from her yesterday written from Texas - she is on her way to New York having been traveling with her father &amp; mother since Christmas - They have
                    gone back &amp;  while she was in Arkansas saw my article in the Arrow &amp; it occured to her that she could stop &amp; visit en route.
                </p>
                <p>
                    She expected to be in New Orleans today &amp; hoped to find a letter from me telling her the way to Gatlinburg - which she said she could not find on the map.
                    I thought the matter over and decided to send a night letter which would reach her in time. She evidently has no idea of distance or the slowness of the mails - 
                    her letter was written last Monday &amp; reached me about 1 p.m. Saturday. The Huffs &amp; we are the only ones who have phones
                    &amp; we have to help each other ring for Central. It&apos;s the regular country phone with a handle at the side to ring you know. Our Central is 
                    <pb ref="arm03040008005" seq="05"></pb> <del>is</del><add place="supralinear">at</add> Pigeon Forge. Well we finally roused him - the regular Central
                    is sick &amp; after I made him understand that I wanted to send a telegram he immediately began to be very hard of hearing &amp; insisted on my being
                    connected with Sevierville whom I could not hear at all. Finally after much turning of the handle I got Pigeon Forge again &amp; begged him to try to hear
                    me But no - &quot;I have six cases of the flu here &amp; they make such a fuss I can&apos;t hear you -&quot; He was immovable &amp; there it was - then we
                    heard of a man through Charlie at the store - who was going down to Pigeon Forge - <pb ref="arm03040008006" seq="06"></pb> &amp; who would take it. So I wrote it 
                    out neatly &amp; thought that matter was settled. Next thing when I got home from Sunday School this morning Aunt Lizzie said Mrs. Huff had heard about my 
                    telegram which was not sent yet! So calling up Pigeon Forge I discovered that it was not sent because no street <del>number</del> had been
                    given for the hotel which Blanche had <del>said</del><add place="supralinear">named</add>. It&apos;s one of the biggest &amp; best known there &amp;
                    perfectly ridiculous to ask the street - Anyway I said Canal Street &amp; they seemed contented so here&apos;s hoping Blanche gets it today &amp; comes!
                    <pb ref="arm03040008007" seq="07"></pb> Then Friday I had a letter from Marion Bowers - Do you remeber that she was one of the Spokane freshmen when I was a Senior?
                    She is now in Minneapolis &amp; saw my Arrow article &amp; so wrote &amp; also enclosed ten dollars for the school - which I can use in anyway I wish! Friday is 
                    the debate - League of Nations - &amp; spent a lot of time yesterday getting material for it &amp; looking over my papers &amp; magazines - also read a while to
                    Aunt Lizzie from &quot;Little Lord Fauntleroy.&quot; Then this <abbr expan="afternoon">p.m.</abbr> Tom came over for quite a spell - he is on the debate &amp;
                    wants material etc. He takes a good deal of time but is worth it &amp; so glad to learn things &amp; so anxious to be like people outside - am trying to 
                    persuade him to go away to school next year - it would be just the thing for him. After he left Abbie &amp; I went up to the Oakley&apos;s who live on Mill 
                    Creek you know - Mrs. <abbr expan="Oakley">O.</abbr> has been sick again. Such a pitiful place! and nothing to <add place="supralinear">be</add> done for them
                    really.
                </p>
                <p><del>
                        Well it&apos;s late - due to the interruptions &amp; I don&apos;t know how intelligent all this scribble sounds. I sent off Marie&apos;s letter that very night
                        to Aunt Carrie as I imagine I told you.</del>
                    </p>
                <p><del>
                        Goodnight with loads of love</del>
                    </p>
                <p><del>
                        Ruth.</del>
                    </p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>