<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03020013000">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[Letter]  Sept. 28, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
                    <name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
                    <name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
                </address>
                <date>2006</date>
                <idno type="SPCID">arm03020013000</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. 
                        For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee 
                        Libraries, Knoxville, TN</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from whi1ch the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
                <bibl>
                    <title>[Letter]  Sept. 28, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                    <date value="1919-09-28">Sept. 28, 1919</date>
                    <author>
                        <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                    </author>
                    <extent>23p</extent>
                    <note type="summary">The Sunday School arrangement of exhibits in school for the fair. The fair diagram of schoolhouse. Visit to two other schools. Trip up Baskins Creek.</note>
                    <note type="box">3</note>
                    <note type="folder">2</note>
                    <note type="document">arm03020013000</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Local Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <list>
                        <item>Living Conditions</item>
                        <item>School buildings</item>
                        <item>Fairs</item>
                        <item>Mountains</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="abstract">
                <pb ref="arm03020013001" seq="01"/>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <item>The Sunday School arrangement of exhibits in school for the fair.</item>
                        <item>The fair diagram of schoolhouse.</item>
                        <item>Visit to two other schools.</item>
                        <item>Trip up Baskins Creek.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="letter">
                <pb ref="arm03020013002" seq="02"/>
                <head>
                    <date value="1919-09-28"> Sept. 28, 1919</date>
                </head>
                <p>
                    Dearest family - Am going to get busy and write you the very first thing this Sunday. It is just noon by Gatlingburg time but 
                    you know we are a good half hour slower than the real time as the people here go by the sun and later on we will be a half 
                    hour ahead of everyone else. We have just finished dinner - Mrs. Bishop - Emily - Evelyn &amp; I with - Aunt Lizzie too of course 
                    and are now scattered to various occupations. Sunday School began about nine and lasted nearly two hours as there was 
                    business connected with it in regard <abbr expan="with">w</abbr> the teachers &amp; officers. They are so slow &amp; deliberate - 
                    none of the youngsters will take part in things. I was in Evelyn&apos;s class for a change this morning - Mrs. Bishop took a class of 
                    grown ups - there is a class of men under our <pb ref="arm03020013003" seq="03"/>&quot;chorister&quot; and superintendent Mr. 
                    Lawson Reagan - and Evelyn&apos;s class of older girls - another of big boys - a class of girls &amp; boys from 8 to 14 &amp; another 
                    of little tots. Think our attendance averages about 50. More turn out for B.Y.P.U. Sunday evenings. Wish I could give you a pen picture 
                    of it all - Most of us sit in the choir seats before and after the lesson &amp; <hi1 rend="underscore">sing</hi1> &amp; <hi1 rend="underscore">sing</hi1> 
                    &amp; <hi1 rend="underscore">sing</hi1>! Am developing considerable lung power &amp; guess my vocal lessons were not amiss 
                    after all. During dinner today we got to talking about our New Orleans trip - Told you that Emily was going with me Christmas &amp; 
                    Mrs. Bishop told Evelyn she aught to go too &amp; put off her northern trip till later. And Evelyn is persuaded &amp; we are going to 
                    let the Pi Phis along the way know about our coming to let them &quot;be nice&quot; to us and tell them <pb ref="arm03020013004" seq="04" n="02"/>
                    all about the school - take my pictures along too. Imagine the trip will cost about &#36;100 but have decided to take it unless the 
                    unexpected happens as its the chance of a lifetime. Am getting more &amp; more interested in the work here and the thought of 
                    teaching in Tacoma again according to rule &amp; method is more &amp; more repugnant. So don&apos;t know just which way things 
                    will turn - as you say we are doing lots of good here and though going along from day to day one is apt to get discouraged at times and 
                    wonder if it&apos;s worth the effort - for the youngsters do not study and are so irresponsible - most of them - the few who do try though 
                    are worthwhile anyway. This community can only be changed through its young people and one can see results here when you go way 
                    up the creeks &amp; see conditions where the people have not been touched by the school in any way. And the other schools - <pb ref="arm03020013005" seq="05"/>
                    I saw two of them yesterday - one about three miles up Baskin Creek &amp; the other the same distance up the Roaring Fork. Log 
                    buildings - benches and a little blackboard in the front end - One had four windows in all - the other six - one had a table for the teacher 
                    - the other a split log on end with little short piece across formed the desk! Absolutely no equipment whatsoever - the youngsters have 
                    readers &amp; learn reading but writing is not usually taught! Just picture it! Took kodaks of the buildings &amp; will send them as soon as 
                    possible. We have been discussing night school lately and are quite enthusiastic about starting it. Mrs. Langmaid now head of 
                    the school committee will be here about the middle of October and we are going to discuss it with her. We girls all get along so well 
                    together. It is surely fortunate and Mr. Cresswell is always <pb ref="arm03020013006" seq="06" n="03"/>willing to help as much as possible.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <del>My last letter was written rather hurriedly Tuesday <abbr expan="evening">eve.</abbr> pa&apos;s letter 
                        came the next day and was very pleased to get. Hope the California trip is all mapped out &amp; ticket bought by this time. When you 
                        go - pa - be sure to plan going south to Los Angeles - or does Mr. St. John live in that section - none of you have mentioned just where 
                        he does live. What will Jane do meanwhile? Think I would not know the house if I were there with your newly painted floors and all. The 
                        attic too!</del>
                </p>
                <p>
                    Have fields here for my cleaning propensities all right - This attic is a perfect sight and some rainy day Emily &amp; I are going to 
                    get busy - Then at school there is an attic where in an old book case is an awful jumble of books - another job for a dark day. The 
                    fruit sounds good as it&apos;s scarce here - Have not seen any big pears - We had a few small <pb ref="arm03020013007" seq="07"/>ones 
                    but they were not very good eating &amp; Aunt Lizzie canned most of them. No pa have not been in bathing once and am glad I did 
                    not get a bathing suit. There is really no time for play when it comes to <hi1 rend="underscore">cleaning</hi1> <hi1 rend="underscore">up</hi1> 
                    - prefer seeing the country to dabbing around in Little Pigeon. The weather is summer like and hot except in the mornings &amp; 
                    evenings when a nap is comfortable - but am still wearing white shoes and thin dresses - That white dress Jane sent me is so suitable 
                    for school and wear first one &amp; then the other most of the time with the gingham in between. At present am clad in my new white 
                    georgette waist &amp; light blue skirt - wore my good straw hat to Sunday School too - though fall hats are in evidence even here! 
                    The heat has not troubled me at all. Yes am very unusual summer color - red &amp; brown - but flatter myself that the <pb ref="arm03020013008" seq="08" n="04"/>
                    freckles are not quite so numerous or else my mirror doesn&apos;t show them - it&apos;s not very good glass you know. I did not burn 
                    much on the <abbr expan="outside">out.</abbr> trip last week - At least when I asked the girls about it they said my face was 
                    <hi1 rend="underscore">so</hi1> <hi1 rend="underscore">red</hi1> all the time they couldn&apos;t see any difference. Guess I do look 
                    quite healthy - certainly have more color than a year ago - and am still eager for food three times a day at least!
                </p>
                <p>
                    Our fair was a great event though not many in the community turned out for it <unclear reason="illegible" resp="tl">nor</unclear> were many things exhibited. 
                    It was the first and no doubt next year there will be more interest &amp; it will be more successful. Wednesday morning we went through 
                    our program - which was as follows -<pb ref="arm03020013009" seq="09"/>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <item n="1">1. Salute to the flag - School</item>
                        <item n="2">2. Star Spangled Banner - <abbr expan="school">&quot;</abbr></item>
                        <item n="3">3. Farm Life - Cora McCarter
                            <p>(A long winded thing on agriculture &amp; the educated farmer written by some <abbr expan="professor">prof</abbr> 
                                at Knoxville &amp; which Miss Whittle was anxious to have read - Cora is my best pupil - is in high school - plans 
                                to be a teacher.)
                            </p></item>
                        <item n="4">4. <unclear reason="illegible" resp="tl">Motion</unclear> Song - Come Little Leaves. <del>by</del> - Primary Class.</item>
                        <item n="5">5. Drill - Shoo Fly Shoo - Intermediate Class.</item>
                        <item n="6">6. America the Beautiful - School.</item>
                        <item n="7">7. Handkerchief Drill - 8 Boys</item>
                        <item n="8">8. Our School Flag Song - School</item>
                        <item n="9">9. Dramatizations - Primary Class
                            <item>a. The Larks</item>
                            <item>b. King Midas</item></item>
                        </list>
                        <pb ref="arm03020013010" seq="10" n="05"/>
                    <list>
                        <item n="10">10. Sunbonnet Drill - 12 girls.</item>
                        <item n="11">11. <del>Cannin</del> Songs - Canning Club Girls</item>
                        <item n="12">12. Songs - Primary Class</item>
                        <item n="13">13. Closing Song - We Thank Thee Oh Father - School.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>
                    The drill by the intermediate class was also given at Miss Whittles request and illustrated the use of the fly swatter 
                    etc. Emily&apos;s little tots were cute. Especially funny were they in the Larks - half a dozen of them represented little 
                    birds whom the Mother Bird had to feed - flying off for a worm to give each. The handkerchief drill was just a lot of motions 
                    with kerchiefs all ridiculous - My sunbonnet drill went off without a hitch for which I was pleased - We <pb ref="arm03020013011" seq="11"/>
                    did not think much of the program - especially on Wednesday when everything was done miserably but it was all right the next day 
                    when our company were present. Well after drilling &amp; drilling <abbr expan="Wednesday">Wed.</abbr> a.m. we worked 
                    in the building all day &amp; had the youngsters help us instead of recite. We put up the panels making one big room - By the way 
                    will you let the girls (Pi Phis) borrow the sketch of the school - it&apos;s not well drawn but gives an idea of how things look anyway. 
                    We on one side of the hall - the manual training exhibit and on the other baskets. The fireplace was banked with autumn leaves &amp; 
                    on mantel were the same and a big fern. Back of the radiators were golden rod &amp; asters. The wild asters here are lovely little 
                    things - pale lavender and white - are in bloom now - the <pb ref="arm03020013012" seq="12" n="06"/>little purple ones are practically gone. 
                    Such qualities of golden rod you never saw - there are several varieties here - some much finer &amp; daintier than ours. You know 
                    how fond I&apos;ve always been of it - I get all I want of it now! In the sewing room were two tables of apples - three of the cases 
                    filled with preserves of various kinds &amp; canned fruits &amp; vegetables - crocheted work - two coverlids - (not perfect enough 
                    to buy) some embroidery - bags made by the little girls &amp; a table of their cookery - peanut bread - cookies &amp; biscuits. In the 
                    shop were the vegetables - a huge pumpkin - sage - sugar cane - corn - peppers - onions - beets - Emily had paper chains of various 
                    colors in her room - butterflies &amp; little paper things they had made on little tables - autumn leaves - On her desk her waste basket 
                    filled with golden rod - I had two corners in the back of my <pb ref="arm03020013013" seq="13"/>room filled with writing papers - Japanese 
                    lanterns they drew (&amp; good ones too single &amp; in clusters of three) pasted on the blackboard as a border &amp; in the corner by 
                    the windows - while in the other corners were their maps - Golden rod &amp; asters stick in the radiators - and on the desk - which was moved 
                    back toward the windows as was the piano. Abbie&apos;s room was similar &amp; had boughs of autumn leaves for trimming. The 
                    building did look pretty &amp; we went home <abbr expan="Wednesday">Wed.</abbr> evening about five weary but pleased - Mrs. 
                    Cresswell &amp; Mrs. Bishop both arrive during the day so there was quite a party of us for dinner. Evelyn was busy too everywhere &amp; 
                    besides had to bake cakes &amp; pies for the picnic dinner the <pb ref="arm03020013014" seq="14" n="07"/>next day - Her mother &amp; 
                    Aunt Lizzie both helped - Emily and I studied the stars a little &amp; we were early in bed. Did I tell you Emily had a star book? We have 
                    found a number of the constellations - take the flashlight turn it on the diagram in the book &amp; then gaze fixedly upward till we 
                    begin to see the ones we&apos;re looking for - Exclaim &amp; point excitedly study the book again &amp; repeat the noise &amp; 
                    gesticulating.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Thursday morning was &quot;<sic corr="bright">brite</sic> and fair&quot; and I donned spotless  
                    white &amp; my green tie in honor of the occasion. The livestock we had 
                    expected dwindled down to a small puppy and a coop of white chickens! However we were kept busy until eleven label<del>l</del>ing 
                    more canned stuff apples etc. that came in the last thing. At eleven the <pb ref="arm03020013015" seq="15"/>school bell was rung - the 
                    children assembled for the program in Abbie&apos;s room and the audience filled only my room - about fifty. After that we went outside 
                    to the back of the schoolhouse when the lunch was set forth on tables - chickens pies cakes - biscuits - bread jelly etc. loads of it 
                    everyone helped themselves &amp; sat around &amp; ate. I took a number of pictures during the day &amp; do hope they prove good. 
                    The next excitement was the arrival of the baseball team from Sevierville with some of the teachers &amp; girls - they came to the house 
                    &amp; had to be shown the exhibit etc. Then about 2:30 the game began - a good close game too - We beat 6 to 4 however. Our team 
                    was not a strictly school team but was filled out <pb ref="arm03020013016" seq="16" n="08"/>with fellows from Sheep Pen - the Glades - 
                    Green Brier. The Murphy people yelled vigorously &amp; ours were soon inspired to do the same - In fact the two crowds of girls got 
                    pretty personal at times &amp; we had to calm ours a little. The day finally came to a close - the Sevierville crowd departed - Miss 
                    Whittle &amp; her two judges also &amp; we turned our thoughts to supper. As everything was taken over to the picnic our prospects 
                    appeared <hi1 rend="underscore">nil</hi1> but Aunt Lizzie found a whole batch of biscuits in the warming oven that had been overlooked 
                    - we made chocolate - got out some canned peas - and bethinking ourselves of the girl&apos;s display of cookery - Abbie &amp; I 
                    rushed over to the schoolhouse for it - However part of it had already found resting places wasn't that the <unclear reason="illegible" resp="tl">limit</unclear>? 
                    But we packed up what <pb ref="arm03020013017" seq="17"/>remained and had a beautiful repast after all. Friday recitations were 
                    pretty slim - people were around packing up a good part of the morning so instead of having my recitations in the sewing room as 
                    usual I went out on the porch &amp; as it was rather cool early in the <abbr expan="morning">a.m.</abbr> we sat on the edge of the 
                    walk in the sunshine. The youngsters thought it great fun! After school Emily &amp; I finished cleaning up while Mr. <abbr expan="Cresswell">C.</abbr> 
                    helped load up the wagon with the exhibits for the Sevierville fair which is Monday &amp; Tuesday - Abbie had gone home &amp; 
                    Evelyn was busy at the house - then I came home &amp; after sitting on the porch a little with Mrs. Bishop eating apples &amp; cookies - 
                    swept downstairs &amp; part of the upstairs. Then cleaned up &amp; proceeded to darn! After dinner we sat around <pb ref="arm03020013018" seq="18" n="09"/>
                    in the living room - Evelyn played &amp; sang for us - Emily read - Mrs. Bishop crocheted &amp; I finished my darning. So ended another big day.
                </p>                
                <p>
                    Yesterday Emily &amp; I bustled around until about eleven and then set forth with lunch &amp; kodak up Baskins Creek - 
                    It is not very pretty &amp; is up hill most of the way - the creek is rather dirty &amp; the people all seem so untouched by 
                    civilization. We took a steep trail which lead us to the top of a ridge overlooking Roaring Fork and very near the foot of Round Top - We 
                    sat here for over an hour - writing in my diary &amp; talking with Emily who wrote a letter - Such a grove of chestnut trees as we were 
                    in. These trees are enormous and are beautiful too - loaded with nuts. When we started down to Roaring Fork we came to a field where 
                    was a huge apple tree loaded with red fruit - Over <pb ref="arm03020013019" seq="19"/>the fence we went and helped ourselves - An 
                    abandoned cabin stood in the middle of the field so we were not <hi1 rend="underscore">stealing</hi1>! The road back was simply 
                    beautiful - In one place the side of the mountain was a rocky cliff - several of them in fact and always we followed the creek - many times 
                    &amp; oft crossing it on narrow little bridges consisting of two planks - The wild grape vines flourish all along the creek - tree after tree 
                    being covered to the very top. As we took our time &amp; made one call along the way &amp; chatted with others it was dark when 
                    we reached home though only 6:45. We had tramped about eight of these <hi1 rend="underscore">long</hi1> miles but frisked around 
                    - made hot chocolate - scrambled some eggs and hunted up fresh biscuits - (&quot;light bread&quot; as <del>(</del> 
                    white <del>br</del> raised bread is called here - Aunt <pb ref="arm03020013020" seq="20" n="10"/>Lizzie never made 
                    bread until last winter - everyone makes biscuits &amp; corn bread) Evelyn &amp; her mother were at the Huff&apos;s and as Aunt Lizzie 
                    had had a spell with her heart that morning we would not let her do anything - After this we went back to the living room - &amp; I 
                    copied a couple of poems from the Outlook about the Kentucky <abbr expan="mountain">mt.</abbr> people - Then the Bishops 
                    got back &amp; in the course of time we were all safe &amp; sound in bed again.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Evelyn &amp; her mother are now on their way to Sevierville as the fair exhibits have to be put in place - Tuesday there will be 
                    no school so that the youngsters may have an opportunity to go - Will probably chaperone some of them down -
                </p>
                <p>
                    Have not worn my pleasant hat yet and think I'll not wear it <abbr expan="Tuesday">Tues.</abbr> as it&apos;s still dusty &amp; 
                    the girls say the crowd is awful - So shall wear my <pb ref="arm03020013021" seq="21"/>old gray with my blue suit maybe will wear gray 
                    silk gloves &amp; gray shoes -
                </p>
                <p>
                    Am going to have Mary fix my two old georgette waists take out fullness in waist part &amp; sleeves - get ready for New Orleans!
                </p>
                <p>
                    A busy week is ahead of us and as I must plan something for my club girls for tomorrow <abbr expan="afternoon">p.m.</abbr> find something 
                    for B. Y. P. tonight (the subject <hi1 rend="underscore">Divorce</hi1> was given me but do not care <del>ta</del> 
                    to take it <hi1 rend="underscore">somehow</hi1>!) write a few letters - study a little - guess I must finish this lengthy epistle by bidding 
                    you all a fond farewell - I do miss you so much - but we are just too busy for repining! and wouldn't be in Tacoma teaching for 
                    <hi1 rend="underscore">anything</hi1>!! Loads of love - Ruth.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Sept. 28th. Sunday.
                </p>
                <pb ref="arm03020013022" seq="22"/>
                <figure>
                    <head>Hasty Sketch of School</head>
                    <figDesc>Hand drawn blueprint of settlement school by Ruth Sterling.</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <pb ref="arm03020013023" seq="23"/>
                <p>
                    On top of the book cases in hall are baskets filled with ferns - over the fireplaces is a large sepia print in brown wood frame of 
                    Corat's morning. Above book case at right of hall as you enter is a service flag - filling a large part of the wall space - while at the 
                    left on opposite wall is a <hi1 rend="underscore">big</hi1> American flag - formerly used on flagpole - but torn so abandoned to 
                    the closet. We found it &amp; mended it the best we could &amp; had the boys put it up - looks fine too! Back of my desk hangs 
                    a big U.S. map &amp; my little silk flag - two or three pictures are on the panel back of the piano - prints and on wall above panel 
                    high up hangs a Pi Phi banner - Behind each of my doors is blackboard &amp; between doors - Above are five prints. Between 
                    the windows are some colored drawings of Japanese lanterns - Had writing papers along panels of back of room - At present 
                    they are all at the at the fair - Under the flag usually sits a flower stand on which is basket with fern - ditto on piano - The two cases 
                    in the hall are for the youngster&apos;s baskets &amp; pails of lunch. In the sewing room are three tables - benches - blackboard 
                    &amp; (I <hi1 rend="underscore">think</hi1>) <hi1 rend="underscore">three</hi1> sewing machines &amp; case in corner for their 
                    work - In kitchen are oil stoves for the cooking - The shop is very well equipped - the only school in the county that teaches manual 
                    training. The water <unclear reason="illegible" resp="tl">tank</unclear> is very nice - water pumped from the house - regulation 
                    drinking fountain!
                </p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
