<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03040004000">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[Letter]  Feb. 5, 1920, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
                    <name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
                    <name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
                </address>
                <date>2006</date>
                <idno type="SPCID">arm03040004000</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. 
                        For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee 
                        Libraries, Knoxville, TN</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from which the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
                <bibl>
                    <title>[Letter]  Feb. 5, 1920, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                    <date value="1920-02-05">Feb. 5, 1920</date>
                    <author>
                        <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                    </author>
                    <extent>7p</extent>
                    <note type="summary">More calls. Primary class has party at the house - Plans for the future of Gatlinburg.</note>
                    <note type="box">3</note>
                    <note type="folder">4</note>
                    <note type="document">arm03040004000</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Local Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <list>
                        <item>Living Conditions</item>
                        <item>Home visits</item>
                        <item>School children</item>
                        <item>Social life</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="abstract">
                <pb ref="arm03040004001" seq="01"/>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <item>More calls</item>
                        <item>Primary class has party at the house - </item>
                        <item>Plans for the the future of Gatlinburg</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="letter">
                <pb ref="arm03040004002" seq="02"/>
                <head>
                    <date value="1920-02-05">Feb. 5, 1920</date>
                </head>    
                <p>
                     Dearest family - 
                </p>
                <p>
                     It&apos;s six o&apos;clock this dark cloudy morning &amp; am sitting in bed done up in bathrobe &amp; comforter. Harrison started the fire in the furnace some time ago
                    but things are not warmed up yet. I intended writing last night but was so sleepy just left my lessons &amp; everything &amp; was in bed by eight or before I guess. We
                    have all had a sleepy spell lately - the weather is warm &amp; rainy again which may partly account for it.
                </p>
                <p><del>
                          Mabel&apos;s letter came Monday with a long one from Ruth Victoria  also has sent me another nice long letter &amp; yours came. Feel real conscience stricken
                        about <abbr expan="Ruth Victoria">Vic</abbr> - as I&apos;ve not written her for months! </del><pb ref="arm03040004003" seq="03"></pb><del>Didn&apos;t have her address part of the time
                        - and then forgot to take it with me to New Orleans &amp; have just put it off from day to day - felt too that she probably read some of my letters home. But am really going
                            to write her. Have to get off my Pi Phi letter this week too.</del>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <del>
                          Am glad you are getting along so well at home - you will miss Mabel &amp; &quot;her little ways&quot; won&apos;t you? Shall send her a letter before she departs Friday
                        the <hi1 rend="underscore">13th</hi1>! If there is another in days - she has selected a good combination hasn&apos;t she?
                        </del>
                    </p>
                    <p><del>
                        No my itinerary is not planned neither is anything else - shall just let things go along &amp; see how they work out by the end of March - seven</del>
                        <pb ref="arm03040004004" seq="04"></pb> <del>more weeks only. Everyone hopes that I see some of the East before starting home - that is several have so expressed themselves in
                        letters - and it does seem like a good opportunity even though my wardrobe is pitiful &amp; my purse nigh empty! We will see!
                        </del>
                    </p>
                <p>
                     No - Evelyn hasn&apos;t given me any singing lessons after all - her music lessons have dropped off - entirely - Stella Huff is the only one starting again - Miss Langmaid
                    stopped them by her absorbing visit.
                </p>
                <p>
                     Monday after school (a lovely day &amp; the last one of this week) Emily &amp; I went up Mill Creek with the Oakley children &amp; made a little call at their cabin &amp;
                    then went on to some cousins of theirs - Nicholas hasn&apos;t been in school lately &amp; I wanted to find out why. They live in a frame house &amp; are quite
                    comfortably fixed for these parts - It&apos;s about three miles from here right at the foot of the mountains which are higher than at the <abbr expan="Gatlinburg">burg</abbr> - 
                    Le Conte the highest peak of <abbr expan="Great Smoky Mountains">Smoky</abbr> is just a short distance away. We had a very nice time and came home through Turkey&apos;s
                    Nest arriving just at dark - Evelyn &amp; Abbie went to the hotel for the night to visit Josie Trentham &amp; her mother - They have charge for the Huff&apos;s you know.
                </p>
                <p>
                     Tuesday Emily had her little tots over - twenty of them - they played games &amp; were fed cookies &amp; chocolate. It was such a rainy day &amp; 
                    <pb ref="arm03040004005" seq="05"></pb> as ordinarily half of her youngsters stay out <del>or</del> such weather - she thought of postponing the party which
                    had been announced the day before - But do you know - every last one of them was at school - so the party came off as scheduled. The girls that stayed with Abbie are at
                    home as the father is away &amp; the weather ill - so Abbie is here now - It&apos;s much pleasanter for her than having to be with them too!
                </p>
                <p>
                    Mr. Cresswell and about half a dozen men - here &amp; in Sevierville have formed a company and are going <pb ref="arm03040004006" seq="06"></pb> to build a dam &amp; put 
                    up a factory for making furniture &amp; coffins. - They have bought the machinery which we had intended using for the same purpose. Miss Langmaid gave up the scheme
                    as it seemed a pretty big undertaking &amp; needed an experienced man at the head of it. This company is going into quite deeply &amp; guess it will pay as the railroad
                    will be through soon. Evelyn is going to wait before putting in the Delco System of lighting as there will be enough power to furnish electricity to the whole
                    <abbr expan="Gatlinburg">burg</abbr> - (I mean <add place="supralinear">power</add> at the factory) <pb ref="arm03040004007" seq="07"></pb> Work is to start this summer - 
                    Gatlinburg seems to have a future before it!
                </p>
                <p>
                     It&apos;s just time to call the family to arise so will cease my erratic pennings for now &amp; high me hence - 
                </p>
                <p>
                     You see there is little news just now to write so fear my letters must seem quite a sameness - 
                </p>
                <p>
                     Oh yes - I wrote to the street car company in New Orleans in regard to lack of courtesy on the part of their <sic corr="employees">employes</sic> &amp; got a reply
                    yesterday saying that was one of the things they tried to make the men understand &amp; that they were surprised  - that my experience had been such - that they thanked
                    me for calling their attention to the matter &amp; would increase their efforts!
                </p>
                <p>
                     Just lots &amp; lots of love
                </p>
                <p>
                     Ruth.
                </p>
              </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>