<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03030001000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[Letter]  Oct. 08, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
				<author>
					<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
				</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
					<name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
					<name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
				<address>
					<addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
				</address>
				<date>2006</date>
				<idno type="SPCID">arm03030001000</idno>
				<availability>
					<p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from whi1ch the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
				<bibl>
					<title>[Letter]  Oct. 08, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
					<date value="1919-10-08">Oct. 08, 1919</date>
					<author>
						<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
					</author>
					<extent>5p</extent>
					<note type="summary">Plans to visit Elkmont. Estel Huff takes us to Pigeon <sic corr="Forge">Ford</sic> and back in the Huff Ford. The four high school students plan their share of the Thanksgiving program</note>
					<note type="box">3</note>
					<note type="folder">3</note>
					<note type="document">arm03030001000</note>
				</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
			</projectDesc>
		<editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<bibl>
						<title>Local Subject Headings</title>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<list>
						<item>Living Conditions</item>
						<item>People</item>
						<item>School programs</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div1 type="abstract">
				<pb ref="arm03030001001" seq="01"/>
				<p>
					<list>
						<item>Plans to visit Elkmont</item>
						<item>Estel Huff takes us to Pigeon <sic corr="Forge">Ford</sic> and back in the Huff Ford.</item>
						<item>The four high school students plan their share of the Thanksgiving program</item>
					</list>
				</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="letter">
				<pb ref="arm03030001002" seq="02"/>
				<head>
					<date value="1919-10-08">Oct. 08, 1919</date>
				</head>
				<p>
                    Dearest pa - your note or rather card came today &amp; was very glad to know that you are en route - 
                    Hope it is Pullman - If not <hi1 rend="underscore">you</hi1>
					<hi1 rend="underscore">see</hi1> - that 
                    it is next time. Shall be interested in hearing your impressions of the Golden State and hope you 
                    like it as well as I did for California more than fulfilled my expectations. Tonight - Wednesday - am 
                    sitting in front of a happy blaze in the fireplace as tis cold &amp; rainy outside. Emily is taking a piano 
                    lesson from Evelyn. I am going to start vocal with her as soon as my music books come from home. 
                    Think that will be loads of fun - Aunt Lizzie left for her daughter&apos;s yesterday. She lives about 
                    seven or eight miles from here up in the Sugar Fords. We girls are planning to go Friday to a place 
                    up in the mountains called Elkmont &amp; quite a summer resort is it too. We will drive to the foot of 
                    the mountain about six miles or so &amp; then climb to the top - stay all night at the hotel &amp; next 
                    morning go in a logging train <pb ref="arm03030001003" seq="03"/>
					<del>all</del> way up 
                    the mountains to a lumber camp getting back to the burg same time Saturday evening. That sounds exciting 
                    doesn&apos;t it? The timber around here is the largest found east of the Mississippi but is not as large as some 
                    of ours.
                </p>
				<p>
                    The way people slide along about things is really remarkable - for instance Evelyn has been trying to find out since last 
                    April how much we owe at the store - and hasn&apos;t succeeded yet - The people are awfully honest too - I forgot my 
                    purse one day at school &amp; left it on my desk &amp; not a penny had been touched &amp; they tell me that is 
                    always so.
                </p>
				<p>
                    Had a lovely ride last night after school of about four miles - A mile on these roads is you know <add place="supralinear">a</add> 
                    much great consumer of time than the same distance on our good roads at home. <pb ref="arm03030001004" seq="04" n="02"/>
                    Evelyn &amp; Abbie decided to go in to a concert at Sevierville last evening and as Estel Huff said he would take 
                    them down about four miles on the way - Emily &amp; I piled into the Ford too &amp; came back with Estel. He is 
                    one of my high school youngsters you know. The girls walked about 3 miles on to Pigeon Forge where they found 
                    a car to take them the remaining seven miles to Sevierville. Then they came up early this 
                    <abbr expan="morning">a.m.</abbr> in time for school - but had to pay &#36;5 for the trip. Monday was a 
                    most peaceful day - Jane had sent me that funny story - &quot;The Young Visitors&quot; and after school where 
                    I stayed late however I sat on the porch &amp; read &amp; chuckled over it. Then in the evening I read it to the 
                    girls whom thoroughly enjoyed it too. <pb ref="arm03030001005" seq="05"/>My  four high school youngsters are 
                    beginning to work up a little play adapted from Courtship of Miles Standish for Thanksgiving. We went through 
                    it all after school tonight and had a great time doing it too - They are so funny - we all had the giggles.
                </p>
				<p>
                    There are going to be <hi1 rend="underscore">long</hi1>
					<hi1 rend="underscore">long</hi1> evenings before many 
                    more days - in fact they have begun already &amp; hope to get things done - just what I don&apos;t know yet - but shall 
                    keep busy - and then can&apos;t get homesick you know.
                </p>
				<p>
                    Write soon do -
                </p>
				<p>
                    With loads of love dear pa -
                </p>
				<p>
                    Ruth.
                </p>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
