<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03030019000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[Letter]  Nov. 20, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
				<author>
					<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
				</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
					<name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
					<name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
				<address>
					<addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
				</address>
				<date>2006</date>
				<idno type="SPCID">arm03030019000</idno>
				<availability>
					<p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from which the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
				<bibl>
					<title>[Letter]  Nov. 20, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
					<date value="1919-11-20">Nov. 20, 1919</date>
					<author>
						<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
					</author>
					<extent>7p</extent>
					<note type="summary">A busy life for us all</note>
					<note type="box">3</note>
					<note type="folder">3</note>
					<note type="document">arm03030019000</note>
				</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
			</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<bibl>
						<title>Local Subject Headings</title>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<list>
						<item>People</item>
						<item>Home visits</item>
						<item>Living conditions</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div1 type="abstract">
				<pb ref="arm03030019001" seq="01"/>
				<p>
					<list>
						<item>A busy life for us all</item>
					</list>
				</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="letter">
				<pb ref="arm03030019002" seq="02"/>
				<head>
					<date value="1919-11-20">Nov. 20, 1919</date>
				</head>
				<p>
                    Dearest Jane - It&apos;s about 8 p.m. this Thursday evening &amp; hope to soon be in bed - would have written you last night but just didn&apos;t 
                    have the pep - Things have been buzzing so lately - Monday after school - the girls practiced their song - then I dashed over to Huffs&apos; to see 
                    about Estel&apos;s costume for the play &amp; of course couldn&apos;t get away till almost dark - Then was supper &amp; before it was 
                    devoured - Cara &amp; Tom McCarter arrived about getting help for their Latin &amp; stayed all evening - They are such nice youngsters &amp; 
                    so worth while helping in every way - Tom is perfectly killing - one never knows what he will say next.
                </p>
				<p>
                    Tuesday we <sic corr="practiced">practised</sic> on the play &amp; <add place="supralinear">I</add> was over at the school house till dark &amp; spent 
                    evening remodeling the sun bonnets in my Fair drill into Puritan bonnets &amp; visiting <pb ref="arm03030019003" seq="03"/>with Evelyn &amp; 
                    Miss Langmaid - Last night when I got back here Dr. Massey was just going up the road in his Ford to the Ogles - (Ephraines) about a mile up the river 
                    - I decided to go along &amp; make a call at Lucretties as she was not in school that <abbr expan="afternoon">p.m.</abbr> We had quite a time getting the car 
                    started - Harrison &amp; I both helped Dan (the horse) even came up back of us to see what was doing. Finally a man on horseback came up &amp; 
                    solved the trouble &amp; away we went. Lucrettie was all huddled over the fire - a big silk handkerchief on her brow. After visiting a little I persuaded her to go 
                    for a walk &amp; gather some of the pine &amp; hemlock boughs covered with cones - perfectly beautiful. We got a big armful <pb ref="arm03030019004" seq="04"/> 
                    which I left at the school to be fixed this morning - (four baskets!)
                </p>
				<p>
                    Evelyn &amp; Miss Langmaid I discovered on my return had gone down the road toward Sevierville with the doctor on his way back so walked down 
                    that way to meet them as they returned on foot. We all enjoy these little snatches of rides so much! But it began to get dark - really dark &amp; no sign of
                    them so returned home. 
                </p>
				<p>
                    We ate supper &amp; still they didn&apos;t come - I finally concluded they went all the way into Sevierville which surmise proved correct. Abbie has had a 
                    bad cold all week as so many are afflicted at present &amp; came home at recess sick enough to go to bed - The doctor prescribed calomel so Emily 
                    &amp; I fussed around with her some &amp; then I went over to the cottage to stay all night with the Carr girls in her place. It sure is cold these days - am
                    wearing my big old coat &amp; wool dresses.
                </p>
				<p>
                    Tonight after school - Cora practiced the 23rd Psalm which she sings while spinning. She just suits the part of Priscilla too. About 4:30 Emily &amp; I
                    started off &amp; called at the Andrew Ogles&apos; just below our bungalow the ones who caused so much trouble between  Marshall - (their son) &amp;
                    Mary &amp; who said so much about us! The father is a regular patriarch in appearance &amp; <del>can&apos;t</del>
					<add place="supralinear">won&apos;t</add> do a bit of work sits around at the stores &amp; <pb ref="arm03030019005" seq="05"/> on his porch - gossips most 
                    of the time - but no wonder - he can neither read nor write and has absolutely nothing to take his mind off his neighbors&apos; affairs! Cora the 
                    daughter whom I have in school is lovely a regular little beauty - big black eyes - dark hair &amp; pretty features. We (Emily &amp; I) are planning to take
                    an all day hike with her &amp; Lucrettie during Thanksgiving vacation! Well - as we left their house we met Mrs. Huff &amp; little Blanche looking for 
                    Mr. <abbr expan="Huff">H.</abbr> &amp; the Ford as Evelyn had phoned from Pigeon Forge for someone to 
                    meet them. Poor Harrison had to go with Dan as no trace could be found of Mr. <abbr expan="Huff">H.</abbr> We walked part way home with her getting
                    back at dark - Aunt Lizzie was <pb ref="arm03030019006" seq="06"/> making cocoa - &amp; had put some bread in the oven to toast - I had the bright idea
                    of sprin<del>n</del>kling grated cheese over it - &amp; by the time it was ready &amp; some remnants of chicken &amp; gravy
                    warmed over - the two ladies arrived - Said they decided to go on to Sevierville as the doctor said he&apos;d take them up to Wears Valley to see about 
                    baskets (had to <del>see</del>
					<add place="supralinear">visit</add> a patient).
                </p>
				<p>
                    We had our supper all together after all - &amp; then tried Ned&apos;s songs which came from Uncle Art today - I like them very much - &amp; Evelyn
                    thinks them <hi1 rend="underscore">very</hi1>
					<hi1 rend="underscore">good</hi1>. She has not yet given me a lesson - but eventually she <hi1 rend="underscore">may</hi1>
                    get around to it - We had a helter skelter life <pb ref="arm03030019007" seq="07"/> you see - 
                </p>
				<p>
                    By the way please find out as soon as possible where we may get the powdered paint for our toys - We must get at them <hi1 rend="underscore">next</hi1>.
                </p>
				<p><del>
                    Do you like this kind of a letter? Have not made one comment on yours have I?</del>
                </p>
				<p><del>
                     Shall be so glad to have the kodaks of the children - should think Nellie would be weary at times! Miss Langmaid wanted some of my kodaks &amp; just
                    sold them to her &amp; will get duplicates to send you - The one of <hi1 rend="underscore">my</hi1>
						<hi1 rend="underscore">hat</hi1> did not come out - 
                    &amp; the other of my gray dress is only <hi1 rend="underscore">so</hi1>
						<hi1 rend="underscore">so</hi1>! It will be fine for <hi1 rend="underscore">them</hi1>
                    (Arthur &amp; Nell) to have a real house &amp; yard - I never felt that the other house suited them somehow - Is the office moved? Wouldn&apos;t it be fine
                    <hi1 rend="strikethrough">th</hi1> for that land to bring <hi1 rend="underscore">something</hi1>
						<hi1 rend="underscore">in</hi1>! </del>
                </p>
				<p><del>
                    Yes I do take care of myself <hi1 rend="underscore">sensibly</hi1> and do not court colds, wet feet, etc. What took Bessie to Chicago? Wonder what she
                    will think of our relations?</del>
                </p>
				<p><del>
                     I don&apos;t know what I want for <abbr expan="Christmas">Xmas</abbr> - Honestly - unless it&apos;s my silver mirror &amp; that is very 
                     unnecessary &amp; expensive - </del>
                 </p>
				<p><del>
                     Would like a lot more of those <unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">photogravures</unclear> - if you want to say <sic corr="goodbye">good by</sic>
                     to them as those I have are awfully flyspecked - </del>
                 </p>
				<p><del>
                     Guess you all will have to have some more baskets from me - Thought  I might have time to make some things but sure <hi1 rend="underscore">won&apos;t</hi1>.
                     Hope you got the others &amp; liked them. Must say goodnight dearest Jane &amp; with so much of love to you all - Ruth</del>
                 </p>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
