<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03030003000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[Letter]  Oct. 15, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
				<author>
					<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
				</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
					<name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
					<name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
				<address>
					<addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
				</address>
				<date>2006</date>
				<idno type="SPCID">arm03030003000</idno>
				<availability>
					<p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from whi1ch the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
				<bibl>
					<title>[Letter]  Oct. 15, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
					<date value="1919-10-15">Oct. 15, 1919</date>
					<author>
						<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
					</author>
					<extent>4p</extent>
					<note type="summary">Description of Aunt Lydia Whaley and her home.</note>
					<note type="box">3</note>
					<note type="folder">3</note>
					<note type="document">arm03030003000</note>
				</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
			</projectDesc>
		 <editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<bibl>
						<title>Local Subject Headings</title>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<list>
						<item>Living conditions</item>
						<item>People</item>
						<item>Home visits</item>
						<item>Social life</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div1 type="abstract">
				<pb ref="arm03030003001" seq="01"/>
				<p>
					<list>
						<item>Description of Aunt Lydia Whaley and her home.</item>
					</list>
				</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="letter">
				<pb ref="arm03030003002" seq="02"/>
				<head>
					<date value="1919-10-15">Oct. 15, 1919</date>
				</head>
				<p>
                    Dearest Jane - Wednesday evening &amp; I&apos;m over here in Abbie&apos;s room as chaperone for the two 
                    Carr girls tonight as Abbie is spending the night up <del>the</del> one of the creeks at Josie 
                    Ogle&apos;s - <del>Your letter came today &amp; am very glad Miss Paucost will be with you 
                        - It will be nice for her &amp; am sure she will be quite a spoiled darling like Mabel &amp; Jo - before long! 
                        Your descriptions of dinners sound awfully good - but do you know I&apos;m getting quite attached to corn bread 
                        &amp; hot biscuits &amp; eat them in preference to &quot;light bread&quot; every time!</del>
				</p>
				<p>
                    To chronicle my doings - Monday was a day of rain - wore my gingham dress &amp; little green sweater - (it&apos;s 
                    first appearance at school) &amp; quite like the combination. After school I studied quite late - while Emily &amp; some 
                    of the girls cleaned the attic which was full of old magazines - Abbie &amp; I came in on the tail end of the cleaning so five o&apos;clock 
                    was upon us before we knew it. Evelyn who had gone to Huff&apos;s called up to say she was <pb ref="arm03030003003" seq="03"/>going 
                    to stay all night &amp; as the rain was quite torrential Maud Clabo &amp; another little girl stayed for supper &amp; the night 
                    here - They live about three miles away.
                </p>
				<p>
                    I made apple &amp; <del>cl</del> celery salad - the first celery we&apos;ve had - for our evening repast. 
                    We spent the evening with literature around the fireplace where a brisk fire of chestnut &amp; oak crackled. Aunt Lizzie knitted 
                    away on some socks. What do think of my picture of her &amp; Mrs. Profit? Tuesday it cleared some - so after school 
                    we four girls tramped up the road to see the famous Aunt Lydia - and a quaint old woman she is. Her cabin is one room - 
                    the ceiling about one inch above my head - Abbie had to stoop to enter the door &amp; inside. She has a fireplace at which 
                    all her cooking is done including baking - there are two doors and two tiny dirty windows about the size of this sheet of paper 
                    when spread out. She is eighty years old - and thinks she is getting old &amp; feeble but told us that she had been picking 
                    apples while on one of her visits climbing to the very top of the tree to get them! She is little &amp; quite <pb ref="arm03030003004" seq="04"/>
                    bent - brown eyes &amp; white scraggly hair - is of Scotch descent - her &quot;grand pap&quot; having come to North Carolina when a young 
                    fellow where he married a Welsh girl who had come over about the same time. She sat there picking over tobacco leaves &amp;
                    recited part of the Book of Revelations till her voice got tired &amp; then said the names of all the books of the Bible in about one
                    minute - rattling them off fast as she could speak - Her memory is not good - for the present &amp; recent past - but says she
                    can recall everything that happened long ago - Couldn't remember Miss Evelyn at all! But let me tell you more about her house - 
                    Around the fireplace is room for settin&apos; but all the rest is full &amp; even from the ceiling are hanging many bags of herbs
                    &amp; all sorts of things done up - some little tables fill up one space between fireplace &amp; door where I imagine she keeps
                    her dishes &amp; eats - the opposite side was <del>where</del>
					<add place="supralinear">for</add> her wood pile - 
                    corn &amp; tobacco. A clay pipe lay on an iron kettle by the fire which she soon tucked out of sight! The rest of the room was filled up
                    by two beds covered with boxes &amp; bundles - innumerable hat boxes were stacked together - a spinning wheel - some more tables - 
                    well I just can&apos;t tell you more definitely now - but am going again &amp; will get more impressions. In a tree outside - up high
                    <unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">ther</unclear> were ears of corn fastened in rows on a stick drying - said she didn&apos;t know where
                    else to put them. When we left she picked a bunch of chrysanthemums exactly like our pink ones only white. Oh yes we found some 
                    persimmons - Do you like them? Spent a quick evening with books and papers - Tonight went for chestnuts with the Huff girls - Litha Carr &amp; 
                    Birthana McCarter - got just a few - then Litha &amp; I went over to Birthana&apos;s &amp; called. The four McCarters are living just a little ways up 
                    the Roaring Fork road so they can go to school. Such nice people as they all are. Emily &amp; Evelyn blew down to Sevierville right after 
                    school - so had supper with Aunt Lizzie - Litha &amp; I have been studying the stars this evening - am beginning to learn a few constellations. 
                    This is about the shortest letter I&apos;ve sent home isn&apos;t it? But it comes with loads of love as ever.
                </p>
				<p>
                    Ruth.
                </p>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
