<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03020011000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[Letter]  Sept. 17, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
				<author>
					<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
				</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
					<name>Carter, Genny</name>
					<name>Lepcyzk, Tim</name>
					<name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
				<address>
					<addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
			 </addrLine>
					<addrLine>556 Parkway
		  	</addrLine>
					<addrLine>PO Box 567
		  	</addrLine>
					<addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
		  	</addrLine>
				</address>
				<date>2006</date>
				<idno type="SPCID">arm03020011000</idno>
				<availability>
					<p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. 
						For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee 
						Libraries, Knoxville, TN</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from which the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
				<bibl>
					<title>[Letter]  Sep. 17, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
					<date value="1919-09-17">Sep. 17, 1919</date>
					<author>
						<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
					</author>
					<extent>9p</extent>
					<note type="summary">Sunbonnet drill for the fair. Plans for a week end trip over the Smokies into <abbr expan="North">No.</abbr> Carolina. Troubles of our <hi1 rend="underscore">handy</hi1>
						<hi1 rend="underscore"> man</hi1> and his wife</note>
					<note type="box">3</note>
					<note type="folder">2</note>
					<note type="document">arm03020011000</note>
				</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
			</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<bibl>
						<title>Local Subject Headings</title>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<list>
						<item>People</item>
						<item>Girls</item>
						<item>Activities</item>
						<item>Social life</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div1 type="abstract">
				<pb ref="arm03020011001" seq="01"/>
				<list>
					<item>Sunbonnet drill for the fair.</item>
					<item>Plans for a week end trip over the Smokies into <abbr expan="North">No.</abbr> Carolina. </item>
					<item>Troubles of our <hi1 rend="underscore">handy</hi1> <hi1 rend="underscore"> man</hi1> and his wife</item>
				</list>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="letter">
				<pb ref="arm03020011002" seq="02"/>
				<head>
					<date value="1919-09-17"> Sept. 17, 1919</date>
				</head>
				<p>Dearest family <del>It&apos;s 8:30 p.m. and I&apos;m <hi1 rend="underscore">all</hi1> ready for 
                    bed except to bid you a fond good night in a few scribbling lines.</del> Jane&apos;s long letter
                    came yesterday (Tuesday) mailed just a week ago today - Just think six days to get
                    here.
					<del>Am glad Mabel and Jo are finally settled and hope that they soon get into 
                    permanent quarters together. Give my love to Victoria &amp; her mother when you meet them. 
                    Hope <abbr expan="Victoria">V.</abbr> get along in school without any more sicknesses. 
                    The babies must be awfully sweet but <unclear reason="illegible" resp="tl">Wein</unclear> is
                    too big for that <unclear reason="illegible" resp="tl">appellation</unclear>. Is he going to kindergarten?
                    Hope so. Perhaps now you can rest on your oars a little both of you - you &amp; Jane - for your 
                        letters have been exceedingly full of activity.</del>
				</p>
				<pb ref="arm03020011003" seq="03 "/>
				<p>Though I wrote you Sunday night it seems as though there is so much 
                to write again - not anything exciting as yet however - Monday I put in part of the day on my two drills for the 
                coming fair but as so many youngsters are out again have almost decided to give up one of the older 
                boys and girls having just the sunbonnet drill of twelve girls. They are dressed <hi1 rend="underscore">backwards</hi1> 
                - bonnets - shawls - aprons &amp; skirts - but the top of the bonnet being thin they see perfectly - march how 
					to go through maneuvers so that it will all look as <add place="supralinear">tho</add> <abbr expan="though">tho</abbr>
                they were doing it <hi1 rend="underscore">backwards.</hi1> Then one of the girls in the neighborhood Lulu May 
                McCarter who has been teaching &amp; is getting ready to go away to school came over to 
						<del>school </del> have me help her get a tele -<pb ref="arm03020011004" seq="04" n="02"/> gram 
                through to Knoxville. We fooled around here at the house unsuccessfully an hour or more &amp; finally strolled with Emily 
                up to the Huff&apos;s where we found some of them including Mrs. <abbr expan="Huff">H.</abbr> picking beans 
                (Beans are planted in the corn fields you know &amp; its now time to get them in since the corn fodder is pulled &amp; 
                also the season for making sorghum) we went over to their house where Mrs. Huff got the message through &amp; 
                then we sat in the big swing on the porch picked beans &amp; ate apples until about six. It was dark before 
                we finished supper and spent the evening quietly in the lamplight with my lessons &amp; papers to correct. The 
					weather is hot again &amp; am glad to have thin dresses to wear. Tuesday was another busy <pb ref="arm03020011005" seq="05"/>day. 
                We girls decided to have a picnic up on the top of Pi Phi hill that night with Mr. Cresswell so after school Emily got the lunch ready 
                as the rest of us were busy. Abbie &amp; I with most of the girls in drill made sunbonnets from paper &amp; thin white 
                material. Aunt Lizzie, Mrs. Proffitt &amp; Harrison came over to the sewing room also &amp; got busy setting up 
                the old loom which had been lying in its seperate parts ever since its return from the fair at Columbus this summer. 
                Then as the little girl Arlena Maples who sweeps my room was absent I got the other two sweepers Maud Clabo and 
					Ethel Carr to help me clean it up and then by that time left for the <pb ref="arm03020011006" seq="06" n="03"/>house where we 
                were soon assembled with 2 baskets - pail of water - frying pan - flashlight &amp; headed up Pi Phi lane We turned 
                directly off from it &amp; went right up till we got to the top in about ten minutes. Here was a comparitively open space 
                we spread out the couch cover which I insisted on bringing &amp; Mr. C. made up a big bonfire. Pine branches burn so 
                beautifully. In the course of time we started the coffee &amp; spread out our frugal lunch - fried eggs - biscuit - weimis 
                peanut butter - pimento cheese - chocolate bars &amp; coffee. Our new Jersey cow provides us with lovely cream so the 
					coffee is delicious &amp; the butter too. In our conversation we <pb ref="arm03020011007" seq="07"/>got to talking about our much
                postponed mountain trip and finally made up our minds to go this Friday! Start right after school with Dan &amp; the hack 
                drive as far as possible &amp; then leave them. We will have just blankets &amp; provisions with us so bad weather will 
                put an end to our festivities. Mr. C. went up to Tom Camel&apos;s after school to find out if he&apos;d take us &amp; sure enough he 
                will he and his <hi1 rend="underscore">two</hi1> hounds! Then Emily &amp; I went up to Lucrettie Reagan&apos;s after supper tonight 
                and asked her mother to go with us as <hi1 rend="underscore">chaperone</hi1>! If she doesn&apos;t go for she is not certain as 
					Mr. Reagan thinks he needs her although she&apos;s wild to go with us we may go regardless we three <pb ref="arm03020011008" seq="08" n="04"/>
                maidens &amp; Mr. Cresswell with Tom Camel. Evelyn isn&apos;t back &amp; probably wouldn&apos;t go any way Besides I warned her we&apos;d 
                celebrate in her absence!</p>
				<p>Then besides all this excitement there has been more about Mary &amp; Marshall.  Monday night every thing was supposedly 
                    lovely he had withdrawn his suit for divorce &amp; wanted her to go to Washington D.C. with him after withdrawing her cross suit. 
                    Well she went to Seveirville Tuesday to have her lawyer withdraw it &amp; on her return here learned that Marshall had skipped 
					out &amp; left orders at the stores not to credit her with anything so <pb ref="arm03020011009" seq="09"/>here she is deserted! I wrote 
                    a letter for her today to send her lawyer asking him about it Poor woman wonder what the next turn will be.</p>
				<p>Must cease this scribble One more joyful item we will have to have our party for the school youngsters tomorrow night since 
                    we won&apos;t be here Friday also pack!</p>
				<p>Will write again in a few days</p>
				<p>With loads of love to each &amp; all</p>
				<p>Ruth.</p>
				<p>Wednesday Sept. 17.</p>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
