<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03030006000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[Letter]  Oct. 22, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
				<author>
					<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
				</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
					<name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
					<name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
				<address>
					<addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
				</address>
				<date>2006</date>
				<idno type="SPCID">arm03030006000</idno>
				<availability>
					<p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from whi1ch the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
				<bibl>
					<title>[Letter]  Oct. 22, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
					<date value="1919-10-22">Oct. 22, 1919</date>
					<author>
						<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
					</author>
					<extent>4p</extent>
					<note type="summary">Lunch time at the school.</note>
					<note type="box">3</note>
					<note type="folder">3</note>
					<note type="document">arm03030006000</note>
				</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
			</projectDesc>
		<editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<bibl>
						<title>Local Subject Headings</title>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<list>
						<item>Living conditions</item>
						<item>People</item>
						<item>Students</item>
						<item>Home visits</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div1 type="abstract">
				<pb ref="arm03030006001" seq="01"/>
				<p>
					<list>
						<item>Lunch time at the school.</item>
					</list>
				</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="letter">
				<pb ref="arm03030006002" seq="02"/>
				<head>
					<date value="1919-10-22">Oct. 22, 1919</date>
				</head>
				<p>
                        Dearest Jane - Your letter came this rainy noon with one from Uncle Art and as I&apos;m in the mood for scribbling will dart off a few 
                        lines here on some cushions in front of the fireplace - Emily upstairs in bed reading Shakespeare - Evelyn down at Sevierville &amp; 
                        coming back to this room - Aunt Lizzie knitting away on her stocking - and two of the school girls playing &quot;Authors&quot; in the corner. 
                        They are <hi1 rend="underscore">V</hi1>eatrice Parton &amp; <hi1 rend="underscore">Birth</hi1>ana McCarcter caught by the rain - Birthana 
                        is one of my special McCarters and a dear girl - She could have been home but some of the youngsters had been teasing her so that after 
                        school I found her crying &amp; brought her home. We have our troubles in school of course - Abbie&apos;s girls are usually at the bottom too. 
                        The McCarter girls are so hard working &amp; have such good stuff in them they will amount to something some day I know - Cora was here 
                        last week and you remember. This noon they all boys &amp; girls too were playing &quot;Farmer in the Dell&quot; in the hall &amp; having 
                        the best time. Two of the older girls practice at noon time - Most of them bring their lunches you know so that it&apos;s a lively place from 
                        <pb ref="arm03030006003" seq="03"/>12 to 1 - Lucrettie Reagan gave me instructions when I left for lunch to hurry back so I could help her with 
                        U.S. History as she couldn&apos;t answer &quot;nary a question&quot;. The little ones always are asking - &quot;Is it time for 
                        <hi1 rend="underscore">books</hi1>? (meaning <hi1 rend="underscore">school</hi1>) When I ask a question in class many a time they will 
                        put up their hands &amp; shake them violently saying under their breath - &quot;Let me - let me!&quot; I love my writing class of Abbie&apos;s 
                        youngsters - I told you didn&apos;t I? That mondays &amp; wednesdays they are in my room from 2:15 to 3:00 - while mine are in domestic 
                        science &amp; manual training. They work so hard with the arm movements - some of them stick out their tongues so far! Then Tuesdays 
                        &amp; Thursdays at the same hour I have drawing with mine. They have been printing a <unclear reason="illegible" resp="tl">motto</unclear> 
                        which looks pretty well. 
                    </p>
				<p>
                        Yesterday was an uncertain sort of a day - after school just as I got to the house Evelyn came down the steps bag in hand - hat &amp; coat. 
                        &quot;Sevierville?&quot; I asked. &quot;Yes&quot; - she said - &quot;Dr. Massey came up this way so am going in &amp; back tomorrow - 
                        come on <del>as</del> ways.&quot; Dawn at the foot of <pb ref="arm03030006004" seq="04"/>our road was the old Ford run 
                        about &amp; Dr. Massey - Emily went along too. He is such a big man - but we all piled in. I sat on the floor with the door swinging open so that 
                        my fair feet could rest on the running board. We went up the Roaring Fork road to the ford - (where I took the picture of the youngsters) - as he was 
                        going back via <hi1 rend="underscore">Booger</hi1> Town!
                    </p>
				<p>
                        Lulu May McCarter&apos;s family live near the ford so we alighted after a delightfully muddy jolty ride of a mile or more &amp; made a short call - 
                        I had a letter from Lulu May who is away at school in Ohio &amp; wanted to tell them about it. We stopped at the hotel on the way back to see 
                        Josie Trentham a girl who works there &amp; ask her to tell fortunes at our Halloween party. Mr. Huff arrived just as we were leaving so he 
                        brought us back in his Ford to the foot of the lane again. Oh yes - we met a soldier lad just back from a year in France on his way home up Roaring 
                        Fork about six miles. He stopped &amp; talked with us quite a spell - so pleased to see <abbr expan="the United States of America">U.S.A.</abbr> 
                        again. Imagine he is some changed mountain boy all right. Today I haven&apos;t done much besides teach - got home late &amp; found Emily 
                        making fudge &amp; Aunt Lizzie starting supper - Dashed off a letter to the Glasier&apos;s &amp; had supper about <hi1 rend="underscore">five</hi1>! 
                        Abbie came in to get some candy &amp; visit - There is so much coming &amp; going &amp; <hi1 rend="underscore">talking</hi1> (Evelyn is 
                        an inveterate talker) that the time sometimes is <hi1 rend="underscore">frittered</hi1> away. She didn&apos;t get back from Sevierville after all. 
                        Have had to play for assembly several times lately and do not particularly enjoy it. <del>We wish you could come for a visit! 
                            Couldn&apos;t <hi1 rend="underscore">we</hi1> manage it? Was interested in the <hi1 rend="underscore">clippings</hi1> - and hope to hear 
                            about Aurora Club &amp; University - Club doings soon. It&apos;s all right about the Arrow as you very well know! Send it to me some time soon. 
                            Know the youngsters must be darling - Had such a nice letter from Nellie yesterday - the coats are lovely. To try swimming! I had to laugh when 
                            I read it - it goes to prove what a <hi1 rend="underscore">modern</hi1> grandmother you are doesn&apos;t it? Give my fond regards to Miss 
                            Paucost! Am glad you have started to fix the house - Hope pa has finally received my letters - said none had come the last I heard from him - 
                            one should have been there the time he first arrived -</del>
				</p>
				<p>
                        Lots &amp; lots of love to you
                    </p>
				<p>
                        Ruth
                    </p>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
