<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03030021000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[Letter]  Nov. 23, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
				<author>
					<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
				</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
					<name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
					<name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
				<address>
					<addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
				</address>
				<date>2006</date>
				<idno type="SPCID">arm03030021000</idno>
				<availability>
					<p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from which the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
				<bibl>
					<title>[Letter]  Nov. 23, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
					<date value="1919-11-23">Nov. 23, 1919</date>
					<author>
						<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
					</author>
					<extent>4p</extent>
					<note type="summary">Description of <abbr expan="Baptist Young Person&apos;s Union">B.Y.P.U.</abbr> services and those of the church - Pledges by 
                    members - Pig killed - Routine affairs</note>
					<note type="box">3</note>
					<note type="folder">3</note>
					<note type="document">arm03030021000</note>
				</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
			</projectDesc>
		<editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<bibl>
						<title>Local Subject Headings</title>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<list>
						<item>Living conditions</item>
						<item>Livestock</item>
						<item>People</item>
						<item>Religion</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div1 type="abstract">
				<pb ref="arm03030021001" seq="01"/>
				<p>
					<list>
						<item>Description of <abbr expan="Baptist Young Person&apos;s Union">B.Y.P.U.</abbr> services and those of the church - </item>
						<item>Pledges by members</item>
						<item>Pig killed</item>
						<item>Routine affairs</item>
					</list>
				</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="letter">
				<pb ref="arm03030021002" seq="02"/>
				<head>
					<date value="1919-11-23">Nov. 23, 1919</date>
					</head>
				<p>
                    Dearest Jane - As usual this is Sunday night &amp; after <abbr expan="Baptist Young Person&apos;s Union">B.Y.P.</abbr> - Mabel said in 
                    her letter that I was always coming <add place="supralinear">from</add> or going to <abbr expan="Baptist Young Person&apos;s Union">B.Y.P.</abbr>
                    This has been a long day of <hi1 rend="underscore">Christian</hi1>
					<hi1 rend="underscore">duty</hi1> as you will see - when I tell you that I spent
                    three solid hours at the &quot;church-house&quot; this <abbr expan="morning">a.m.</abbr> &amp; went to <abbr expan="Baptist Young Person&apos;s Union">B.Y.</abbr>
                    for over an hour tonight. Poor Emily did the same - only had her own particular <abbr expan="Baptist Young Person&apos;s Union">B.Y.</abbr> in the
                    <abbr expan="afternoon">p.m.</abbr> besides - I really enjoyed the sermon this morning - it was by a Mr. Conner a man who used to preach here at
                    one time and a real character but <del>about</del> the most broad minded individual any of us know who is connected with the 
                    Baptist Church. The Southern Baptists are trying to raise 75 million by the 7th of next month &amp; Gatlinburg&apos;s quota is <hi1 rend="underscore">&#36;700</hi1>!
                    &#36; 249 was pledged this morning <pb ref="arm03030021003" seq="03"/> and the church was not more than a third full at that! It is rather hard work getting
                    them started but imagine that they will come through with the full amount eventually.
                </p>
				<p>
                    It&apos;s awfully windy this dark night but not very cold - Can you picture us all trailing over to the school single file each with an unlighted lamp in her
                    hand &amp; back again - The schoolroom (mine) filled up before it was over &amp; imagine about sixty were there as many sat two together. Betty Russell
                    one of the girls was leader - about half a dozen topics from the Quarterly were briefly discussed by different boys &amp; girls - most of them in school - 
                    We sang several hymns - I read the Thanksgiving Proclamation &amp; made a few remarks - quite the thing for us to get up &amp; talk - you know - 
                    about every so often. <pb ref="arm03030021004" seq="04"/>
				</p>
				<p>
                    After this we came home and had our lunch around the library table in front of the fireplace just as we do home - Emily &amp; I got it for fun - cold biscuits - 
                    <del>jelly</del> - roast pork - blackberry jam &amp; tea - Evelyn&apos;s pig was killed yesterday - 273 <abbr expan="pounds">lbs</abbr>,
                    &amp; perfectly wonderful pork as it makes - Aunt Lizzie &amp; Mrs. <sic corr="Proffitt">Profitt</sic> worked over it all day after the men killed it.
                </p>
				<p>
                    We were busy as usual doing the Saturday tasks &amp; in the <abbr expan="afternoon">p.m.</abbr> made some calls - really looking for a rattlesnake skin
                    to use in the play - which we didn&apos;t get but found out where one can be - We also explored a perfect little &quot;holler&quot; with a deserted cabin in
                    the middle of it. Spent the evening making three Puritan hats of paper for the boys - 
                </p>
				<p>
                    Friday was a full day as I guess I told you it would be - dinner party &amp; debate in the evening. 
                </p>
				<p>
                    It&apos;s over an hour since I started this epistle as Miss Langmaid who was writing also at the other end of the table has been telling me of some of the 
                    difficulties of the early days of the school - so have been rather incoherent in spots haven&apos;t I?
                </p>
				<p><del>
                    What are <gap reason="illegible" resp="bds"/> for Christmas &amp; can&apos;t realize it is so close at hand - Have not heard from you since last 
                    Monday &amp; hope all has been well with you - I know you are busy as you always find something to do!</del>
                </p>
				<p><del>
                    Will cease for now &amp; dash off a scribble to pa - </del>
                </p>
				<p><del>
                    With just lots &amp; lots of love to you and all - </del>
                </p>
				<p><del>
                    Ruth - </del>
                </p>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
