<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03020010000">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[Letter]  Sept. 14, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
                    <name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
                    <name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
                </address>
                <date>2006</date>
                <idno type="SPCID">arm03020010000</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. 
                        For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee 
                        Libraries, Knoxville, TN</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from which the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
                <bibl>
                    <title>[Letter]  Sept. 14, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                    <date value="1919-09-14">Sept. 14, 1919</date>
                    <author>
                        <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                    </author>
                    <extent>17p</extent>
                    <note type="summary">Go to shivaree up Wildcat Holler - Miss Turner&apos;s visit - All night at the Maples&apos; home - Visit at Sevierville</note>
                    <note type="box">3</note>
                    <note type="folder">2</note>
                    <note type="document">arm03020010000</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Local Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <list>
                        <item>Social events</item>
                        <item>School activities</item>
                        <item>Sports</item>
                        <item>Social life</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="abstract">
                <pb ref="arm03020010001" seq="01"/>
                <list>
                    <item>Go to shivaree up Wildcat Holler -</item>
                    <item>Miss Turner&apos;s visit -</item>
                    <item>All night at the Maples&apos; home -</item>
                    <item>Visit at Sevierville</item>
                </list>
                </div1>
            <div1 type="letter">
                <pb ref="arm03020010002" seq="02"/>
                <head>
                    <date value="1919-09-14"> Sept. 14, 1919</date>
                </head>
                <p>
                    Dearest family one and all - <del>Pa&apos;s letter written the 4th and mailed the <hi1 rend="underscore">6th</hi1> is the last news I&apos;ve had - From
                        you all - I hope you don&apos;t consider me a pill about writing for its just a week ago today since I wrote you!</del> It has been a busy week and will have to 
                    consult my daylogue about it - but first let me say that <del>pa you must take a trip somewhere just as soon as you get the house
                    fixed up - am curious to know where you will go after you sell it! Was pleased to get the papers and read about institute etc. Miss Chesney sent me a 
                    nice postal not long ago &amp; also had one from Miss Sillix that was sent from <unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">Miagona</unclear> Falls. Some of
                        the girls thought Mr. </del><pb ref="arm03020010003" seq="03"></pb><del>Sherman might be the new principal - hope he suits! Wonder where Mrs. French went.</del>     
                </p>
                <p>
                <del>
                        Some time could you pick out about a dozen of those old photogravures of ours and send them to me? Brought a few but 
                        would really like some more in the room. I have cut off part of the extremely wide margin leaving it about three inches wide and they look much better. 
                        Will leave the selection to the good judgement of you all!
                </del>   
                </p>
                    <p>
                        <del>Your party Jane sounded very nice - What did you wear? Where will Miss Hartman live this winter? Has Jo come and is Mabel with you or not? 
                            When she leaves I&apos;ll </del><pb ref="arm03020010004" seq="04" n="2"></pb> <del>sure write her some letters.</del> Yes I&apos;ve half a dozen small baskets the same
                        kind as that I&apos;m holding in the picture with Mrs. <sic corr="Campbell">Camel</sic>. Hope to find some others &amp; a coverlet - but such things are 
                        very scarce it seems. As to the race riots - they were very serious and the merchants estimated their losses at about 15 million. However I must confess that
                        I seldom see more than the headlines of the paper &amp; often not even that. There are no colored people whatsoever in Gatlinburg - though there seem to be
                        a number in Sevierville. It&apos;s perfectly safe here - no one locks their doors. Our screens are latched at night but the doors and windows are left wide
                        open. By the way did I ever tell you that the hangings in the dining room are exactly like ours? Not nearly so pretty with<pb ref="arm03020010005" seq="05"></pb>
                        <del>the chestnut wood which is in a perfectly natural state as the ivory!</del>
                    </p>
                <p>
                    <del>Your trip sounds fine and think you all are becoming quite wonderful drivers without me! Wonder if I&apos;ll have the nerve to drive
                    when I get home? Have not the slightest wish to attempt it on <hi1 rend="underscore">these</hi1> roads. Started a long letter to Jo last Sunday but as I 
                    did not finish it - will wind up by sending it to Gretta as I want Charlotte to see it - have written about some things to <abbr expan="Charlotte">C.</abbr>
                    &amp; the others to the Thomlins so they can exchange.</del>
                </p>
                <p>
                    This is Sunday eve, about 7:45 by Gatlinburg time - which is <hi1 rend="underscore">sun</hi1> time you know - any sitting in the living room in the light 
                    of the big Rochester lamp - Aunt Lizzie <add place="supralinear">(Housekeeper)</add> is rocking away on the other <pb ref="arm03020010006" seq="06" n="3"></pb>
                    side of the table occasionally spitting as she is a dipper of snuff you know. Her eyes bother her so she is just swaying back &amp; forth &amp; watching
                    little Rellie who is on the seat near the fireplace looking at a magazine &amp; chattering away about everything he sees. His mother Mary went with
                    Abbie &amp; Emily to <abbr expan="Baptist Young Person&apos;s Union">B.Y.P.</abbr> tonight - Evelyn <add place="supralinear">Head of School"</add> is gone
                    again - went to Sevierville Thursday morning &amp; by this time is in southern Alabama. She went Saturday morning with Blanche Mass<add place="supralinear">e</add>y
                    Wood - &amp; the two youngsters - Blanche has been visiting her people all summer you know. She &amp; Evelyn are old pals &amp; as someone had to help her
                    go home &amp; none of the Masseys felt that they could leave - they offered to pay Evelyn&apos;s expenses - so she is gone for a week.
                    <pb ref="arm03020010007" seq="07"></pb>
                </p>
                <p>
                    We girls told her not to worry about things here that we&apos;d celebrate her absence every day somehow! This has sure been a week of festivity! Monday
                    we got a new cow in the <abbr expan="afternoon">p.m.</abbr> a very nice Jersey &amp; in the <abbr expan="evening">eve.</abbr> went to a 
                    <hi1 rend="underscore">shivaree!</hi1> One of my girls Flora Reagan has a sister who was married just a week ago &amp; the young people got up the affair
                    in their honor. Abbie Evelyn &amp; I went with three of the school girls and a dozen or more youths. Lillard Maples took us girls in his Ford three miles
                    up to the Forks of the river the boys meanwhile having started to walk. Then Lillard went back &amp; brought them all up. It was a most glorious balmy
                    night fulll moon &amp; so warm that no wraps were <pb ref="arm03020010008" seq="08" n="4"></pb> needed though we brought them along in case -
                </p>
                <p>
                    We turned off the main road and went toward a mountain crossing a creek first &amp; leaving the car started on foot up the steepest trail along
                    the <abbr expan="mountain">mt.</abbr> side. It wound along up &amp; up &amp; soon I learned that we were going up <hi1 rend="underscore">Wildcat</hi1>
                    <hi1 rend="underscore">Holler</hi1>! Wasn&apos;t that delicious? At last we came to the top or near it where was a little clearing (called
                    <hi1 rend="underscore">Dry</hi1> <hi1 rend="underscore">Pond</hi1>) &amp; a large cabin. We stopped &amp; assembling our forces proceeded to march
                    round &amp; round shouting - blowing ox horns - ring<del>s</del> cow-bells - sheep bells &amp; I know not what. My noise was
                    produced by clapping together two tin pan covers - Then some sticks of dynamite were set off - By this time strange to say the cabin was astir &amp;
                    eventually the bridegroom was hauled <pb ref="arm03020010009" seq="09"></pb> out &amp; ridden around on a fence rail. We girls went inside &amp; such a place!
                    The married couple were at his brother&apos;s and I guess about a dozen people slept in beds in the two rooms we were in - It was a pathetic honeymoon 
                    to us girls - the bride is a bright pretty girl whom Mrs. Helmick has been anxious to help with her education &amp; for whom she made plans when here - but
                    Allie all the time had it in her mind to be married but with nary a word to any one. Next she was given a ride around &amp; after &quot;settin&apos;&quot;
                    awhile we started for home. It was really harder going down Wildcat Holler than coming up - We were pleased to get in the little car again &amp; buzz
                    home where we arrived tired dirty &amp; full of giggles - Tuesday Mrs. Hall &amp; Miss Turner came <pb ref="arm03020010010" seq="10" n="5"></pb> over from the
                    hotel &amp; spent the balmy moonlight <abbr expan="evening">eve.</abbr> on the porch. Wednesday Emily Abbie &amp; I go with Dan &amp; the hack with the
                    two Maples boys Ephraim &amp; Rellie in my room <del>it</del> &amp; the youngest brother Bruce in Abbie&apos;s to their home four
                    miles from here on Fightin&apos; Creek. This is the place where Emily &amp; I went one evening long ago in the car &amp; found them all in bed. Do you
                    remember? They visited cheerfully with us as they were &amp; then got up &amp; fed us watermelon. Well this time we were expected for dinner and the night.
                    Mr. Maples is a mail carrier besides having  the usual farm. He has twenty-six miles of <hi1 rend="underscore">mountain</hi1> rural delivery which takes
                    about eight hours each day! They are very nice people &amp; have a real house - <pb ref="arm03020010011" seq="11"></pb>We had the whole upstairs to ourselves - 
                    two bedrooms in each of which were two double beds - but besides a chair and washstand that was all. Life consists of essentials only in all these
                    houses - 
                </p>
                <p>
                    We each took one of the beds but in spite of the many feathers Abbie &amp; I slept very little - don&apos;t know why but don&apos;t believe I got in
                    more than a couple of hours. Then we arose about 6 &amp; by 7 had started for school arriving at 7:45. That morning of all times Miss Turner decides
                    to visit school &amp; brings three fair ladies from the hotel with her. However in spite of my dirty white &amp; sleepy apperance got along all right
                    for she afterwards commented on my <hi1 rend="underscore">neat</hi1> appearance &amp; the good work we were all doing everywhere. Such is life!
                    <pb ref="arm03020010012" seq="12" n="6"></pb>
                </p>
                <p>
                    She visited us in the evening again - Emily &amp; I were real naughtly though. Aunt Lizzie told us that she left word she&apos;d be over but as Evelyn
                    had stayed here the night before expecting her &amp; giving up going to Maples with us as was originally planned - only to be disappointed we went off
                    for a walk. Had a very early supper &amp; went up the Mill Creek road &amp; branching off took a steep rocky path down to the river road &amp; so home
                    again - about a two mile walk. It was exactly 7:10 when we arrived &amp; of course Miss Turner was waiting for us on the porch with Aunt Lizzie. We
                    like her but she is so full of searching &amp; probing questions about the school &amp; people that it&apos;s somewhat wearing. Evelyn took her up Tom
                    <sic corr="Campbell">Camel</sic>&apos;s trail Wednesday morning &amp; got <pb ref="arm03020010013" seq="13"></pb> home quite fagged in mind as well as body.
                </p>
                <p>
                    To continue - Friday was the day of the Bishop&apos;s party for the Murphy College faculty &amp; as we all were asked we went down that 
                    <abbr expan="afternoon">p.m.</abbr> right after school - that is - Mr. Cresswell - Emily &amp; I - Abbie stayed here - Evelyn had gone the day before. Mary
                    asked me to take her &quot;cross bill&quot; in to her lawyer &amp; ask him about some things. All of which I did as soon as we got to Sevierville - then
                    Emily &amp; I went up to the Bishops&apos; &amp; helped with the preparation for the party. We had an early supper winding up with lemon pie topped off
                    with huge slices of watermelon. About eight we were all dressed (I in my new tan wool) &amp; people began coming. There <pb ref="arm03020010014" seq="14" n="7"></pb>
                    were seven tables of us &amp; we played progressive hearts - with cubes - quite fun - Started out very nicely with Mr. Cresswell - his brother
                    and Miss Whittle - She is such a dear! Progressed nine times out of the twelve which was unusually good for me - but didn&apos;t encounter Emily
                    all evening. Then we had the most delicious chicken patties - olives &amp; sandwiches - followed by cake and layer icecream and coffee. As the
                    Sevierville lights go out at ten we finished by lamplight quite early. Then next after all had gone we cleared up everything &amp; washed the dishes.
                    Next morning instead of getting up &amp; writing this letter &amp; darning as I had planned I simply lay in bed - wasn&apos;t that an act of laziness? 
                    But really felt like <pb ref="arm03020010015" seq="15"></pb> that &amp; nothing else so did it. <del>Sat</del> In the
                    <abbr expan="afternoon">p.m.</abbr> we had to go to the baseball game - as Gatlinburg played Murphy College - score 16 to 3 - <hi1 rend="underscore">not</hi1>
                    in our favor - wasn&apos;t that awful - the field is just across the street from the depot &amp; the college building. We sat on a bench in the hot sun
                    the only Gatlinburgers. All of the team didn&apos;t come down either &amp; they had to fill out with Sevierville-ites - most of them are school boys - Mr.
                    <abbr expan="Cresswell">C.</abbr> is catcher for them. Murphy College they say will be here to play in a couple of weeks. 
                </p>
                <p>
                    We got back in Mr. Huff&apos;s car about 5:30 most pleased to return too &amp; glad to go to bed early after the strenuous weekend. This morning Abbie &amp;
                    I went to Sunday School &amp; between <pb ref="arm03020010016" seq="16" n="8"></pb> us managed to teach Evelyn&apos;s large class of girls - Wore my tan dress today
                    as it has been cool - in spite of the bright sun. Some of the hotel people about a dozen escorted by Miss Turner came over to see the school and the
                    house &amp; were charmed with everything. We girls made out our fair program which comes off the 25th &amp; planned a party here at the house for Friday
                    night. Darned up my stockings which was some job - read a little &amp; wrote a little &amp; now its about 9:15 &amp; time for bed.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <del>Am sending my travelling check which came </del><pb ref="arm03020010017" seq="17"></pb><del>for travelling expenses - and Jane will you put in bank with
                    yours &amp; pay my January insurance with it? Please - Then the &#36;14 which will be left can go on postage for things I&apos;ve
                    sent for and pay for that book of games etc.</del>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <del>Will close now - with just loads of love to you all as ever - </del>
                </p>
                <p>
                    Ruth.
                </p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>