<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03030010000">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[Letter]  Oct. 30, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] Tacoma Alumnae Club</title>
				<author>
					<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
				</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
					<name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
					<name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
				<address>
					<addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
					<addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
				</address>
				<date>2006</date>
				<idno type="SPCID">arm03030010000</idno>
				<availability>
					<p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, TN.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from which the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
				<bibl>
					<title>[Letter]  Oct. 30, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] Tacoma Alumnae Club</title>
					<date value="1919-10-30">Oct. 30, 1919</date>
					<author>
						<name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
					</author>
					<extent>10p</extent>
					<note type="summary">Letter to Tacoma alumnae (Inez Smith Soule Alumnae Club - Mr. Cresswell &amp; Mrs. Proffitt move from Maple Cottage 
                    to the Stewart Cottage Boys&apos; dormitory</note>
					<note type="box">3</note>
					<note type="folder">3</note>
					<note type="document">arm03030010000</note>
				</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
			</projectDesc>
		<editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<bibl>
						<title>Local Subject Headings</title>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<list>
						<item>Living Conditions</item>
						<item>Social life</item>
						<item>School programs</item>
						<item>Baskets</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div1 type="abstract">
				<pb ref="arm03030010001" seq="01"/>
				<p>
					<list>
						<item>Letter to Tacoma alumnae (Inez Smith Soule Alumnae Club).</item>
						<item>Mr. Cresswell &amp; Mrs. Proffit move from Maple Cottage to the Stewart Cottage Boys&apos; dormitory</item>
					</list>
				</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="letter">
				<pb ref="arm03030010002" seq="02"/>
				<head>
					<date value="1919-10-30">Oct. 30, 1919</date>
				</head>
				<p>
                    Dear Sister Pi Phis -
                </p>
				<p>
                    What time do you suppose it is and what are we all doing this Thursday evening? It&apos;s 7:45 and all have <hi1 rend="underscore">gone</hi1>
					<hi1 rend="underscore">to</hi1>
					<hi1 rend="underscore">bed</hi1> - not only in this house but all over the <abbr expan="Gatlinburg">burg</abbr>.
                    But when you consider the fact that nearly everyone is up before daylight these early hours are not quite so surprising.
                </p>
				<p>
                    This has been a most strenuous week and fear I may not be very clear and lucid at intervals while composing this epistle! Emily Burton and I 
                    spent the weekend in Knoxville - Monday had to make out grades for papers and report cards - Tuesday get off a letter for the Arrow (an awful
                    ment-<pb ref="arm03030010003" seq="03"/>al strain) Wednesday prepare for a debate in the evening and today wind up things for our <hi1 rend="underscore">
                        Halloween</hi1>
					<hi1 rend="underscore">Party</hi1> tomorrow night. A Miss Freeman (Iowa Alpha) arrived for short visit today. In between had to
                    have a club meeting with the girls - go to a corn husking and make a call up Baskin&apos;s Creek - 
                </p>
				<p>
                    So you see if I don&apos;t write individually and thank you for your letters - books for <abbr expan="Christmas">Xmas</abbr> programs - wooden
                    toys etc. it&apos;s because of the short days up here. I did so enjoy the letters from Lida, Nellie May, Harrich and Charlotte - and in the course of
                    time shall answer each with appropriate observations. <pb ref="arm03030010004" seq="04"/>
				</p>
				<p>
                    The principal reason for my not having said anything about baskets is because they are so scarce - The chief basket maker died last summer and
                    others do not take much interest as it&apos;s hard work and little pay. Evelyn has so many many orders now that she can&apos;t fill - much as she 
                    would like to. Perhaps things will work out later on. We have talked about putting it (basket making) into the school but there seem to be about as
                    many reasons <hi1 rend="underscore">for</hi1>
					<hi1 rend="underscore">not</hi1> doing it as <hi1 rend="underscore">for</hi1> - Miss Langmaid the head
                    of the committee in charge of the school as you no doubt observed in the last Arrow arrives here Saturday for a visit of two months and as her visit
                    has long been anticipated many things have been consequently &quot;hanging five.&quot; It does take so long to get things done up here - for the 
                    atmosphere is so peaceful - like that the spirit of progress sort of dies out and one grows content with things as they are. For instance one of the 
                    chapters sent us dishes months and months ago and they are ambling around somewhere in Tennessee yet for notice came after they had been 
                    given up for lost - Meanwhile our cupboard is growing emptier day by day <hi1 rend="underscore">almost</hi1> - company causes a great planning so
                    <pb ref="arm03030010005" seq="05" n="02"/> that the meal will suit the scanty supply of dishes - Soup and cereals have to be eaten in cups and tumblers - 
                    dinner plates are served three times a day - and every so often you draw a <sic corr="handleless">handlesless</sic> and saucerless cup - the latter 
                    being remedied by an odd small sized plate - the only one of it&apos;s kind. Isn&apos;t this pathetic sounding? It is too. This house reminds me in so
                    many ways of the frat house in Seattle!
                </p>
				<p>
                    We are all living up here on the hill now for the very day that Mary &amp; Marshall Ogle moved from the little bungalow Mrs. <sic corr="Proffitt">Profit</sic>
                    and Mr. Cresswell moved up from the Maples house at the foot of the lane. Ever since <pb ref="arm03030010006" seq="06"/> my arrival the domestic
                    troubles of these particular Ogles have been the chief topic of conversation <add place="supralinear">in the <abbr expan="Gatlinburg">burg.</abbr>
					</add>
                    For they involved many people and even the school. It has been very unpleasant at times for us and especially for the two principal actors in the tangle
                    but things all calmed down of a sudden &amp; complete reconciliation followed. Marshall got work at a lumber camp up in the mountains and off they
                    went bag and baggage. He had been very satisfactory on the place till this &quot;other woman&quot; interfered with his home life and Evelyn had to 
                    discharge him.
                </p>
				<p>
                    The attendance has been very poor at school this month - molasses <pb ref="arm03030010007" seq="07"/> making, digging potates, picking corn and beans
                    seem to be the pricipal reasons. Then too it has been pretty rainy until this week and that has kept some at home. Most of them splash to school 
                    barefooted through the mud and real sure enough mud it is! Not even the Fords can get through now to Pigeon Forge - It <del>
                        takes</del> took us two hours to make the seven miles in a buggy down there last week so you can judge of the ruts - <unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">
                            chuq</unclear> holes and depth of mud from that. Several of the girls have stayed here all night rather than go home so far when it is so wet.
                    They like to do it and try to use their napkins knives and forks etc. just right at the table - keeping one eye on <hi1 rend="underscore">us!</hi1>
				</p>
				<p>
                    Lately all the boys and girls have been playing ring games together at noon and recess and very nicely too. &quot;Farmer in the Dell&quot; is the favorite.
                    They are so funny! I wish you could hear my Lucrettie pour forth excuses for not knowing her history. Today she and one of the others came rushing in
                    just before time for &quot;books&quot; at one - simply dripping with perspiration and demanded that I explain the &quot;census&quot; to them - &quot;
                    <unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">O</unclear> hits so hard Miss Sturley - I can&apos;t get <hi1 rend="underscore">nary</hi1> a thing - not nary a 
                    thing!&quot; They are very enthusiastic over the party for tomorrow. The cooking class made doughnuts today and will finish up that part
                    <pb ref="arm03030010008" seq="08" n="03"/> of it tomorrow. Yesterday noon they all made their jack-o-lanterns - boys and girls together &amp; produced
                    fifteen nice big ones. Then we have made a lot from paper - also black cats - owls - witches and moons which adorn our rooms and the windows for
                    it&apos;s to be at the schoolhouse. The girls <add place="supralinear">in the</add> club are going to give a witch song marching around the rooms holding
                    jack-o-lanterns &amp; dressed in sheets and pillow cases. This excitement will be followed by a &quot;track meet&quot; - bobbing for apples and
                    fortune telling. 
                </p>
				<p>
                    We have had a spellin&apos; - a &quot;sing&quot; - corn husking and lastly the debate of last night given by the newly organized <pb ref="arm03030010009" seq="09"/>
                    Gatlinburg Literary Society - The subject was purely local and good for the community - &quot;Resolved that a public highway is of greater benefit to 
                    <abbr expan="Gatlinburg">G.</abbr> than <add place="supralinear">a</add> railroad.&quot; Steve Whaley one of the substantial citizens is president
                    and Mr. Cresswell secretary - So far both boys and girls belong but we rather hope it will work out just for the boys and men.
                </p>
				<p>
                    We are working hard on our Thanksgiving play - &quot;The Courtship of Miles Standish&quot; which will be staged with scenery and costumes complete. 
                    We have the spinning wheel at any rate.
                </p>
				<p>
                    Do you know I&apos;m getting quite spoiled for the city ways - We did enjoy our trip <pb ref="arm03030010010" seq="10"/> to Knoxville - <unclear reason="illegible" resp="bds">
                        paning</unclear> - electric lights - stores etc. looked very good to us - but we were simply delighted with our own green mountains and peaceful 
                    <abbr expan="Gatlinburg">burg</abbr> Sunday night when we made the turn in the road which gives the first glimpse of it all. The foliage is growing
                    quite gorgeous though the bees and butterflies are still with us - and we&apos;ve been wearing thin clothes all week doors and windows stretched 
                    wide open.
                </p>
				<p>
                    If any of you have copies of &quot;Current Events&quot; the &quot;Outlook&quot; &quot;Literary Digest&quot; or similar magazines and papers - we
                    would like to have them for the history classes - in both of which there is need for a certain amount of time <del>for</del>
					<add place="supralinear">on</add> topics of the day as they never see a newspaper or magazine at home.
                </p>
				<p>
                    Near the close of this letter I discovered a huge blot on <del>the</del>
					<add place="supralinear">a</add> page of the first part and if
                    you will excuse it am not going to stop and copy but send if as it is - with regret!
                </p>
				<p>
                    With love to each and all of the Inez Smith Soule Alumnae and best wishes for another good meeting next Saturday - the second in the month
                </p>
				<p>
                    Ruth E. Sturley.
                </p>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
