<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03040007000">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[Letter]  Feb. 15, 1920, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
                    <name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
                    <name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
                </address>
                <date>2006</date>
                <idno type="SPCID">arm03040007000</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. 
                        For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee 
                        Libraries, Knoxville, TN</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from which the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
                <bibl>
                    <title>[Letter]  Feb. 15, 1920, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                    <date value="1920-02-15">Feb. 15, 1920</date>
                    <author>
                        <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                    </author>
                    <extent>7p</extent>
                    <note type="summary">Snowstorm - Valentine&apos;s Day - School Magazine</note>
                    <note type="box">3</note>
                    <note type="folder">4</note>
                    <note type="document">arm03040007000</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Local Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <list>
                        <item>Social events</item>
                        <item>Snow</item>
                        <item>Holidays</item>
                        <item>People</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="abstract">
                <pb ref="arm03040007001" seq="01"/>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <item>Snowstorm</item>
                        <item>Valentine&apos;s Day</item>
                        <item>School magazine</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="letter">
                <pb ref="arm03040007002" seq="02"/>
                <head>
                    <date value="1920-02-15">Feb. 15, 1920</date>
                </head>    
                <p>
                    Dearest family, nine - fifteen and all in bed this cold Sunday night - but your child. Winter seems to have struck us at last - A little of the New York storm 
                    drifted over our peaceful mountain tops yesterday afternoon. It was a perfectly gorgeous sunny cloudless morning - Emily &amp; I half planned a long 
                    tramp over the hills &amp; far away for the <abbr expan="afternoon">p.m.</abbr> but by noon clouds rolled in &amp; by 2:30 it was dark &amp; in half an 
                    hour we had to light the lamp - Then it began to rain &amp; finally settled down to a real snowstorm - so <pb ref="arm03040007003" seq="03"></pb>earnestly did 
                    this continue that by five o&apos;clock it was a white world and a very lovely one too. Evelyn &amp; I walked up through Pi Phi lane to Harrison&apos;s 
                    with some milk and enjoyed the snow woods immensely.
                </p>
                <p>
                    All day it has been &quot;right smart&quot; cold but sunny. Everyone stayed home I guess - for hardly a soul has stirred on the &quot;big road&quot; all 
                    day. Evelyn decided to go home this morning and had to walk to Pigeon Forge where a buggy met her. Emily walked about four miles down the road with her 
                    and got back about 1 - mud even <pb ref="arm03040007004" seq="04"></pb>splashed on her shoulders as they footed it down the <abbr expan="mountain">mt.</abbr> 
                    The roads are worse than they have ever been partly because of so much hauling of lumber. Evelyn will be gone also this week.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Friday night was the debate - Resolved, that the works of nature are more attractive than the arts of man. All who took part were girls and they certainly 
                    entered into it with more pep than has been displayed yet - the negative side got the decision. After this display of fireworks we were treated to an embryo 
                    minstrel show gotten up by Mr. Cresswell &amp; aided &amp; abetted by Tom &amp; Harve Reagan - who played the guitar - all three blacked up - 
                    The youngsters liked it immensely but some of it was sacreligous and certainly might better have been left unsaid. Mr. <abbr expan="Cresswell">C.</abbr> 
                    is to blame &amp; we are quite surprised at him. Evelyn is especially.
                </p>
                <p>
                    That afternoon we had our school magazine &amp; a valentine box. The magazine was quite good and has a very pretty &amp; appropriately decorated 
                    cover - white with red hearts &amp; printing. In it were a number of paragraphs telling what each wanted to be - Most of them want to go on to <pb ref="arm03040007005" seq="05"></pb>
                    school &amp; then teach - also travel - one wishes to be a foreign missionary - another a nurse &amp; look after Belgian orphans - Only one of the boys wants 
                    to be a farmer - Some were absent however &amp; there&apos;s no telling what they would have written.
                </p>
                <p>
                    We made valentines Thursday afternoon - red &amp; white strips of card board given to each youngsters with patterns for hearts of different sizes - arrows - 
                    cupids etc. They just loved making them.
                </p>
                <pb ref="arm03040007006" seq="06"></pb>
                <p>
                    All day I&apos;ve been working on a letter Miss Langmaid asked me to write - a copy of which is to be sent to each province vice - <abbr expan="president">pres.</abbr> 
                    for chapters. Emily wrote one last month, I have described the reading of the school magazine quoting <gap reason="illegible" resp="tal"></gap> of the articles 
                    to show the influence of the school on the lives &amp; thoughts of the pupils - Found it rather slow work &amp; am glad it&apos;s done.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <del>Had a letter from Katherine with application blank for position in Oakland schools </del><pb ref="arm03040007007" seq="07"></pb><del>thinks I&apos;m 
                        sure of getting a position in a junior high school - Have not filled it out yet but think I will - though I just don&apos;t want to teach in a regular routine again. 
                        Guess I&apos;m a shirk or something but that&apos;s the way I feel about it. <gap reason="illegible" resp="tal"></gap> I guess that&apos;s the reason. 
                        Was glad to get June&apos;s little valentine card yesterday &amp; hope mine reached you in time. </del>
                </p>
                <p>
                   <del>Saw something in the paper - (Tacoma &amp; Monitor) about irrigation in the Columbia River Basin. Will that not make our land 
                       valuable?</del>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <del>Here is another picture that I overlooked. It was taken in the Meta<add place="supralinear">ir</add>ie 
                        Cementary (pronounced Met&apos;a rie) the expensive &#36;5000 minimum cemetery that used to be a race course.</del>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <del>Hoping to hear from you all Monday (tomorrow) &amp; that all is well wtih my dearest family -</del>
                </p>
                <p>
                    Loads of love as ever
                </p>
                <p>
                    Ruth
                </p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>